
Brihat Parashara Hora Sashtra by Rishi Parashara
Page 1 
Ch. 1. The Creation  
1-4. Offering his obeisance to all-knowing Mahārśi Parāśara and with folded hands, Maitreya said: O venerable Mahārśi, Jyotishya, the supreme limb of the Vedas, has three divisions, viz. Horā, Ganita and Samhita. Among the said three divisions Horā, or the general part of Jyotishya is still more excellent. I desire to know of its glorious aspects from you. Be pleased to tell me, how this Universe is created? How does it end? What is the relationship of the animals, born on this earth, with the heavenly bodies? Please speak elaborately 5-8. Mahārśi Parāśara answered. O Brahmin, your query has an auspicious purpose in it for the welfare of the Universe. Praying Lord Brahma and Śrī Saraswatī, his power (and consort) and Sun, the leader of the Planets and the cause of Creation, I shall proceed to narrate to you the science of Jyotishya, as heard through Lord Brahma. Only good will follow the teaching of this Vedic Science to the students, who are peacefully disposed, who honor the preceptors (and elders), who speak only truth and are God fe6thng. Woeful forever, doubtlessly, will it be to impart knowledge of this science to an unwilling student, to a heterodox and to a crafty person.  
9-12. Śrī Vishnu, who is the Lord (of all matters), who has undefiled spirit, who is endowed with the three Gunas, although he transcends the grip of Gunas (Gunatita), who is the Author of this Universe, who is glorious, who is the Cause and who is endowed with valor, has no beginning. He authored the Universe and administers it with a quarter of his power. The other three quarters of Him, filled with nectar, are knowable only to the philosophers (of maturity). The Principal Evolver, who is both perceptible and imperceptible, is Vasudeva. The Imperceptible part of the Lord is endowed with dual powers, while the Perceptible with triple powers.  
13-15. The three powers are Śrī Shakti (Mother Lakshmi) with Sattva-Gun, Bhū Shakti (Mother-Earth) with Rajo-Gun and Nīla Shakti with Tamo-Gun. Apart from the three, the fourth kind of Vishnu, influenced by Śrī Shakti and Bhoo Shakti, assumes the form of Shankarshan with Tamo-Gun, of Pradyumna with Rajo Guna and of Anirudh with Sattva Guna.  
16-17. Mahatatwa, Ahamkara and Ahamkara Murti and Brahma, are born from Shankarshana, Pradyumna and Anirudha, respectively. All these three forms are endowed with all the three Gunas, with predominance of the Guna due to their origin.  
18-19. Ahamkara is of three classes, i.e. with Sattvic, Rajasic and Tamasic dispositions. Divine class, sensory organs and the five primordial compounds (space, air, fire, water and earth) are, respectively, from the said three Ahamkaras.  
20. Lord Vishnu, coupled with Śrī Shakti, rules over the three worlds. Coupled with Bhoo Shakti, He is Brahma causing the Universe. Coupled with Neel Shakti, He is Shiva, destroying the Universe.  
21-24. The Lord is in all beings and the entire Universe is in Him. All beings contain both Jivatma and Paramatmāńśas. Some have predominance of the former, while yet some have the latter in predominance. Paramatmāńśa is predominant in the Planets, viz. Sun etc. and Brahma, Shiva and others. Their powers or consorts too have predominance of Paramatmāńśa. Others have more of Jivatmāńśa.  
Ch. 2. Great Incarnations  
1. Maitreya: O Mahārśi Parāśara, are the incarnations of Vishnu, viz. Śrī Rama, Śrī Krishna etc., endowed with Jivāńś? 2. Mahārśi Parashara: O Brahmin, the four incarnations, viz. Ram, Krishna, Narasimha and Varaha are wholly with Paramatmāńś. The other incarnations (than these, out of the ten) have in them Jivāńś too.  
3-4. The unborn Lord has many incarnations. He has incarnated, as the 9 (Nava) Planets to bestow on the living beings the results due to their 10ths. He is Janardana. He assumed the auspicious form of Planets to destroy the demons (evil forces) and sustain the divine beings.  
5-7. From Sun came the incarnation of Rama, from Moon that of Krishna, from Mars that of Narasimha, from Mercury that of Buddha, from Jupiter that of Vamana, from Venus that of Parashurama, from Saturn that of Kurma (Tortoise), from Rahu that of Varaha (Pig) and from Ketu that of Pisces (Fish) occurred. Incarnations other than these also are through the Planets. The beings with more Paramatmāńś are called divine beings.  
8-13. The beings with more Jivatmāńś are (mortal) beings. The high degree of Paramatmāńś from the Planets, viz. Sun etc. did incarnate, as Ram, Krishna etc. After completing the mission, the Paramatmāńśas (of the respective) Planets again merge (in the respective) Planets. The Jivatma portions from the Planets take births, as human beings and live their lives according to their 10ths and again merge in the Planets. And at the time of Great Destruction the Planets as well merge in Lord Vishnu. The one, who knows of all these, will become versed in the knowledge of the past, present and future. Without knowledge of Jyotishya these cannot be known. Hence, everyone should have knowledge of Jyotishya, particularly the Brahmin. The one, who, devoid of knowledge of Jyotishya, blames this Vedic Science will go to the hell called Raurava and will be reborn blind.  
Ch. 3. Planet Characters and Description   
1. Maitreya: O Mahārśi, you have affectionately explained about the incarnations of Planets. Now kindly tell me in detail their characters and dispositions. 2-3. Parāśara: O Brahmin, listen to the account of placement of the heavenly bodies. Out of the many luminous bodies sighted in the skies some are stars, yet some are Planets. Those, that have no movements, are the Nakshatras (asterisms).  
4-6. Those are called Planets, which move through the Nakshatras (or stellar mansions) in the zodiac. The said zodiac comprises of 27 Nakshatras commencing from Ashvini. The same area is divided in 12 parts equal to 12 Rāśis commencing from Aries. The names of the Planets commence from Sun. The Rāśi rising is known, as Lagna. Based on Lagna and the Planets, joining and departing from each other, the natives good and bad effects are deducted.  
Addition from Santhanam till Sloka 7. The names of the 27 Nakshatras are Ashvini, Bharani, Krittika, Rohini, Mrigasira, Ardra, Punarvasu, Pushya, Aslesha, Magha, Purvaphalguni, Uttaraphalguni, Hasta, Chitra, Swati, Vishaka, Anuradha, Jyeshtha, Mula, Purvashadh, Uttarashadh, Shravana, Dhanistha, Satabhisha, Purvabhadra, Uttarabhadra, Revati.  
Lagna is a very important point in the horoscope. It is the Rāśi that rises in the East, on the latitude of birth. The apparent rising of a Rāśi is due to the rotation of the earth on its own axis at a rate of motion, causing every degree of the zodiac seemingly ascend on the eastern horizon. Approximately two hours are required for a Rāśi to pass via the horizon, thereby every degree taking four minutes to ascend. This duration, however, is actually dependent on the concerned latitude.  
Actually Sun has no motion. His motion is an apparent one, as viewed from the rotating earth. Other Planets, including the nodes, have v6thed rates of motion. The average daily motions of the Planets, which are not, however standard, are, as follows: Sun 1, Moon 13-15, Mars30-45, Mercury 65-100, Venus 62-82, Jupiter 5-15, Saturn 2, Rahu/Ketu 3.  
With such different motions, a Planet forms various Aspects with others. These Aspects through longitudinal distances have a great deal of utility in Jyotishya. This is what Mahārśi Parashara suggests to be considered.  
7. Details (of astronomical nature) of stars have to be understood by general rules, while I narrate to you about the effects of Planets and Rāśis. 
8-9. The positions of the Planets for a given time be taken, as per Drikganit. And with the help of Rāśi durations, applicable to the respective places, Lagna at birth should be known. Now, I tell you about the castes, descriptions and dispositions of the Planets.  
10. Names of Planets. The names of the nine Planets, respectively, are Sun, Moon, Mars, Mercury, Jupiter, Venus, Saturn, Rahu and Ketu.  
11. Benefics and Malefics. Among these, Sun, Saturn, Mars, decreasing Moon, Rahu and Ketu (the ascending and the descending nodes of Moon) are malefics, while the rest are benefics. Mercury, however, is a malefic, if he joins a malefic.  
Addition from Santhanam till Sloka 12-13. When Moon is ahead of Sun, but within 120, she has medium strength. Between 120 to 240 she is very auspicious,( see Atishubhapred). From 240 to 0 she is bereft of strength. This is Yavana’s view; vide P. 70 of my English Translation of Saravali. This view is, however, related to Moon’s strength, or otherwise, while the waning Moon (Krishna Paksha, dark half) is a malefic and waxing Moon (Shukla Paksha, bright half) is a benefic. Should Moon be conjunct with a benefic, or receiving a Aspect from a benefic, she turns a benefic, even if in a waning state. As regards Mercury, we have clear instructions from Mahārśi Parashara, that he becomes a malefic, if he joins a malefic. If waning Moon and Mercury are together, both are benefics. 
12-13. Planet governances. Sun is the soul of all. Moon is the mind. Mars is ones strength. Mercury is speech-giver, while Jupiter confers Knowledge and happiness. Venus governs semen (potency), while Saturn denotes grief.  
14-15. Planet cabinet. Of royal status are Sun and Moon, while Mars is the Army chief. Prince-apparent is Mercury. The ministerial Planets are Jupiter and Venus. Saturn is a servant. Rahu and Ketu form the Planet Army.  
16-17. Complexions of Planets. Sun is blood-red. Moon is tawny. Mars, who is not very tall is blood-red, while Mercury’s hue is akin to that of green grass. Tawny, v6thegated and dark are Jupiter, Venus and Saturn in their order. 
18. Deities of Planets. Fire (Agni) (?), Water (Varuna), Subrahmanya (Lord Shiva’s son, following Ganesha), Maha Vishnu, Indra, Shachi Devi (the consort of Lord Indra) and Brahma (?) are the presiding deities of the 7 Planets in their order. 
19. Gender of the Planets. Mercury and Saturn are neuters. Moon and Venus are females, while Sun, Mars and Jupiter are males.  
20. Primordial compounds. Jupiter, Saturn, Mars, Venus and Mercury, respectively govern the Panchabhutas, space, air, fire, water and earth.  
21. Castes of Planets. Jupiter and Venus are Brahmins. Sun is a royal Planet, while Moon and Mercury belong to commercial community. Saturn rules the Sudras (4th caste).  
22. Nature of Planets. Sattvic Planets are the lumin6thes (Sun & Moon) and Jupiter, Venus and Mercury are Rajasik, while Mars and Saturn are Tamasic.  
23. Description of Sun. Sun’s eyes are honey-colored. He has a square body. He is of clean habits, bilious, intelligent and has limited hair (on his head). 
24. Description of Moon. Moon is very windy and phlegmatic. She is learned and has a round body. She has auspicious looks and sweet speech, is fickle-minded and very lustful.  
25. Description of Mars. Mars has blood-red eyes, is fickle-minded, liberal, bilious, given to anger and has thin waist and thin physique.  
26. Description of Mercury. Mercury is endowed with an attractive physique and the capacity to use words with many meanings. He is fond of jokes. He has a mix of all the three humors.  
27. Description of Jupiter. Jupiter has a big body, tawny hair and tawny eyes, is phlegmatic, intelligent and learned in Shastras.  
28. Description of Venus. Venus is charming, has a splendorous physique, is excellent or great in disposition, has charming eyes, is a poet, is phlegmatic and windy and has curly hair.  
29. Description of Saturn. Saturn has an emaciated and long physique, has tawny eyes, is windy in temperament, has big teeth, is indolent and lame and has coarse hair.  
30. Description of Rahu and Ketu. Rahu has smoky appearance with a blue mix physique. He resides in forests and is horrible. He is windy in temperament and is intelligent. Ketu is akin to Rahu.  
31. Primary ingredients (or Sapta Dhatus). Bones, blood, marrow, skin, fat, semen and muscles are respectively denoted by the Planets: Sun, Moon, Mars, Mercury, Jupiter, Venus and Saturn.  
32. Abodes of the Planets. Temple, watery place, place of fire, sport-ground, treasure-house, bed-room and filthy ground: these are, respectively, the abodes for the seven Planets from Sun onward.  
33. Planet periods. Ayan, Muhurta, a day (consisting day and night), Ritu, month, fortnight and year: these are the periods allotted to the Planets from Sun to Saturn.  
34. Tastes of the Planets. Pungent, saline, bitter, mixed, sweet, acidulous and astringent are, respectively, tastes lorded by Sun, Moon, Mars, Mercury, Jupiter, Venus and Saturn.  
35-38. Strengths of Planets. Strong in the East are Mercury and Jupiter. Sun and Mars are so in the South, while Saturn is the only Planet, that derives strength in the West. Moon and Venus are endowed with vigor, when in the North. Again, strong during night are Moon, Mars and Saturn, while Mercury is strong during day and night. The rest (i.e. Jupiter, Sun and Venus) are strong only in daytime. During the dark half malefics are strong. Benefics acquire strength in the bright half of the month. Malefics and benefics are, respectively, strong in Dakshinayan and Uttarayan. The Lords of the year, month, day and Hora (hour of Planet) are stronger than the other in ascending order. Again, stronger than the other in the ascending are Saturn, Mars, Mercury, Jupiter, Venus, Moon and Sun.  
39-40. Related to trees. Sun rules strong trees (i.e. trees with stout trunks), Saturn useless trees, Moon milky trees (and rubber yielding plants), Mars bitter ones (like lemon plants), Venus floral plants, Jupiter fruitful ones and Mercury fruitless ones.  
41-44. Other matters. Rahu rules the outcaste, while Ketu governs mixed caste. Saturn and the nodes indicate ant-hills. Rahu denotes multi-coloured clothes and Ketu rags. Lead and blue gem belong to Rahu and Ketu. Sun, Moon, Mars, Mercury, Jupiter, Venus and Saturn in their order govern red silken, white silken, red, black silken, saffron, silken and multi-coloured robes.  
45-46. Seasons of Planets. Vasanta, Greeshma, Varsh, Sarad, Hemanta and Sisir are the six Ritus (or seasons), respectively, governed by Venus, Mars, Moon, Mercury, Jupiter and Saturn. Rahu and Ketu denote 8 months and 3 months, respectively.  
47. Dhatu, Mool and Jiva Divisions. Dhatu Planets are Rahu, Mars, Saturn and Moon, while Sun and Venus are Mula Planets. Mercury, Jupiter and Ketu rule Jivas.  
48. Age. Out of all the Planets Saturn is the eldest. He bestows maximum number of years in Naisargik Dasha.  
49-50. Exaltation and Debilitation. For the seven Planets, from Sun on, the exaltation Rāśis are, respectively, Aries, Taurus, Capricorn, Virgo, Cancer, Pisces and Libra. The deepest exaltation degrees are, respectively, 10, 3, 28, 15, 5, 27 and 20 in those Rāśis. And in the seventh Rāśi from the said exaltation Rāśi each Planet has its own debilitation. The same degrees of deep exaltation apply to deep fall.  
51-54. Additional Dignities. In Leo the first 20 degrees are Sun’s Moolatrikona, while the rest is his own House. After the first 3 degrees of exaltation portion in Taurus, for Moon, the rest is her Moolatrikona. Marsh as the first 12 degrees in Aries, as Moolatrikona with the rest therein becoming simply his own House. For Mercury, in Virgo the first 15 degrees are exaltation zone, the next 5 degrees Moolatrikona and the last 10 degrees are own House. The first one third of Sagittarius is the Moolatrikona of Jupiter, while the remaining part thereof is his own House. Venus divides Libra into two halves keeping the first, as Moolatrikona and the second, as own House. Saturn’s arrangements are same in Aquarius, as Sun has in Leo. 
55. Natural Relationships. Note the Rāśis, which are the 2nd, 4th, 5th, 8th, 9th and 12th from the Moolatrikona of a Planet. The Planets ruling such Rāśis are its friends, apart from the Lord of its exaltation Rāśi. Lords other than these are its enemies. If a Planet becomes its friend as well, as its enemy (on account of the said two computations), then it is neutral, or equal.  
56. Temporary Relationships. The Planet, posited in the 2nd, 3rd, 4th, 10th, 11th, or the 12th from another, becomes a mutual friend. There is enmity otherwise. (This applies to a given Janm Kundali)  
57-58. Compound Relationship. Should two Planets be naturally and tempor6thly friendly, they become extremely friendly. Friendship on one count and neutrality on another count make them friendly. Enmity on one count combined with affinity on the other turns into equality. Enmity and neutral-ship cause only enmity. Should there be enmity in both manners, extreme enmity is obtained. The astrologer should consider these and declare horoscope effects accordingly.  
59-60. Ratio of Effects. A Planet in exaltation gives fully good effects, while in Moolatrikona it is bereft of its auspicious effects by one fourth. It is half beneficial in its own House. Its beneficence is one fourth in a friendly Rāśi. In an equals Rāśi one eighth of auspicious disposition is useful. The good effects are nil in debilitation, or enemy’s camp. Inauspicious effects are quite reverse with reference to what is stated. 
61-64. Non-luminous Upa Grahas (Sub-Planets). Add 4 Rāśis 13 degrees and 20 minutes of arc to Sun’s longitude at a given moment to get the exact position of the all inauspicious Dhoom. Reduce Dhoom from 12 Rāśis to arrive at Vyatipat. Vyatipat is also inauspicious. Add six Rāśis to Vyatipat to know the position of Prithvesh. He is extremely inauspicious. Deduct P6thvesh from 12 Rāśis to arrive at the position of Chap (Indra 2ndus), who is also inauspicious. Add 16 degrees 40 minutes to Chap, which will give Ketu (UpaKetu), who is a malefic. By adding a Rāśi to UpaKetu, you get the original longitude of Sun. These are the Planets, devoid of splendor, which are malefics by nature and cause affliction. 
65. Effects of Sub-Planets. If one of these afflicts Sun, the natives dynasty will decline, while Moon and Lagna, respectively, associated with one of these, will destroy the longevity and wisdom. So declared Lord Brahma, the Lotus-Born.  
66-69. Calculations of Gulika etc. The portions of Sun etc. up to Saturn denote the periods of Gulika and others. Divide the day duration (of any week day) into eight equal parts. The eighth portion is Lord-less. The seven portions are distributed to the seven Planets commencing from the Lord of the week day. Whichever portion is ruled by Saturn, will be the portion of Gulika. Similarly make the night duration into eight equal parts and distribute these, commencing from the Lord of the 5th (by) week. Here again, the eighth portion is Lord-less, while Saturn’s portion is Gulika. Sun’s portion is Kaal, Mars’s portion is Mrityu, Jupiter’s portion is Yamaghantak and Mercury’s portion is Ardhaprahar. These durations differently apply to different places (commensurate with v6thable day and night durations). 
70. Gulika’s Position. The degree, ascending at the time of start of Gulika’s portion (as above), will be the longitude of Gulika at a given place. Based on this longitude only, Gulika’s effects for a particular nativity be estimated. 
71-74. Calculation of Pranapad. Convert the given time into Vighatis and divide the same by 15. The resultant Rāśi, degrees etc. be added to Sun, if he is in a Movable Rāśi, which will yield Pranapad. If Sun is in a Fixed Rāśi, add 240 degrees additionally and, if in a Dual Rāśi, add 120 degrees in furtherance to get Pranapad. The birth will be auspicious, if Pranapad falls in the 2nd, 5th, 9th, 4th, 10th, or 11th from the natal Lagna. In other Houses Pranapad indicates an inauspicious birth.  
Notes by Santanam. Ardhaprahar, Yamaghantak, Mrityu, Kaal and Gulika are the 5 Kaal Velas, suggested by Mahārśi Parashara. The day duration, according to altitude, is divided into eight equal parts. The eighth portion is unlorded. The first portion is allotted to the weekday Lord. Other portions follow in the order of weekday Lords. We consider 5 portions of Planets, ignoring that of Moon and Venus. The portions of Sun, Mars, Mercury, Jupiter and Saturn are, respectively, called Kaal, Mrityu, Ardhaprahar, Yamaghantak and Gulika.  
In the case of night the durations, or 1/8th parts are allotted in a different order. The first portion goes to the Planet, ruling the 5th weekday Lord, counted from the day in question. The others follow in the usual order. Here again, the 8th part is Lord-less. The portions of Planets from Kaal to Gulika are the same in nomenclature in the night also.  
Jatakalankaram gives Rāśis of dignities for these UpaPlanets and Gulika etc.: Exaltation, Debilitation, Swakshetra (own Rāśi)) Dhoom: Leo, Aquarius, Capricorn; Vyatipat: Scorpio, Taurus, Gemini; Parivesh: Gemini, Sagittarius, Sagittarius; Indrachap: Sagittarius, Gemini, Cancer; UpaKetu: Aquarius, Leo, Cancer; Gulika: Aquarius; Yamaghantak: - Sagittarius; Ardhaprahar: - Gemini; Kaal: - Capricorn; Mrityu: Scorpio. From Sun to Saturn no one is exalted in the above-mentioned exaltation Rāśis, nor debilitated in the above-mentioned debilitation Rāśis. Out of the 5 Kaal Velas, viz. Gulika etc., four except Kaal (related to Sun) have their own Rāśi system in the respective Rāśis, ruled by their fathers. Gulika, son of Saturn, has Aquarius, as his own House. Jupiter’s son, Yamaghantak, has it in Sagittarius. Ardhaprahar, Mercury’s son, is in own Rāśi, if in Gemini. Mrityu, son of Mars, has Scorpio, as own House. It is not known, why Kaal, a son of Sun shifted to Capricorn, a Rāśi of his brother (Saturn), leaving his fathers Leo. Obviously, Saturn has given his Moolatrikona to his son Gulika, while he gave Capricorn (a secondary Rāśi) to his brother Kaal.   
Ch. 4. Zodiacal Rāśis Described  
1-2. Importance of Hora. The word Hora is derived from Ahoratr after dropping the first and last syllables. Thus Hora (Lagna as) remains in between Ahoratr (i.e. day and night) and after knowing Hora the good and bad effects of a native be known. Śrī Vishnu, the Invisible is Time personified. His limbs are the 12 Rāśis, commencing from Aries. 3. Names of Rāśis. The 12 Rāśis of the zodiac in order are Aries, Taurus, Gemini, Cancer, Leo, Virgo, Libra, Scorpio, Sagittarius, Capricorn, Aquarius and Pisces.  
4-4. Limbs of Kaal Purush. Kaal Purush (or Time personified) has his limbs, as under with reference to the 12 Rāśis, respectively: Head, face, arms, heart, stomach, hip, space below navel, privities, thighs, knees, ankles and feet.  
5-5. Classification of Rāśis. Movable, Fixed and Dual are the names given to the 12 Rāśis in order. These are again known, as malefic and benefic, successively. Similarly are male and female. Aries, Leo and Sagittarius are bilious. Taurus, Virgo and Capricorn are windy. Gemini, Libra and Aquarius are mixed, while the rest are phlegmatic.  
6-7. Aries described. The Aries is blood-red in complexion. lt has a prominent (big) physique. It is a quadruped Rāśi and strong during night. It denotes courage. It resides in the East and is related to kings. It wanders in hills and predominates in Rajo-Gun (the second of the three constituent qualities and the cause of great activity in living beings). It rises with its back (a Prishtodaya Rāśi) and is fiery. Its ruler is Mars.  
8. Taurus described. Taurus complexion is white and it is lorded by Venus. It is long and is a quadruped Rāśi. It has strength in night and resides in the South. It represents villages and businessmen. An earthy Rāśi, Taurus rises with its back.  
9-9. Gemini described. The Rāśi Gemini rises with its head and represents a male and a female, holding a mace and lute. It lives in the West and is an airy Rāśi. It is a biped Rāśi as well and is strong in nights. It lives in villages and is windy in temperament. It has an even body with a green (grass like) hue. Its ruler is Mercury.  
10-11. Cancer described. The Rāśi Cancer is pale-red. It resorts to forests and represents Brahmins. It is strong in nights. It has many feet (i.e. it is a centipede Rāśi) and has a bulky body. It is Sattvic in disposition (seen in gods) and it is a watery Rāśi. It rises with its back and is ruled by Moon.  
12. Leo described. Leo is ruled by Sun and is Sattvic. It is a quadruped Rāśi and a royal Rāśi. It resorts to forests and rises with its head. It has a large, white body. It resides in the East and is strong during daytime.  
13-14. Virgo described. This Rāśi is a hill-resorter and is strong in daytime. It rises with its head and has a medium build. It is a biped Rāśi and resides in the South. It has grains and fire in its hands. It belongs to the business community and is v6thegated. It relates to hurricanes (Prabharanjani). It is a Virgin and is Tamasic (a disposition of demons). Its ruler is Mercury.  
15-16. Libra described. Libra is a Seershodaya Rāśi, rising with its head; Libra is strong in daytime. It is black in complexion and is predominant with Rajo-Gun. It relates to the western direction and resorts to land. It is destructive, or mischievous (Dhatin). It represents Sudras, or the 4th Varna. It has a medium build physique and is a biped Rāśi. Its Lord is Venus. Scorpio described. Scorpio has a slender physique and is a centipede Rāśi. It denotes Brahmins and resides in holes. Its direction is north and it is strong in daytime. It is reddish-brown and resorts to water and land. It has a hairy physique and is very sharp (or passionate). Mars is its ruler.  
17-18. Sagittarius described. The Rāśi Sagittarius rises with its head and is lorded by Jupiter. It is a Sattvic Rāśi and is tawny in hue. It has strength in night and is fiery. A royal Rāśi, Sagittarius is biped in first half. Its second half is quadruped. It has an even build and adores an arch. It resides in the East, resorts to land and is splendorous.  
19-20. Capricorn described. Capricorn is lorded by Saturn and has predominance of Tamo-Gun (a disposition, seen in demons). It is an earthy Rāśi and represents the southern direction. It is strong in nights and rises with back. It has a large body. Its complexion is v6thegated and it resorts to both forests and lands. Its first half is quadruped and its second half footless, moving in water.  
21-21. Aquarius described. The Rāśi Aquarius represents a man holding a pot. Its complexion is deep-brown. It has medium build and is a biped Rāśi. It is very strong in daytime. It resorts to deep water and is airy. It rises with its head and is Tamasic. It rules Sudras, the 4th Varna and the West. Its Lord is Saturn, Sun’s offspring. 22-24. Pisces described. Pisces resembles a pair of fish, one tailed with the head of the other. This Rāśi is strong at night. It is a watery Rāśi and is predominant with Sattva-Gun. It denotes resoluteness and is a water-resorter. It is footless and has a medium build. It rules the North and rises with both head and back. It is ruled by Jupiter. This is how the twelve Rāśis, each of 30 degrees extent, are described to evaluate gross and specific effects.  
25-30. Nishek Lagna. O excellent of Brahmins, now is a step explained to arrive at the Nishek Lagna, when the natal Lagna is known. Note the angular distance between Saturn and Mandi (Gulika). Add this to the difference between the Lagna House (Madhya, or cusp) and the 9th House (cusp). The resultant product in Rāśis, degrees etc. will represent the months, days etc. that elapsed between Nishek and birth. At birth, if Lagna Lord is in the invisible half (i.e. from Lagna cusp to descendental cusp), add the degrees etc., Moon moved in the particular Rāśi, occupied by her, to the above-mentioned product. Then Lagna at Nishek can be worked out and the good and bad, experienced by the native in the womb, can be guessed. One can also guess with the help of Nishek Lagna effects, like longevity, death etc. of the parents.  
Ch. 5. Special Lagnas   
1. Oh excellent of the Brahmins, I explain below again some special Lagnas, viz. House Lagna, Hora Lagna and Ghati Lagna.  
2-3. House Lagna. From sunrise to the time of birth every 5 Ghatis (or 120 minutes) constitute one House Lagna. Divide the time of birth (in Ghatis, Vighatis etc.) from sunrise by 5 and add the quotient etc. to Sun’s longitude, as at sunrise. This is called House Lagna. 
4-5. Hora Lagna. Again from sunrise till the time of birth Hora Lagna repeats itself every 2 Ghatis (i. e. 60 minutes). Divide the time past up to birth from sunrise by 2 and add the quotient etc. in Rāśis, degrees and so on to the longitude of Sun, as at the sunrise. This will yield Hora Lagna in Rāśi, degrees etc. 
6-8. Ghati Lagna (Ghatik Lagna). Now listen to the method of working out Ghati Lagna. This Lagna changes along with every Ghati (24 minutes) from the sunrise. Note birth time in Ghatis and Vighatis. Consider the number of Ghatis past, as number of Rāśis, or Ghati Lagnas. The Vighatis be divided by 2 to arrive at degrees and minutes of arc, past in the said Ghati Lagna. The product so arrived in Rāśis, degrees and minutes should be added to Sun’s longitude, as at sunrise, to get the exact location of Ghati Lagna. So say Mahārśis, like Narada. 
9. Use of Special Lagnas. Keeping the Planets at birth, as it is, prepare v6thous House Charts with respect to each special Lagna and analyze, as done for the natal Lagna.  
10-13. Varnada Dasha. I now detail Varnada Dasha, just by knowing which one can deal with the longevity of a native. If the natal Lagna is an odd Rāśi, count directly from Aries to natal Lagna. If the natal Lagna is an even Rāśi, count from Pisces to the natal Lagna in the reverse order. Similarly, if the Hora Lagna is an odd one, count from Aries to Hora Lagna in direct order. If the Hora Lagna is an even one, count from Pisces to Hora Lagna in the reverse order. If both the products are odd Rāśis, or even Rāśis, then add both the figures. If one is odd and the other is even, then know the difference between the two products. If the latest product in this process is an odd one, count so many Rāśis from Aries in a direct manner; if an even one, count so many Rāśis from Pisces in reverse order. The Rāśi so known will be the Varnada for Lagna.  
14-15. Effects of Varnada. Now listen to the use of the above. Out of the two, viz. natal Lagna and Hora Lagna, whichever is stronger, from there Varnada starts. If the natal Lagna is an odd Rāśi, the counting of Dashas is clockwise, otherwise anticlockwise. Lagna Dasha years will equal the number of Rāśis, intervening between the natal Lagna and Varnada. Similarly for other Houses.  
16-20. Effects of Varnada (cont.). Should a Kona from Lagnas Varnada be occupied, or aspected by a malefic, the native will live only up to the Dasha of the said Rāśi. Just, as the Rudra Planet in Sool Dasha is capable of causing evils, the above-mentioned Planets related to Varnadas Kona be treated. The Varnada Lagna be considered, as natal Lagna, while the 7th from Varnada will denote the longevity of the spouse, the 11th longevity of elder brothers and sisters, the 3rd longevity of younger brothers and sisters, the 5th the longevity of sons, the 4th longevity of mother and the 9th longevity of father. The Dasha of the Sool Rāśi will inflict greater evils.  
21-24. Effects of Varnada (cont.). Similar assessments be made with reference to the Varnada of each House, commencing the first, and the evils and goods due to a nativity be known. These Varnada Dashas are only for Houses (Rāśis) and not their occupants. The sub period of each Dasha will be one twelfth of the Dasha and the order will also be clockwise, or anti-clockwise, as explained earlier. The natal Lagna is to be calculated according to birth place, while House Lagna, Hora Lagna etc. are common to all places.  
Ch. 6. The Sixteen Divisions of a Rāśi  
1. O Mahārśi Parāśara, I have known from you about the Planets, Rāśis and their descriptions. I desire to know the details of v6thous divisions of a Rāśi, will you please narrate. 
2-4. Names of the 16 Vargaas. Lord Brahma has described 16 kinds of Vargaas (Divisions) for each Rāśi. Listen to those. The names are Rāśi, Horā, Dreshkana, Chaturthāńśa, Saptāńśa, Navāmśa, Dashāńśa, Dvadashāńśa, Shodashāńś, Vimshāńś, Chaturvimshāńś, Saptavimshāńś, Trimshāńśa, Khavedāńś, Akshavedāńś and Shashtiāńś.  
5-6. Rāśi and Horā. The Rāśi, owned by a Planet, is called its Kshetra. The first half of an odd Rāśi is the Hora, ruled by Sun. While the second half is the Hora of Moon. The reverse is true in the case of an even Rāśi. Half of a Rāśi is called Hora. These are totally 24, counted from Aries and repeated twice (at the rate of 12) in the whole of the zodiac.  
7-8. Dreshkana. One third of a Rāśi is called Dreshkana. These are totally 36, counted from Aries, repeating thrice at the rate of 12 per round. The 1st, 5th and the 9th Rāśis from a Rāśi are its three Dreshkanas and are, respectively, lorded by Narada, Agasthya and Durvash.  
9. Chaturthāńśa. The Lords of the 4 Kendras from a Rāśi are the rulers of respective Chaturthāńśa of a Rāśi, commencing from Aries. Each Chaturthāńśa is one fourth of a Rāśi. The deities, respectively, are Sanak, Sanand, Kumar and Sanatan.  
10-11. Saptāńśa. The Saptāńśa (one seventh of a Rāśi) counting commences from the same Rāśi in the case of an odd Rāśi. It is from the seventh Rāśi thereof, while an even Rāśi is considered. The names of the seven divisions in odd Rāśis are Kshaar Ksheer, Dadhi, Ghrith, Ikshu, Ras, Madhya and Suddh Jal. These designations are reversed for an even Rāśi.  
12. Navāmśa. The Navāmśa calculation are for a Movable Rāśi from there itself, for a Fixed Rāśi from the 9th thereof and for a Dual Rāśi from the 5th thereof. They go by designations Deva (divine), Manushya (human) and Rakshasa (devilish) in a successive and repetitive order for a Movable Rāśi. (Manushya, Rakshasa and Deva are the order for a Fixed Rāśi, while Rakshasa, Manushya and Deva are a Dual Rāśis order)  
13-14. Dashāńśa. Starting from the same Rāśi for an odd Rāśi and from the 9th with reference to an even Rāśi, the 10 Dashāńśas, each of 3 degrees, are reckoned. These are presided over by the ten rulers of the cardinal directions, viz. Indra, Agni, Yama, Rakshasa, Varuna, Vayu, Kuber, Isan, Brahma and Ananth in case of an odd Rāśi. It is in the reverse order, that these presiding deities are reckoned, when an even Rāśi is given.  
15. Dvadashāńśa. The reckoning of the Dvadashāńśa (one twelfth of a Rāśi, or 2 degrees each) commences from the same Rāśi. In each Rāśi the presidentship repeats thrice in the order of Ganesh, Ashvini Kumar, Yama and Sarpa for the 12 Dvadashāńśaas.  
16. Shodashāńś (or Kalāńś). Starting from Aries for a Movable Rāśi, from Leo for a Fixed Rāśi and from Sagittarius for a Dual Rāśi, the 16 Shodashāńśas (16th part of a Rāśi, i.e. of 1ｰ5230) are regularly distributed. The presiding deities of these repeat in the order Brahma, Vishnu, Shiva and Sun four times in the case of an odd Rāśi. It is reverse in the case of an even Rāśi, that these ruling deities are understood. 
17-21. Vimshāńś. From Aries for a Movable Rāśi, from Sagittarius for a Fixed Rāśi and from Leo for a Common Rāśi: this is how the calculations of Vimshāńśas (1/20th of a Rāśi, or 1030 each) are to commence. The presiding deities of the 20 Vimshāńśas in an odd Rāśi are, respectively: Kali, Gauri, Jaya, Lakshmi, Vijaya, Vimal, Sati, Tara, Jvalamukhi, Sveta, Lalita, Bagalamukhi, Pratyangir, Shachi, Raudri, Houseni, Varad, Jaya, Tripura and Sumukhi. In an even Rāśi these 20 deities, respectively, are Daya, Megha, Chinnasi, Pisachini, Dhumavathi, Matangi, Bala, Bhadr, Arun, Anal, Pingal, Chuchchuk, Ghora, Vaarahi, Vaishnavi, Sita, Bhuvanesv6th, Bhairavi, Mars and Aparajit.  
22-23. Chaturvimshāńś. The Chaturvimshāńś (1/24th part of a Rāśi, or 1:15 each) distribution commences from Leo and Cancer, respectively, for an odd and an even Rāśi. In the case of an odd Rāśi the ruling deities repeat twice in the order of Skand, Parusdhar, Anal, Vishwa10th, Bhag, Mitr, Maya, Antaka, Vrisha-Dwaja, Govinda, Madan and Bhima. Reverse these from Bhima twice to know the deities for the Chaturvimshāńś in an even Rāśi.  
24-26. Saptavimshāńś (Nakshatraāńś, or Bhāńś). The Saptavimshāńś Lords are, respectively, the presiding deities of the 27 Nakshatras, as under: Dastra (Ashvini Kumar), Yama, Agni, Brahma, Moon, Isa, Adhiti, Jiva, Ahi, Pitar, Bhag, Aryama, Sun, Tvasht, Marut, Chakragni, Mitr, Vasava, Rakshasa, Varuna, Vishwadeva, Govinda, Vasu, Varuna, Ajap, Ahirbuddhnya and Pushya. These are for an odd Rāśis. Count these deities in a reverse order for an even Rāśi. The Saptavimshāńś distribution commences from Aries and other Movable Rāśis for all the 12 Rāśis.  
27-28. Trimshāńśa. The Trimshāńśa Lords for an odd Rāśi are Mars, Saturn, Jupiter, Mercury and Venus. Each of them in order rules 5, 5, 8, 7 and 5 degrees. The deities, ruling over the Trimshāńśaas, are, respectively, Agni, Vayu, Indra, Kuber and Varuna. In the case of an even Rāśi the quantum of Trimshāńśa, Planet lordship and deities get reversed.  
29-30. Khavedāńś (1/40th part of a Rāśi). For odd Rāśis count from Aries and for an even Rāśi from Libra in respect of Khavedāńśas (each of 45 of arc). Vishnu, Moon, M6thchi, Tvasht, Dhata, Shiva, Ravi, Yama, Yaksh, Gandharv, Kaal and Varuna repeat successively, as presiding deities, in the same order for all Rāśis.  
31-32. Akshavedāńś (1/45th part of a Rāśi). Aries, Leo and Sagittarius are the Rāśis, from which the distributions, respectively, commence for Movable, Immovable and Common Rāśis. In Movable Rāśis Brahma, Shiva and Vishnu; in Immovable Rāśis Shiva, Vishnu and Brahma and in Common Rāśis Vishnu, Brahma and Shiva repeat 15 times the presidentship over these Akshavedāńśas.  
33-41. Shashtiāńś (1/60th part of a Rāśi, or half a degree each). To calculate the Shashtiāńś Lord ignore the Rāśi position of a Planet and take the degrees etc. it traversed in that Rāśi. Multiply that figure by 2 and divide the degrees by 12. Add 1 to the remainder, which will indicate the Rāśi, in which the Shashtiāńś falls. The Lord of that Rāśi is the Planet, ruling the said Shashtiāńś. In odd Rāśis the names of Shashtiāńśas are 1. Ghora, 2. Rakshasa, 3. Deva, 4. Kuber, 5. Yaksh, 6. Kindar, 7. Bhrasht, 8. Kulaghna, 9. Garal, 10. Vahni, 11. Maya, 12. Purishak, 13. Apampathi, 14. Marutwan, 15. Kaal, 16. Sarpa, 17. Amrit, 18. Indu, 19. Mridu, 20. Komal, 21. Heramba, 22. Brahma, 23. Vishnu, 24. Maheshwara, 25. Deva, 26. Ardr, 27. Kalinas, 28. Kshitees, 29. Kamalakar, 30. Gulika, 31. Mrityu, 32. Kaal, 33. Davagni, 34. Ghora, 35. Yama, 36 Kantak, 37. Suddh, 38. Amrit, 39. PurnaMoon, 40. Vishadagdha, 41. Kulanas, 42. Vamshakshaya, 43. Utpat, 44. Kaal, 45. Saumya, 46. Komal, 47. Sheetal, 48. Karaladamshtr, 49. Moonamukhi, 50. Praveen, 51. Kaalpavak, 52. 2ndnayudh, 53. Nirmal, 54. Saumya, 55. Krur, 56. Atisheetal, 57. Amrit, 58. Payodhi, 59. Brahman, 60. MoonaRekha (InduRekha). The reverse is the order for even Rāśis in so much, as these names are cased. Planets in benefic Shashtiāńśas produce auspicious, while the opposite is true in case of Planets in malefic Shashtiāńśas.  
42-53. Varga Classification. Maitreya, explained now are the sum effects of classifications of different divisions (or Vargaas, so far narrated). These are four kinds, viz. Shad Varga, Sapth Varga, Dasha Varga and Shodasha Varga. In the Shad Varga classification the Varga designations are Kimshuk, Vyanjan, Chamar, Chatr and Kundal, according to a Planet being in 2 to 6 combinations of good Vargaas. Next is the Sapth Varga, in which these classifications continue in the same manner up to six combinations of good Vargaas, the 7th additional Varga getting classified, as Mukut. In the Dasha Varga scheme the designations commence from Parijata etc., such as 2 good Vargaas - Parijatha, 3 Uttama, 4 Gopur, 5 Leoasan, 6 Paravata, 7 Devaloka, 8 Brahmaloka, 9 Sakravahana and 10 Vargaas - Shridham. In the Shodasha Varga scheme the combinations of Vargaas go with designations thus: two good Vargaas - Bhedak, 3 Kusum, 4 Nagapushpa, 5 Kanduk, 6 Kerala, 7 Kalpa Vriksha, 8 Chandan Vana, 9 Purnachandra, 10 Uchchaisrava, 11 Dhanvantara, 12 Sunkant, 13 Vidrum, 14 Chakra-Leoasan, 15 Golok and 16 Vargaas - Śrī Vallbha. In these divisions the divisions, falling in the Planets exaltation Rāśi, Moolatrikona Rāśi, own Rāśi and the Rāśis, owned by the Lord of a Kendra from the Arudha Lagna, are all to be considered (as good Vargaas). The divisions of a combust Planet, defeated Planet, weak Planet and a Planet in bad Avasthas, like Sayan, be all ignored to be auspicious, for these destroy the good Yogas.  
Ch. 7. Divisional Considerations   
1-8. Use of the 16 Divisions. Now I will explain the use of these sixteen divisions. The physique from Lagna, wealth from Hora, happiness through co-born from Dreshkana, fortunes from Chaturthāńśa, sons and grandsons from Saptāńśa, spouse from Navāmśa, power (and position) from Dashāńśa, parents from Dvadashāńśa, benefits and adversities through conveyances from Shodashāńś, worship from Vimshāńś, learning from Chaturvimshāńś, strength and weakness from Saptavimshāńś, evil effects from Trimshāńśa, auspicious and inauspicious effects from Khavedāńś and all indications from both Akshavedāńś and Shashtiāńś: these are the considerations to be made through the respective Vargaas. The House, whose Lord is in a malefic Shashtiāńś, will diminish; so say Garga and others. The House, whose Lord is in a benefic Shodashāńś, flourish. This is how the 16 Vargaas are to be evaluated. 
9-12. After assessing the 20 point strength of the ascending degree, of other Houses and of the Planets, the good and bad effects be declared. I explain below the method of knowing the Vimsopak strength (20 point strength), just by knowing which an idea of the results of actions of this birth and of former birth will clearly emerge. The Planets from Sun on get full strength, when in exaltation, or in own Rāśi and are bereft of strength, when in the 7th (from exaltation). In between the strength be known by the rule of three process. In the case of a Planet, owning two Rāśis, distinction of placement in odd/even Rāśi identical with own Rāśi be made.  
13-16. Horā, Dreshkana and Trimshāńśa Effects. Jupiter, Sun and Mars give (pronounced) effects in the Hora of Sun. Moon, Venus and Saturn do so, when in Moon’s Horas; Mercury is effective in both the Horas. In the case of an even Rāśi the Hora of Moon will be powerful in effects, while Sun’s Hora in an odd Rāśi will be so. Full, medium and nil will be the effects, respectively, in the beginning middle and the end of a Hora. Similar applications be made for a Dreshkana, Turyāńśa, Navāmśa etc. As for Trimshāńśa effects, Sun is akin to Mars and Moon is akin to Venus. The effects, applicable to Rāśi, will apply to Trimshāńśa. 
17-19. Vimshopaka Bala. The Shad Vargaas consist of Rāśi, Hora, Dreshkana, Navāmśa, Dvadashāńśa and Trimshāńśa. The full Bala for each of the divisions, respectively, are 6, 2, 4, 5, 2 and 1. This is the Vimshopaka Bala, relating to Shad Varga division. Adding the Saptāńśa to the Shad Vargaas, we get Sapta Varga, the Vimshopaka Bala for which is 5, 2, 3, 2, 4, 2 and 1. These are gross strengths, while subtle ones should be understood by exact positions.  
20. Add Dashāńśa, Shodashāńś and Shashtiāńś to the said Sapta Varga Divisions to get the scheme of Dasha Varga. The Vimshopaka Bala in this context is 3 for Rāśi, 5 for Shashtiāńś and for the other 8 divisions 1 each.  
21-25. When the 16 divisions (Shodash Varga Scheme) are considered together, the Vimshopaka score goes thus: Hora 1, Trimsāńś 1, Dreshkana 1, Shodashāńś 2, Navāmśa 3, Rāśi 3, Shashtiāńś 4 and the rest of the nine divisions each a half. The Vimshopaka Bala remains as 20, only when the Planet is in own House Vargaas. Otherwise, the total strength from 20 declines to 18 in Pramudit Vargaas, to 15 in Shant Vargaas, to 10 in Svasth divisions, to 7 in Duhkhit Vargaas and to 5 in Khal Vargaas. (These figures are called Varga Vishwa)  
26-27. Vimshopaka Proportional Evaluation. Multiply the figure due to full strength for the division by the Varga Vishwa and divide by 20 to get the exact strength of the Planet. If the total is below 5, the Planet will not be capable of giving auspicious results. If it is above 5, but below 10, the Planet will yield some good effects. Later on up to 15 it is indicative of mediocre effect. A Planet with above 15 will yield wholly favourable effects.  
28-29. Other Sources of Strength. Maitreya, there are other kinds of sources, as I explain below. Planets in the 7th from Sun will be fully effective. One with an identical longitude in comp6thson to Sun’s will destroy the good effects. Rule of three process be applied to the Planet in between these positions. 30-32. Dasha effects with Vimshopaka Bala. Maitreya, after assessing the Vimshopaka Bala through the v6thous divisions, the rising and setting of the Planets be considered. The Vimshopaka Bala is classified under Purna, AtiPurna, Madhya, AtiMadhya, Heen, AtiHeen, Swalpa and AtiSwalp. Thus should be classified the Vimshopaka Bala and the Dasha period results declared accordingly.  
33-36. Kendras, Konas etc. defined. O Maitreya, listen to other matters, which I am explaining. The Kendras are specially known, as Lagna (the ascendent), 4th House, 7th House (the descendant) and 10th House (mid-heaven). 2nd, 5th, 8th and 11th House are Panapharas (succedents), while 3rd, 6th, 9th and 12th House are called Apoklimas (cadents). 5th and 9th House are known by the name Kona (or trine). Evil Houses, or Dusthana Houses are 6th, 8th and 12th House. Chaturasras are 4th and 8th House. 3rd, 6th, 10th and 11th House are Upachaya Houses.  
37-38. Names of Houses. 1st, 2nd, 3rd, 4th, 5th, 6th, 7th, 8th, 9th, 10th, 11th and 12th are in order the Houses. I explained these briefly and leave it to you to grasp more, according to your intelligence. As delivered by Lord Brahma, some further information is added thus (i.e. in the following verses).  
39-43. Indications from Houses. 9th House and the 9th from Sun deal with ones father. Whatever effects are to be known from the 10th and 11th House, be also known from similar Houses, counted from Sun. Whatever results are to be known from 4th, 1st, 2nd, 11th and 9th should also be known from the 4th of Moon, from Cancer Rāśi itself and from the 2nd, 11th and 9th from Moon, respectively. Whatever has to be known through 3rd House, be also analyzed through the 3rd from Mars. The 6th from Mercury be also considered in regard to indications, derivable from 6th House. The 5th from Jupiter, the 7th from Venus and both the 8th and 12th from Saturn stand for consideration, respectively, in respect of offspring, spouse and death. The Lord of the House is equally important, when estimating the indications of a particular House.  
Ch. 8. Aspects of the Rāśis 
1-3. Rāśi Aspects. O Maitreya, now detailed are the Aspects, emanating from the Rāśi Aries etc. Every Movable Rāśi aspects the 3 Fixed Rāśis, leaving the Fixed Rāśi adjacent to it. Every Fixed Rāśi gives Aspect to the 3 Movable Rāśis, barring the adjacent Movable Rāśi. And a Common Rāśi gives a Aspect to the other three Common Rāśis. The Planet in a Rāśi gives the same Aspect, as the Rāśi (in which the Planet is) does.  
4-5. Aspects of the Planets. A Planet in a Movable Rāśi gives a Aspect to the other 3 Fixed Rāśis, leaving the Fixed Rāśi next to it. A Planet in a Fixed Rāśi does not give a Aspect to the next Movable Rāśi, but the remaining 3 Movable Rāśis. The one in a Common Rāśi gives a Aspect to the remaining 3 Common Rāśis. Simultaneously a Planet in the Rāśi, that receives a Aspect, is also subjected to the Aspect concerned.  
6-9. Diagram of Aspects. As depicted by Lord Brahma, I now narrate the diagram of Aspects, so that Aspects are easily understood by a mere sight of the diagram. Draw a square, or a circle marking the 8 directions (4 corners and 4 quarters thereof). Mark the zodiacal Rāśis, as under: Aries and Taurus in East, Gemini in the North-East, Cancer and Leo in the North, Virgo in the North-West, Libra and Scorpio in the West, Sagittarius in the South-West, Capricorn and Aquarius in the South and Pisces in the South-East.  
Ch. 9. Evils at Birth   
1. O Brahmin, first of all estimate the evils and checking factors thereof through Lagna and then declare the effects of the 12 Houses.  
2. Evils, causing premature end, exist up to the 24th year of ones age. As such, no definite calculation of life span should be made till such year of age.  
3-6. Short-life Combinations (up to Sloka 23). Should Moon be in 6th, 8th, or 12th House and receives a Aspect from a malefic, the child will die soon. If in the process there be a Aspect from a benefic, it may live up to 8. If a benefic is retrograde in 6th, 8th, or 12th House, receiving a Aspect from a malefic, death will occur within a month of birth. This is true, only when Lagna is not occupied by a benefic. Should 5th House be occupied by Saturn, Mars and Sun jointly, (early) death of mother and brother will come to pass. Mars, placed in 1st, or in 8th House and be conjunct with Saturn, or Sun, or receiving a Aspect from a malefic, being bereft of a Aspect from a benefic, will prove a source of (immediate) death.  
7-11. If Saturn and Mars give a Aspect to Lagna, as the lumin6thes are conjunct with Rahu (elsewhere), the child will live a fortnight. Immediate death of the child along with its mother will occur, if Saturn is in 10th House, Moon in 6th House and Mars in 7th House. One will immediately go to the abode of Yama, if Saturn is in 1st House, while Moon and Jupiter are in their order in 8th and 3rd House. Only a month will be the span of ones life, who had Sun in 9th House, Mars in 7th House and Jupiter and Venus in 11th House. All Planets (any Planet) in 12th House will be the source of a short life, specifically the lumin6thes, Venus and Rahu. But the Aspect of these four Planets (on 12th House) will counteract such evils.  
12. Moon is capable of causing early end, if she is with a malefic in 7th, 8th, or 1st House and unrelated to a benefic.  
13. Early death will come to pass, if there be a birth in the morning, or evening junctions, or in a Hora, ruled by Moon, or in Gandanta, while Moon and malefics occupy Kendras from Lagna.  
14. Definition of Sandhya. 3 Ghatis before the sight of the semi disc (half) of the rising Sun and a similar duration, following Sun’s set, are called, as morning twilight and evening twilight, respectively. 
15. Early Death. Should all the malefics be in the oriental half, while benefics are in the occidental half, early death of one born in Scorpio will follow. In this case there is no need of any rethinking. 
16. Malefic in 12th and 6th House, or in 8th and 2nd House, while Lagna is hemmed between other malefics, will bring early death.  
17. Malefics, occupying 1st and 7th House, while Moon is conjunct with a malefic with no relief from a benefic, will also cause premature death.  
18. Early death will be inflicted on the native, if decreasing Moon is in 1st House, while malefics capture 8th House and a Kendra. There is no doubt about that.  
19. Moon in 1st, 8th, 12th, or 7th House and hemmed between malefics will confer premature death.  
20. Should Moon be in 1st House, hemmed between malefics, while 7th, or 8th House has a malefic in it, he will face immediate death along with his mother.  
21. Should Saturn, Sun and Mars be in 12th, 9th and 8th House without Aspect from a benefic, the child will face instant death.  
22. With a malefic in 7th House, or in the rising Dreshkana, while decreasing Moon is in 1st House, death be experienced early.  
23. The life span of the child will be either 2 months, or 6 months only, if all Planets devoid of strength are relegated to Apoklima Houses.  
24. Evils to Mother (up to Sloka 33). The mother of the native will incur evils (will die soon), if Moon at birth receives a Aspect from three malefics. Benefics, giving a Aspect to Moon, will bring good to the mother.  
25. Should 2nd House be occupied by Rahu, Mercury, Venus, Sun and Saturn, the child's birth has been after its fathers death, while even the mother will face early death.  
26. If Moon is in the 7th, or the 8th from a malefic, be herself with a malefic and receives a Aspect from a strong malefic, predict mothers end to be early.  
27. The child will not live on mothers milk, but on that of she-goat, if Sun is exalted, or debilitated in 7th House.  
28. Should a malefic be in the 4th, identical with an inimical Rāśi, counted from Moon, while there is no benefic in a Kendra, the child will lose its mother in a premature manner. 29. Malefics in 6th and 12th House will bring evils to mother. The child's father will receive similar effects, if 4th and 10th House are captured by malefics.  
30. Mercury in 2nd House, while malefics occupy 1st and 12th House: this Yoga will destroy the entire family.  
31. Jupiter, Saturn and Rahu, respectively, posited in 1st, 2nd and 3rd House will cause mothers death early.  
32. Doubtlessly the mother will give up the child, if it has malefics in Konas, counted from the decreasing Moon. No benefic shall be conjunct with the said malefics.  
33. If Mars and Saturn are together in a Kendra with reference to Moon and occupy one and the same Navāmśa, the child will have two mothers. Yet it will be short-lived.  
34. Evil to Father (up to Sloka 42). Ones father will incur early death, if Saturn, Mars and Moon in their orders are in 1st, 7th and 6th House.  
35. The native will at the time of his marriage lose his father, if Jupiter is in 1st House, while Saturn, Sun, Mars and Mercury are together in 2nd House.  
36. Early loss of father will take place, if Sun is with a malefic, or is hemmed between malefics, as there is another malefic in the 7th from Sun.  
37. Remote will be the possibility of ones father sustaining, if Sun is in 7th, while Mars is in 10th and Rahu is in 12th House.  
38. Early and troubled will be ones fathers death, if Mars is in 10th House identical with his enemy Rāśi.  
39. Moon in 6th House, Saturn in 1st House and Mars in 7th House: this array of heavenly bodies at birth will not ensure a long span of life for the father.  
40. If Sun receives a Aspect from Saturn and be in Aries, or in Scorpio Navāmśa, the father would have given up the family before birth of the child, or would have passed away.  
41. If 4th, 10th and 12th House are all occupied by malefics, both the parents will leave the child to its own fate and wander from place to place.  
42. The father will not see the native till his (the natives) 23rd year, if Rahu and Jupiter are together in an inimical Rāśi identical with 1st, or 4th House.  
43-45. Parents. Sun is the indicator of father for all beings, while the mother is indicated by Moon. Should Sun receive a Aspect from one, or more malefics, or be hemmed between them, this will cause evils to father. Similarly Moon be considered in respect of mother. Malefics in the 6th, the 8th, or the 4th from Sun will bring inauspicious results about the father. Malefics in such places from Moon will be adverse for the mother. The strength, or otherwise of the occupants concerned be suitably estimated.  
Ch. 10. Antidotes for Evils  
1. Those are the evils (due to a native). I now narrate the antidotes for such evils as well, which will be helpful to assess the extent of inauspiciousness.  
2. Should one among Mercury, Jupiter and Venus be in an angle from Lagna, all evils are destroyed, as Sun eliminates darkness.  
3. Just as a single reverential obeisance before Lord Shiva, the Trident holder frees one from all sins, a single, but strong Jupiter in Lagna will ward off all the evils.  
4. Lagna Lord is singly capable of counteracting all evils, if he is strongly placed in an angle, just as Lord Shiva, the holder of the Bow destroyed the three cities, built of gold, silver and iron for the demons by Maya.  
5. All evils are destroyed, if a benefic aspects Lagna of one born during the night in the bright half. Similarly a malefics Aspect on Lagna of one born during day time in the dark half.  
6. Sun in 12th will confer a hundred-year life span on one born in Libra Lagna.  
7. It will prove auspicious for the mother as well as the native, if Mars joins, or is aspected by Jupiter.  
8. If malefics are surrounded by benefics, while angles, or trines are themselves benefic-occupied, evils disappear soon. Not only this, evils will not follow from the Houses concerned. 
