
Brihat Parashara Hora Sashtra by Rishi Parashara
Page 8
Ch. 61. Effects of Pratyantar Dashas in Antar Dashas  
1. By multiplying the years etc. of the Antar Dasha of the Planets separately by the Dasha years of each Planet and by dividing the product by the total span of the Vimshott6th Dasha, namely 120 years, we will arrive at the Pratyantar Dasha of each Planet. 
2. Sun-Sun (Pratyantar Dasha of Sun in the Antar Dasha of Sun). Argument with other persons, loss of wealth, distress to wife, headache etc. The above are general effects. Such inauspicious effects will not be produced, if Sun is in a Trikona etc., if Sun is the Lord of an auspicious House, or is in a auspicious House and in a benefic Varga. All other Pratyanta effects should be judged in this manner. 
3. …-Moon. Excitement, quarrels, loss of wealth, mental agony etc. 
4. …-Mars. Danger from the king and from weapons, imprisonment and distress from enemies and fire. 
5. …-Rahu. Disorder of phlegm, danger from weapons, loss of wealth, destruction of a kingdom and mental agony. 
6. …-Jupiter. Victory, increase in wealth, gains of gold, garments, conveyances etc. 
7 …-Saturn. Loss of wealth, distress to cattle, excitement, diseases etc. 
8. …-Mercury. Affectionate relations with kinsmen, availability of good food, gains of wealth, religious-mindedness, reverence from the king. 
9. …..Ketu. Danger to life, loss of wealth, danger from the king, trouble with enemies 10. …-Venus. Moderate effects, or some gains of wealth may be expected. 
11. …Moon-Moon. Acquisition of land, wealth and property, reverence from the king and availability of sweetish preparations. 
12. …-Mars. Wisdom and discretion, reverence from the people, increase in wealth, enjoyments to kinsmen, but there will be danger from an enemy. 
13. …-Rahu. Well-being, gain of wealth from the king and danger of death, if Rahu is conjunct with a malefic. 
14. …-Jupiter. Enjoyments, increase in dignity and glory, gain of knowledge through the preceptor, acquisition of a kingdom and acquisition of gems etc. 
15. …-Saturn. Bilious troubles, loss of wealth and name and fame. 
16. …-Mercury. Birth of a son, acquisition of a horse and other conveyances, success in education, progress, gain of white garments and grains. 
17. …-Ketu. Quarrels with Brahmins, fear of premature death, loss of happiness and distress all-round. 
18. …-Venus. Gain of wealth, enjoyments, birth of a daughter, availability of sweet preparations and cordial relations with all. 
19. …-Sun. Gain of happiness, grains and garments, victories everywhere. 
20. ….Mars-Mars. Danger from enemies, quarrels and fear of premature death on account of blood diseases. 
21. …-Rahu. Destruction of wealth and kingdom (fall of government), unpalatable food and quarrels with the enemy. 
22. …-Jupiter. Loss of intelligence, distress, sorrows to children, fear of premature death, negligence, quarrels and no fulfillment of any ambition. 
23. …-Saturn. Destruction of the employer, distress, loss of wealth, danger from enemies, anxiety, quarrels and sorrows. 
24. …-Mercury. Loss of intelligence, loss of wealth, fevers and loss of grains, garments and friends. 
25. …-Ketu. Distress from diseases, lethargy, premature death, danger from the king and weapons. 
26. …-Venus. Distress from Chandal, sorrows, danger from the king and from weapons, dysentery and vomiting. 
27. …-Sun. Increase in landed property and wealth, satisfaction, visits of friends, happiness all-round. 
28. …-Moon. Gains of white garments etc. from the southern direction, success in all ventures. 
29. ….Rahu-Rahu. Imprisonment, disease, danger of injuries from weapons. 
30. …-Jupiter. Reverence everywhere, acquisition of conveyances, like elephants etc., gain of wealth. 
31. …-Saturn. Rigorous imprisonment, loss of enjoyments, danger from enemies, affliction with rheumatism. 
32. …-Mercury. Gain in all ventures, abnormal gain through wife. 
33. …-Ketu. Loss of intelligence, danger from enemies, obstacles, loss of wealth, quarrels, excitement. 
34. …-Venus. Danger from a Yogini, danger from the king, loss of conveyances, availability of unpalatable food, loss of a wife, sorrow in the family. 
35. …-Sun. Danger from enemies, fevers, distress to children, fear of premature death, negligence. 
36. …-Moon. Excitement, quarrels, worries, loss of reputation, fear, distress to father. 37. …-Mars. Septic boil in the anus (Bhagandhar), distress, due to a bite and pollution of blood, loss of wealth, excitement. 
38. …Jupiter-Jupiter. Acquisition of gold, increase in wealth etc. 
39. …-Saturn. Increase in lands, conveyances and grains. 
40. …-Mercury. Success in the educational sphere, acquisition of clothes and gems, like pearls etc., visits of friends. 
41. …-Ketu. Danger from water and thieves. 
42. …-Venus. Several kinds of learning, gain of gold, clothes, ornaments, well-being and satisfaction. 
43. …-Sun. Gain from the king, friends and parents, reverence everywhere. 
44. …-Moon. No distress, gain of wealth and conveyances, success in ventures. 
45. …-Mars. Danger from weapons, pain in anus, burning in the stomach, indigestion, distress from enemies. 
46. …-Rahu. Antagonism with menials (Chandaldhi) and loss of wealth and distress through them. 
47. ….Saturn-Saturn. Physical distress, quarrels, danger from menials. 
48. …-Mercury. Loss of intelligence, quarrels, dangers, anxiety about availability of food, loss of wealth, danger from enemy. 
49. …-Ketu. Imprisonment in the camp of the enemy, loss of luster, hunger, anxiety and agony. 
50. …-Venus. Fulfillment of ambitions, well-being in the family, success in ventures and gains there from. 
51. …-Sun. Conferment of authority by the king, quarrels in the family, fevers. 
52. …-Moon. Development of intelligence, inauguration of big a venture, loss of luster, extravagant expenditure, association with many women. 
53. …-Mars. Loss of valor, distress to son, danger from fire and enemy, distress from bile and wind. 
54. …-Rahu. Loss of wealth, clothes, land, going away to foreign lands, fear of death. 55. …-Jupiter. Inability to prevent losses, caused by women, quarrels, excitement. 
56. ….Mercury-Mercury. Gain of intelligence, education, wealth, clothes etc. 
57. …-Ketu. Coarse food, stomach troubles, eye troubles, distress from bilious and blood disorders. 
58. …-Venus. Gains from a northern direction, loss of cattle, acquisition of authority from government. 
59. …-Sun. Loss of splendor and distress through diseases, distress in the heart. 
60. …-Moon. Marriage, gain of wealth and property, birth of a daughter, enjoyments all-round. 
61. …-Mars. Religious-mindedness, increase in wealth, danger from fire and enemies, gain of red clothes, injury from a weapon. 
62. …-Rahu. Quarrels, danger from wife, or some other woman, danger from the king. 63. …-Jupiter. Acquisition of a kingdom, conferment of authority by the king, reverence from the king, education, intelligence. 
64. …-Saturn. Bilious and windy troubles, injuries to the body, loss of wealth. 
65. ….Ketu-Ketu. Sudden disaster, going away to foreign lands, loss of wealth. 
66. …-Venus. Loss of wealth through a non-Hindu king, eye troubles, headache, loss of cattle. 
67. …-Sun. Antagonism with friends, premature death, defeat, exchange of arguments. 68. …-Moon. Loss of grains, physical distress, misunderstanding, dysentery. 
69. …-Mars. Injury from weapons, distress from fire, danger from menials and enemies. 70. …-Rahu. Danger from women and enemies, distress, caused by menials. 
71. …-Jupiter. Loss of friends, wealth and garments, opprobrium in the house, troubles from everywhere. 
72. …-Saturn. Death of cattle and friends, physical distress, very meager gain of wealth. 
73. …-Mercury. Loss of understanding, excitement, failure in education, dangers, failure in all ventures. 
74. ….Venus-Venus. Gains of white clothes, conveyances, gems, like pearls etc., association with beautiful damsel. 
75. …-Sun. Rheumatic fever, headache, danger from the king and enemies and meager gain of wealth. 
76. …-Moon. Birth of a daughter, gain of clothes etc. from the king, acquisition of authority. 
77. …-Mars. Blood and bile troubles, quarrels, many kinds of distresses. 
78. …-Rahu. Quarrels with wife, danger, distress from the king and enemies. 
79. …-Jupiter. Acquisition of kingdom, wealth, garments, gems, ornaments and conveyance, like elephants etc. 
80. …-Saturn. Acquisition of donkey, camel, goat, iron, grains, sesame seeds, physical pains. 
81. …-Mercury. Gains of wealth, knowledge, authority from the king, gain of money, distributed by others. 
82. …-Ketu. Premature death, going away from homeland, gains of wealth at times. Ch. 62. Effects of Sukshmantar Dashas in Pratyantar Dashas  
1. The Sukshmantar Dasha is arrived at by multiplying the periods of Pratyantar Dasha separately for each Planet by the Dasha years of that Planet and then by dividing the product by 120. 
2….. Sun-Sun (Sukshm Dasha of Sun in Pratyantar Dasha of Sun). Going away from homeland, danger of death, loss of position, losses all-round. 
3. …-Moon. Devotion towards deities and Brahmins, interest in pious deeds, affectionate relations with friends. 
4. …-Mars. Indulgence in sinful deeds, distress from cruel enemies, bleeding 
5. …-Rahu. Danger from thieves, fire and poison, defeat in war, religious inclination. 
6. …-Jupiter. Recognition by government, respected by government employees, becoming favourite of the king. 
7. …-Saturn. Causing trouble to respected persons and Brahmins by theft and by other bold deeds, going away from ones own place, mental agony. 
8. …-Mercury. Gains of fancy garments, association with a beautiful damsel, sudden success in ventures. 
9. …-Ketu. Achievement of glory through wife and employees, loss of wealth, comforts from servants. 
10. …-Venus. Happiness from son, friends and wife, acquisition of many kinds of properties. 
11. ….Moon-Moon. Gain of ornaments and land, reverence, recognition from the king, anger, glory. 
12. …-Mars. Distress, antagonism with the enemy, stomach troubles, death of father, troubles, due to imBalaance of wind and bile. 
13. …-Rahu. Disharmony with friends and kinsmen, going away from homeland, loss of wealth, imprisonment. 
14. …-Jupiter. Opulence and glory with royal symbols, birth of a son, gain of property, enjoyments all-round. 
15. …-Saturn. Wrath of the king, loss of wealth in business dealings, danger from thieves and Brahmins. 
16. …-Mercury. Reverence from the king, gain of wealth, gain of conveyance from a foreign land, increase in the number of children. 
17. …-Ketu. Loss in the livelihood, earned by sale etc., grains, medicines, cattle etc., danger from fire and the Sun’s rays (sun-stroke). 
18. …-Venus. Marriage, gain of a kingdom, land, garments, ornaments, reputation etc.
19. …-Sun. Troubles, losses in ventures, destruction of grains and cattle, physical distress. 
20. ….Mars-Mars. Sorrows on account of loss of lands, epilepsy, imprisonment, unhappiness. 
21. …-Rahu. Physical distress, danger from the people (due to unpopul6thty), loss of wife and children, danger from fire. 
22. …-Jupiter. Devotion towards deities, Mantra Siddhi, reverence from the people, enjoyments. 
23. …-Saturn. Release from imprisonment, happiness on account of wealth, gains of clothes and servants. 
24. …-Mercury. Comforts of Chatr, Chamar etc. (receiving respect, as that of a king), breathing troubles. 
25. …-Ketu. Indulgence in undesirable deeds at the instance of others, one always remains filthy. 
26. …-Venus. Enjoyment with women of choice, gain of wealth, food etc. 
27. …-Sun. Wrath of the king, distress through Brahmins, failure in ventures, odium in public (Loka Nindha). 
28. …-Moon. Piousness, gain of wealth, devotion towards deities and Brahmins, danger from diseases. 
29. ….Rahu-Rahu. Tendering to create turbulence by people, lack of wisdom in performance of duties, affliction of the mind. 
30. …-Jupiter. Affliction with a chronic disease, poverty, but revered by the people and the religious-mindedness. 
31. …-Saturn. Gain of wealth through unfair means, wicked, or mean nature, performing other persons duties, undesirable association. 
32. …-Mercury. Increase in desires for sexual acts with women, eloquence, hunger, physical distress. 
33. …-Ketu. Politeness, loss of reputation, imprisonment, cold heartedness, loss of public money. 
34. …-Venus. Freedom from imprisonment, gain of position and wealth. 
35. …-Sun. Settling down in foreign lands, affliction with Gulma, even temperament, comforts of conveyances. 
36. …-Moon. Gain of gems (money), wealth, education, attachment to prayers, good behavior and devotion towards deities. 
37. …-Mars. Fleeing after defeat, anger, imprisonment, indulgence in thefts and stealing. 
38. ….Jupiter-Jupiter. Banishment of sorrows, increase in wealth, performing Havan, devotion to Lord Shiva, gains of conveyance, marked with royal symbols. 
39. …-Saturn. Obstacles in fasting, agony, foreign journeys, loss of wealth, antagonism with kinsmen. 
40. …-Mercury. Success in education, increase in intelligence, reverence from the people (popul6thty), gains of wealth, all sorts of enjoyments and comforts at home. 
41. …-Ketu. Knowledge, glory, learning, study of Shastras, worship of Lord Shiva, Havan, devotion toward preceptor. 
42. …-Venus. Recovery from diseases, enjoyments, gain of wealth, happiness from wife and children. 
43. …-Sun. Troubles of wind and bile, stomach pains through imBalaance of phlegm and Rasas. 
44. …-Moon. Glory with umbrella with royal symbols, celebrations on the birth of a son, distress in eyes and stomach. 
45. …-Mars. Administration of poison by wife, imprisonment, danger from diseases, going away to foreign lands, confusion and misunderstandings. 
46. …-Rahu. Danger from thieves, snakes and scorpions, diseases and distress. 
47. ….Saturn-Saturn. Loss of wealth, diseases, like rheumatism etc., destruction of the family, taking meals separately from the family, full of sorrows. 
48. …-Mercury. Profits in business, progress in education, increase in wealth and lands. 
49. …-Ketu. Turbulence by thieves, leprosy, loss of livelihood, physical pains. 
50. …-Venus. Opulence and glory, learning the use of weapons, birth of a son, coronation, good health and fulfillment of all ambitions. 
51. …-Sun. Wrath of the king, quarrels in the family, physical distress. 
52. …-Moon. Development of intelligence, inauguration of a big project, loss of luster, extravagance, happiness from wife and children. 
53. …-Mars. Loss of luster, excitement, burning in the stomach, misunderstanding, quarrels and wind and bile disorders. 
54. …-Rahu. Death of parents, agony, extravagance, failure in ventures. 
55. …-Jupiter. Acquisition of gold coins, reverence from the public, increase in wealth and grains, acquisition of Chatr with royal symbols. 
56. ….Mercury-Mercury. Dawn of fortune, reverence from the king, increase in wealth and property and affectionate relations with all. 
57. …-Ketu. Danger from fire, agony, distress to wife, coarse food and immoral tendencies. 
58. …-Venus. Gain of conveyances, wealth, grains, produced in water, good repute and enjoyments. 
59. …-Sun. Injuries, wrath of the king, confusion in the mind, diseases, loss of wealth, ridicule in public. 
60. …-Moon. Good fortune, stability of mind, reverence from the king, gains of property, visits of friends and the preceptor. 
61. …-Mars. Danger from fire and poison, idiocy, poverty, confusion of mind, excitement. 
62. …-Rahu. Danger from fire and snakes and the victory over an enemy (with difficulty), opprobrium from goblins (evil, mischievous spirit). 
63. …-Jupiter. Construction of a house, interest in charities, comforts and enjoyments, increase in opulence, gain of wealth from the king. 
64. …-Saturn. Profits in business, progress in education and increase in wealth, marriage, circumambience of comprehensiveness. 
65. ….Ketu-Ketu. Happiness from wife and children, physical troubles, poverty, begging. 
66. …-Venus. Freedom from diseases, gains of wealth, devotion towards Brahmins and the preceptor, union with members of the family. 
67. …-Sun. Quarrels, loss of land, residence in foreign lands, disaster upon friends. 68. …-Moon. Promotion in service, victory in war, good reputation in public. 
69. …-Mars. Danger of falling down from a horse etc., distress from thieves and the wicked, suffering from Gulma and headache. 
70. …-Rahu. Destruction of wife, father etc., defamation, due to association with a wicked woman, vomiting, blood pollution, bilious diseases. 
71. …-Jupiter. Antagonism with the enemy, increase in property and opulence, distress, due to losses in cattle, wealth and agricultural production. 
72. …-Saturn. Imaginary distress, little comfort, fasting, antagonism with wife, indulgence in falsehood. 
73. …-Mercury. Union and separation from many kinds of people, distress to the enemy, increase in wealth and property. 
74. ….Venus-Venus. Destruction of enemies, enjoyments, construction of temples of Lord Shiva etc. and reservoirs. 
75. …-Sun. Agony in mind and heart, confusion of mind, wanderings, both losses and gains at different times. 
76. …-Moon. Sound health, increase in wealth, success in ventures through business dealings, progress in education and increase of intelligence. 
77. …-Mars. Idiocy, danger from an enemy, going away from ones homeland, danger from diseases. 
78. …-Rahu. Danger from fire and snakes, destruction of kinsmen, resignation from position (service etc.). 
79. …-Jupiter. Success in ventures, increase in wealth and agricultural production, abnormal profits from purchase and sale business. 
80. …-Saturn. Distress from an enemy, sorrows, destruction of cattle, loss of persons, belonging to the Gotra of the native and elders (preceptors). 
81. …-Mercury. Increase in wealth with the assistance of kinsmen, gain of wealth through business, happiness from wife and children. 
82. …-Ketu. Danger from fire, distress from diseases, distress in mouth, eyes and forehead, loss of accumulated wealth, mental agony. 
Ch. 63. Effects of Prana Dashas in Sukshma Dashas 
1. If we multiply the Sukshma Dasha spans by the Dasha years of each Planet and divide the product by 120, we will get the Prana Dasha. 
2….. Sun-Sun. Interest in unnatural sexual intercourse, danger from thieves, fire and the king, physical distress. 
3. …-Moon. Enjoyments, availability of good food, development of intelligence, opulence and glory, like that of a king, by the beneficence of generous people. 
4. …-Mars. Antagonism with the king with the connivance of others, dangers and great losses. 
5. …-Rahu. Hunger, danger from poison, loss of wealth, as a result of punishment by the king. 
6. …-Jupiter. Success in many educational spheres, gain of wealth, success in ventures, as a result of the exchange of visits with the king and Brahmins. 
7. …-.Saturn. Imprisonment, death, excitement, obstacles and losses in ventures. 
8. …-.Mercury. Feeding from the kings kitchen, acquisition of Chatr and Chamar with royal symbols, attainment of the position of a high dignitary in government. 
9. …-.Ketu. Loss of wealth, due to quarrels with the preceptor (elders), wife and kinsmen. 
10. …-Venus. Recognition, or reverence from the king, increase in wealth, happiness from wife and children, enjoyments from eating and drinking. 
11. ….Moon-Moon. Happiness from wife and children, gain of wealth and clothes, Yoga Sidhi. 
12. …-Mars. Consumption, leprosy, destruction of kinsmen, bleeding, creation of turbulence by friends and goblins. 
13. …-Rahu. Danger from snakes, creation of turbulance by evil spirits, weakness of eyesight, confusion of mind. 
14. …-Jupiter. Growth of religious-mindedness, forgiveness, devotion towards deities and Brahmins, good fortune, meeting with near and dear ones. 
15. …-Saturn. Unexpected and sudden physical distress, creation of troubles by enemies, weakness of eyesight, gain of wealth. 
16. …-Mercury. Gift of Chamar and Chatr by the king, acquisition of a kingdom, even-mindedness in people. 
17. …-Ketu. Danger from weapons, from fire, from an enemy and from poison, stomach troubles, separation from wife and children. 
18. …-Venus. Acquisition of friends and wife, gain of wealth from foreign lands, all kinds of enjoyments. 
19. …-Sun. Brutality, increase in anger, fear of death, agony, going away from the homeland, dangers. 
20. ….Mars-Mars. Quarrels with the enemy, imprisonment, bilious and blood pollution troubles. 
21. …-Rahu. Separation from wife and children, distress, as a result of oppression by kinsmen, fear of death, poison. 
22. …-Jupiter. Devotion towards deities, gain of wealth, competence in Mantra rituals.
23. …-Saturn. Danger from fire, death, loss of wealth, loss of position, but good relations with kinsmen. 
24. …-Mercury. Gains of splendid garments, ornaments, marriage. 
25. …-Ketu. Fear of falling down from a high place, eye troubles, danger from snakes, loss of reputation. 
26. …-Venus. Gain of wealth, reverence amongst people, enjoyment of many kinds of luxuries. 
27. …-Sun. Fevers, lunacy, loss of wealth, wrath of the king, poverty. 
28. …-Moon. Comforts of good food and garments, distress from heat and cold. 
29. ….Rahu-Rahu. Loss of taste in eating, danger from poison, loss of wealth through rashness. 
30. …-Jupiter. Physical well-being, fearlessness, gain of conveyance and quarrels with menials. 
31. …-Saturn. Danger from fire, diseases, loss of wealth through menials, imprisonment. 
32. …-Mercury. Devotion towards the preceptor and increase of wealth through his beneficence, good qualities and well cultured. 
33. …-Ketu. Antagonism with wife and children, going away from home, loss of wealth through rashness. 
34. …-Venus. Acquisition of Chatr, Chamar, conveyances etc., success in all ventures, worship of Lord Shiva, construction of a house. 
35. …-Sun. Affliction with piles, wrath of the king, loss of cattle. 
36. …-Moon. Development of mental powers and intelligence, popul6thty, visits of preceptors, danger of committing sins. 
37. …-Mars. Dangers from menials and fire, loss of position, disaster, filthiness and meanness. 
38. …Jupiter-Jupiter. Happiness, increase in wealth, performance of Havan, worship of Lord Shiva, acquisition of Chatr and conveyances. 
39. …-Saturn. Failure in fasting, unhappiness, going away to foreign lands, loss of wealth, antagonism with kinsmen. 
40. …-Mercury. Progress in education, increase in intelligence, happiness to wife and children, popul6thty, gain of wealth. 
41. …-Ketu. Opulence and glory, learnedness, gain of knowledge of Shastras, worship of Lord Shiva, performance of Havan, devotion towards preceptor. 
42. …-Venus. Freedom from diseases, enjoyments, increase in wealth, happiness from wife and children. 
43. …-Sun. Disorders of wind, bile and phlegm, pains, due to disorders of juices in the body. 
44. …-Moon. Acquisition of Chatr with royal symbol, opulence and glory, increase in children, eye and stomach troubles. 
45. …Mars. Danger of administration of poison by wife, imprisonment, foreign journeys, confusion of mind. 
46. …Rahu. Distress from diseases, troubles from thieves, danger from snakes, scorpions etc. 
47. ….Saturn-Saturn: Loss of luster, due to fevers, leprosy, stomach troubles, danger of death from fire. 
48. …-Mercury. Gain of wealth and grains, profits in business, reverence, devotion towards deities and Brahmins. 
49. …-Ketu. Death-like distress, creation of turbulence by evil spirits, insult from a woman, other than ones wife. 
50. …-Venus. Enjoyments through wealth, son and beneficence of the king, performance of Havanas, marriage etc. 
51. …-Sun. Troubles in the eyes and forehead, danger from snakes and enemies, loss of wealth, distress. 
52. …-Moon. Sound health, birth of a son, relief, thriving strength, devotion towards deities and Brahmins. 
53. …-Mars. Affliction with Gulma, danger from enemy, danger of death during hunting, danger from snakes, from fire and from poison. 
54. …-Rahu. Going away from the homeland, danger from the king, bewitchment, taking of poison, troubles from wind and bile. 
55. …-Jupiter. Attainment of the position of a Commander in the Army, gain of land, association with ascetics, reverence from the king. 
56. ….Mercury-Mercury. Increase in enjoyments, wealth and religious-mindedness, even-mindedness in all living beings. 
57. …-Ketu. Danger from thieves, from fire and from poison, death-like suffering. 
58. …-Venus. Supremacy over others, increase in wealth, reputation and religious-mindedness, devotion to Lord Shiva, happiness from son. 
59. …-Sun. Agony, fevers, lunacy, affectionate relations with wife and kinsmen, receipt of stolen property. 
60. …-Moon. Happiness from wife, birth of a daughter, gain of wealth and enjoyments all-round. 
61. …-Mars. Tendency to indulge in nef6thous activities, pain in eyes, teeth and stomach, piles, danger from death. 
62. …-Rahu. Gain of clothes, ornaments and wealth, separation from ones own people, antagonism with Brahmins, delirium. 
63. …-Jupiter. Sublimately, progress in education, increase in wealth and good qualities, profits in business. 
64. …-Saturn. Danger of death from thieves, poverty, beggary. 
65. ….Ketu-Ketu. Danger of fall from a conveyance, quarrels with the enemy, committing a murder inadvertently. 
66. …-Venus. Gain of land and conveyance, happiness, destruction of enemy, increase in cattle wealth. 
67. …-Sun. Danger from fire and enemy, loss of wealth, mental agony, death-like suffering. 
68. …-Moon. Devotion towards deities and Brahmin, journeys to distant places, gain of wealth and happiness, eye and ear troubles. 
69. …-Mars. Bilious troubles, enlargement of veins, delirium, antagonism with kinsmen. 70. …-Rahu. Antagonism with son and wife, going away from home, loss in ventures, due to rashness. 
71. …-Jupiter. Injuries from weapons, wounds, heart disease, separation from wife and children. 
72. …-Saturn. Confusion of mind, tendencies towards nef6thous deeds, imprisonment on account of addictions (in drugs etc.), distress. 
73. …-Mercury. Enjoyments of bed, perfumery, ornaments and sandal, good food and availability of all kinds of comforts. 
74…... Venus-Venus. Learning, devotion to deities, satisfaction, gain of wealth, increase in the number of children. 
75. …-Sun. Good reputation in public, loss of happiness in respect of children, heat troubles. 
76. …-Moon. Devotion towards deities, competence, relief by the application of Mantras, increase in wealth and fortune. 
77. …-Mars. Fevers, wounds, ringworms, itches, devotion towards deities and Brahmins. 
78. …-Rahu. Distress from an enemy, eye and stomach troubles, antagonism with friends. 
79. …-Jupiter. Good longevity, sound health, happiness from wealth, wife and children, acquisition of Chatr and conveyances. 
80. …-Saturn. Danger from the king, loss of happiness, critical disease, controversy with menials. 
81. …-Mercury. Satisfaction, reverence from the king, gains of land and wealth from many directions, increase in enthusiasm. 
82. …-Ketu. Loss of life, wealth and reputation, only some money is left for charities and sustenance. 
Ch. 64. Effects of Antar Dashas in the Kala Chakra 
1. Mahārśi Parashara said. Now I am going to describe to you the effects of Antar Dashas in the Kala Chakra Dasha, as related by Lord Shiva to the Goddess Parvati. 
2. Dasha of Aries Ańś. There will be wounds and fever in the Antar Dasha of Mars in the Dasha of Aries Ańś. In the same Dasha and Antar Dasha of the Rāśis, owned by Mercury, Venus, Moon and Jupiter, all kinds of happiness will be enjoyed. Danger from an enemy will be experienced in the Antar Dasha of Sun. 
3-5. Dasha of Taurus Ańś. Effects, like quarrels and diseases, will be experienced in Antar Dasha of Saturn. There will be gains of education and physical felicity in the Antar Dasha of Jupiter, going away from home, death, or distress from fevers in the Antar Dasha of Mars and gains of garments, happy association with women in the Antar Dashas of the Rāśis, owned by Venus and Mercury. Danger from the king and violent animals may be expected in the Antar Dasha of Rāśi, owned by Sun. 
6-10. Dasha of Gemini Ańś. The effects in the Antar Dashas of the Rāśis concerned will be, as follows. Venus - gain of wealth and garments. Mars- death of parents, danger, fever, wounds and travels to distant places. Jupiter - increase in intelligence, success in education, opulence and glory, popul6thty and affection towards others. Saturn - foreign journeys, diseases, fear of death, loss of wealth and kinsmen. Mercury - success in education, gains of garments etc., happiness from wife and children and reverence from all quarters. 
11-16. Dasha of Cancer Ańś. The effects in the various Antar Dashas of the Rāśis concerned will be, as follows. Moon - happiness from wife and children, gain of wealth and reverence from the public. Sun - danger from enemies, animals and the royal family, mental agony and fear of diseases. Mercury and Venus - happiness from wife, children and friends, increase in wealth, popularity and name and fame. Mars- danger from poison, weapons and diseases, like fever. Jupiter - gains of wealth, physical felicity, honors from the king. Saturn - rheumatism, danger from snakes and scorpions and distress of all kinds. 
17-21. Dasha of Leo Ańś. … Mars- diseases of the mouth, bilious fever and danger from weapon. Mercury and Venus - gain of clothes, happiness from wife and children. Moon - danger from fall from some height, meager gains of wealth, foreign journeys. Sun - danger from enemies, fevers, loss of wisdom, fear of death. Jupiter - gains of wealth and grains, beneficence of the king and Brahmins, progress in education. 
22-26. Dasha of Virgo Ańś. … Saturn - many kinds of troubles, travels to distant places, fevers, distress from hunger. Jupiter - gains of wealth through the beneficence of the king, arrival of friends and kinsmen and success in education. Mars- bilious fever, travels to distant places, danger from fire and from weapons. Mercury, Venus and Moon - gains of wealth through sons and employees, many enjoyments. Sun - travel to distant lands, danger from diseases, quarrels with kinsmen, danger of assaults by weapons. 
27-31. Dasha of Libra Ańś. … Venus - wisdom, comforts, happiness from wife and children and from wealth, garments etc. Mars- distress to father, enmity with friends, danger from disease of forehead, fevers, poison, weapons etc. Jupiter - gain of wealth, acquisition of a kingdom, performance of religious rites, honors from the king and happiness all-round. Saturn - travels to distant places, critical diseases, loss in the agricultural sphere, danger from enemies. Mercury - birth of a son, gain of wealth, happiness from ones wife, joy, dawn of fortune. 
32-33. Dasha of Scorpio Ańś. The following effects will be experienced in the Antar Dashas of the Rāśis concerned. Moon, Mercury and Venus - gain of wealth and grains in different ways, freedom from diseases, enjoyments of many kinds. Sun - danger from enemies, loss of wealth, distress to father, danger from wild and violent animals. Mars- troubles from wind and bile, wounds, danger from fire and from weapons. Jupiter - gains of wealth, grains,. and gems, devotion towards deities and Brahmins, beneficence of the king. Saturn - loss of wealth, separation from kinsmen, mental anxiety, danger from enemies, diseases. 
34-40. Dasha of Sagittarius Ańś. The following effects will be derived in the various Antar Dashas of the Rāśis, owned by… Mars- heart burn, fevers, cold, diseases of the mouth, many kinds of troubles. Venus, Mercury and Moon - increase in wealth and property and fortune, progress in education, destruction of enemies, happiness from the king. Sun - loss of wife and wealth, quarrels, danger from the king, travels to distant lands. Jupiter - ch6thty, self-mortifications, honors from the king, increase in religious-mindedness, happiness from wife, gain of wealth. 
41-44. Dasha of Capricorn Ańś. The following effects will be experienced in the various Antar Dashas of the Rāśis, owned by… Saturn - wrath of Brahmins, deities and the king, loss of kinsmen, abandonment of the homeland. Venus, Mercury, Moon and Jupiter - devotion towards deities, self-mortification, honors from the government. Mars- disease of the forehead, assaults on hands and feet, danger from dysentery, blood pollution and bilious troubles. Saturn - loss of father and kinsmen, fevers, danger from the king and the enemies. 
45-49. Dasha of Aquarius Ańś. … Venus - many kinds of educational attainments, gains of property, happiness from wife and children, sound health and increase in wealth. Mars- fevers, danger from fire and from enemies, distress from enemies and mental agony. Saturn - danger of troubles from wind, bile and phlegm, quarrels, foreign journey, danger of suffering from tuberculosis. Jupiter - freedom from ill health, happiness, honors from the king and joy. Mercury - happiness from wife, children and wealth, joy, increase in good fortune. 
50-55. Dasha of Pisces Ańś. … Moon - increase in wisdom and educational attainments, happiness from wife, freedom from disease, association with friends, joy and happiness. Sun - quarrels with kinsmen, danger from thieves, mental agony, loss of position. Mercury and Venus - victory in war, birth of a son, gains of land and cattle, increase in wealth. Mars- bilious troubles, dissension with members of the family, danger from enemies. Jupiter - gain of wealth and grains, happiness from wife, honors from the king, name and fame. Saturn - loss of wealth, mental agony, abandonment of the homeland on account of associations with prostitutes. 
56-58. Mahārśi Parashara said to Maitreya. O Brahmin! The effects of Antar Dashas in the Kala Chakra, which have been described above, are based on Savya Chakra. The effects of Antar Dashas in the Dashas of the Rāśis in the Apsavya Chakra have to be assessed, after taking into account the benefic and malefic natures of the Lords of the Rāśis. People have to enjoy the good, or suffer the bad results, according to their good, or bad actions in the previous births. Everybody suffers, or enjoys accordingly. The peculi6thty in this respect is, that inauspicious results have been ascribed to malefics. But, if during the Antar Dasha the Planet concerned is a friend of the Lord of the Dasha, the results of the Antar Dasha will be favourable. If the Planet concerned is a benefic, but an enemy of the Lord of the Dasha, his Antar Dasha effects will not prove favourable. This is how the Antar Dasha effects have to be analyzed and conclusions arrived at. 
Ch. 65. Effects of Dashas of Rāśis in the Ańśas of the Various Rāśis  
1-3. The following will be the effects in the Dashas of Rāśis in Aries Ańś. Aries - distress from diseases, caused by blood pollution, Taurus - increase in grain production, Gemini - dawn of knowledge (Gyanodaya), Cancer - increase in wealth, Leo - danger from enemies, Virgo - happiness from wife, Libra - ministership, Scorpio - danger of death, Sagittarius - gains of wealth. 
4-5. … Taurus Ańś. Capricorn - tendency to indulge in sinful actions, Aquarius - profits in business, Pisces - success in all ventures, Scorpio - danger from fire, Libra - honors from the king, Virgo - danger from enemies, Cancer - distress to wife, Leo - eye troubles, Gemini - danger from poison. 
6-8. … Gemini Ańś. Taurus - gains of wealth, Aries - fever, Pisces - affectionate relations with maternal uncle, Aquarius - increase in enemies, Capricorn - danger from thieves, Sagittarius - progress in education, Aries - assaults from enemies, Taurus - quarrels, Gemini - happiness. 
9-10. … Cancer Ańś. Cancer - enjoyments, Leo - danger from the king, Virgo - happiness from kinsmen, Libra - good reputation, Scorpio - distress from father, Sagittarius - gain of knowledge and wealth, Capricorn - disgrace in public, Aquarius - loss in business, Pisces - travels to distant lands. 
11-13. … in Leo Ańś. Scorpio - quarrels, distress, Libra - gain of wealth, happiness, Virgo - increase in wealth and grains, Cancer - danger from animals, Leo - both happiness and sorrows, Gemini - increase in enemies, Taurus - gain of property, happiness, Aries - distress, Pisces - long journey. 
14-15. … Virgo Ańś. Aquarius - gain of wealth, Capricorn - increase in wealth, Sagittarius - happiness from brothers, Aries - happiness from mother, Taurus - happiness from sons, Gemini - danger from enemies, Cancer - affectionate relation with wife, Leo - increase in ill health, Virgo - birth of a son. 
16-18. … Libra Ańś. Libra - gain of wealth, Scorpio - happiness from brothers, Sagittarius - happiness from brothers and uncles, Capricorn - distress to mother, Aquarius - profits in business, Pisces - gain of property, happiness, Scorpio - distress to wife, Libra - danger from water, Virgo - increase in property and happiness. 
19-20. … Scorpio Ańś. Cancer - loss of wealth, Leo - danger from government, Gemini - gain of lands, Taurus - increase in wealth, Aries - distress on account of blood pollution, Pisces - happiness, Aquarius - profits in business, Capricorn - loss of wealth, Sagittarius - gain of property, happiness. 
21-23. … Sagittarius Ańś. Aries - gain of wealth, Taurus - gain of lands, Gemini - success in all ventures, Cancer - gain of property, happiness, Leo - all comforts, Virgo - quarrels, Libra - profits in business, Scorpio - danger from diseases, Sagittarius - happiness to sons. 
24-25. … Capricorn Ańś. Capricorn - birth of a son, Aquarius - increase in wealth, Pisces - well-being, Scorpio - danger from animals, Libra - gain of wealth, Virgo - danger from enemies, Cancer - gain of wealth, Leo - danger from enemies, Gemini - danger from poison. 
26-28. … Aquarius Ańś. Taurus - increase in wealth, Aries - eye troubles, Pisces - travels to distant lands, Aquarius - increase in wealth, Capricorn - success in all ventures, Sagittarius - increase in knowledge and learning, Aries - loss of happiness, Taurus - danger of death, Gemini - gains of property, happiness. 
29-31. … Pisces Ańś. Cancer - increase in wealth, Leo - assistance from the king, Virgo - increase in wealth and grains, Libra - profits in business, Scorpio - distress from fever, Sagittarius - increase in knowledge and wealth, Capricorn - antagonism with wife, Aquarius - danger from water, Pisces - all kinds of enjoyments. 
32. There is no doubt, that observance of remedial measures in the form of prescribed Mahārśi Yagyas destroys the evil effects of the inauspicious Dashas and yield happiness. 
Ch. 66. AshtakaVargaa 
1-4. Maitreya said: O Venerable Sage! You have described many kinds of effects, relating to the Planets and Houses, after incorporating the views of many sages and Acharyas, but it is not possible to say with certainty, if a particular effect is quite correct, after considering the contradictions in the effects by the movements of the various Planets. As because of sinful deeds, committed by people in Kaliyuga, their minds have become blunt, be kind enough to describe a method, which would enable even the shallow minded persons to ascertain their happiness and sorrows and determine their longevity on the basis of the positions of the Planets in transit. 
5-6. The sage replied: O Brahmin! You have put a very intelligent question. I will now describe the Shastra for the benefit of all, the Shastra, in which there will be no contradictions in judging the effects of happiness and sorrows and for determination of the longevity. You now listen to me carefully. 
7-11. If the 12 Houses, including Lagna, are occupied by, or aspected by benefic Planets, they yield auspicious results, according to their characteristics, but this happens, where the Planets concerned are in their exaltation Rāśi, own Rāśi, or posited in a benefic House. There will be no good effects, if such Planets are in depression, or posited in an inauspicious House. Similarly the Houses, associated with, or aspected by malefics in depression, or posited in malefic Houses, yield adverse results, according to their characteristics. If such Planets be in their exaltation Rāśi, the effects will not be adverse. This is how the general effects have been described by the Daivajnas. I have only repeated those effects. The main purposes of this Jyotishya Shastra are to determine the longevity and joys and sorrows of the people, but because the movements of the Planets are so subtle, even sages, like Vashista and Brihaspati, have not been able to be quite definite in this respect. Then how can a common man, particularly in Kaliyuga, do so. 
12. There are two divisions, or parts of the Jyotishya Shastra, namely general and particular. I have already dealt with the general part. I now come to the other part, which deals with this subject in particular. 
13-15. As the effects of the twelve Houses are judged from Lagna and Moon, effects of the twelve Houses and the various Planets are judged in the same manner. Therefore the inauspicious places from the seven Planets, named, as Karan, beginning from Sun and Lagna (total 8), should be marked by dots (Bindus) and auspicious places, named, as Sthan, by small vertical lines (Rekhas) and on the basis of their assessment should the judgment of the horoscope and predictions be made. 
Notes. The above arrangement is known, as AshtakaVargaa. The meaning of AshtakaVargaa is literally the group of eight things. In other words it is the combination of the good and bad positions of a Planet with reference to the seven Planets and Lagna. So it is the combination of the benefic and malefic marks (the Rekhas and the Bindus) in a planets chart with reference to the position of the eight Planets (here Lagna is to be treated, as a Planet). 
16. Five Planets in 1st, 2nd, 8th, 3rd and the 12th Houses from Sun are Karanprad (dot significators). Similarly four Planets in the 7th and 4th, three Planets in the 6th and 9th, six Planets in the 5th, 2 Planets in the 10th and one Planet in the 11th are dot significators. 
17-19. Thus Lagna, Moon, Jupiter, Venus and Mercury in the 1st, 2nd and 8th from Sun; Sun, Mars, Saturn, Moon and Jupiter in the 12th; Mercury, Moon, Venus, Jupiter in the 4th; Lagna, Moon, Venus in the 9th; Sun, Saturn and Mars in the 6th; Lagna, Mercury, Jupiter and Moon in the 7th; Venus in the 11th; Sun, Saturn, Venus, Jupiter and Mars in the 3rd; Jupiter and Venus in the 10th; Sun, Saturn, Moon, Lagna Mars and Venus in the 5th are Karanprad, or dot indicators. 
20-22. In Moon’s AshtakaVargaa 6 Planets in the 9th and the 2nd, 5 Planets in the 4th, 8th and the 1st, one Planet in the 10th and the 3rd, 4 Planets in the 5th, 3 Planets in the 6th and the 7th and 1st, eight in the 12th are Karanprad. Thus Lagna, Sun, Mars, Saturn and Venus, these five in the 1st; Lagna, Mercury, Sun, Moon, Saturn and Venus, these 6 in the 2nd; Jupiter in the 3rd; Sun, Saturn, Moon, Lagna and Mars, these 5 in the 4th; Venus, Mercury, Jupiter, these 3 in the 6th; Mars, Lagna and Saturn, these 3 in the 7th; Mars, Lagna, Saturn, Venus and Moon, these five in the 8th; Lagna, Sun, Mars, Saturn, Mercury and Jupiter, these 6 in the 9th; Saturn only in the 10th; none in the 11th; all the eight in the 12th from their own places are Karanprad. These Planets in the other Houses are Rekhaprad (line significators). 23-27. In the AshtakaVargaa of Mars6 Planets in the 12th, 4th and 7th, 5 Planets in the 5th, 6 Planets in the 2nd, 7 Planets in the 9th, 5 Planets in the 1st and 8th, 4 Planets in the 3rd, 3 Planets in the 10th and 2 Planets in the 6th are Karanprad. In the 11th no Planet is Karanprad. In other words all the Planets in the 11th from their own places are Rekhaprad. Thus Sun, Moon, Mercury, Jupiter and Venus, these five in the 1st; Lagna, Sun, Moon, Mercury, Jupiter and Saturn, these 6 in the 2nd; Venus, Mars, Jupiter and Saturn, these 4 in the 3rd; Sun, Moon, Mercury, Jupiter, Venus and Lagna, these 6 in the 4th; Moon, Mars, Jupiter, Venus and Lagna, these 5 in the 5th; Mars and Saturn, these 2 in the 6th; Mercury, Moon, Sun, Venus, Jupiter and Lagna, these 6 in the 7th; Mercury, Moon, Sun, Lagna and Jupiter, these five in the 8th; Sun, Moon, Mars, Mercury, Jupiter, Venus and Lagna, these 7 in the 9th; Venus, Moon and Mercury, these 3 in the 10th; none in the 11th; Sun, Saturn, Mercury, Moon, Lagna and Mars, these 6 in the 12th from their own places are Karanprad. 
28-30. In the AshtakaVargaa of Mercury 3 Planets in the 1st, 2nd, 4th, 10th, 6th and 9th, 2 Planets in the 8th, 6 Planets in the 3rd and the 7th, none in the 11th, 5 Planets in the 5th and 12th are Karanprad. Thus Sun, Moon and Jupiter, these 3 in the 1st; Jupiter, Sun and Mercury, these 3 in the 2nd; Lagna, Sun, Mars, Saturn, Moon and Jupiter, these 6 in the 3rd; Mercury, Sun and Jupiter, these 3 in the 4th; Jupiter, Mars, Moon, Saturn and Lagna, these 5 in the 5th; Venus, Saturn and Mars, these 3 in the 6th; Mercury, Moon, Lagna, Sun, Venus and Jupiter, these 6 in the 7th; Mercury and Sun, these 2 in the 8th; Jupiter, Moon and Lagna, these 3 in the 9th; Sun, Jupiter and Venus, these 3 in the 10th; none in the 11th; Lagna, Moon, Mars, Saturn and Venus these 5 in the 12th from their own places are Karanprad. 
31-34. In the AshtakaVargaa of Jupiter one Planet in the 2nd and 11th, 2 Planets in the 10th, 7 Planets in the 12th, 4 Planets in the 6th, 5 Planets in the 8th and 3rd, 3 Planets in the remaining Houses are Karanprad. Thus Venus, Moon and Saturn, these 3 in the 1st; Saturn in the 2nd and 11th; Lagna, Mars, Moon, Mercury and Venus, these 5 in the 3rd; Sun, Jupiter and Mars, these 3 in the 5th; Venus, Saturn and Moon, these 3 in the 4th; Mercury, Venus and Saturn, these 3 in the 7th; Jupiter, Mars, Sun and Moon, these 4 in the 6th; all except Saturn, these 7 in the 12th; Moon and Saturn, these 2 in the 10th; Saturn, Mars and Jupiter, these 3 in the 9th; Lagna, Saturn, Venus, Moon and Mercury, these 5 in the 8th from their own places are Karanprad. 
35-38. In the AshtakaVargaa of Venus 2 Planets in the 5th, 8th and 3rd, 5 Planets in the 1st, 2nd, 12th, 10th, 8 Planets in the 7th, 6 Planets in the 6th, one in the 9th, 3 in the 4th, none in the 11th are Karanpradas. Thus Sun, Mars, Mercury, Jupiter and Saturn, these 5 in the 1st and the 2nd; all the 8 Planets in the 7th; Jupiter and Sun, these 2 in the 3rd; Sun and Mars, these 2 in the 5th; Sun in 9th; Sun, Mercury and Jupiter, these 3 in the 4th; Mars and Mercury, these 2 in the 8th; Venus, Sun, Moon, Saturn, Lagna and Jupiter, these 6 in the 6th; none in the 11th; Lagna, Saturn, Mercury, Venus and Jupiter, these 5 in the 12th; Lagna, Mars, Mercury, Moon, Sun, these 5 in the 10th from their own places are Karanpradas. 
39-42. In the AshtakaVargaa of Saturn 7 Planets in the 2nd, 7th, 9th, 6 Planets in the 8th, Lagna and 4th, 4 Planets in the 10th, 3rd and 12th, one Planet in the 6th, 5 Planets in the 5th, none in the 11th are Karanpradas. Thus Moon, Mars, Mercury, Jupiter, Venus and Saturn, these 6 in the 4th and the 1st; Moon, Mars, Mercury, Jupiter, Venus, Saturn and Lagna, these 7 in the 2nd and the 7th; Sun, Moon, Mars, Jupiter, Venus, Saturn and Lagna, these 7 in the 9th; Moon, Jupiter, Venus and Saturn, these 4 in the 10th; Jupiter, Sun, Mercury and Venus, these 4 in the 3rd; Sun in the 6th; Lagna, Moon, Saturn, Sun, these 4 in the 12th; Venus, Sun, Moon, Mercury and Lagna, these 5 in the 5th; Moon, Mars, Jupiter, Venus, Saturn and Lagna, these 6 in the 8th; none in the 11th from their own places are Karanpradas. The remaining places are Rekhapradas and are auspicious. 
43-45. The sage said. Now I will describe the auspicious Houses for the benefit of the Acharyas. In the AshtakaVargaa of Sun: Saturn, Mars and Sun in the 2nd, 8th and 1st; Jupiter and Mercury in the 5th; Mercury, Moon and Lagna in the 3rd; Lagna, Sun, Saturn and Mars in the 4th; Lagna, Sun, Saturn, Mars, Mercury and Moon in the 10th; Sun, Moon, Mars, Mercury, Jupiter, Saturn and Lagna in the 11th; Lagna, Venus and Mercury in the 12th; Lagna, Venus, Mercury, Jupiter and Moon in the 6th; Sun, Mars, Saturn and Venus in the 7th; Sun, Mars, Saturn, Mercury and Jupiter in the 9th from their own places are Rekhapradas. 
46-48. In the AshtakaVargaa of Moon: Mercury, Moon and Jupiter in the 1st; Jupiter and Mars in the 2nd; Mercury, Sun, Moon, Mars, Saturn, Venus and Lagna in the 3rd; Jupiter, Venus and Mercury in the 4th; Mars, Mercury, Venus and Saturn in the 5th; Sun, Moon, Mars, Saturn and Lagna in the 6th; Sun, Moon, Jupiter, Mercury and Venus in the 7th; Sun, Mercury and Jupiter in the 8th; Venus and Moon in the 9th; Sun, Mercury, Jupiter, Venus, Moon, Lagna and Mars in the 10th and all the 8 Planets in the 11th from their own places are Rekhapradas. No Planet is Rekhaprad in the 12th. 
49-50. In the AshtakaVargaa of Mars: Lagna, Saturn and Mars in the 1st; Mars in the 2nd; Lagna, Mercury, Moon and Sun in the 3rd; Saturn and Mars in the 4th; Mercury and Sun in the 5th; Mercury, Moon, Jupiter, Sun, Lagna and Venus in the 6th; Saturn and Mars in the 7th; Saturn, Mars and Venus in the 8th; Saturn in the 9th; Mars, Sun, Jupiter, Saturn and Lagna in 10th; all in the 11th and Jupiter and Venus in the 12th from their own places are Rekhapradas. 
51-52. In the AshtakaVargaa of Mercury: Lagna, Saturn, Mars, Venus and Mercury in the 1st; Lagna, Mars, Moon, Venus and Saturn in the 2nd; Venus and Mercury in the 3rd; Lagna, Moon, Saturn, Venus and Mars in the 4th; Mercury, Saturn and Venus in the 5th; Jupiter, Mercury, Sun, Moon and Lagna in the 6th; Mars and Saturn in the 7th; Mars, Saturn, Lagna, Moon, Venus and Jupiter in the 8th; Saturn, Mars, Sun, Mercury and Venus in the 9th; Lagna, Saturn, Mars, Mercury and Moon in the 10th; all in the 11th and Jupiter, Mercury and Sun in the 12th from their own places are Rekhapradas. 
53-55. In the AshtakaVargaa of Jupiter: Lagna, Mars, Sun and Mercury in the 1st and 4th; Jupiter, Lagna, Mars, Sun, Mercury, Moon and Venus in the 2nd; Saturn, Jupiter and Sun in the 3rd; Venus, Moon, Lagna, Mercury and Saturn in the 5th; Venus, Lagna, Mercury and Saturn in the 6th; Lagna, Mars, Jupiter, Sun and Moon in the 7th; Jupiter, Sun and Mars in the 8th; Venus, Sun, Lagna, Moon and Mercury in the 9th; Jupiter, Mercury, Mars, Sun, Venus and Lagna in the 10th; all except Saturn in the 11th and Saturn in the 12th from their own places are Rekhapradas. 
56-58. In the AshtakaVargaa of Venus: Lagna, Venus and Moon in the 1st; Lagna, Venus and Moon in the 2nd; Lagna, Venus, Moon, Mercury, Saturn and Mars in the 3rd; Lagna, Venus, Moon, Saturn and Mars in the 4th; Lagna, Mercury, Moon, Jupiter, Saturn and Venus in the 5th; Mercury and Mars in the 6th; none in the 7th; Venus, Sun, Moon, Jupiter, Lagna and Saturn in the 8th; all except Sun in the 9th; Venus, Jupiter and Saturn in the 10th; all in the 11th; Mars, Moon and Sun in the 12th from their own places are Rekhapradas. 
59-60. In the AshtakaVargaa of Saturn: Sun and Lagna in the 1st; Sun in the 2nd; Lagna, Moon, Mars and Saturn in the 3rd; Lagna and Sun in the 4th; Jupiter, Saturn and Mars in the 5th; all except Sun in the 6th; Sun in the 7th; Sun and Mercury in the 8th; Mercury in the 9th; Sun, Mars, Lagna and Mercury in the 10th; all in the 11th; Mars, Mercury, Jupiter and Venus in the 12th from their own places are Rekhapradas. 
61-64. In the AshtakaVargaa of Lagna 3 Planets in the 1st and 4th, 2 Planets in the 3rd, 5 Planets in the 2nd, 6 Planets in the 5th, 8th, 9th and 12th, one Planet in the 10th, 11th and 6th and all except Jupiter in the 7th are Karanpradas. Thus Lagna, Sun and Moon in the 1st; Lagna, Mars, Moon, Sun and Saturn in the 2nd; Jupiter and Mercury in the 3rd; Lagna, Moon, Mars, Mercury, Saturn and Sun in the 5th; Lagna, Moon and Mars in the 4th; Venus in the 6th; all except Jupiter in the 7th; Lagna, Sun, Moon, Mars, Jupiter and Saturn in the 8th; Lagna, Sun, Moon, Mars, Mercury and Saturn in the 9th; Venus in the 10th and 11th; Lagna, Mars, Mercury, Jupiter, Venus and Saturn in the 12th from their own places are Karanpradas. 
65-68. In the AshtakaVargaa of Lagna: Saturn, Mercury, Venus, Jupiter and Mars in the 1st; Mercury, Jupiter and Venus in the 2nd; Lagna, Sun, Moon, Mars, Venus and Saturn in 3rd; Sun, Mercury, Jupiter, Venus and Saturn in the 4th; Jupiter and Venus in the 5th; all except Venus in the 6th; Jupiter in the 7th; Mercury and Venus in the 8th; Jupiter and Venus in the 9th; all except Venus in the 10th; all except Venus in the 11th and Sun and Moon in the 12th from their own places are Rekhapradas. 
69. In the charts of AshtakaVargaa Karan is signified by a Bindu, or dot (0) and Sthan by a Rekhapradas, or line (1). Karan is inauspicious, while Sthan is auspicious. 
70-72. To identify the auspicious and inauspicious Houses in the AshtakaVargaa a chart should be prepared with 14 horizontal lines and ten vertical lines. The form of the chart so prepared will consist of 117 apartments. In this chart in the first line incorporates the names of the seven Planets and Lagna. In the first column write the numbers of all the 12 Houses. After this mark dots under the Planet and against the Karanprad Houses. By doing so the Karanprad Houses of all the 8 Planets, including Lagna, will become known clearly and whenever the AshtakaVargaa Planet will pass in transit the dot-marked Houses, he will yield unfavorable results. In his transit to other Houses he would give favourable effects.The following table shows the dots in the AshtakaVargaa of Sun. 
Ch. 67. Trikona Shodhana in the AshtakaVargaa  
1-2. The sage said. O Brahmin! After preparing the AshtakaVargaa of all the Planets, including Lagna, Trikona Shodhana has to be done for each Rāśi. A Trikona is made of three Rāśis equidistant from each other. Thus Aries, Leo and Sagittarius, Taurus, Virgo and Capricorn, Gemini, Libra and Aquarius, Cancer, Scorpio and Pisces form the Trikonaas of the Rāśis. 
3-5. The Trikona Shodhana (rectification) should be done by writing the Rekhas in the AshtakaVargaas of Sun etc. under the Rāśis Aries etc. Amongst the Trikona Rāśis the Rāśi, which has lesser number of Rekhas, should be allotted Rekhas, arrived at by deducting its number of Rekhas from the greater number of Rekhas of the three Trikona Rāśis. No Trikona Shodhana is necessary, if any of the Trikona Rāśis has no Rekha. Shodhana should be done, if all the three of them have equal number of Rekhas, that is a zero should be written against all of them. Thereafter Ekadhipatya Shodana should be done in the same manner, described later. (For Shodhana of the AshtakaVargaa of a Planet the first thing to be done is to see, in which Rāśi the Planet is posited. Beginning from that Rāśi, the names of the 12 Rāśis should be written and then the names of the Planets, posited in them, should be mentioned against them. Thereafter the Rekhas, gained by that Rāśi, should be written below them and the number, achieved after Shodana, below it) 
Ch. 68. Ekadhipatya Shodhana in the AshtakaVargaa  
1-5. Ekadhipatya Shodana is done after writing the numbers for Rāśis, arrived at by Trikona Sho2nda. Ekadhipatya Shodhana is done, if both the two Rāśis, owned by a Planet, have gained a number after Trikona Shodhana. Ekadhipatya Shodhana is not to be done, if one Rāśi has got a number and the other is bereft of any number. The following are the rules for Ekadhipatya Shodhana. If both the Rāśis are without a Planet and the Trikona Shodana numbers are different, both should be given the smaller number. If both the Rāśis are with Planets, no Shodana is to be done. If amongst the two Rāśis one is with a Planet and a smaller Trikona rectified number and the other is without Planet with a bigger number, deduct the smaller number from the bigger number and the number of the Rāśi with Planet should be kept unchanged. If the Rāśi with the Planet has a bigger number than that of the Rāśi without Planet, the Shodana should be done of the number of the Rāśi without Planet and the number of the Rāśi with Planet should be kept unchanged. If both the Rāśis are without Planets and possess the same numbers, Shodhana of both the numbers should be done and the rectified numbers should be reduced to zero. If one Rāśi is with Planet and the other is without any Planet, the number of the latter should be reduced to zero. Sun and Moon own one Rāśi only, their numbers should be kept unchanged. 6. After doing Ekadhipatya Shodana, Pinda Shodhana should be taken in hand. 
Ch. 69. Pinda Shodana in the AshtakaVargaa 
1-4. The Sage said. O Brahmin! After completing the Trikona and Ekadhipatya Shodana in the AshtakaVargaas of all the Planets, the rectified number should be multiplied by the measure of the Rāśi. If there be any Planet in any Rāśi, the rectified number should be multiplied by the measure of the Planet also. Then, after multiplying the rectified number of each Rāśi, the products should be added up. The total so arrived at will be Pinda of that Planet. The multiples of Rāśis are 10 for Taurus and Leo, 8 for Gemini and Scorpio, 7 for Aries and Libra, 6 for Capricorn and Virgo. The multipliers of the remaining Rāśis are the same, as their numbers. (Rāśiman Chakra. Aries 7, Vris 10, Mith 8, Cancer 4, Leo 10, Kany 6, Libra 7, Vrsk 8, 2nd 9, Maka 5, Kumb 11, Mina 12) The multipliers of Planets are 10 for Jupiter, 3 for Mars, 7 for Venus, 6 for Mercury, Sun, Moon and Saturn. (Planetman Chakra. Sun 5, Moon 5, Mars8, Mercury 5, Jupiter 10, Venus 7, Saturn 5) 
Ch. 70. Effects of the AshtakaVargaa  
1-6. The matters to be considered from Sun and other Planets are, as follows. Sun - the soul (Atma), nature, physical strength, joys and sorrows and father. Moon - mind, wisdom, joy and mother. Mars- co-borns, strength, qualities and land. Mercury - business dealings, livelihood and friends. Jupiter - nourishment of the body, learning, son (children), wealth and property. Venus - marriage, enjoyments, conveyance, prostitution and sexual intercourse with women. Saturn - longevity, source of maintenance, grief, danger, losses and death. The following procedure should be adopted to ascertain the effects of a house. Multiply the number of Rekhas with the Yoga Pinda (Rāśi Pinda plus Planet Pinda), connected with the AshtakaVargaa of that Planet and divide the product by 27. The remainder will denote the number of the Nakshatra. During the transit of Saturn in that Nakshatra the House concerned will be harmed. 
7-9. The 9th house from Sun at the time of birth deals with father. The Rekhas of that Rāśi, as marked in Sun’s AshtakaVargaa, should be multiplied by the Yoga Pinda and the product be divided by 27. The remainder will denote the number of Nakshatra. The father will be in distress, or he will otherwise suffer, when Saturn in transit passes through the Nakshatra. Even, when Saturn passes in transit the Trikona Nakshatras, father, or relatives, like father, may die, or suffer. Notes. By dividing the 27 Nakshatras in three equal parts, the 1st, 10th and 19th fall in Trikona from each other. Sun is PitraKarak (significator of father). Therefore all about father is ascertained from the Sun’s AshtakaVargaa. 
10-11. If the AshtakaVargaa Rekha number is multiplied by the Yoga Pinda and the product is divided by 12, the remainder will denote the Rāśi, through which, or through the Rāśis in Trikona to it, the transit of Saturn will cause harm, or unfavorable effects to father. Death of the father may occur, if the Dasa prevailing at that time be unfavorable. If the Dasa be favourable, father will face only adverse effects. 
12-14. The death of the father may be expected, if Rahu, Saturn, or Marsare in the 4th from Sun at the time of transit of Saturn through any of the above three Rāśis (Trikona Rāśis). The death of the father will come to pass by such transit, if at that time Saturn, associated, or aspected by a malefic, be in the 9th from Lagna, or Moon and/or the Dasa of the Lord of the 4th from Lagna be in operation. The death does not take place, if a favourable Dasa be in force at the time of Saturn’s transit. This should be kept in mind by the Jyotishyais, while making predictions. 
15. If the Rāśi of Lagna of the native be the 8th Rāśi from Lagna of the father, or, if the Lord of the 8th from fathers Lagna be in Lagna of the native, he takes over all the responsibilities of his father after the latters death. 
16-18. The father enjoys happiness in the Dasa of the Lord of the 4th from Lagna. The native is obedient to his father, if the Lord of the 4th be in Lagna, or the 11th, or in the 11th, or 10th from Moon. If the birth be in the 3rd Rāśi from Lagna, or Moon of the father, the native makes proper use of the wealth, inherited from his father. If the birth be in the 10th Rāśi from Lagna, or Moon of the father, the native will inherit all the good qualities of his father. If the Lord of the 10th be in Lagna, the native will be more distinguished than his father. 
19-20. No auspicious functions, like marriage etc., should be performed in the month of Rāśis (that is, when Sun transits that Rāśi), which has more number of dots in Sun’s AshtakaVargaa. The same applies to the Samvatsar of that Rāśi (that is, when the mean Jupiter transits that Rāśi). Auspicious functions should be performed, when Sun, or the mean Jupiter transits the Rāśi, which has more Rekhas in Sun’s AshtakaVargaa. 21-23. In the same manner no auspicious functions should be performed during the transit of Moon in the Rāśi, which has larger number of dots in Moon’s AshtakaVargaa. Consideration, regarding mother, house and village, should be done from the 4th House from Moon. Therefore multiply the number of Rekhas in the AshtakaVargaa of Moon by the Yoga Pinda of that AshtakaVargaa and divide the product by 27. The death of, or distress to mother may be expected, when Saturn passes in transit through the Nakshatra, denoted by the remainder. Then divide the product by 12. The death of the mother may occur, when Saturn transits the Rāśi, denoted by the remainder. Distress to mother may be predicted, when Saturn transits the Nakshatras, or Rāśis in Trikona to Nakshatra and Rāśi, indicated above. 
24-27. Consideration of brothers (co-borns), valor and patience is done from Mars’s Ashtaka Vargaa. If the number of Rekha is larger in any Rāśi after Trikona Sho2nda, there will be gains of land, happiness from wife and great happiness to brother, when Marspasses through that Rāśi in transit. If Mars be weak, the brothers will be short lived. There will be distress to brothers, when Marstransits a Rāśi without Rekhas. Here also the Yoga Pinda of Mars’should be multiplied by the number of Rekhas in the Ashtaka Vargaa and the product be divided separately by 27 and 12. The remainders will denote the Nakshatra and Rāśi. The brother will suffer, whenever Saturn transits that Nakshatra, or Rāśi (or the Trikona Nakshatras, or Rāśis). 
28-29. Consideration in regard to family, maternal uncle and friends should be done from the 4th House from Mercury. The family etc. will enjoy happiness during the transit of Mercury’s Ashtaka Vargaa. After performing Trikona and Ekadhipatya Shodana in Mercury’s Ashtaka Vargaa, the happiness, or distress of the family should be predicted from the transit of Saturn through the resultant Nakshatra and Rāśi (and those in Trikona to them). 
30-33. All about knowledge, religious inclinations of the native and son (progeny) is to be ascertained from the 5th House from Jupiter. If the Rekhas in the 5th House from Jupiter are larger in number in the Ashtaka Vargaa, there will be great happiness in respect of progeny. If the dots are larger in number, the happiness in respect of progeny will be meager. The number of children are equal to the number of Rekhas in the 5th House (from Jupiter), provided it is not the Rāśi of debilitation of Jupiter, or his enemies Rāśi. In that case the number of children will be very limited. The number of children is also equal to the number of Navams, in which the Lord of the 5th from Jupiter is posited. Multiply the Yoga Pinda of Jupiter by the number of Rekhas in the AshtakaVargaa and divide the product separately by 27 and 12. The remainders will denote the Nakshatra and Rāśi. Transit of Saturn through that Nakshatra and its Trikona Nakshatras and of that Rāśi and its Trikona Rāśis will be inauspicious. During that period the knowledge, learning and religious activities of the native will also be adversely affected. 
34-36. There will be gain of wealth, land and happiness and marriage, whenever Venus passes in transit through the Rāśis, which have larger number of Rekhas in the AshtakaVargaa of Venus. These gains will be from the directions of the 7th Rāśi from Venus and of its Trikona Rāśis. The effects should be judged in the manner, already explained earlier, after multiplying the Rekhas in the 7th House from Venus by the Yoga Pinda. 
37-40. The 8th House from Saturn signifies death, as well as longevity. Assessment about longevity should be made from that House through the AshtakaVargaa. Therefore predict distress to the native in the year, equal to the number of Rekhas in the AshtakaVargaa from Lagna up to Saturn. The year, equal to the number of Rekhas from Saturn up to Lagna, will also be of distress. If in the year, equal to the total of the above Rekhas, 6thshta Dasa be also in operation, there can be possibility of death of the native. 
41-42. Multiply the Yoga Pinda by the number of Rekhas in the AshtakaVargaa and divide the product by 27. The death of the native will take place, when Saturn passes in transit through the Nakshatra, denoted by the remainder, or its Trikona Nakshatras. Again, divide the product by 12. The native will face danger of death, when Saturn passes in transit through the Rāśi, denoted by the remainder, or through its Trikona Rāśis. 
43-44. The results will be favourable, when Saturn passes in transit through Rāśis, which have larger number of Rekhas in Saturn’s AshtakaVargaa. Saturn’s transit through Rāśis, which have larger number of dots, will produce only evil effects.  
