
Brihat Parashara Hora Sashtra by Rishi Parashara
Page 4
Ch. 31. Argala, or Intervention from Planets 
1. O Mahārśi Parashara, you have told of auspicious effects, related to Argala. Kindly narrate its conditions and effects. 
2-9. Formation of Argala. Maitreya, I explain below Argala to know the definite effects of Houses and Planets. Planets in the 4th, 2nd and the 11th cause Argalas, while obstructors of the Argala will be those in the 10th, 12th and 3rd from a House, or a Planet. If the Argala causing Planet is stronger than the obstructing one, the former will prevail. Or, if the number of Argalas are more than the obstructing Planets, then also the Argala will prevail. If there are 3, or more malefics in the 3rd they will cause Vipreeta Argala (more effective intervention), which will also be harmless and be very favourable. The 5th is also an Argala place, while the Planet in the 9th will counteract such Argala. As Rahu and Ketu have retrograde motions, the Argalas and obstructions be also counted accordingly in a reverse manner. Mahārśis say, that the Argala, caused by one Planet, will yield limited effect, by two medium and by more than two, excellent effects. Argalas should be counted from a Rāśi, or a Planet, as the case may be. The Argala, which is unobstructed will be fruitful, while the one duly obstructed will go astray. The Argala effects will be derived in the Dasha periods of the Rāśi, or Planet concerned. 
Notes. Argala in Sanskrit is figuratively used to denote an impediment, or obstruction. Some suggest, that the Argala obstruction places are countable from the Argala place instead of from the original place, or Planet. This is not logical and a glance into Gochara Vedha (obstructions during transits) will confirm our findings. 
10. Special. The Argala, caused by placement of a Planet in the first one fourth part of the Rāśi, is countered by another, placed in the 4th quarter of the respective obstructive Rāśi. Similarly 2nd quarters Argala is eliminated by the 3rd quarter placement of another Planet. 
Notes. If the Argala causing Planet and the obstructing Planet are in the respective quarters, the obstruction will come to pass. Otherwise not. 
11-17. Argala Effects. Should there be Argala for the Arudh Pad, for the natal Lagna and for the 7th from both, the native will be famous and fortunate. A malefic, or a benefic, causing unobstructed Argala, giving a Aspect to Lagna will make one famous. Similarly a malefic, or a benefic, causing unobstructed Argala, giving a Aspect to 2nd House denotes acquisition of wealth and grains, to 3rd House happiness from co-born, to 4th House residences, quadrupeds and relatives, to 5th House sons, grand sons and intelligence, to 6th House fear from enemies, to 7th House abundant wealth and m6thtal happiness, to 8th House difficulties, to 9th House fortunes, to 10th House royal honour, to 11th House gains and to 12th House expenses. The Argala by benefics will give various kinds of happiness, while benefic effects will be meddling with malefic Argalas. Argala by both benefics and malefics will yield results. 
Notes. 1. Argala can be caused by a benefic, which is known, as Subha Argala. This Argala can be from a malefic also, so that the benefic, causing Argala, stalls the malefic role. If the benefics Argala is obstructed by another, then the benefic will become ineffective in Argala and the first-mentioned malefic will operate freely. 
2. Argala can be by a malefic with reference to a benefic, so that the native does not enjoy good effects, due to the benefic. This is Pap (malefic) Argala. If the Argala is eliminated by a benefic, or a malefic, then the first mentioned benefic will be at liberty to act, according to his own disposition. 
18. Should there be (unobstructed) Argala for Lagna, 5th and 9th House, the native will doubtlessly become a king and fortunate.
Ch. 32. Karakatwas of the Planets 
1-2. I now detail below Atma Karak etc., obtainable from among the 7 Planets, viz. Sun to Saturn. Some say, that Rahu will become a Karak, when there is a state of simil6thty in terms of longitude between (two) Planets. Yet some say, that the 8 Planets, including Rahu, will have to be considered irrespective of such a state. 
3-8. Atma Karak Defined. Among the Planets from Sun etc. whichever has traversed maximum number of degrees in a particular Rāśi is called Atma Karak. If the degrees are identical, then the one with more minutes of arc and, if the minutes are also identical, then the one with higher seconds of arc, have to be considered. In that case these three are called Anthya Karak, Madhya Karak and Upakheta. In the case of Rahu deduct his longitude in that particular Rāśi from 30. The Karakas will have to be decided, as above and, as per further rules given below. Out of these Karakas, Atma Karak is the most important and has a prime say on the native, just as the king is the most famous among the men of his country and is the head of all affairs and is entitled to arrest and release men. 
9-12. Importance of Atma Karak. O Brahmin, as the minister cannot go against the king, the other Karakas, viz. 5th Karak, Amatya Karak etc. cannot predominate over Atma Karak in the affairs of the native. If the Atma Karak is adverse, other Karakas cannot give their benefic effects. Similarly, if Atma Karak is favourable, other Karakas cannot predominate with their malefic influences. 
13-17. Other Karakas. The Planet next to Atma Karak in terms of longitude is called Amatya Karak. Similarly following one another in terms of longitude are Bhratru Karak, Matru Karak, Pitru Karak, 5th Karak, Gnati Karak and Stri Karak. These are Char Karakas, or inconstant significators. Some consider Matru Karak and 5th Karak, as identical. If two Planets have the same longitude, both become the same Karak, in which case there will be a deficit of one Karak. In that circumstance consider constant significator in the context of benefic/malefic influence for the concerned relative. 
18-21. Constant Karakatwas. I narrate below the constant Karakatwas, as related to the Planets. The stronger among Sun and Venus indicates the father, while the stronger among Moon and Mars indicates the mother. Mars denotes sister, brother-in-law, younger brother and mother. Mercury rules maternal relative, while Jupiter indicates paternal grand father. Husband and sons are, respectively, denoted by Venus and Saturn. From Ketu note wife, father, mother, parents-in law and maternal grand father. These are constant Karakatwas. 
22-24. Houses Related. These constant significances are derivable from the Houses, counted from the said constant Karakatwas. The 9th from Sun denotes father, the 4th from Moon mother, the 3rd from Mars brothers, the 6th from Mercury maternal uncle, the 5th from Jupiter sons, the 7th from Venus wife and the 8th from Saturn death. The learned should consider all these and declare related effects accordingly. 
25-30. Yoga Karakas. O Brahmin, I make below a passing reference to Yoga Karakas (mutual co-workers). Planets become Yoga Karakas, if they are in mutual angles identical with own Rāśis, exaltation Rāśis, or friendly Rāśis. In 10th House a Planet will be significantly so. Planets simply (not being in friendly, own, or exaltation Rāśis) in Lagna, 4th and 7th House do not become such Yoga Karakas. Even, if they be placed in other Houses, but with such dignities, as mentioned, shall become Yoga Karakas. With such Planets even a person of mean birth will become a king and be affluent. One born of royal scion, then will surely become a king. Thus the effects be declared, considering the number of such Planets and the order the native belongs to. 
31-34. House Significance. I now narrate the significance of the Houses. 1st House denotes the soul (self), 2nd family, finance, wife etc., 3rd younger brothers/sisters, 5th progeny and 7th wife. It is also said, that a Planet in 5th becomes a Karak for wife. The Karakatwas of the House in order are Sun, Jupiter, Mars, Moon, Jupiter, Mars, Venus, Saturn, Jupiter, Mercury, Jupiter and Saturn. 
35-37. O excellent of the Brahmins, after knowing the merits of 1st House etc. the good and bad effects can be declared. 6th, 8th and 12th are Trikas, Dusthana, or malefic Houses. 3rd, 6th, 10th and 11th are Upachayas. 2nd, 5th, 8th and 11th are Panapharas and 3rd, 6th, 9th and 12th are Apoklimas. Association with Trikas will inflict evils. Kendras and Konas (5th and 9th) are auspicious Houses, the association with which turns even evil into auspiciousness. 
(Also see Ch. 34 for more information) 
Ch. 33. Effects of Karakāńśa  
1. O Brahmin, as laid down by Lord Brahma, I now tell you about the effects of Karakāńśa identical with Aries etc. (Karakāńśa is the Navāmśa, occupied by the Atma Karak Planet) 
2-8. Karakāńśa in Various Rāśis. If Atma Karak happens to be in Aries Navāmśa, there will be nuisance from rats and cats at all times. A malefic joining will further increase the nuisance. Should Atma Karak be in Taurus Navāmśa, happiness from quadrupeds will result. Should Atma Karak be in Gemini Navāmśa, the native will be afflicted by itch etc. Should Atma Karak be in Cancer Navāmśa, there will be fear from water etc. If Atma Karak happens to be in Leo Navāmśa, fear will be from tiger etc. If Atma Karak happens to be in Virgo Navāmśa, itch, corpulence, fire etc. will cause trouble, while, if Atma Karak is in Libra Navāmśa, he will make one a trader and skilful in making robes etc. Scorpio Navāmśa, holding Atma Karak, will bring troubles from snakes etc. and also affliction to mothers breasts. There will be falls from height and conveyances etc., if it is Sagittarius Navāmśa, that is occupied by Atma Karak. Capricorn Navāmśa in this respect denotes gains from water dwelling beings and conch, pearl, coral etc. If it is Aquarius Navāmśa, holding Atma Karak, the native will construct tanks etc. And in Pisces Navāmśa the Atma Karak will grant final emancipation. The Aspect of a benefic will remove evils, while that of a malefic will cause no good. 
9-11. O Brahmin, if there be only benefics in Karakāńś and the Navāmśa of Lagna receives a Aspect from a benefic, the native will undoubtedly become a king. Should the Kendras/Konas from the Karakāńś be occupied by benefics, devoid of malefic association, the native will be endowed with wealth and learning. The combination of benefic and malefic influence will in this context yield mixed results. If the Upakheta (UpaPlanet, vide Ch.32 Sloka 5) is in its exaltation, or own, or friendly Rāśi and is devoid of a Aspect from a malefic, the native will go to heaven after death. 
12. If the Atma Karak is in the divisions of Moon, Mars, or Venus, the native will go to others wives. Otherwise the contrary will prevail. 
13-18. Effects of Planets in the Karakāńś. O Brahmin, if Sun is in the Karakāńś, the native will be engaged in royal assignments. If the full Moon is there, he will enjoy pleasures and be a scholar, more so, if Venus gives a Aspect to the Karakāńś. If strong Mars is in Karakāńś, he will use the weapon spear, will live through fire and be an alchemist. Should strong Mercury be Karakāńś, he will be skilful in arts and trading, be intelligent and educated. Jupiter in Karakāńś denotes one, doing good acts, endowed with spiritualism and Vedic learning. One will be endowed with a longevity of 100 years, be sensuous and will look after state affairs, if Venus is in Karakāńś. Saturn in Karakāńś will give such livelihood, as due to the natives family. Rahu in Karakāńś denotes a thief, a bowman, a machinery maker and a doctor, treating poisonous afflictions. If Ketu be in Karakāńś, one will deal in elephants and be a thief. 
19-22. Rahu-Sun in Karakāńś. Should Rahu and Sun be in Karakāńś, there will be fear from snakes. If a benefic gives a Aspect to Rahu-Sun in Karakāńś, there will be no fear, but a malefic Aspect will bring death (through serpents). If Rahu and Sun occupy benefic Shad Vargas, being in Karakāńś, one will be a doctor, treating poisonous afflictions, while the Aspect from Marson Rahu-Sun in Karakāńś denotes, that the native will burn either his own house, or that of others. Mercury’s Aspect on Rahu-Sun in Karakāńś will not cause the burning of ones own house, but that of others. If Rahu and Sun happen to be in Karakāńś and are in a malefics Rāśi, receiving a Aspect from Jupiter, one will burn a house in ones neighborhood, while the Aspect of Venus will not cause such an event. 
23-24. Gulika in Karakāńś. Should the full Moon give a Aspect to Gulika, placed in the Karakāńś, the native will lose his wealth to thieves, or will himself be a thief. If Gulika is in Karakāńś, but does not receive a Aspect from others, one will administer poison to others, or will himself die of poisoning. Mercury’s Aspect in this context will give large testicles. 
25-29. Effects of Aspects on Ketu in Karakāńś. If Ketu is in Karakāńś, receiving a Aspect from a malefic, ones ears will be severed, or one will suffer from diseases of the ears. Venus, giving a Aspect to Ketu in Karakāńś, denotes one, initiated into religious order. One will be devoid of strength, if Mercury and Saturn give a Aspect to Ketu in Karakāńś. If Mercury and Venus give a Aspect to Ketu in Karakāńś, one will be the son of a female slave, or of a female remarried. With Saturn’s Aspect on Ketu in Karakāńś one will perform penance, or be a servant, or will be a pseudo-ascetic. Venus and Sun together, giving a Aspect to Ketu in Karakāńś, will make one serve the king. Thus, o Brahmin, are told briefly the effects of Karakāńś. 
30-31. Effects of the 2nd from Karakāńś. If the 2nd from Karakāńś falls in the divisions of Venus, or Mars, one will be addicted to others wives and, if Venus, or Mars give a Aspect to the 2nd from Karakāńś, the tendency will last till death. If Ketu is the 2nd from Karakāńś in a division of Venus, or Mars, addiction to others wives will not prevail, while the position of Jupiter will cause such an evil. Rahu in the 2nd from Karakāńś will destroy wealth. 
32. Effects of the 3rd from Karakāńś. A malefic in the 3rd from Karakāńś will make one valorous, while a benefic in the 3rd from Karakāńś will make one timid. 
33-35. Effects of the 4th from Karakāńś. If the 4th from Karakāńś happens to be occupied by Venus and Moon, one will own large buildings, like palaces etc. Similar is the effect of an exalted Planet in the said 4th. A house, made of stones, is denoted by the occupation of the 4th from Karakāńś by Rahu and Saturn. Mars and Ketu in the 4th from Karakāńś indicate a house, made of bricks, while Jupiter in the 4th from Karakāńś denotes a house, made of wood. Sun in the 4th from Karakāńś will give a house of grass. If Moon is in the 4th from Karakāńś, one will have union with his wife in an uncompounded house. 
36-40. Effects of the 5th from Karakāńś. If Rahu and Mars are in the 5th from Karakāńś, one will suffer from a pulmonary consumption, more so, if Moon gives them a Aspect. The Aspect of Mars on the 5th from Karakāńś will bring boils, or ulcers, Ketu's Aspect on the 5th from Karakāńś will cause dysentery and other diseases, caused by (impure) water. If Rahu and Gulika happen to be in the 5th from Karakāńś, there will be fear from mean people and poison. Should Mercury be in the 5th from Karakāńś, the native will be an ascetic of the highest order, or one, holding staff. Sun in the 5th from Karakāńś denotes one, using a knife. Mars in the 5th from Karakāńś denotes one, using a spear. Saturn denotes a bowman, if Saturn is placed in the 5th from Karakāńś. Rahu in the 5th from Karakāńś denotes a machinist. Ketu in the 5th from Karakāńś denotes a watch maker. Venus in the 5th from Karakāńś will make one a poet and an eloquent speaker. 
41-45. Effects of Karakāńś and the 5th from there. If Jupiter and Moon are in Karakāńś, or the 5th thereof, the native will be an author. Venus will make one an ordinary writer, while Mercury will indicate, that the writing skills are less than those of an ordinary writer. Should Jupiter be alone, one will be a knower of everything, be a writer and be versed in Vedas and Vedanta philosophy, but not an oratorian, or a gramm6than. Mars denotes a logician, Mercury a Mimamsaka (follower of 10th Mimansa), Saturn indicates, that one is dull-witted in the assembly, Sun denotes, that one is a musician, Moon denotes a follower of Sankhya philosophy (of Mahārśi Kapila, who enumerated 25 true principles with emphasis on final bliss) and indicates, that one is versed in rhetoric and singing and Ketu, or Rahu denotes, that one is a astrologer. Should Jupiter be related to the positions of Karakāńś, or the 5th from there, while the Karakāńś is caused by others than him, the effects, as stated, will effectively come to pass. Some say, that the 2nd from Karakāńś should also be similarly considered. 
46. Effects of the 6th from Karakāńś. If the 6th from Karakāńś is occupied by a malefic, the native will be an agriculturist, while he will be indolent, if a benefic is in the 6th from Karakāńś. The 3rd from Karakāńś should also be similarly considered. 
47-48. Effects of the 7th from Karakāńś. If Moon and Jupiter are in the 7th from Karakāńś, the native will beget a very beautiful wife. Venus in the 7th form Karakāńś denotes a sensuous wife, while Mercury in the 7th from Karakāńś indicates a wife, versed in arts. Sun in the 7th from Karakāńś will give a wife, who will be confining domestic core, while Saturn in the 7th from Karakāńś denotes a wife of a higher age bracket, or a pious and/or sick wife. Rahu in the 7th from Karakāńś will bring a widow in marriage. 
49. Effects of the 8th from Karakāńś. If a benefic, or the Planet, owning the 8th from Karakāńś, happens to be in the 8th from Karakāńś, the native will be long-lived, while a malefic, placed in the 8th from Karakāńś, will reduce the life span. Aspect/Conjunct of both benefics and malefics will yield a medium span of life. 
50-56. Effects of the 9th from Karakāńś. If the 9th from Karakāńś receives a Aspect from, or is occupied by a benefic, the native will be truthful, devoted to elders and attached to his own religion. If a malefic gives a Aspect to, or occupies the 9th from Karakāńś, one will be attached to his religion in boyhood, but will take to falsehood in old age. If Saturn and Rahu, one will betray his elders and be adverse to ancient learning. If Jupiter and Sun, one will betray his elders and will be disobedient to them. Should Mars and Venus give a Aspect to, or occupy the 9th from Karakāńś and are joining in six identical Vargas, a female, ill-related to the native, will die. Mercury and Moon giving a Aspect to, or occupying the 9th from Karakāńś and joining in six identical Vargas will cause imprisonment of the native, due to association with a female not of his own. If Jupiter is alone, related to the 9th from Karakāńś by Aspect, or by Conjunct, the native will be addicted to females and be devoted to sensual enjoyments.  
57-60. Effects of the 10th from Karakāńś. If the 10th from Karakāńś receives a Aspect from, or is conjoined by a benefic, the native will have firm riches, be sagacious, strong and intelligent. A malefic, giving a Aspect to the 10th from Karakāńś, or occupying this House, will cause harm to his profession and deprive him of paternal bliss. Mercury and Venus, giving a Aspect to the 10th from Karakāńś, or conjoining this House, will confer many gains in business and will make him do many great deeds. Sun and Moon, giving a Aspect to the 10th from Karakāńś, or conjoining this place and receiving a Aspect from, or be in Conjunct with Jupiter, the native will acquire a kingdom. 
61-62. Effects of the 11th from Karakāńś. If the 11th from Karakāńś receives a Aspect from, or is conjunct with a benefic, the native will enjoy happiness from co-born apart from gaining in every undertaking of his. If a malefic is in the 11th from Karakāńś, the native will gain by questionable means, be famous and valorous.  
63-74. Effects of the 12th from Karakāńś. If the 12th from Karakāńś has a benefic, the expenses will be on good account, while a malefic in the 12th from Karakāńś will cause bad expenses. If the 12th from Karakāńś is vacant, then also good effects will follow. If there happens to be a benefic Planet in exaltation, or in own House in the 12th from Karakāńś, or, if Ketu is so placed and receives a Aspect from, or is conjunct with a benefic, one will attain heaven after death. One will attain full enlightenment, if Ketu is in the 12th identical with Aries, or Sagittarius and receives a Aspect from a benefic. If Ketu is in the 12th from Karakāńś, receiving a Aspect from a malefic, or is there conjunct with a malefic, one will not attain full enlightenment. If Sun and Ketu are in the 12th from Karakāńś, the native will worship Lord Shiva. Moon and Ketu denotes a worshiper of Gauri. Venus and Ketu of Lakshmi and a wealthy person. Mars and Ketu of Lord Subramanya. Rahu will make one worship Durga, or some mean deity. Ketu alone denotes Subramanya's, or Ganesh's worshipper. If Saturn is in the 12th from Karakāńś in a malefics Rāśi, one will worship mean deities. Venus and Saturn in the 12th from Karakāńś in a malefics Rāśi will also make one worship mean deities. Similar inferences can be drawn from the 6th Navāmśa, counted from Amatya Karaks Navāmśa.  
75-76. Miscellaneous Matters (up to Sloka 84). O Brahmin, if there are two malefics in a Kon from Karakāńś, the native will have knowledge of Mantras and Tantras (formulas for the attainment of super-human powers). If a malefic simultaneously gives a Aspect to two malefics in a Kon from Karakāńś, the native will use his learning of Mantras and Tantras for malevolent purposes, while a benefics Aspect will make him use the learning for public good.  
77-84. If Moon is in the Karakāńś, receiving a Aspect from Venus, the native will be an alchemist and, if receiving a Aspect from Mercury the native will be a doctor capable of curing all diseases. If Moon is in the 4th from Karakāńś and receives a Aspect from Venus, the native will be afflicted by white leprosy. If receiving a Aspect from Mars, the native will have blood and bilious disorders and, if receiving a Aspect from Ketu, the native will suffer from black leprosy. Should Rahu and Mars be in the 4th, or 5th from Karakāńś, the native will suffer from pulmonary consumption and, if simultaneously there happens to be Moon’s Aspect on the 4th, or the 5th, this affliction will be certain. Marsalone in the 4th, or the 5th will cause ulcers. If Ketu is in the 4th, or the 5th, one will suffer from dysentery and afflictions, due to (impure) water. Rahu and Gulika will make one a doctor, curing poisonous afflictions, or will cause troubles through poison. Should Saturn be alone in the 4th, or 5th, the native will be skillful in archery. Ketu lonely placed in the 4th, or the 5th will make one a maker of watches etc. Mercury lonely placed in the 4th, or the 5th will make one an ascetic of the highest order, or an ascetic, holding staff. Rahu, Sun and Mars, respectively, in these places denote a machinist, a knife user and a spear, or arrow user. 
85-86. Moon and Jupiter in the Karakāńś, or in the 5th there from denotes a writer well versed in all branches of learning. The grade of writership will comparatively descend in the case of Venus and even further in the case of Mercury. 
87-92. Planets in the 5th from Karakāńś. Should Venus be in the 5th from Karakāńś, the native will be eloquent and a poet. Jupiter denotes, that he be an exponent and be all knowing, but be unable to speak in an assembly. He will be further a gramm6than and a scholar in Vedas and Upanishads. Saturn will make one ineffective in an assembly, while Mercury will make him skilful in 10th Mimansa. Mars in Karakāńś, or the 5th there from will make one justice, while Moon in Karakāńś, or the 5th from there denotes a Sankhya Yogi, a rhetoric, or a singer. Sun in the 5th from Karakāńś will make one learned in Vedanta and music. Ketu will make one a mathematician and skilful in Jyotishya. Should Jupiter be related to the said Ketu, these learning will be by inheritance. All these as well apply to 2nd and 3rd from Karakāńś and to the Karakāńś itself apart from applying to the 5th from Karakāńś.  
93-93. Should Ketu be in the 2nd, or 3rd from Karakāńś, the native will be defective in speech, more so, if a malefic gives a Aspect to Ketu, as above.  
94-99. If malefics be in Karakāńś, Arudh Lagna and the 2nd and 8th from these places, there will be Kemadruma Yoga, the effects of which will be still severer, if Moon’s Aspect happens to be there. The effects, due for these Yogas, will come to pass in the Dasha periods of the Rāśis, or Planets concerned. Kemadruma Yoga will operate additionally, if there are malefics in the 2nd and 8th from the Rāśi, whose Dasha will be in currency. The results of such Yoga will also be inauspicious. If the 2nd and 8th in the Kundali, cast for the beginning of a Dasha, have malefics, then also Kemadruma prevails throughout the Dasha. 
Ch. 34. Yoga Karakas 
1. O Brahmin, thus I have told you about the effects, derivable through Karakāńś. Now listen to the effects, 6thsing out of lordships of Planets over Houses.  
2-7. Nature due to Lordships of Planets. Benefics, owning Kendras, will not give benefic effects, while malefics, owning Kendras, will not remain inauspicious. The Lord of a Kona will give auspicious results. The Lord of Lagna is specially auspicious, as Lagna is a Kendra, as well as a Kon. 5th and 9th House are specially for wealth, while 7th and 10th House are specially for happiness. Any Planet, owning 3rd, 6th, or 11th House, will give evil effects. The effects, due to the Lords of 12th and 8th House, will depend on their association. In each group the significance will be in the ascending order. 8ths Lord is not auspicious, as he owns the 12th from 9th House. If the Lord of 8th House simultaneously owns 3rd, 7th, or 11th House, he will prove specifically harmful, while his simultaneous ownership of a Kona will bestow auspicious effects. The Planet, owning a predominant House, will stall the effects, due to another, owning a less significant House and will give his own results. 8ths lordship of Sun and Moon is not evil.  
8-10. Natural Benefics and Malefics. Jupiter and Venus are benefics, while Moon is mediocre in benefice and Mercury is neutral (a benefic, when associated with a benefic and a malefic, when related to a malefic). Malefics are Sun, Saturn and Mars. Full Moon, Mercury, Jupiter and Venus are stronger in the ascending order. Weak Moon, Sun, Saturn and Mars are stronger (in malefic disposition) in the ascending order. In revealing maleficence, due to rulership of Kendras, Moon, Mercury, Jupiter and Venus are significant in the ascending order.  
11-12. Lordships of Kendras and Konas. If there be an exchange between a Lord of a Kendr and a Lord of a Kon, or, if a Lord of a Kendr is conjunct with a Lord of a Kon in a Kendr, or in a Kon, or, if a Lord of a Kon is in a Kendr, or vice versa, or, if there happens to be a full Aspect between a Lord of a Kendr and a Lord of a Kon, they cause a Yoga. One born in such a Yoga will become a king and be famous.  
13. If one and the same Planet gets the lordships of a Kon, as well as a Kendr, or, if a Planet is in a Kendr, or in a Kon, it will prove specially a Yoga Karak.  
14. Lordship of Kendr. It has been said, that a malefic, owning a Kendr, will become auspicious, which is true, only when it simultaneously Lords over a Kon and not by merely owning a Kendr.  
15. If the Lords of a Kendr, or a Kon own simultaneously an evil House, he does not cause a Raja Yoga by mere relations stipulated (as per Ch. 34, Slokas 11 and 12).  
16. Rahu and Ketu. Rahu and Ketu give predominantly the effects, as due to their conjunct with a House Lord, or, as due to the House they occupy.  
17. If Rahu and/or Ketu are in Kendr, receiving a Aspect from, or in association with the Lord of a Kon, or of a Kendr, it will become Yoga Karak.  
18. O Mahārśi Parashara, please narrate, according to the Rāśis rising, as to which Planet is a Yoga Karak and which is inauspicious.  
19-22. Planets and Aries Lagna. O Brahmin, listen to these with examples. Even though Mars is the Lord of 8th House, he will be helpful to auspicious Planets. Saturn, Mercury and Venus are malefics. Auspicious are Jupiter and Sun. The mere Conjunct of Saturn with Jupiter will not produce auspicious effects (although they own a Kon and a Kendr). If Jupiter is at the disposal of a malefic, he will surely give inauspicious results. Venus is a direct (independent) killer. Saturn etc. will also inflict death, if associated with an adverse Planet (Venus).  
23-24. Planets and Taurus Lagna. Jupiter, Venus and Moon are malefics. Saturn and Sun are auspicious. Saturn will cause Raja Yoga. Mercury is somewhat inauspicious. The Jupiter group (Jupiter, Moon and Venus) and Mars will inflict death.  
25-26. Planets and Gemini Lagna. Mars, Jupiter and Sun are malefics, while Venus is the only auspicious Planet. The Conjunct of Jupiter with Saturn is similar to that for Aries Lagna. Moon is the prime killer, but it is dependant on her association.  
27-28. Planets and Cancer Lagna. Venus and Mercury are malefics, Mars, Jupiter and Moon are auspicious. Mars is capable of conferring a full-fledged Yoga and giving auspicious effects. Saturn and Sun are killers and give effects, according to their associations.  
29-30. Planets and Leo Lagna. Mercury, Venus and Saturn are malefics. Auspicious effects will be given by Mars, Jupiter and Sun. Jupiter’s Conjunct with Venus (though, respectively, Kon and Kendr Lords) will not produce auspicious results. Saturn and Moon are killers, who will give effects, according to their associations. 
31-32. Planets and Virgo Lagna. Mars, Jupiter and Moon are malefics, while Mercury and Venus are auspicious. Venus Conjunct with Mercury will produce Yoga. Venus is a killer as well. Sun’s role will depend on his association. 
33-34. Planets and Libra Lagna. Jupiter, Sun and Mars are malefics. Auspicious are Saturn and Mercury. Moon and Mercury will cause Raja Yoga. Mars is a killer. Jupiter and other malefics will also acquire a disposition to inflict death. Venus is neutral.  
35-36. Planets and Scorpio Lagna. Venus, Mercury and Saturn are malefics. Jupiter and Moon are auspicious. Sun, as well as Moon are Yoga Karakas. Mars is neutral. Venus and other malefics acquire the quality of causing death.  
37-38. Planets and Sagittarius Lagna. Only Venus is inauspicious. Mars and Sun are auspicious. Sun and Mercury are capable of conferring a Yoga. Saturn is a killer, Jupiter is neutral. Venus acquires killing powers.  
39-40. Planets and Capricorn Lagna. Mars, Jupiter and Moon are malefics, Venus and Mercury are auspicious. Saturn will not be a killer on his own. Mars and other malefics will inflict death. Sun is neutral. Only Venus is capable of causing a superior Yoga.  
41-42. Planets and Aquarius Lagna. Jupiter, Moon and Mars are malefics, while Venus and Saturn are auspicious. Venus is the only Planet, that causes Raja Yoga. Jupiter, Sun and Mars are killers. Mercury gives meddling effects.  
43-44. Planets and Pisces House. Saturn, Venus, Sun and Mercury are malefics. Mars and Moon are auspicious. Mars and Jupiter will cause a Yoga. Though Mars is a killer, he will not kill the native (independently). Saturn and Mercury are killers.  
45-46. General. Thus the auspicious and inauspicious effects, derivable through the Planets, due to their lordship, according to the rising Rāśi, have to be estimated. Apart the effects, due to Nabhash Yogas etc., should also be known, which I narrate, as under. 
Ch. 35. Nabhash Yogas  1-2. O excellent of the Brahmins, explained below are 32 Nabhash Yogas, which have a total of 1800 different v6theties. These consist of 3 Asraya Yogas, 2 Dala Yogas, 20 Akriti Yogas and 7 Sankhya Yogas.  
3-6. Names of Nabhash Yogas. The 3 Asraya Yogas are Rajju, Musala and Nala Yogas. The 2 Dala Yogas are Maal and Sarpa. The 20 Akriti Yogas are Gada, Sakat, Shringatak, Vihag, Hal, Vajr, Kamal, Vapi, Yup, Shar, Shakti, Danda, Nisk, Koot, Chatr, 2ndushi (Chap), Ardh, Moon, Chakra and Samudr Yogas. The 7 Sankhya Yogas are Vallaki, Daam, Paash, Kedara, Sool, Yuga and Gola Yogas. Thus these are 32 in total.  
7. Rajju, Musala and Nala Yogas. All the Planets in Movable Rāśis cause Rajju Yoga. All the Planets in Fixed Rāśis cause Musala Yoga. All the Planets in Dual Rāśis cause Nala Yoga. 
8. Maal and Sarpa Yogas. If 3 Kendras are occupied by benefics, Maal Yoga is produced, while malefics so placed will cause Bhujang, or Sarpa Yoga. These Yogas, respectively, produce benefic and malefic results.  
9-11. Gada, Sakata, Vihaga, Shringataka, Hala, Vajra and Yava Yogas. If all the Planets occupy two successive Kendras, Gada Yoga is formed. Sakata Yoga occurs, when all the Planets are disposed in Lagna and 7th House. If all confine to 4th and 10th House, then Vihaga Yoga occurs. All Planets in Lagna, 5th and 9th House cause Shringataka Yoga, while all Planets in 2nd, 6th and 10th House, or in 3rd, 7th and 11th House, or in 4th, 8th and 12th House cause Hala Yoga. Vajra Yoga is caused by all benefics in Lagna and 7th House, or all malefics in 4th and 10th House. In a contrary situation, i.e. all benefics in 4th and 10th House, or all malefics in Lagna and 7th House, Yava Yoga is generated.  
12. Kamala and Vapi Yogas. If all the Planets are in the 4 Kendras, Kamala Yoga is produced. If all of them happen to be in all the Apoklimas, or in all the Panapharas, Vapi Yoga occurs.  
13. Yupa, Shara, Shakti and Danda Yogas. If all the 7 Planets are in the 4 Houses, commencing from Lagna, they cause Yup Yoga, if from 4th, Shara Yoga occurs, if from 7th, Shakti Yoga occurs and, if from 10th, Danda Yoga is formed.  
14. Nauka, Koot, Chatra and Chap Yogas. If all the Planets occupy the seven Houses from Lagna, Nauka Yoga occurs, if from 4th, Koota Yoga is formed, if from 7th, Chatra Yoga occurs and, if from 10th, Chap Yoga occurs. Here again the Planets should occupy seven continuous Houses. 
Quoted from Saravali. If the seven Planets occupy continuously seven Houses, commencing from a House, which is not angular to the Lagnaa, the Yoga produced is known, as Ardh Chandra Yoga.  
15. Chakra and Samudr Yogas. If all the Planets occupy six alternative Rāśis, commencing from Lagna, Chakra Yoga is formed. Samudr Yoga is produced, if all Planets occupy six alternative Rāśis, commencing from 2nd House.  
16-17. Sankhya Yogas. If all Planets are in one Rāśi, Gola Yoga is formed, if in 2, Yuga Yoga is formed, if in 3, Soola Yoga occurs, if in 4, Kedara Yoga occurs, if in 5, Paasha Yoga is formed, if in 6, Daama Yoga occurs and, if in 7, Veena Yoga is produced. None of these seven Yogas will be operable, if another Nabhash Yoga is derivable.  
18. Effects of Nabhash Yogas (up to Sloka 50). Rajju Yoga. One born in Rajju Yoga will be fond of wandering, be charming, will earn in foreign countries. He will be cruel and mischievous.  
19. Musala Yoga. One born in Musala Yoga will be endowed with honour, wisdom, wealth etc., be dear to king, famous, will have many sons and be firm in disposition.  
20. Nala Yoga. One born in Nala Yoga will have uneven physique, be interested in accumulating money, very skilful, helpful to relatives and charming.  
21. Maala Yoga. One born in Maala Yoga will be ever happy, endowed with conveyances, robes, food and pleasures, be splendorous and endowed with many females.  
22. Sarpa Yoga. One born in Sarpa Yoga will be crooked, cruel, poor, miserable and will depend on others for food and drinks.  
23. Gada Yoga. One born in Gada Yoga will always make efforts to earn wealth, will perform sacrificial rites, be skilful in Shastras and songs and endowed with wealth, gold and precious stones.  
24. Sakata Yoga. One born in Sakata Yoga will be afflicted by diseases, will have diseased, or ugly nails, be foolish, will live by pulling carts, be poor and devoid of friends and relatives.  
25. Vihaga Yoga. One born in Vihaga Yoga will be fond of roaming, be a messenger, will live by sexual dealings, be shameless and interested in quarrels.  
26. Shringataka Yoga. One born in Shringataka Yoga will be fond of quarrels and battles, be happy, dear to king, endowed with an auspicious wife, be rich and will hate women.  
27. Hal Yoga. One born in Hal Yoga will eat a lot, will be very poor, will be miserable, agitated, given up by friends and relatives. He will be a servant.  
28. Vajra Yoga. One born in Vajra Yoga will be happy in the beginning and at the end of life, be valorous, charming, devoid of desires and fortunes and be inimical.  
29. Yava Yoga. One born in Yava Yoga will observe fasts and other religious rules, will do auspicious acts, will obtain happiness, wealth and sons in his mid-life. He will be ch6thtable and firm.  
30. Kamala Yoga. One born in Kamala Yoga will be rich and virtuous, be long lived, very famous and pure. He will perform hundreds of auspicious acts and he will be a king.  
31. Vapi Yoga. One born in Vapi Yoga will be capable of accumulating wealth, be endowed with lasting wealth and happiness and sons, be free from eye afflictions and will be a king.  
32. Yup Yoga. One born in Yup Yoga will have spiritual knowledge and will be interested in sacrificial rites. He will be endowed with a wife, be strong, interested in fasts and other religious observations and be distinguished. 
33. Shara Yoga. One born in Shara Yoga will make arrows, be head of a prison, will earn through animals, will eat meat, will indulge in torture and mean handiworks. 
34. Shakti Yoga. One born in Shakti Yoga will be bereft of wealth, be unsuccessful, miserable, mean, lazy, long lived, interested and skilful in war, firm and auspicious. 
35. Danda Yoga. One born in Danda Yoga will lose sons and wife, will be indigent, unkind, away from his men and will serve mean people. 
36. Nauka Yoga. One born in Nauka Yoga will derive his livelihood through water, be wealthy, famous, wicked, wretched, dirty and miserly. 
37. Koota Yoga. One born in Koota Yoga will be a liar, will head a jail, be poor, crafty, cruel and will live in hills and fortresses. 
38. Chatra Yoga. One born in Chatra Yoga will help his own men, be kind, dear to many kings, very intelligent, happy at the beginning and end of his life and be long-lived. 
39. Chapa Yoga. One born in Chapa Yoga will be liar, will protect secrets, be a thief, be fond of wandering, forests, be devoid of luck and be happy in the middle of the life. 
40. Ardh Chandra Yoga. One born in Ardha Chandra Yoga will lead an Army, will possess a splendorous body, be dear to king, be strong and endowed with gems, gold and ornaments. 
41. Chakra Yoga. One born in Chakra Yoga will be an emperor, at whose feet will be the prostrating kings, heads, adoring gem studded diadems. 
42. Samudra Yoga. One born in Samudra Yoga will have many precious stones and abundant wealth, be endowed with pleasures, dear to people, will have firm wealth and be well disposed. 
43. Veena Yoga. One born in Veena Yoga will be fond of songs, dance and musical instruments, be skilful, happy, wealthy and be a leader of men. 
44. Daamini Yoga. One born in Daamini Yoga will be helpful to others, will have righteously earned wealth, be very affluent, famous, will have many sons and gems, be courageous and red-lettered. 
45. Paasha Yoga. One born in Paasha Yoga will be liable to be imprisoned, be skilful in work, be deceiving in disposition, will talk much, be bereft of good qualities and will have many servants. 
46. Kedara Yoga. One born in Kedara Yoga will be useful to many, be an agriculturist, be truthful, happy, fickle-minded and wealthy. 
47. Soola Yoga. One born in Soola Yoga will be sharp, indolent, bereft of wealth, be tortuous, prohibited, valiant and famous through war. 
48. Yuga Yoga. One born in Yuga Yoga will be heretic, be devoid of wealth, be discarded by others and be devoid of sons, mother and virtues. 
49. Gola Yoga. One born in Gola Yoga will be strong, be devoid of wealth, learning and intelligence, be dirty, sorrowful and miserable. 
50. Ancestors say, that the results, due to said (Nabhash) Yogas, will be felt throughout in all the Dasha periods. 
Ch. 36. Many Other Yogas  
1-2. Benefic and Malefic Yogas. If there be a benefic in Lagna, Subha Yoga is produced, while a malefic in Lagna causes Asubha Yoga. Benefics in both 12th and 2nd House cause Subha Yoga. Malefics in both 12th and 2nd House cause Asubha Yoga. One born in Subha Yoga will be eloquent, charming and virtuous, while his counterpart will be sensuous, will do sinful acts and will enjoy (swallow) others wealth. 
3-4. Gaja Kesari Yoga. Should Jupiter be in a Kendr from Lagna, or from Moon and be conjunct with, or receiving a Aspect from benefic, avoiding at the same time debilitation, combustion and inimical Rāśi, Gaja Kesari Yoga is caused. One born in Gaj Kes6th Yoga will be splendorous, wealthy, intelligent, endowed with many laudable virtues and will please the king. 
5-6. Amala Yoga. If there be exclusively a benefic in the 10th from Lagna, or Moon, Amala Yoga exists. Amala Yoga will confer fame, lasting till Moon and stars exist and will make the native honoured by the king, enjoy abundant pleasures, ch6thtable, fond of relatives, helpful to others, pious and virtuous. 
7-8. Parvata Yoga. Benefics in Kendras will produce Parvata Yoga, as 7th and 8th House are vacant, or are occupied by only benefics. One born in Parvata Yoga will be wealthy, eloquent, ch6thtable, learned in Shastras, fond of mirth, famous, splendorous and be the leader of a city. 
9-10. Kahala Yoga. Should 4ths Lord and Jupiter be in mutual Kendras, while Lagnas Lord is strong, Kahala Yoga occurs. Alternatively 4ths Lord, being in his own, or exaltation Rāśi, should be conjunct with 10ths Lord. In effect the native will be energetic, adventurous, charming, endowed with a complete Army, consisting of ch6thots, elephants, horses and infantry and he will Lord over a few villages. 
11-12. Chamara Yoga. If Lagnas Lord is exalted in a Kendr and receives a Aspect from Jupiter, Chamar Yoga is formed. This Yoga also occurs, if two benefics are in Lagna, or 9th, or 10th, or 7th House. The effects of Chamara Yoga are: the native will be a king, or honoured by the king, long lived, scholarly, eloquent and versed in all arts. 
13-14. Shankha Yoga. If Lagnas Lord is strong, while the Lords of 5th and 6th House are in mutual Kendras, then what is known, as Shankha Yoga, is produced. Alternatively, if Lagnas Lord along with 10ths Lord is in a Movable Rāśi, while 9ths Lord is strong, Shankha Yoga is obtained. One born with Shankha Yoga will be endowed with wealth, spouse and sons. He will be kindly disposed, propitious, intelligent, meritorious and long-lived. 
15-16. Bhairi Yoga. If 12th, 1st, 2nd and 7th House are occupied, as 9ths Lord is strong, the native obtains Bhairi Yoga. Again another kind of Bhairi Yoga is formed, if Venus, Jupiter and Lagnas Lord are in a Kendr, while 9ths Lord is strong. The results of Bhairi Yoga are: the native will be endowed with wealth, wife and sons. He will be a king, be famous, virtuous and endowed with good behavior, happiness and pleasures. 
17. Mridanga Yoga. If Lagnas Lord is strong and others occupy Kendras, Konas, own Houses, or exaltation Rāśis, Mridanga Yoga is formed. The native concerned will be a king, or equal to a king and be happy. 
18. Shrinath Yoga. If 7ths Lord is in 10th House, while 10ths Lord is exalted and conjunct with 9ths Lord, Shrinath Yoga takes place. The native with Shrinath Yoga will be equal to Lord Devendra (god of gods). 
19-20. Sharada Yoga. Should 10ths Lord be in 5th House, while Mercury is in a Kendr, as Sun with strength is in Leo, Sharada Yoga is formed. This will again be obtained, if Jupiter, or Mercury is in a Kon to Moon, while Mars is in 11th House. One born in either kind of Yoga will obtain wealth, spouse and sons, be happy, scholarly, dear to the king, pious and virtuous. 
21-22. Matsya Yoga. Benefics in 9th and 1st House, mixed Planets in 5th House and malefics in 4th and 8th House: this array of Planets at birth will produce Matsya Yoga. In effect the native will be a astrologer, be a synonym of kindness, be virtuous, strong, beautiful, famous, learned and pious. 
23-24. Kurma Yoga. If 5th, 6th and 7th House are occupied by benefic Planets identical with own House, or exaltation, or friendly Rāśi, while malefics are in 3rd, 11th and 1st House, in own House, or in exaltation, Kurma Yoga is formed. The results of Kurma Yoga are: the native will be a king. be courageous, virtuous, famous, helpful, happy. He will be a leader of men. 
25-26. Khadga Yoga. Should there be an exchange of Rāśis between the Lords of 2nd and 9th House, as Lagnas Lord is in a Kendr, or in a Kon, Khadga Yoga is obtained. One with Khadga Yoga will be endowed with wealth, fortunes and happiness, be learned in Shastras, be intelligent, mighty, grateful and skilful. 
27-28. Lakshmi Yoga. If 9ths Lord is in a Kendr identical with his Moolatrikona Rāśi, or own Rāśi, or in exaltation, while Lagnas Lord is endowed with strength, Lakshmi Yoga occurs. The native with Lakshmi Yoga will be charming, virtuous, kingly in status, endowed with many sons and abundant wealth. He will be famous and of high moral merits. 
29-30. Kusuma Yoga. Venus in a Kendr, Moon in a Kon along with a benefic and Saturn in 10th House: these Planets thus cause Kusuma Yoga for one born in a Fixed Rāśi ascending. Such a native will be a king, or equal to him, be ch6thtable, will enjoy pleasures, be happy, prime among his race men, virtuous and red-lettered. 
31-32. Kalanidhi Yoga. If Jupiter is placed in 2nd, or 5th House and receives a Aspect from Mercury and Venus, Kalanidhi Yoga is caused. In effect the native will be virtuous, honoured by the kings, bereft of diseases, be happy, wealthy and learned. 
33-34. Kalpa Drum Yoga. Note the following four Planets: Lagnas Lord , the depositor of Lagnas Lord (a), the depositor of the Planet a (b), the Navāmśa depositor of the Planet b. If all these are disposed in Kendras and in Konas from Lagna, or are exalted, Kalpa Drum Yoga exists. One with Kalpa Drum Yoga will be endowed with all kinds of wealth, be a king, pious, strong, fond of war and merciful. 
35-36. Trimurthi Yogas. Counted from 2nds Lord, if benefics occupy the 2nd, 12th and 8th, H6th Yoga is formed. If the 4th, 9th and 8th with reference to the Rāśi, occupied by 7ths Lord, are occupied by benefics, Hara Yoga is obtainable. Brahma Yoga is generated, if, counted from Lagnas Lord, benefics are in the 4th, 10th and 11th Rāśis. One born in anyone of the said three Yogas will be happy, learned and endowed with wealth and sons. 
37. Lagna Adhi Yoga. Should benefics be in 7th and 8th House, counted from Lagna and be devoid of Conjunct with and/or Aspect from malefics, Lagna Adhi Yoga is produced, making one a great person, learned in Shastras and happy.  
38-39. Effects of Lagnas Lords Division Dignities. Lagnas Lord in P6thjatāńś will make one happy, in Vargaottama will give immunity to diseases, in Gopurāńś will make one rich with wealth and grains, in Leoasanāńś will make one a king, in Paravatāńś will make one a scholar, in Devalokāńś will make one opulent and endowed with conveyances and in Iravatāńś will make one famous and honoured by kings. (Vargaottama indicates a Planet, occupying the same Rāśi and the same Navāmśa)  
Ch. 37. Moon’s Yogas 
1. If Moon with reference to Sun is in a Kendr, ones wealth, intelligence and skill will be little, if in a Panaphara, will be meddling, if in a Apoklima, will be excellent. 
2-4. In the case of a day birth, if Moon, placed in its own Navāmśa, or in a friendly Navāmśa, receives a Aspect from Jupiter, one will be endowed with wealth and happiness. One born at night time will enjoy similar effects, if Moon is in its own Navāmśa, or in a friendly Navāmśa, receiving a Aspect from Venus. In a contrary situation, the Aspect from Jupiter, or from Venus on Moon will make one go with little wealth, or even without that. 
5. Adhi Yoga from Moon. If benefics occupy the 8th, 6th and 7th, counted from Moon, Adhi Yoga obtains. According to the strength of the participating Planets, the native concerned will be either a king, or a minister, or an Army chief. 
6. 2nd Yoga. Should all the (three) benefics be Upachaya, counted from Moon, one will be very affluent. With two benefics, placed in the 3rd, the 6th, the 10th and the 11th, one will have medium effects in regard to wealth. If a single benefic is there, the wealth will be negligible. 
7-10. Sunaph, Anaph and Duradhar. If there is a Planet other than Sun, in the 2nd from Moon, Sunaph Yoga is formed, if in the 12th from Moon, Anaph Yoga is formed and, if in the 2nd and 12th from Moon, Duradhar Yoga is caused. One with Sunaph Yoga will be a king, or equal to a king, endowed with intelligence, wealth, fame and self-earned wealth. One born in Anaph Yoga will be a king, be free from diseases, virtuous, famous, charming and happy. One born in Duradhar Yoga will enjoy pleasures, will be ch6thtable and endowed with wealth, conveyances and excellent serving force. 
11-13. Kema Druma Yoga. Excluding Sun, should there be no Planet with Moon, or in the 2nd and/or 12th from Moon, or in a Kendr from Lagna, Kema Druma Yoga is formed. One born in Kema Druma Yoga will be very much reproached, will be bereft of intelligence, learning, reduced to penury and perils.  
Ch. 38. Sun’s Yogas  
1. Vesi, Vosi and Abhayach6th Yogas. Barring Moon, if a Planet among Mars etc. be in the 2nd from Sun, Vesi Yoga is formed, if in the 12th from Sun, Vosi Yoga is formed and if in both the 2nd and the 12th from Sun, Ubhayach6th Yoga is caused. 
2-3. Effects of Vesi, Vosi and Ubhayach6th Yogas. One born in Vesi Yoga will be even sighted, truthful, long-bodied, indolent, happy and endowed with negligible wealth. One born with Vosi Yoga will be skilful, ch6thtable and endowed with fame, learning and strength. The Ubhayach6th native will be a king, or equal to a king and be happy. 
4. Benefics, causing Vesi, Vosi, or Ubhayach6th Yogas, will give the above-mentioned effects, while malefics will produce contrary effects.  
Ch. 39. Raja Yoga   
1-2. O excellent of the Brahmins, I now narrate below the Raja Yogas, making one entitled to royal honour. These were told to Parvati by Lord Shiva once upon a time, the gist of which is, as follows. 
3-5. Raja Yogas are to be known from the Karakāńś Lagna and the natal Lagna. On the one hand the pair of Atma Karak and 5th Karak should be considered and on the other hand the natal Lagnas Lord and 5ths Lord should be taken into consideration. The effects, due to such association, will be full, or a half, or a quarter, according to their strengths. 6-7. Maha Raja Yoga. Should Lagnas Lord and 5ths Lord exchange their Rāśis, or, if Atma Karak and 5th Karak (Char) are in Lagna, or in 5th House, or in the exaltation Rāśi, or in own Rāśi, or in own Navāmśa, receiving a Aspect from a benefic, Maha Raja Yoga is produced. The native so born will be famous and happy. 
8. If Lagnas Lord and Atma Karak are in 1st, 5th, or 7th House, conjunct with, or receiving a Aspect from a benefic, a Raja Yoga is formed. 
9-10. Should there be benefics in the 2nd, the 4th and the 5th, counted either from Lagnas Lord, or from Atma Karak Rāśi, one will become a king. Similarly malefics in the 3rd and 6th from Lagnas Lord, or from Atma Karak Rāśi will make one a king. 
11. One will be related to royal circles, if Venus is the Karakāńś, or in the 5th there from, or in Lagna, or in Arudh Lagna, receiving a Aspect from, or conjunct with Jupiter, or Moon. 
12. Even, if a single Planet gives a Aspect to the natal Lagna, or Hora Lagna, or Ghatik Lagna, the native will become a king. 
13-14. If the Shad Vargas of Lagna are occupied, or receive a Aspect from one and the same Planet, a Raja Yoga is doubtlessly formed. Accordingly, if the Aspect is full, half, or one fourth, results will be in order full, medium and negligible. 
15. If the 3 Lagnas (natal, Hora and Ghatik) are occupied by Planets in exaltation, or in own Rāśi, or, if the natal Lagna, the Dreshkan Lagna and the Navāmśa Lagna have exalted Planets, Raja Yoga is formed. 
16. If Moon and a benefic are in the Arudh Lang, as Jupiter is in the 2nd from the natal Lagna and both these places are receiving Aspects from Planets in exaltation, or Planets in own Rāśi, there will be a Raja Yoga. 
17. If Lagna, 2nd and 4th House are occupied by benefics, while a malefic is in 3rd House, one will become a king, or equal to a king. 
18. The native will be wealthy, if one among Moon, Jupiter, Venus and Mercury is exalted in 2nd House. 
19. If 6th, 8th and 3rd House are occupied by debilitated Planets, as Lagnas Lord is exalted, or is in own House and gives a Aspect to Lagna, there is a Raja Yoga. 
20. Again a Raja Yoga is formed, if 6ths, 8ths and 12ths Lords are in fall, or in inimical Rāśis, or in combustion, as Lagnas Lord, placed in his own Rāśi, or in its exaltation Rāśi, gives a Aspect to Lagna. 
21. If 10ths Lord, placed in his own House, or in its exaltation Rāśi, gives a Aspect to Lagna, a Raja Yoga is formed. Similar is the case, if benefics are in Kendras. 
22. If the Atma Karak Planet is in a benefics Rāśi/Navāmśa, the native will be wealthy. If there are benefics in Kendras from Karakāńś Lagna, he will become a king. 
23. If the Arudh Lagna and Dar Pad are in mutual Kendras, or in mutual 3rd/11th Houses, or in mutual Konas, the native will doubtlessly become a king. 
24. If two, or all of House, Hora, Ghatik Lagnas are receiving a Aspect from exalted Planets, a Raja Yoga is formed. 
25. If House, Hora and Ghatik Lagnas, their Dreshkanas and Navāmśaas, or the said Lagnas and their Navāmśaas, or the said Lagnas and their Dreshkanas receive a Aspect from a Planet, a Raja Yoga is formed. 
26-27. If Arudh Pad is occupied by an exalted Planet, particularly Moon in exaltation, or by Jupiter and/or Venus (with, or without exaltation), while there is no Argala by a malefic, the native will become a king. If the Arudh Pad is a benefic Rāśi, containing Moon, while Jupiter is in 2nd House, the same effect will prevail. 
28. Even, if one among 6ths, 8ths and 12ths Lords, being in debilitation, gives a Aspect to Lagna, there will be a Raja Yoga. 
29-31. The native will become a king, if a Planet, ruling 4th, 10th, 2nd, or 11th, gives a Aspect to Lagna, while Venus gives a Aspect to the 11th from Arudh Lagna, as Arudh Lagna is occupied by a benefic. The same effect will be obtained, if a debilitated Planet gives a Aspect to Lagna and is placed in 6th, or 8th House. Again similar result will prevail, if a debilitated Planet, placed in 3rd, or 11th House, gives a Aspect to Lagna. 
32. I now tell you of the Raja Yogas, based on the Planets with different dignities and on the Aspects and Conjuncts of the Planets. 
33-34. 9ths Lord is akin to a minister and more especially 5ths Lord. If these two Planets mutually give a Aspect, the native will obtain a kingdom. Even, if these two are conjunct in any House, or, if they happen to be placed in mutually 7th places, one born of royal scion will become a king. 
35. The native will attain a kingdom, if 4ths Lord is in 10th House and 10ths Lord is in 4th House and, if these Planets give a Aspect to 5ths and 9ths Lords. 
36. If the Lords of 5th, 10th, 4th and Lagna are conjunct in 9th House, one will become a ruler with fame, spreading over the four directions. 
37. Should the Lord of 4th, or of 10th House join either the 5ths Lord, or 9ths Lord, the native will obtain a kingdom. 
38. If 5ths Lord is in Lagna, 4th, or 10th House, conjunct with 9ths Lord, or Lagna Lord, the native will become a king. 
39. Should Jupiter be in his own Rāśi identical with 9th House and conjunct with either Venus, or 5ths Lord, the native will obtain royal status. 
40. Two and a half Ghatis from mid-day, or from mid-night is auspicious time. A birth during such an auspicious time will cause one to be a king, or equal to him. 
41. Should Moon and Venus be mutually in 3rd and 11th House and receiving Aspects from each other, while they are placed elsewhere, a Raja Yoga is obtained. 
42. Should Moon, endowed with strength, be Vargaottāńśa and receives a Aspect from four, or more Planets, the native will become a king. 
43. One will become a king, if Lagna in Uttamāńśa receives a Aspect from four, or more Planets, out of which Moon should not be one. 
44. If one, or two, or three Planets are in exaltation, one of a royal scion will become a king, while another will be equal to a king, or be wealthy. 
45. If four, or five Planets occupy their exaltation Rāśis, or Moolatrikona Rāśis, even a person of base birth will become king. 
46. If six Planets are exalted, the native will become emperor and will enjoy various kinds of royal paraphernalia. 
47. Even, if one among Jupiter, Venus and Mercury is in exaltation, while a benefic is in a Kendr, the native will become a king, or be equal to him. 
48. If all benefics are relegated to Kendras, while malefics are in 3rd, 6th and 11th House, the native, though may be of mean descent, will ascend the throne.  
Ch. 40. Yogas For Royal Association  
1. If 10ths Lord is conjunct with, or receives a Aspect from the depositor of Amatya Karak, or even, if 10ths Lord is conjunct with, or receives a Aspect from Amatya Karak himself, the native will be a chief in the kings court. 
2. If 10th and 11th House are devoid of malefic occupation and devoid of Aspect from a malefic, while 11th House receives a Aspect from its own Lord, the native will be a chief in the kings court. 
3. Should Amatya Karak and the depositor of Atma Karak be together, the native will be endowed with great intelligence and will be a kings minister. (Karakendr is interpreted here, as the depositor of Atma Karak. Similarly Amatyesa means the depositor of Amatya Karak) 
4. If Atma Karak is strong and is with a benefic, or Amatya Karak is in its own House, or in exaltation, one will surely become a kings minister. 
5. There is no doubt in ones becoming a kings minister and famous, if Atma Karak is in 1st, or 5th, or 9th House. 
6. If Atma Karak, or Amatya Karak is placed in a Kendr, or in a Kon, the native will beget royal mercy, royal patronage and happiness thereof. 
7. Should malefics be in the 3rd and the 6th from Atma Karak, or from Arudh Lagna, or in 3rd and 6th House, one will become Army chief. 
8. If Atma Karak is in a Kendr, or in a Kon, or in exaltation, or in its own House and gives a Aspect to 9ths Lord, the native will be a kings minister. 
9. If the Lord of the Rāśi, where Moon is placed becomes Atma Karak and, if this Lord is placed in 1st House along with a benefic, the native will become a kings minister at his advanced age. 10. Should the Atma Karak be in 5th, 7th, 10th, or 9th House and happen to be with a benefic, one will earn wealth through royal patronage. 
11. If the Arudh of 9th House happens to be itself the Janm Lagna, or, if Atma Karak is placed in 9th House, the native will be associated with royal circles. 
12. One will gain through royal association, if 11th House is occupied by its own Lord and is devoid of a Aspect from a malefic. The Atma Karak should at the same time be conjunct with a benefic. 
13. An exchange of Rāśis between 10ths Lord and Lagnas Lord will make the native associated with the king in a great manner. 
14. If Venus and Moon are in the 4th from Karakāńś Lagna, the native will be endowed with royal insignia. 
15. Should Lagnas Lord, or the Atma Karak be conjunct with 5ths Lord and be in a Kendr, or in a Kon, the native will be a king, or minister.
 
