
Brihat Parashara Hora Sashtra by Rishi Parashara
Ch. 21. Effects of 10th House 
1. I now explain the effects of 10th House. Listen to these, o Maitreya, in the words of Brahma, Garga and others. 
2. Paternal Happiness. If 10ths Lord is strong and in exaltation, or in its own Rāśi/Navāmśa, the native will derive extreme paternal happiness, will enjoy fame and will perform good deeds. 3. If 10ths Lord is devoid of strength, the native will face obstructions in his work. If Rahu is in an angle, or in a trine, he will perform religious sacrifices, like Jyotishyatoma. 
4. If 10ths Lord is with a benefic, or be in an auspicious House, one will always gain through royal patronage and in business. In a contrary situation, only opposite results will come to pass. 
5. Should 10th and 11th House be both occupied by malefics, the native will indulge only in bad deeds and will defile his own men. 
6. If the Lord of 10th House is relegated to 8th House along with Rahu, the native will hate others; be a great fool and will do bad deeds. 
7. If Saturn, Mars and 10ths Lord are in 7th, as 7ths Lord is with a malefic, the native will be fond of carnal pleasures and of filling his belly. 
8-10 Should 10ths Lord be in exaltation and be in the company of Jupiter, as 9ths Lord is in 10th the native will be endowed with honour, wealth and valor. One will lead a happy life, if 11ths Lord is in 10th and 10ths Lord is in Lagna, or, if the Lord of 10th House is conjunct with the Lord of 11th House in an angle. Should 10ths Lord in strength be in Pisces along Jupiter, the native will doubtless obtain robes, ornaments and happiness. 
11. Should Rahu, Sun, Saturn and Mars be in 11th House, the native will incur cessation of his duties. 
12. One will be learned and wealthy, if Jupiter is in Pisces along with Venus, while Lagnas Lord is strong and Moon is in exaltation. 
13. Should 10ths Lord be in 11th, while 11ths Lord is in 1st House and Venus is in 10th, the native will be endowed with precious stones. 
14. If the 10ths Lord is exalted in an angle, or a trine and is conjunct with Jupiter, or receives a Aspect from Jupiter, one will be endowed with deeds. 
15. Should 10ths Lord be in Lagna along with Lagnas Lord, as Moon is in an angle, or in a trine, the native will be interested in good deeds. 
16. If Saturn is in 10th House along with a debilitated Planet, while 10th House in the Navāmśa Kundali is occupied by a malefic, the native will be bereft of acts. 
17. One will indulge in bad acts, if 10ths Lord is in 8th House, while 8ths Lord is in 10th House with a malefic. 
18. Obstructions to the natives acts will crop up, if 10ths Lord is in fall, as both 10th House and the 10th from 10th House have malefic occupations. 
19-21. Combinations for Fame. One will be endowed with fame, if Moon is in 10th House, while 10ths Lord is in a trine from 10th House and Lagnas Lord is in Lagnas angle. Similar effects will come to pass, if 11ths Lord is in 10th House, while 10ths Lord is strong and gives a Aspect to Jupiter. Fame will come to the native, if 10ths Lord is in 9th House, as Lagnas Lord is in 10th House and Moon is in 5th House. 
22. O excellent of the Brahmins, thus have been told about the effects of 10th House in a brief manner. Other related effects be guessed by you based on the relationship of the Lords of Lagna and of 10th House. 
Ch. 22. Effects of 11th House 
1. O excellent of the Brahmins, I now explain effects relating to 11th House, the auspiciousness of which House will make one happy at all times. 
2. Should 11ths Lord be in 11th itself, or be in an angle, or in a trine from Lagna, there will be many gains. Similarly, if 11ths Lord is exalted, though in combustion there will be many gains. 
3. If 11ths Lord is in 2nd House, while 2nds Lord is in an angle along with Jupiter, the gains will be great. 
4. If 11ths Lord is in 3rd House, while 11th House is occupied by a benefic, the native will gain 2000 Nishkas in his 36th year. 
5. If 11ths Lord is conjunct with a benefic in an angle, or in a trine, the native will acquire 500 Nishkas in his 40th year. 
6. The native will own 6000 Nishkas, if 11th House is occupied by Jupiter, while 2nd House and 9th House are, respectively, taken over by Moon and Venus by position. 
7. Should Jupiter, Mercury and Moon be in the 11th from 11th, the native will be endowed with wealth, grains, fortunes, diamonds, ornaments etc. 
8. One will gain 1000 Nishkas in his 33rd year, if 11ths Lord is in Lagna and Lagnas Lord is in 11th House. 
9. If 11ths Lord is in 2nd House, as 2nds Lord is in 11th House, one will amass abundant fortunes after marriage. 
10. If 11ths Lord is in 3rd House, as 3rds Lord is in 11th House, one will gain wealth through co-borns and will be endowed with excellent ornaments. 
11. There will be no gains in spite of numerous efforts, if 11ths Lord is in fall, in combustion, or be in 6th, 8th, or 12th House with a malefic. 
Ch. 23. Effects of 12th House  
1-4. O Brahmin, now I tell you about the effects of 12th House. There will be expenses on good accounts, if 12ths Lord is with a benefic, or in his own House, or exalted, or, if a benefic occupies 12th. One will own beautiful houses and beds and be endowed with superior scented articles and pleasures, if Moon happens to be 12ths Lord and be exalted, or be in its own Rāśi and/or Navāmśa, or in 11th/9th/5th House in Rāśi/Navāmśa. The said native will live with rich clothes and ornaments, be learned and Lordly. 5-6. And, if 12ths Lord is in 6th, or 8th House, or be in enemy Navāmśa, in debilitation Navāmśa, or in 8th House in Navāmśa, one will be devoid of happiness from wife, be troubled by expenses and deprived of general happiness. If he be in an angle, or trine, the native will beget a spouse. 
7. Just as these effects are derived from 1st House in regard to the native, similar deductions be made about co-borns etc. from 3rd and other Houses. 
8. Planets placed in the visible half of the zodiac will give explicit results, while the ones in the invisible half will confer secret results. 
9. If Rahu is in 12th along with Mars, Saturn and Sun, the native will go to hell. Similar effect will occur, if 12ths Lord is with Sun. 
10. If there is a benefic in 12th, while its Lord is exalted, or is conjunct with, or receives a Aspect from a benefic, one will attain final emancipation. 
11. One will wander from country to country, if 12ths Lord and 12th House are with malefics and 12ths Lord gives a Aspect to, or receives a Aspect from malefics. 
12. One will move in his own country, if 12ths Lord and 12th House are with benefics and 12ths Lord gives a Aspect to, or receives a Aspect from benefics. 
13. Earnings will be through sinful measures, if 12th is occupied by Saturn, or Marsetc. and is not receiving a Aspect from a benefic. 
14. If Lagnas Lord is in 12th, while 12ths Lord is in Lagna with Venus, expenses will be on religious grounds. 
Ch. 24. Effects of the House Lords  
1. Effects of Lagnas Lord in Various Houses (up to Sloka 12). 
Should Lagnas Lord be in Lagna itself, the native will be endowed with physical happiness and prowess. He will be intelligent, fickle-minded, will have two wives and will unite with other females. 
2. If the Lagnas Lord is in 2nd, he will be gainful, scholarly, happy, endowed with good qualities, be religious, honourable and will have many wives. 
3. If Lagnas Lord is in 3rd House, the native will equal a lion in valor, be endowed with all kinds of wealth, be honourable, will have two wives, be intelligent and happy. 
4. If Lagnas Lord is in 4th House, the native will be endowed with paternal and maternal happiness, will have many brothers, be lustful, virtuous and charming. 
5. If Lagnas Lord is in 5th House, the native will have mediocre progenic happiness, will lose his first child, be honourable, given to anger and be dear to king. 
6. If Lagnas Lord is in 6th House and related to a malefic the native will be devoid of physical happiness and will be troubled by enemies, if there is no benefic Aspect. 
7. If Lagnas Lord is a malefic and is placed in 7th House, the natives wife will not live (long). If the Planet in question is a benefic, one will wander aimlessly, face penury and be dejected. He will alternatively become a king (if the said Planet is strong). 
8. If Lagnas Lord is in 8th House, the native will be an accomplished scholar, be sickly, thievish, be given to much anger, be a gambler and will join others wives. 
9. If Lagnas Lord is in 9th House, the native will be fortunate, dear to people, be a devotee of Śrī Vishnu, be skilful, eloquent in speech and be endowed with wife, sons and wealth. 10. If Lagnas Lord is in 10th House, the native will be endowed with paternal happiness, royal honour, fame among men and will doubtlessly have self-earned wealth. 
11. If Lagnas Lord is in 11th House, the native will always be endowed with gains, good qualities, fame and many wives. 
(12) If Lagnas Lord is in 12th House and is devoid of benefic Aspect and/or Conjunct, the native will be bereft of physical happiness, will spend unfruitfully and be given to much anger. 
13. Effects of 2nds Lord in Various Houses (up to Sloka 24). 
If 2nds Lord is in 1st House, the native will be endowed with sons and wealth, be inimical to his family, lustful, hard-hearted and will do others jobs. 
14. If 2nds Lord is in 2nd House, the native will be wealthy, proud, will have two, or more wives and be bereft of progeny. 
15. If 2nds Lord is in 3rd House, the native will be valorous, wise, virtuous, lustful and miserly; all these, when related to a benefic. If related to a malefic, the native will be a heterodox. 
16. If 2nds Lord is in 4th House, the native will acquire all kinds of wealth. If 2nds Lord is exalted and is conjunct with Jupiter, one will be equal to a king. 
17. If 2nds Lord is in 5th House, the native will be wealthy. Not only the native, but also his sons will be intent on earning wealth. 
18. If 2nds Lord is in 6th House along with a benefic, the native will gain wealth through his enemies; if 2nds Lord is conjunct with a malefic, there will be loss through enemies apart from mutilation of shanks. 
19. If 2nds Lord is in 7th House, the native will be addicted to others wives and he will be a doctor. If a malefic is related to the said placement by conjunct with 2nds Lord, or by Aspect, the natives wife will be of questionable character. 
20. If 2nds Lord is in 8th House, the native will be endowed with abundant land and wealth. But he will have limited m6thtal felicity and be bereft of happiness from his elder brother. 
21. If 2nds Lord is in 9th House, the native will be wealthy, diligent, skilful, sick during childhood and will later on be happy and will visit shrines, observing religious code etc. 
22. If 2nds Lord is in 10th House, the native will be libidinous, honourable and learned; he will have many wives and much wealth, but he will be bereft of filial happiness. 
23. If 2nds Lord is in 11th House, the native will have all kinds of wealth, be ever diligent, honourable and famous. 
24. If 2nds Lord is in 12th House, the native will be adventurous, be devoid of wealth and be interested in others wealth, while his eldest child will not keep him happy. 
25. Effects of 3rds Lord in Various Houses (up to Sloka 36). 
If 3rds Lord is in 1st House, the native will have self-made wealth, be disposed to worship, be valorous and be intelligent, although devoid of learning. 
26. If 3rds Lord is in 2nd House, the native will be corpulent, devoid of valor, will not make much efforts, be not happy and will have an eye on others wives and others wealth. 
27. If 3rds Lord is in 3rd House, the native will be endowed with happiness through co-born and will have wealth and sons, be cheerful and extremely happy. 
28. If 3rds Lord is in 4th House, the native will be happy, wealthy and intelligent, but will acquire a wicked spouse. 
29. If 3rds Lord is in 5th House, the native will have sons and be virtuous. If in the process 3rds Lord be conjunct with, or receives a Aspect from a malefic, the native will have a formidable wife. 
30. If 3rds Lord is in 6th House, the native will be inimical to his co-born, be affluent, will not be well disposed to his maternal uncle and be dear to his maternal aunt. 
31. If 3rds Lord is in 7th House, the native will be interested in serving the king. He will not be happy during boyhood, but the end of his life he will be happy. 
32. If 3rds Lord is in 8th House, the native will be a thief, will derive his livelihood serving others and will die at the gate of the royal palace. 
33. If 3rds Lord is in 9th House, the native will lack paternal bliss, will make fortunes through wife and will enjoy progenic and other pleasures. 
34. If 3rds Lord is in 10th House, the native will have all lands of happiness and self-made wealth and be interested in nurturing wicked females. 
35. If 3rds Lord is in 11th House, then native will always gain in trading, be intelligent, although not literate, be adventurous and will serve others. 
36. If 3rds Lord is in 12th, the native will spend on evil deeds, will have a wicked father and will be fortunate through a female. 
37. Effects of 4ths Lord in Various Houses (up to Sloka 48). 
If 4ths Lord is in 1st House, the native will be endowed with learning, virtues, ornaments, lands, conveyances and maternal happiness. 
38. If 4ths Lord is in 2nd House, the native will enjoy pleasures, all kinds of wealth, family life and honour and be adventurous. He will be cunning in disposition. 
39. If 4ths Lord is in 3rd House, the native will be valorous, will have servants, be liberal, virtuous and ch6thtable and will possess self-earned wealth. He will be free from diseases. 
40. If 4ths Lord is in 4th, the native will be a minister and will possess all kinds of wealth. He will be skilful, virtuous, honourable, learned, happy and be well disposed to his spouse. 
41. If 4ths Lord is in 5th House, the native will be happy and be liked by all. He will be devoted to Śrī Vishnu, be virtuous, honourable and will have self-earned wealth. 
42. If 4ths Lord is in 6th House, the native will be devoid of maternal happiness, be given to anger, be a thief and a conjurer, be independent in action and be indisposed. 
43. If 4ths Lord is in 7th House, the native will be endowed with a high degree of education, will sacrifice his patrimony and be akin to the dumb in an assembly. 
44. If 4ths Lord is in 8th House, the native will be devoid of domestic and other comforts, will not enjoy much parental happiness and be equal to a neuter. 
45. If 4ths Lord is in 9th House, the native will be dear to one and all, be devoted to God, be virtuous, honourable and endowed with every land of happiness. 
46. If 4ths Lord is in 10th House, the native will enjoy royal honors, be an alchemist, be extremely pleased, will enjoy pleasures and will conquer his five senses. 
47. If 4ths Lord is in 11th House, the native will have fear of secret disease, he will be liberal, virtuous, ch6thtable and helpful to others. 
48. If 4ths Lord is in 12th House the native will be devoid of domestic and other comforts, will have vices and be foolish and indolent. 
49. Effects of 5ths Lord in Various Houses (up to Sloka 60). 
If 5ths Lord is in Lagna, the native will be scholarly, be endowed with progenic happiness, be a miser, be crooked and will steal others wealth. 
50. If 5ths Lord is in 2nd House, the native will have many sons and wealth, be a pater familias, be honourable, be attached to his spouse and be famous in the world. 
51. If 5ths Lord is in 3rd, the native will be attached to his co-born, be a tale bearer and a miser and be always interested in his own work. 
52. If 5ths Lord is in 4th House, the native will be happy, endowed with maternal happiness, wealth and intelligence and be a king, or a minister, or a preceptor. 
53. If 5ths Lord is in 5th House, the native will have progeny, if related to a benefic; there will be no issues, if malefic is related to 5ths Lord, placed in 5th House. 5ths Lord in 5th House will, however, make one virtuous and dear to friends. 
54. If 5ths Lord is in 6th House, the native will obtain such sons, who will be equal to his enemies, or will lose them, or will acquire an adopted, or purchased son. 
55. If 5ths Lord is in 7th House, the native will be honourable, very religious, endowed with progenic happiness and be helpful to others. 
56. If 5ths Lord is in 8th House, the native will not have much progenic happiness, be troubled by cough and pulmonary disorders, be given to anger and be devoid of happiness. 
57. If 5ths Lord is in 9th House, the native will be a prince, or equal to him, will author treatises, be famous and will shine in his race. 
58. If 5ths Lord is in 10th House, the native will enjoy a Raja Yoga and various pleasures and be very famous. 
59. If 5ths Lord is in 11th House, the native will be learned, dear to people, be an author of treatises, be very skilful and be endowed with many sons and wealth. 
60. If 5ths Lord is in 12th House, the native will be bereft of happiness from his own sons, will have an adopted, or purchased son. 
61. Effects of 6ths Lord in Various Houses (up to Sloka 72). 
If 6ths Lord is in 1st House, the native will be sickly, famous, inimical to his own men, rich, honourable, adventurous and virtuous. 
62. If 6ths Lord is in 2nd House, the native will be adventurous, famous among his people, will live in alien countries, be happy, be a skilful speaker and be always interested in his own work. 
63. If 6ths Lord is in 3rd House, the native will be given to anger, be bereft of courage, inimical to all of his co-born and will have disobedient servants. 
64. If 6ths Lord is in 4th House, the native will be devoid maternal happiness, be intelligent, be a tale bearer, be jealous, evil-minded and very rich. 
65. If 6ths Lord is in 5th House, the native will have fluctuating finances. He will incur enmity with his sons and friends. He will be happy, selfish and kind. 
66. If 6ths Lord is in 6th House, the native will have enmity with the group of his kinsmen, but be friendly to others and will enjoy mediocre happiness in matters, like wealth. 
67. If 6ths Lord is in 7th House, the native will be deprived of happiness through wedlock. He will be famous, virtuous, honourable, adventurous and wealthy. 
68. If 6ths Lord is in 8th House, the native will be sickly, inimical, will desire others wealth, be interested in others wives and be impure. 
69. If 6ths Lord is in 9th House, the native will trade in wood and stones (Pashan also means poison) and will have fluctuating professional fortunes. 
70. If 6ths Lord is in 10th House, the native will be well known among his men, will not be respectfully disposed to his father and will be happy in foreign countries. He will be a gifted speaker. 
71. If 6ths Lord is in 11th House, the native will gain wealth through his enemies, be virtuous, adventurous and will be somewhat bereft of progenic happiness. 
72. If 6ths Lord is in 12th House, the native will always spend on vices, be hostile to learned people and will torture living beings. 
73. Effects of 7ths Lord in Various Houses (up to Sloka 84). 
If 7ths Lord is in 1st House, the native will go to others wives, be wicked, skilful, devoid of courage and afflicted by windy diseases. 
74. If 7ths Lord is in 2nd House, the native will have many wives, will gain wealth through his wife and be procrastinating in nature. 
75. If 7ths Lord is in 3rd House, the native will face loss of children and sometimes with great difficulty there will exist a living son. There is also the possibility of birth of a daughter. 
76. If 7ths Lord is in 4th House, the wife of the native will not be under his control. He will be fond of truth, intelligent and religious. He will suffer from dental diseases. 
77. If 7ths Lord is in 5th House, the native will be honourable, endowed with all (i.e. seven principal) virtues, always delighted and endowed with all kinds of wealth. 
78. If 7ths Lord is in 6th House, the native will beget a sickly wife and he will be inimical to her. He will be given to anger and will be devoid of happiness. 
79. If 7ths Lord is in 7th House, the native will be endowed with happiness through wife, be courageous, skilful and intelligent, but only afflicted by windy diseases. 
80. If 7ths Lord is in 8th House, the native will be deprived of m6thtal happiness. His wife will be troubled by diseases, be devoid of good disposition and will not obey the native. 
81. If 7ths Lord is in 9th House, the native will have union with many women, be well disposed to his own wife and will have many undertakings. 
82. If 7ths Lord is in 10th House, the native will beget a disobedient wife, will be religious and endowed with wealth, sons etc. 
83. If 7ths Lord is in 11th House, the native will gain wealth through his wife, be endowed with less happiness from sons etc. and will have daughters. 
84. If 7ths Lord is in 12th House, the native will incur penury, be a miser and his livelihood will be related to clothes. His wife will be a spendthrift. 
85. Effects of 8ths Lord in Various Houses (up to Sloka 96). 
If 8ths Lord is in 1st House, the native will be devoid of physical felicity and will suffer from wounds. He will be hostile to gods and Brahmins. 
86. If 8ths Lord is in 2nd House, the native will be devoid of bodily vigor, will enjoy a little wealth and will not regain lost wealth. 
87. If 8ths Lord is in 3rd House, the native will be devoid of fraternal happiness, be indolent and devoid of servants and strength. 
88. If 8ths Lord is in 4th House, the child will be deprived of its mother. He will be devoid of a house, lands and happiness and will doubtlessly betray his friends. 
89. If 8ths Lord is in 5th House, the native will be dull witted, will have limited number of children, be long-lived and wealthy. 
90. If 8ths Lord is in 6th House, the native will win over his enemies, be afflicted by diseases and during childhood will incur danger through snakes and water. 
91. If 8ths Lord is in 7th House, the native will have two wives. If 8ths Lord is conjunct with a malefic in 7th House, there will surely be downfall in his business. 
92. If 8ths Lord is in 8th House, the native will be long-lived. If the said Planet is weak, being in 8th House, the longevity will be medium, while the native will be a thief, be blameworthy and will blame others as well. 
93. If 8ths Lord is in 9th House, the native will betray his religion, be a heterodox, will beget a wicked wife and will steal others wealth. 
94. If 8ths Lord is in 10th House, the native will be devoid of paternal bliss, be a talebearer and be bereft of livelihood. If there is a Aspect in the process from a benefic, then these evils will not mature. 
95. If 8ths Lord along with a malefic is in 11th House, the native will be devoid of wealth and will be miserable in boyhood, but happy later on. Should 8ths Lord be conjunct with a benefic and be in 11th House, the native will be long-lived. 
96. If 8ths Lord is in 12th House, the native will spend on evil deeds and will incur a short life. More so, if there be additionally a malefic in the said House. 
97. Effects of 9ths Lord in Various Houses (up to Sloka 108). 
If 9ths Lord is in Lagna, the native will be fortunate, will be honoured by the king, be virtuous, charming, learned and honoured by the public. 
98. If 9ths Lord is in 2nd House, the native will be a scholar, be dear to all, wealthy, sensuous and endowed with happiness from wife, sons etc. 
99. If 9ths Lord is in 3rd House, the native will be endowed with fraternal bliss, be wealthy, virtuous and charming. 
100. If 9ths Lord is in 4th House, the native will enjoy houses, conveyances and happiness, will have all kinds of wealth and be devoted to his mother. 
101. If 9ths Lord is in 5th House, the native will be endowed with sons and prosperity, devoted to elders, bold, ch6thtable and learned. 
102. If 9ths Lord is in 6th House, the native will enjoy meager prosperity, be devoid of happiness from maternal relatives and be always troubled by enemies. 
103. O Brahmin, If 9ths Lord is in 7th House, the native beget happiness after marriage, be virtuous and famous. 
104. If 9ths Lord is in 8th House, the native will not be prosperous and will not enjoy happiness from his elder brother. 
105. If 9ths Lord is in 9th House, the native will be endowed with abundant fortunes, virtues and beauty and will enjoy much happiness from co-born. 
106. If 9ths Lord is in 10th House, the native will be a king, or equal to him, or be a minister, or an Army chief, be virtuous and dear to all. 
107. If 9ths Lord is in 11th House, the native will enjoy financial gains day by day, be devoted to elders, virtuous and meritorious in acts. 
108. If 9ths Lord is in 12th House, the native will incur loss of fortunes, will always spend on auspicious acts and will become poor on account of entertaining guests. 
109. Effects of 10ths Lord in Various Houses (up to Sloka 120). 
If 10ths Lord is in 1st House, the native will be scholarly, famous, be a poet, will incur diseases in boyhood and be happy later on. His wealth will increase day by day. 
110 If 10ths Lord is in 2nd House, the native will be wealthy, virtuous, honoured by the king, ch6thtable and will enjoy happiness from father and others. 
111. If 10ths Lord is in 3rd House, the native will enjoy happiness from brothers and servants, be valorous, virtuous, eloquent and truthful. 
112. If 10ths Lord is in 4th House, the native will be happy, be always interested in his mothers welfare, will Lord over conveyances, lands and houses, be virtuous and wealthy. 
113. If 10ths Lord is in 5th House, the native will be endowed with all kinds of learning, he will be always delighted and he will be wealthy and endowed with sons. 
114. If 10ths Lord is in 6th House, the native will be bereft of paternal bliss. Although he may be skilful, he will be bereft of wealth and be troubled by enemies. 
115. If 10ths Lord is in 7th House, the native will be endowed with happiness through wife, be intelligent, virtuous, eloquent, truthful and religious. 
116. If 10ths Lord is in 8th House, the native will be devoid of acts, long-lived and intent on blaming others. 
117. If 10ths Lord is in 9th House, one born of royal scion will become a king, whereas an ordinary native will be equal to a king. This placement will confer wealth and progenic happiness etc. 
118. If 10ths Lord is in 10th House, the native will be skilful in all jobs, be valorous, truthful and devoted to elders. 
119. If 10ths Lord is in 11th House, the native will be endowed with wealth, happiness and sons. He will be virtuous, truthful and always delighted. 
120. If 10ths Lord is in 12th House, the native will spend through royal abodes, will have fear from enemies and will be worried in spite of being skilful. 
121. Effects of 11ths Lord in Various Houses (up to Sloka 132). 
If 11ths Lord is in 1st House, the native will be genuine in disposition, be rich, happy, even-sighted, be a poet, be eloquent in speech and be always endowed with gains. 
122. If 11ths Lord is in 2nd House, the native will be endowed with all kinds of wealth and all kinds of accomplishments, ch6thtable, religious and always happy. 
123. If 11ths Lord is in 3rd House, the native will be skilful in all jobs, wealthy, endowed with fraternal bliss and may sometimes incur gout pains. 
124. If 11ths Lord is in 4th House, the native will gain from maternal relatives, will undertake visits to shrines and will possess happiness of house and lands. 
125. If 11ths Lord is in 5th House, the native will be happy, educated and virtuous. He will be religious and happy. 
126. If 11ths Lord is in 6th House, the native will be afflicted by diseases, be cruel, living in foreign places and troubled by enemies. 
127. If 11ths Lord is in 7th House, the native will always gain through his wifes relatives, be liberal, virtuous, sensuous and will remain at the command of his spouse. 
128. If 11ths Lord is in 8th House, the native will incur reversals in his undertakings and will live long, while his wife will predecease him. 
129. If 11ths Lord is in 9th House, the native will be fortunate, skilful, truthful, honoured by the king and be affluent. 
130. If 11ths Lord is in 10th House, the native will be honoured by the king, be virtuous, attached to his religion, intelligent, truthful and will subdue his senses. 
131. If 11ths Lord is in 11th House, the native will gain in all his undertakings, while his learning and happiness will be on the increase day by day. 
132. If 11ths Lord is in 12th House, the native will always depend on good deeds, be sensuous, will have many wives and will befriend barb6thans. 
133. Effects of 12ths Lord in Various Houses (up to Sloka 144). 
If 12ths Lord is in 1st House, the native will be a spendthrift, be weak in constitution, will suffer from phlegmatic disorders and be devoid of wealth and learning. 
134. If 12ths Lord is in 2nd House, the native will always spend on inauspicious deeds, be religious, will speak sweetly and will be endowed with virtues and happiness. 
135. If 12ths Lord is in 3rd House, the native will be devoid of fraternal bliss, will hate others and will promote self-nourishment. 
136. If 12ths Lord is in 4th House, the native will be devoid of maternal happiness and will day by day accrue losses with respect to lands, conveyances and houses. 
137. If 12ths Lord is in 5th House, the native will be bereft of sons and learning. He will spend, as well as visit shrines in order to beget a son. 
138. If 12ths Lord is in 6th House, the native will incur enmity with his own men, be given to anger, be sinful, miserable and will go to others wives. 
(139) If 12ths Lord is in 7th House, the native will incur expenditure on account of his wife, will not enjoy conjugal bliss and will be bereft of learning and strength. 
140. If 12ths Lord is in 8th House, the native will always gain, will speak affably, will enjoy a medium span of life and be endowed with all good qualities. 
141. If 12ths Lord is in 9th House, the native will dishonour his elders, be inimical even to his friends and be always intent on achieving his own ends. 
142. If 12ths Lord is in 10th House, the native will incur expenditure through royal persons and will enjoy only moderate paternal bliss. 
143. If 12th Lord is in 11th House, the native will incur losses, be brought up by others and will sometimes gain through others. 
144. If 12ths Lord is in 12th House, the native will only face heavy expenditure, will not have physical felicity, be irritable and spiteful. 
145-148. Miscellaneous. O Brahmin, those are the effects of House Lords, which are to be deduced, considering their strengths and weaknesses. In the case of a Planet, owning two Houses, the results are to be deducted based on its two lordships. If contrary results are thus indicated, the results will be nullified, while results of v6thed nature will come to pass. The Planet will yield full, half, or a quarter of the effects according to its strength being full, medium and negligible, respectively. Thus I have told you about the effects, due to House Lords in various Houses. 
Ch. 25. Effects of Non-Luminous Planets  
1. Thus I have explained the effects of the seven Planets, viz. Sun, Moon, Mars, Mercury, Jupiter, Venus, Saturn, Rahu and Ketu. Now I tell you about the effects of non-luminous Planets. 
2. Effects of Dhum in Various Houses (up to Sloka 13). If Dhum is in Lagna, the native will be valiant, endowed with beautiful eyes, stupefied in disposition, unkind, wicked and highly short-tempered. 
3. If Dhum is in 2nd House, the native will be sickly, wealthy, devoid of a limb, will incur humiliation at royal level, be dull witted and be a eunuch. 
4. Dhum is in 3rd House, the native will be intelligent, very bold, delighted, eloquent and be endowed with men and wealth. 
5. If Dhum is in 4th House, the native will be grieved on account of being given up by his female, but will be learned in all Shastras. 
6. If Dhum is in 5th House, the native will have limited progeny, be devoid of wealth, be great, will eat anything and be bereft of friends and Mantras. 
7. If Dhum is in 6th House, the native will be strong, will conquer his enemies, be very brilliant, famous and free from diseases. 
8. If Dhum is in 7th House, the native will be penniless, be ever sensuous, skilful in going to others females and be always devoid of brilliance. 
9. If Dhum is in 8th House, the native will be bereft of courage, but be enthusiastic, be truthful, disagreeable, hardhearted and selfish. 
10. If Dhum is in 9th House, the native will be endowed sons and fortunes, be rich, honourable, kind, religious and well disposed to his relatives. 
11. If Dhum is in 10th House, the native will be endowed with sons and fortunes, be delighted, intelligent, happy and truthful. 
12. If Dhum is in 11th House, the native will be endowed with wealth, grains and gold, be beautiful, will have knowledge of arts, be modest and be skilful in singing. 
13. If Dhum is in 12th House, the native will be morally fallen, will indulge in sinful acts, be interested in others wives, addicted to vices, unkind and crafty. 
14. Effects of Vyatipat in Various Houses (up to Sloka 25). If Vyatipat (also known in short, as Pat) is in 1st House, the native will be troubled by miseries, be cruel, will indulge in destructive acts, be foolish and will be disposed to his relatives. 
15. If Vyatipat is in 2nd House, the native will be morally crooked, be bilious, will enjoy pleasures, be unkind, but grateful, be wicked and sinful. 
16. If Vyatipat is in 3rd House, the native will be firm in disposition, be a warrior, be liberal, very rich, dear to the king and be head of an Army. 
17. If Vyatipat is in 4th House, the native will be endowed with relatives etc., but not sons and fortunes. 
18. If Vyatipat is in 5th House, the native will be poor, be charming in appearance, will have imBalaances of phlegm, bile and wind, be hard-hearted and shameless. 
19. If Vyatipat is in 6th House, the native will destroy his enemies, be physically mighty, skilful in use of all kinds of weapons and in arts and be peaceful in disposition. 
20. If Vyatipat is in 7th House, the native will be bereft of wealth, wife and sons, will subdue to females, be miserable, sensuous, shameless and friendly to others. 
21. If Vyatipat is in 8th House, the native will have deformity of eyes, be ugly, unfortunate, spiteful to Brahmins and be troubled by disorders of blood. 
22. If Vyatipat is in 9th House, the native will have many kinds of business and many friends; he will be very learned, well disposed to his wife and he will be eloquent. 
23. If Vyatipat is in 10th House, the native will be religious, peaceful, skilful in religious acts, very learned and far-sighted. 
24. If Vyatipat is in 11th House, the native will be extremely opulent, be honourable, truthful, firm in policy, endowed with many horses and be interested in singing. 
25. If Vyatipat is in 12th House, the native will be given to anger, associated with many activities, disabled, irreligious and hate his own relatives. 
26. Effects of Paridhi (or Prithvesh) in Various Houses (up to Sloka 37). If P6thdhi is in 1st House, the native will be learned, truthful, peaceful, rich, endowed with sons, pure, ch6thtable and dear to elders. 
27. If Parithdhi is in 2nd House, the native will be wealthy, charming, will enjoy pleasures, be happy, very religious and be a Lord. 
28. If Parithdhi is in 3rd House, the native will be fond of his wife, be very charming, pious, well disposed to his men, be a servant and be respectful of his elders. 
29. If Parithdhi is in 4th House, the native will be wonder-struck, helpful to enemies as well, kind, endowed with everything and be skilful in singing. 
30. If Parithdhi is in 5th House, the native will be affluent, virtuous, splendorous, affectionate, religious and dear to his wife. 
31. If Parithdhi is in 6th House, the native will be famous and wealthy, be endowed with sons and pleasures, be helpful to all and will conquer his enemies. 
32. If Parithdhi is in 7th House, the native will have limited number of children, be devoid of happiness, be of mediocre intelligence, very hard-headed and will have a sickly wife. 
33. If Parithdhi is in 8th House, the native will be spiritually disposed, peaceful, strong-bodied, firm in decision, religious and gentle. 
34. If Parithdhi is in 9th House, the native will be endowed with sons, be happy, brilliant, very affluent, be devoid of excessive passion, be honourable and be happy with even a iota. 
35. If Parithdhi is in 10th House, the native will be versed in arts, will enjoy pleasures, be strong-bodied and be learned in all Shastras. 
6. If Parithdhi is in 11th House, the native will enjoy pleasures through women, be virtuous, intelligent, dear to his people and will suffer disorders of digestive fire. 
37. If Parithdhi is in 12th House, the native will always be a spendthrift, be miserable, firm and will dishonour elders. 
38. Effects of Chap (Indr dhanus, or Kodanda, up to Sloka 49). If Chap is in 1st House, the native will be endowed with wealth, grains and gold, be grateful, agreeable and devoid of all actions. 
39. If Chap is in 2nd House, the native will speak affably, be very rich, modest, learned, charming and religious. 
40. If Chap is in 3rd House, the native will be a miser, be versed in many arts, will indulge in thieving, be devoid of some limb and be unfriendly. 
41. If Chap is in 4th House, the native will be happy, endowed with quadrupeds, wealth, grains etc., be honoured by the king and be devoid of sickness. 
42. If Chap is in 5th House, the native will be splendorous, far-sighted, pious, affable and will acquire prosperity in all his undertakings. 
43. If Chap is in 6th House, the native will destroy his enemies, be happy, affectionate, pure and will achieve plentifulness in all his undertakings. 
44. If Chap is in 7th House, the native will be wealthy, endowed with all virtues, learned in Shastras, religious and agreeable. 
45. If Chap is in 8th House, the native will be interested in others [213] jobs, be cruel, interested in others wives and have a defective limb. 
46. If Chap is in 9th House, the native will perform penance, will take to religious observations, be highly learned and be famous among men. 
47. If Chap is in 10th House, the native will be endowed with many sons, abundant wealth, cows, buffaloes etc. and will be famous among men. 
48. If Chap is in 11th House, the native will gain many treasures, will be free from diseases, very fiery in disposition, affectionate to his wife and will have knowledge of Mantras and weapons. 
49. If Chap is in 12th House, the native will be wicked, very honourable, evil in disposition, shameless, will go to others females and be ever poor. 
50. Effects of Dhwaj (Sikhi, or UpaKetu) in Various Houses (up to Sloka 61). If Dhwaj is in 1st House, the native will be skilful in all branches of learning, be happy, efficient in speech, agreeable and be very affectionate. 
51. If Dhwaj is in 2nd House, the native will be a good and affable speaker, be splendorous, will write poetry, be scholarly, honourable, modest and endowed with conveyances. 
52. If Dhwaj is in 3rd House, the native will be miserly, cruel acts, thin-bodied, poor and will incur severe diseases. 
53. If Dhwaj is in 4th House, the native will be charming, very virtuous, gentle, interested in Vedic Knowledge and be always happy. 
54. If Dhwaj is in 5th House, the native will be happy, will enjoy pleasures, be versed in arts, skilled in expedients, intelligent, eloquent and will respect elders. 
55. If Dhwaj is in 6th House, the native will be ominous for material relatives, will win over his enemies, be endowed with many relatives, valiant, splendorous and skilful. 
56. If Dhwaj is in 7th House, the native will be interested in gambling, be sensuous, will enjoy pleasures and will befriend prostitutes. 
57. If Dhwaj is in 8th House, the native will be interested in base acts, be sinful, shameless, will blame others, will lack in m6thtal happiness and will take others side. 
58. If Dhwaj is in 9th House, the native will wear badges, be delighted, helpfully disposed to all and he will be skilled in religious deeds. 
59. O Brahmin, if Dhwaj is in 10th House, the native will be endowed with happiness and fortunes, be fond of females, be ch6thtable and will befriend Brahmins. 
60. If Dhwaj is in 11th House, the native will ever acquire gains, be very religious, honourable, affluent, fortunate, valiant and skilled in sacrificial rites. 
61. If Dhwaj is in 12th House, the native will be interested in sinful acts, be valiant, untrustworthy, unkind, interested in others females and be short-tempered. 
62. Effects of Gulika in Various Houses (up to Sloka 73). If Gulika is in 1st House, the native will be afflicted by diseases, be lustful, sinful, crafty, wicked and very miserable. 
63. If Gulika is in 2nd House, the native will be unsightly in appearance, miserable, mean, given to vices, shameless and penniless. 
64. If Gulika is in 3rd House, the native will be charming in appearance, will head a village, be fond of virtuous men and be honoured by the king. 
65. If Gulika is in 4th House, the native will be sickly, devoid of happiness, sinful and afflicted due to windy and billious excesses. 
66. If Gulika is in 5th House, the native will not be praise-worthy, be poor, short-lived, spiteful, mean, be a eunuch, be subdued by his wife and be a heterodox. 
67. If Gulika is in 6th House, the native will be devoid of enemies, be strong-bodied, splendorous, liked by his wife, enthusiastic, very friendly and helpful in disposition. 
68. If Gulika is in 7th House, the native will subdue to his spouse, be sinful, will go to others females, be emaciated, devoid of friendship and will live on his wifes wealth. 
69. If Gulika is in 8th House, the native will be troubled by hunger, be miserable, cruel, very much short-tempered, very unkind, poor and bereft of good qualities. 
70. If Gulika is in 9th House, the native will undergo many ordeals, be emaciated, will perform evil acts, be very unkind, sluggish and be a talebearer. 
71. If Gulika is in 10th House, the native will be endowed with sons, be happy, will enjoy many things, be fond of worshipping gods and fire and will practice meditation and religion. 
72. If Gulika is in 11th House, the native will enjoy women of class, be a leader of men, be helpful to his relatives, be short stature and be an emperor. 
73. If Gulika is in 12th House, the native will indulge in base deeds, be sinful, defective-limbed, unfortunate, indolent and will join mean people. 
74. Effects of Pranapads Position with reference to Lagna and in Various Houses (up to Sloka 85). If Pranapad is in 1st House, the native will be weak, sickly, dumb, lunatic, dull witted, defective-limbed, miserable and emaciated. 
75. If Pranapad is in 2nd House, the native will be endowed with abundant grains, abundant wealth, abundant attendants, abundant children and be fortunate. 
76. If Pranapad is in 3rd House, the native will be injurious (or mischievous), proud, hard-hearted, very dirty and be devoid of respect for elders. 
77. If Pranapad is in 4th House, the native will be happy, friendly, attached to females and elders, soft and truthful. 
78. If Pranapad is in 5th House, the native will be happy, will do good acts, be kind and very affectionate. 
79. If Pranapad is in 6th House, the native will be subdued by his relatives and enemies, be sharp, will have defective digestive fire, be wicked, sickly, affluent and short-lived. 
80. If Pranapad is in 7th House, the native will be green-eyed, ever libidinous, fierce in appearance, be not worth respect and be ill-disposed. 
81. If Pranapad is in 8th House, the native will be afflicted by diseases, be troubled and will incur misery on account of the king, relatives, servants and sons. 
82. If Pranapad is in 9th House, the native will be endowed with sons, be very rich, fortunate, charming, will serve others and be not wicked, but be skilful. 
83. If Pranapad is in 10th House, the native will be heroic, intelligent, skilful, be an expert in carrying out royal orders and will worship gods. 
84 If Pranapad is in 11th House, the native will be famous, virtuous, learned, wealthy, fair-complexioned and attached to mother. 
85. If Pranapad is in 12th House, the native will be mean, wicked, defective-limbed, will hate Brahmins and relatives and suffer from eye diseases, or be one-eyed. 
86-87. O Brahmin, these are the effects for Dhum etc. Before declring these results, the effects of Sun and other Planets should be wisely conceived by their positions, relations and Aspects apart from their strength, or weakness. 
Ch. 26. Evaluation of Aspects of Planets  
1. O Glorious, it is said, that Aspects (of Planets) and their strengths are to be known in deciding the effects. How many kinds are these? Please clarify doubts.  
2-5. Aspects of the Planets. O Brahmin, I have earlier stated Aspects, based on Rāśis. The other kind is between Planets, which I detail below. 3rd and 10th, 5th and 9th, 4th and 8th and lastly 7th. On these places the Aspects increase gradually in slabs of quarters, i.e ｼ, , ｾ and full. The effects will also be proportionate. All Planets give a Aspect to the 7th fully. Saturn, Jupiter and Marshave special Aspects, respectively, on the 3rd and the 10th, the 5th and the 9th and the 4th and the 8th. The ancient preceptors have explained these, which ordinary. By subtle mathematical calculations these Aspects will have to be clearly understood, as under. 
6-8. Evaluation of the Aspects of the Planets. Deduct the longitude of the Planet (or House), that receives a Aspect, from that of the Planet, which gives the Aspect. If the sum exceeds six Rāśis, deduct the sum again from 10 Rāśis. Convert the latter sum into degrees and divide by two. The resultant product is Aspect Kona (or aspectual angle). If the difference is in excess of 5 Rāśis, ignore the Rāśis and multiply the degrees etc. by 2, which is the value of the Aspect. If the difference is in excess of 4 Rāśis, deduct it from 5 Rāśis, and the resultant degees etc. become the Aspect value. If the difference is in excess of 3 Rāśis, deduct it from 4 Rāśis and (increase 30 by) halve the product to get the Aspect value. If the difference is above 2 Rāśis, ignore the Rāśis and add 15 to the degrees etc. to get the Aspect value. If it is in excess of one Rāśi, ignore the Rāśis and divide the degrees by 2 to get the Aspect value.  
9-10. Special consideration for Saturn’s Aspects. O Brahmin, if Saturn is the Planet, that gives a Aspect, find out the difference between him and the Planet, that receives the Aspect; if the sum is above 1 Rāśi, multiply the degrees etc. by 2 to get the Aspect value. If the sum is above nine Rāśis, the degrees to elapse be doubled to get the Aspect value. If the sum is above 2 Rāśis, the degrees etc. be halved and deducted from 60. If the sum exceeds 8 Rāśis, add to the degrees etc. a figure of 30 to get the Aspect value. In other cases, the sums be processed, as explained earlier. 
11. Special consideration for Mars’s Aspects. Deduct the longitude of Marsfrom that of the Planet, that receives the Aspect. If the sum is 3 Rāśis & c, or 7 Rāśis & c, the degrees etc. be reduced from 60. If it is above 2 Rāśis, the degrees etc. be increased by half of it and superadd 15. If the sum is 6 Rāśis, one Rup is the value. 
12. Special consideration for Jupiter’s Aspects. Deduct the longitude of Jupiter from that of the Planet, that receives the Aspect from Jupiter. If the resultant sum is 3 Rāśis & c, or 7 Rāśis & c, halve the degrees etc. and increase it by 15. It the sum is 4 Rāśis & c, or 8 Rāśis & c, the degrees etc. be subtracted from 60. This will be the Aspect value. The sum, being in conformity with others than these, be treated, as stated earlier. 
Ch. 27. Evaluation Of Strengths 
Shad Bala consists of the following: Sthan Bala (positional), Dig Bala (directional), Kaal Bala (Temporal), inclusive of Ayan Bala (equinoctial), Chesht Bala (motional), Naisargika Bala (natural), Drik Bala (aspectual). These strengths are computed for the seven Planets from Sun to Saturn. The nodes are not considered.  
Sthan Bala comprises of the following considerations: Uchch Bala (exaltation), Sapt Vargaaj Bala (strength accruing out of positions in Rāśi, Hora, Dreshkan, Saptāńś, Navāmśa, Dvadashāńś and Trimshāńś), OjhayugmaRāśiāńś Bala (acquired by placement in odd, or even Rāśi and in odd, or even Navāmśa), Kendradi Bala (due to placement in Kon, or Panaphara, or Apoklima House), Dreshkan Bala (due to placement in first, second, or third decanate of a Rāśi).  
Kaal Bala comprises of the following subdivisions: Nathonnata Bala (diurnal and nocturnal), Paksh Bala (fortnight), Tribhag Bala (due to day/night being made in 3 parts), Varsh, Maas, Dina and Hora Bala (Varsh - astrological year, Maas - month, Dina - weekday and Hora - planetary hour), Ayan Bala (equinoctial), Yudhdh Bala (due to partaking in war between Planets).  
1-1. Sthan Bala (up to Sloka 6). Firstly Uchch Bala. Now about the strengths by classes positional, temporal etc. Deduct from the longitude of the Planet its (deep) debilitation point. If the sum is less than 6 Rāśis, consider it, as it is; if it exceeds 6 Rāśis, deduct the same from 12 Rāśis. The sum so got be converted into degrees etc. and divided by 3, which is the Planets Uchch Bala in Virupas. 
2-4. Sapt Vargaaj Bala. If a Planet is in its Moolatrikona Rāśi, it gets 45 Virupas, in Svasth Rāśi 30 Virupas, in Pramudit Rāśi 20 Virupas, in Shant Rāśi 15 Virupas, in Din Rāśi 10 Virupas, in Dukhita Rāśi 4 Virupas and in Khal Rāśi 2 Virupas. Similarly these values occur for the other 6 divisional occupations, viz. Hora, Dreshkan, Saptāńś, Navāmśa, Dvadashāńś and Trimshāńś. When all these are added together the Planets Sapt Vargaaj Bala emerges. 
4. OjhayugmaRāśiāńś Bala. Each of Venus and Moon in even Rāśis and others in odd Rāśis acquire a quarter of Rupa. These are applicable to such Navāmśaas also. 
5. Kendradi Bala. A Planet in a Kon gets full strength, while one in Panaphara House gets half and the one in Apoklima House gets a quarter, as Kendradi Bala. 
6. Dreshkan Bala. Male, female and hermaphrodite Planets, respectively, get a quarter Rupa according to placements in the first, second and third decanates.  
7-7. Dig Bala. Deduct 4th House (Nadir) from the longitudes of Sun and Mars, 7th House from that of Jupiter and Mercury, 10th House from that of Venus and Moon and lastly Lagna from that of Saturn. If the sum is above 180 degrees, deduct the sum from 360. The sum arrived in either way be divided by 3, which will be Dig Bala of the Planet. 
8-9. Kaala Bala (up to Sloka 17). Firstly Nathonnata Bala. Find out the difference between midnight and the apparent birth time, which is called Unnata. Deduct Unnata from 30 Ghatis to obtain Nata. Double the Nata in Ghatis, which will indicate identical Nata Bala for Moon, Mars and Saturn. Deduct the Nata from 60 to know the Unnata Bala of Sun, Jupiter and Venus. Mercury, irrespective of day and night, gets full Nathonnata Bala.  
10-11. Paksh Bala. Deduct from Moon’s longitude that of Sun. If the sum exceeds 6 Rāśis, deduct the same from 12. The product so obtained be converted into degrees etc. and divided by 3, which will indicate the Paksh Bala of each of the benefic Planets. The Paksh Bala of benefic should be deducted from 60, which will go to each malefic, as Paksh Bala. 12. Tribagh Bala. One Rupa is obtained by Mercury in the first 1/3 part of day time, by Sun in the second 1/3 part of the day and by Saturn in the last 1/3 part of the day. Similarly Moon, Venus and Mars get full Bala in the first, second and last 1/3 parts of the night. Jupiter gets this Bala at all times.  
13. Varsh-Maas-Dina-Hora Bala. 15, 30, 45 and 60 Virupas are in order given to Varsh Lord, Maas Lord, Dina Lord and Hora Lord. Naisargika Bala has already been explained. 
The Varsh Lord is the Lord of the day, on which the astrological year of birth starts. To calculate this we first need the number of days, past from the beginning of Creation, the Ahargan. According to late Rev. Ebenezer Burgess, who translated Sun Sid2ndta in English, as on January 1, 1860, the number of days, past from the beginning of Creation are 714,404,108,573. Divide the number of days, past from the day of Creation till the day of birth, by 60. Reject remainder and multiply the quotient by 3. Increase the post-multiplied product by 1 and divide by 7. The remainder will indicate the week day, on which the astrological year, giving birth to the native, opened. Remainder 1 indicates Sunday, 2 Monday and so on.  
Maasa Lord. Divide the same Ahargan by 30 and the quotient indicates months, passed from Creation to birth. The completed months be multiplied by 2 and increased by 1. The latter sum should be divided by 7 and the remainder indicates, on which day the birth month began. Continuing with the same case, we divide 65295 by 30. Quotient is 2176. This sum multiplied by 2 and increased by 1 denotes 4353. Dividing 4353 by 7, we get a remainder of 6, denoting Friday. That is, the month of birth began on Friday and the Maas Bala goes to Venus, the Lord of Friday.  
Dina Lord. Though the week day of birth can be known from ephemeris, or perpetual calendars, we better adopt the method prescribed, which will confirm, if the Ahargan followed is correct. The number of days, as arrived above, indicating Ahargan, be divided by 7 and the remainder will indicate the week day of birth.  
Hora Bala. Hora means planetary hour. Each day from sunrise to sunrise is divided into 24 equal parts of one hour. These Horas are ruled by the 7 Planets from Sun to Saturn. The first Hora of the day is ruled by the Lord of the week day. The 2nd one is ruled by the Lord of the 6th week day, counted from the first ruler. The 3rd Hora is ruled by the Lord of the 6th week day, counted from the 2nd Hora Lord. Similarly it proceeds in the same manner, till the first Hora of the next day is taken over by the Lord of that day himself. Whichever Planet rules the birth Hora, gets the Hora Bala. Horas are to be calculated for mean local time and not standard time of births.  
14. Naisargika Bala. Divide one Rupa by 7 and multiply the resultant product by 1 to 7 separately, which will indicate the Naisargika Bala, due to Saturn, Mars, Mercury, Jupiter, Venus, Moon and Sun, respectively.  
15-17. Ayan Bala. 45, 33 and 12 are the Khandas for calculating Ayan Bala. Add Ayanāńś to the Planet and find out the Bhuja (distance from the nearest equinox). Add the figure, corresponding to the Rāśi (of the Bhuja) to the Bhuja. The degrees etc. of the Bhuja should be multiplied by the figure, corresponding to the highest of the left out Khandas and divided by 30. Add the resultant product to the sum, obtained earlier. Convert this to Rāśi, degrees, minutes and seconds. If Moon and Saturn are in Libra, or ahead, add to this 3 Rāśis and, if in Aries to Virgo, reduce from this 3 Rāśis. Similarly it is reverse for Sun, Mars, Venus and Jupiter. For Mercury 3 Rāśis are always additive. The resultant sum in Rāśi, degrees and minutes be divided by 3 to get the Ayan Bala in Rupas.  
Notes by Santanam. Ayan Bala can be found out on the following simple formula: Ayan Bala = 60*(23-27 + Kranti)/(46-54) = (23-27 ± Kranti)*1.2793. The following points have to be remembered in respect of Krantis. When Moon, or Saturn have southern Kranti, or, when Sun, Mars, Jupiter, or Venus have northern Kranti, take plus. In a contrary situation in respect of these 6 Planets, take minus. As far as Mercury is concerned, it is always plus. Krantis (or declinations) can be ascertained from a standard modern ephemeris. 
Sun’s Ayan Bala is again multiplied by 2 whereas for others the product arrived in Virupas is considered, as it is. 18. Motional Strength for Sun and Moon. Sun’s Chesht Bala will correspond to his Ayan Bala. Moon’s Paksh Bala will itself be her Chesht Bala. 19. Drik Bala. Reduce one fourth of the Aspect Pinda, if a Planet receives malefic Aspects and add a fourth, if it receives a Aspect from a benefic. Super add the entire Aspect of Mercury and Jupiter to get the net strength of a Planet.  
20. War Between Planets (graha yuddha). Should there be a war between the starry Planets, the difference between the Shad Balaas of the two should be added to the victors Shad Bala and deducted from the Shad Bala of the vanquished.  
21-23. Motions of Planets (Mars to Saturn). Eight kinds of motions are attributed to Planets. These are Vakr (retrogression), Anuvakr (entering the previous Rāśi in retrograde motion), Vikala (devoid of motion), Mand (somewhat slower motion than usual), Mandatar (slower than the previous), Sama (somewhat increasing in motion), Char (faster than Sama) and Atichar (entering next Rāśi in accelerated motion). The strengths, allotted due to such 8 motions are 60, 30, 15, 30, 15, 7.5, 45 and 30. 24-25. Motional Strength for Mars etc. Add together the mean and true longitudes of a Planet and divide the one by two. Reduce this sum from the Seeghroch (or apogee) of the Planet. The resultant product will indicate the Cheshta Kendra (or Seeghra Kendra) of the Planet from 12 Rāśis. The Rāśi, degrees and minutes so arrived should be converted into degrees, minutes etc. and divided by 3, which will denote the motional strength of the Planet. Thus there are six sources of strength, called Sthan Bala, Dig Bala, Kaal Bala, Drik Bala, Chesht Bala and Naisargika Bala.  
26-29. House Balaas. Thus I explained about the strengths of the Planets. Deduct 7th House from the House, if the House happens to be in Virgo, Gemini, Libra, Aquarius, or the first half of Sagittarius. If Aries, Taurus, Leo, or first half of Capricorn, or the second half of Sagittarius happen to be the House, deduct 4th House from it. Should the House be in Cancer, or in Scorpio, deduct from it Lagna. Deduct 10th House from the House, happening to fall in Capricorn second half, or Pisces. Convert the product so obtained into degrees etc. and divide by 3 to get House Bala. If the Balaance in the process of deducting Nadir, Meridian, Lagna, or 7th exceeds 6 Rāśis, deduct it again from 12 Rāśis, before converting into degrees and dividing by 3. The product after division should be increased by one fourth, if the House in question receives a benefic Aspect. If the House receives a malefic Aspect, one fourth should be reduced. If Jupiter, or Mercury give a Aspect to a House, add that Planets Drik Bala also. And then superadd the strength, acquired by the Lord of that House. This will be the net House Bala.  
30-31. Special Rules. The Houses, occupied by Jupiter and Mercury will each get an addition of 1 Rupa, while each of the Houses, occupied by Saturn, Mars and Sun, suffer 1 Rupa reduction. 15 Virupas will have to be added to the Houses, falling in Seershodaya Rāśis, if birth happens to be in day time, to the Houses, falling in Dual Rāśis, if birth happens to be in twilight and to the Houses, falling in Prishtodaya Rāśis, if birth be in night time.  
32-33. Shad Bala Requirements. 390, 360, 300, 420, 390, 330 and 300 Virupas are the Shad Bala Pindas, needed for Sun etc. to be considered strong. If the strength exceeds the above-mentioned values, the Planet is deemed to be very strong. If a Planet has the required Shad Bala, it will prove favourable to the native by virtue of its strength. However, Saturn’s extreme strength will give long life as well as miseries. 34-36. Jupiter, Mercury and Sun are strong, if each of their Sthan Bala, Dig Bala, Kaal Bala, Chesht Bala and Ayan Bala are, respectively, 165, 35, 50, 112 and 30 Virupas. The same required for Moon and Venus are 133, 50, 30, 100 and 40. For Mars and Saturn these are 96, 30, 40, 67 and 20.  
37-38. House Effects. O Brahmin, thus the various sources of strengths be gathered together and effects declared. Whatever Yogas, or effects have been stated with respect to a House, will come to pass through the strongest Planet. 
39-40. Eligibility of Issue Fruitful Predictions. O Maitreya, the words of one, who has achieved skill in mathematics, one, who has put in industrious efforts in the branch of grammar, one, who has knowledge of justice, one, who is intelligent, one, who has knowledge of geography, space and time, one, who has conquered his senses, one, who is skilfully logical (in estimation) and one, who is favourable to Jyotishya, will doubtless be truthful.  
Ch. 28. Isht and Kasht Balaas 
1. Now I narrate the benefic and malefic tendencies of the Planets, based on which the Dasha effects can be decided. 
2. Exaltation Rays. Deduct the Planets debilitation point from its actual position. If the sum exceeds 6 Rāśis, deduct from 12 Rāśis. The said sum should then be increased by 1 Rāśi. The degrees etc. be multiplied by 2, which, when considered along with Rāśis, will indicate the Uchch Rasmi of the Planet. 
3-4. Chesht Rasmi. Chesht Rasmis are to be calculated from Chesht Kendr similar to Uchch Rasmi computations. The Chesht Kendras of Planets from Marsto Saturn have already been explained. Add 3 Rāśis to Sayana Sun (i.e. with Ayanāńś), which will be the Chesht Kendr for Sun. The sidereal longitude of Sun should be deducted from Moon to get Moon’s Chesht Kendr. If the Chesht Kendr (for any Planet) is in excess of 6 Rāśis, deduct it from 12 Rāśis. Add 1 Rāśi and multiply the degrees etc. by 2, which will indicate the Chesht Rasmi of the Planet. 5. Benefic and Malefic Rays. Add the Uchch Rasmis and Chesht Rasmis together and divide by two. The result will be auspicious rays (Subh Rasmis). Deduct from 8 the Subh Rasmis to obtain inauspicious rays (Asubh Rasmis). 
6. Isht and Kasht Tendencies. Reduce 1 from each of Chesht Rasmi and Uchch Rasmi. Then multiply the products by 10 and add together. Half of the sum will represent the Isht Phala (benefic tendency) of the Planet. Reduce Isht Phala from 60 to obtain the Planets Kasht Phala (malefic tendency). 
7-9. Isht and Kasht and Sapt Varga Phal. 60, 45, 30, 22, 15, 8, 4, 2 and 0 are the Subhankas (Subha Griha Pankthis, benefic points), due to a Planets placement, respectively, in exaltation, Moolatrikona, own, great friends, friends, neutral, enemy, great enemy and debilitation Rāśi. If Subhanka is deducted from 60, Asubhanka (Asubh Pankthi, inauspicious points) will emerge. O Brahmin, in other Vargas these are halved. 
10. A Planet is considered auspicious in the first five of the said places. In the sixth place it is neutral, i.e. neither good nor bad. And in the other three places it is inauspicious. 
11-12. Nature of Effects, due to Dig Bala etc. The directional strength of a Planet is itself representative of the effects, due to the direction; and Kaal Bala itself is indicative of effects, due to the day. Whatever quantum of Dig Bala etc. are obtained by a Planet, will be the extent of auspicious effects, acquirable on account of that strength. Deducting those figures from 60, the extent of inauspiciousness is known. If auspiciousness is more in the case of a Planets strength, the Dasha and Houses, related to that Planet will be auspicious. These are converse, if inauspiciousness is predominant. 
13-14. Sapt Varga Phal and Isht and Kasht (Continued). The various strengths (i.e. the other 6 Vargas) be multiplied by the respective Planets Shad Bala Pinda, which will indicate the auspiciousness of the Varga concerned. Auspicious, or inauspicious aspect will be by multiplying the Subh, or Asubh Pankthi. Similarly auspicious, or inauspicious effects will be known by multiplying the auspicious, or inauspicious strength by the respective Pankthi. 
15-20. Effects of a House. The strength of a House and its Lord have already been explained. The actual effects will be a combination of House strength and its Lords strength. If there is a benefic in the House add the same to the auspicious effects and deduct from inauspicious effects, which will denote the inauspicious effects. If a malefic is in the House, reverse the process, i.e. add inauspicious effects and deduct auspicious effects. Similarly Aspects and Balaas. If a Planet is exalted, or with such a dignity, add auspicious effects and reduce inauspicious effects. For debilitation etc. it is converse. In Ashtak Varga add Bindus (auspicious points) and deduct Karanas (inauspicious points). If a House extends to two Rāśis, the rectification will be done, as per both the Lords. In that case, whichever Rāśi has more Bindus, that Rāśi will yield more favourable results, concerning that House. If both the Rāśis have more auspicious Bindus, take the average. Thus the auspicious and inauspicious effects of a House be understood. 
Ch. 29. House Padas  
1-3. Method of House Calculation. O Brahmin, I shall now tell you about the Padas (Arudhas) for Houses and Planets as well, as laid down by the earlier Mahārśis. The Pad of Lagna will correspond to the Rāśi, arrived at by counting so many Rāśis from Lagnas Lord, as he is away from 1st House. Similarly Padas for other Houses be known through their Lords. The word Pad exclusively denotes the Pad for Lagna. Names of the 12 Arudhas are Lagna Pad - Arudh of 1st House, 2nd of 2nd, Vikram (Bhratru) of 3rd, Matru (Sukh) of 4th, Mantra (5th) of 5th, Rog (Satru) of 6th, Dar (Kalatr) of 7th, Maran of 8th, Pitru of 9th House, 10th of 10th, 11th of 11th, 12th of 12th.  
4-5. Special Exceptions. The same House, or the 7th from it does not become its Pad. When the Pad falls in the same House, the 10th there from be treated, as its Pad. Similarly, when the 7th becomes the Pad of a House, the 4th from the original House in question be treated, as its Pad. If the ruler of a House be in the 4th from the House, then the very House occupied be noted, as the Pad.  
6-7. Padas for Planets. Note the position of a Planet and see how many Rāśis away is its own Rāśi with reference to its position. Count so many Rāśis from the said own Rāśi and the resultant Rāśi will become the Arudh of the Planet. If a Planet owns two Rāśis, or, if a Rāśi is owned by two Planets; consider the stronger and declare effects accordingly.  
8-11. Pad and Finance (up to Sloka 15). O Brahmin, I now tell you of some effects of Planets, based on Pad. If the 11th from Lagna Pad is occupied, or receives a Aspect from a Planet the native will be happy and rich; wealth will come through various means, if a benefic is related, as above. A malefic will confer wealth through questionable means. If there be both a benefic and a malefic, it will be through both means. If the Planet in question be in exaltation, or in own Rāśi etc., there will be plenty of gains and plenty of happiness.  
12. O excellent of the Brahmins, if the 12th from Lagna Pad does not receive a Aspect, as the 11th from Lagna Pad receives a Aspect from a Planet, then the gains will be uninterrupted.  
13-15. O Brahmin, the quantum of gains will correspond to the number of Planets in, or giving a Aspect to the 11th from Lagna Pad. If there is Argala for the said 11th, there will be more gains, while a benefic Argala will bring still more gains. If the said benefic, causing Argala is in his exaltation Rāśi, the gains will be still higher. If the said 11th receives a Aspect from a benefic from Lagna, the 9th etc., gains will increase in the ascending order. In all these cases, the 12th from Pad should simultaneously be free from malefic association. A benefic, placed in Lagna, giving a Aspect to the 11th from Arudh Lagna will be still beneficial. If the Aspect is from the 9th from Lagna, it will confer much more gains.  
16-17. Pad and Financial Losses (up to Sloka 21). If the 12th from Lagna Pad receives a Aspect from, or is conjunct with both benefics and malefics, there will be abundant earnings, but plenty of expenses. The benefic will cause through fair means, malefic through unfair means and mixed Planets through both fair and unfair means.  
18. If the 12th from Lagna Pad is conjunct Sun, Venus and Rahu, there will be loss of wealth through the king. Moon, giving a Aspect to (the said trio in the said House), will specifically cause more such losses.  
19. If Mercury is in the 12th from Lagna Pad and is conjunct with, or receives a Aspect from a benefic, similarly there will be expenses through paternal relatives. A malefic so related to the said Mercury will cause loss of wealth through disputes.  
20. O Brahmin, if Jupiter is in the 12th from Lagna Pad, receiving a Aspect from others, the expenses will be through taxes and on the person himself.  
21. O Brahmin, if Saturn is in the 12th from Lagna Pad along with Mars and receives a Aspect from others, the expenses will be through ones co-born.  
22. Gainful Sources. Whatever sources of expenses are indicated above with reference to the 12th from Lagna Pad, gains through similar sources will occur, if 11th House so features with reference to Lagna Pad.  
23. The 7th House from Pad (up to Sloka 27). If Rahu, or Ketu is placed in the 7th from Lagna Pad, the native will be troubled by disorders of the stomach, or by fire.  
24. Should there be Ketu in the 7th from Lagna Pad, receiving a Aspect from, or being conjunct with another malefic, the native will be adventurous, will have (prematurely) grey hair and a big male organ.  
25. Should one, two, or all three of Jupiter, Venus and Moon be in the 7th from Lagna Pad, the native will be very wealthy.  
26. Whether a benefic, or a malefic, if be exalted in the 7th from Lagna Pad, the native will be affluent and be famous.  
27. O Brahmin, these Yogas, as narrated by me with reference to the 7th from Lagna Pad, should also be considered from the 2nd of Lagna Pad.  
28. Anyone of Mercury, Jupiter and Venus being exalted in the 2nd from Lagna Pad and being with strength will make the subject rich.  
29. The Yogas so far stated by me with reference to Lagna Pad be similarly evaluated from Karakāńś as well.  
30-37. General. If Mercury is in the 2nd from Arudh Lagna, the native will Lord over the whole country. Venus in the 2nd from Lagna Pad will make one a poet, or a speaker. If the Dar Pad falls in an angle, or in a trine, counted from Lagna Pad, or, if Lagna Pad and Dar Pad both have strong Planets, the native will be rich and be famous in his country. If the Dar Pad falls in the 6th/ 8th/12th from Lagna Pad, then the native will be poor. If Lagna Pad and the 7th there from, or an angle, a trine, an Upachaya there from is occupied by a strong Planet, there will be happiness between the husband and wife. If Lagna Pad and Dar Pad are mutually in Kendras, or Konas, there will be amity between the couple. If these be in mutually 6th/8th/12th, doubtlessly mutual enmity will crop up. O Brahmin, similarly mutual relationship, or gain, or loss through son etc. be known, based on Lagna Pad and the relative House Pad. If Lagna Pad and Dar Pad are mutually angular, or 3rd and 11th, or in Konas, the native will be a king, ruling the earth. Similar deductions be made with reference to mutual positions of Lagna Pad and 2nd Pad. 
Ch. 30. Upa Pad  
1-6. O Brahmin, now I tell you about Upa Pad, the auspiciousness of which will confer on the native happiness from progeny, wife etc. The Pad of Lagna, as discussed earlier, is of prime importance. Upa Pad is calculated for the House, following the natal Lagna. This Upa Pad is also called Gaun Pad. O excellent of the Brahmins, if Upa Pad is conjunct with, or receives a Aspect from a benefic Planet, one will obtain full happiness from progeny and spouse. Should the Upa Pad be in a malefics Rāśi, or receives a Aspect from, or is conjunct with a malefic, one will become an ascetic and go without a wife. If (in the said circumstances) there be a benefic Aspect (on Upa Pad, or the related malefic), or a conjunct, deprival of spouse will not come to pass. In this case Sun, being exalted, or in a friendly Rāśi, is not a malefic. He is a malefic, if in debilitation, or in an enemy Rāśi.  
Notes by Santanam. Regarding Upa Pad calculations, there are more than two views on the same Sloka of Mahārśi Parashara, or an identical Sutra from Jaimini. In this text, the word Anuchar is used, which denotes the House, following the Lagna at birth. Normally this is 12th House. However, when we study other comment6thes on Jaimini (Chaukhambh Hindi edition), we are taught, that it is 12th House in the case of an odd Rāśi ascending and it is 2nd House in the case of an even Rāśi ascending. Accordingly the Pad for the 12th, or the 2nd from Lagna is called Upa Pad. In calculating Upa Pad the rules mentioned in verses 4 and 5 of the previous chapter be kept in mind. 
7-12. Effect from the 2nd from Upa Pad. If the 2nd from Upa Pad is a benefic Rāśi, or receives a Aspect from, or is conjunct with a benefic, the same good results (as for wife and sons) will come to pass. If there is a Planet in the 2nd from Upa Pad in its debilitation Rāśi, or debilitation Ańś, or is conjunct with a debilitated, or malefic Planet, there will be destruction of wife. If the said occupant be in its exaltation Rāśi, or Navāmśa, or receives a Aspect from another Planet, there will be many charming and virtuous wives. Oh Brahmin, if Gemini happens to be the 2nd from Upa Pad, then also there will be many wives. O excellent of the Brahmins, if the Upa Pad, or the 2nd there from be occupied by its own Lord, or, if the said Lord is in his other own House, the death of wife will be at advanced age. 
13-15. Wife from the 2nd of Upa Pad (up to Sloka 22). If a Planet being constant indicator of wife (i.e. the 7th Lord, or Venus) is in its own House, there will be loss of wife only at a later stage. If the Lord of Upa Pad, or the constant significator of wife is in exaltation, the wife will be from a noble family. Reverse will be the case, if he is debilitated. O Brahmin, if the 2nd from Upa Pad is related to a benefic, the wife will be beautiful, fortunate and virtuous. 
16. Should Saturn and Rahu be in the 2nd from Upa Pad, the native will lose his wife on account of calumny, or through death. 
17. The natives wife will be troubled by disorder of blood, leucorrhoea (Pradar) etc., if Venus and Ketu are in the 2nd from Upa Pad. 
18. Mercury with Ketu in the 2nd from Upa Pad will cause breakage of bones, while Rahu, Saturn and Sun will cause distress of bones. 
19-22. Mercury and Rahu in the 2nd from Upa Pad will give a stout-bodied wife. If the 2nd from Upa Pad happens to be one of Mercury’s Rāśis and is tenanted by Mars and Saturn, the wife of the native will suffer from nasal disorders. Similarly a Rāśi of Mars, becoming the 2nd from Upa Pad and occupied by Mars and Saturn, will cause nasal disorders to ones wife. Jupiter and Saturn will, if be in the 2nd from Upa Pad, cause disorders of ears and/or eyes to the wife. If Mercury and Marsare placed in the 2nd from Upa Pad other than their own Rāśis, or, if Rahu is with Jupiter in the 2nd from Upa Pad, the natives wife will suffer from dental disorders. Saturn and Rahu together in one of Saturn’s Rāśis, which is the 2nd from Upa Pad, will cause lameness, or windy disorders to the natives wife. These evils will not come to pass, if there happens to be a Conjunct with, or a Aspect from a benefic (or from another benefic in the case of affliction being caused by a benefic himself). 23-23. O Brahmin, all these effects be deduced from the natal Lagna, Lagna Pad, the 7th from Upa Pad and the Lords thereof. So say Narada and others. 
25-28. About Sons. If Saturn, Moon and Mercury are together in the 9th from one of the said places (Sloka 23), there will be no son at all, while Sun, Jupiter and Rahu so placed will give a number of sons. Moon so placed will give a son, while a mixture of Planets will delay the obtainment of a son. The son, caused by the Conjunct of Sun, Jupiter and Rahu, will be strong, valorous, greatly successful and will destroy enemies. If Mars and Saturn are in the said 9th, there will be no son, or a son will be obtained by adoption, or brothers son will come in adoption. In all these cases odd Rāśis will yield many sons, while even Rāśis will cause only a few. 
29-30. Many Sons and Many Daughters. O Brahmin, if Leo happens to be Upa Pad and receives a Aspect from Moon, there will be a limited number of children. Similarly Virgo will cause many daughters. 
31. Co-born form Lagna Pad (up to Sloka 36). Rahu and Saturn in the 3rd, or the 11th from Lagna Pad will destroy the co-born of the native. Rahu and Saturn in the 11th will indicate the destruction of elder brothers and/or sisters and in the 3rd younger ones. 
32. If Venus is in the 3rd, or the 11th from Lagna Pad, there would have been an abortion to the mother earlier. Same is the effect, if Venus is in the 8th from natal Lagna, or from Lagna Pad. 
33-36. These are the effects, o Brahmin, as stated by Mahārśis for the 3rd and the 11th from Lagna Pad. Should Moon, Jupiter, Mercury and Mars be in the 3rd, or the 11th from Lagna Pad, there will be many valorous co-born. Should Saturn and Mars be in the 3rd, or the 11th from Lagna Pad, or give Aspects thereto, younger and elder co-born will, respectively, be destroyed. If Saturn is alone in one of the said Houses, the native will be spared, while the co-born will die. Ketu in the 3rd, or the 11th will give abundant happiness from ones sisters. 
37. Other Matters from Lagna Pad (up to Sloka 43). If the 6th from Lagna Pad is occupied by a malefic and is bereft of a Conjunct with, or a Aspect from a benefic, the native will be a thief. 
38. If Rahu is in the 7th, or the 12th from Lagna Pad, or gives a Aspect to one of the said Houses, the native will be endowed with spiritual knowledge and be very fortunate. 
39. If Mercury is in Lagna Pad, the native will Lord over a whole country, while Jupiter will make him a knower of all things. Venus in this context denotes a poet/speaker (also see Ch. 29, verse 30). 
40. O excellent of the Brahmins, if benefics occupy the 2nd from Upa Pad, or from Lagna Pad, the native will be endowed with all kinds of wealth and be intelligent. 
41. One will surely become a thief, if the Lord of the 2nd from Upa Pad is in 2nd House and is there conjunct with a malefic Planet. 
42-43. O Brahmin, if Rahu is in the 2nd from the Lord of the 7th, counted from Upa Pad, the native will have long and projected teeth. Ketu in the 2nd from the Lord of the 7th, counted from Upa Pad, will cause stammering and Saturn in the 2nd from the Lord of the 7th, counted from Upa Pad, will make one look ugly. Mixed will be the effects, if there are mixed Planets. 
