
Brihat Parashara Hora Sashtra by Rishi Parashara
Page 5
Ch. 41. Combinations for Wealth
1. I now tell you of special combinations, giving wealth. One born to these Yogas will surely become wealthy.
2. Yogas for Great Affluence (up to Sloka 8). Should a Rāśi of Venus be 5th House and be occupied by Venus himself, while Mars is in 11th House, the native will obtain great riches.3. Should a Rāśi of Mercury be 5th House and be occupied by Mercury himself, as 11th House is occupied by Moon, Mars and Jupiter, the native will be very affluent.4. Should Leo be 5th House and be occupied by Sun himself, as Saturn, Moon and Jupiter are in 11th House, the native will be very affluent.
5. Should Sun and Moon be in 11th House, as Saturn is in 5th House identical with his own House, the native will be very affluent.
6. Should Jupiter be in 5th House identical with his own Rāśi, as Mercury is in 11th House, the native will be very affluent. 
7. If a Rāśi of Mars happens to be 5th House with Mars therein, while Venus is in 11th House, the native will become very affluent.8. If Cancer happens to be 5th House, containing Moon therein, while Saturn is in 11th House, the native will become very affluent.
9. Yogas for Wealth (up to Sloka 15). Should Sun be in Leo identical with Lagna and be conjunct with, or receiving a Aspect from Mars and Jupiter, one will be wealthy. 
10. Should Moon be in Cancer identical with Lagna and be conjunct with, or receiving a Aspect from Mercury and Jupiter, one will be wealthy.
11. Should Mars be in Lagna identical with his own Rāśi and be conjunct with, or receiving a Aspect from Mercury, Venus and Saturn, the native will be rich. 
12. Should Mercury’s Rāśi be Lagna with Mercury therein and should Mercury be conjunct with, or receiving a Aspect from Saturn and Jupiter, the native will be rich. 
13. Should Jupiter be in Lagna identical with his own Rāśi and be conjunct with, or receiving a Aspect from Mercury and Mars , the native will be rich.
14. If Venus happens to be in Lagna identical with his own Rāśi and be conjunct with, or receiving a Aspect from Saturn and Mercury, one will be wealthy.
15. If Saturn is in his own Rāśi identical with Lagna and receiving a Aspect from, or being conjunct with Mars and Jupiter, the native will be wealthy. 
16. Other Qualified Planets. 9ths Lord and 5ths Lord are capable of bestowing wealth. Similarly Planets, conjunct with 9ths Lord and/or 5ths Lord are capable of bestowing wealth. There is no doubt, that these Planets will give wealth during their Dasha periods.
17. The Yogas, mentioned above (up to Sloka 16) should be delineated after knowing favourable, or unfavorable dispositions of the participant Planets and their strength and weakness.
18-19. Effects of the Divisional Dignities of the Lords of Kendras. If the Lord of a Kendra is in Parijatāńśa, the native will be liberal, if in Uttamāńśa, will be highly liberal, if in Gopurāńśa, will be endowed with prowess, if in Simhasanāńś, will be honourable, if in Paravatāńśa, will be valorous, if in Devalokāńśa, will be head of an assembly, if in Brahmalokāńśa, will be a sage and, if in Iravatāńśa, will be delighted and be celebrated in all quarters. 
20-22. Effects of the Divisional Dignities of 5ths Lord. If 5ths Lord is in Parijatāńś, the native will take to the branch of learning, befitting his race, if in Uttamāńśa, will have excellent learning, if in Gopurāńśa, will receive world-wide honors, if in Simhasanāńś, will become a minister, if in also Paravatāńśa, will be endowed with Vedic Knowledge, if in Devalokāńśa, will be a 10th Yogi (performer of actions, worldly and religious rites), if in Brahmalokāńśa, will be devoted to the Lord and, if in Iravatāńśa, will be pious.
23-27. Effects of the Divisional Dignities of 9ths Lord. If 9ths Lord is in P6thjatāńś, the native will visit holy places, if in Uttamāńśa, has been visiting holy places in the past births and he will do the same within this life-time, if in Gopurāńśa, will perform sacrificial rites, if in Simhasanāńś, will be mighty and truthful, conquerer of his senses and will concentrate only on the Brahman, giving up all religions, if in Paravatāńśa, will be the greatest of ascetics, if in Devalokāńśa, will be an ascetic, holding a cudgel (Lagudi), or he will be a religious mendicant, that has renounced all mundane attachments and carrying three long staves, tied together, in his right hand (Tridandin) and, if in Brahmalokāńśa, will perform Aswamedh Yagya (Horse Sacrifice) and will attain the state of Lord Indra, if in Iravatāńś, will be a synonym of dharma, or virtues just, as Lord Ram and Yudhishtira. 
28. Lords of Kendras and Konaas Related. The Kendras are known, as Vishnu Sthanas (Houses of Lord Vishnu), while the Konaas are called Lakshmi Sthanas. If the Lord of a Kendra establishes a relationship with the Lord of a Konaa, a Raja Yoga is obtained.
(A sixth kind of relationship can also be extended in this context to Navāmśa positions, though there is no specific classic sanction for this. For example in the case of a Capricorn native Mars in the Navāmśa of Venus and Venus in the Navāmśa of Mars will confer a superior Raja Yoga. This form of relationship will be equally superior, like the first 3 relationships, mentioned in the earlier paragraph). 
29-34 Effects of the Divisional Dignities of Related Lords of Kendras and Lords of Konaas. If the Lord of a Kendra and the Lord of a Kona, having a relationship, as indicated in Sloka 28, happen to be in P6thjatāńś, the native will be king and will protect men, if in Uttamāńś, will be an excellent king, endowed with elephants, horses, ch6thots etc., if in Gopurāńś, will be a tiger of kings, honoured by other kings and, if in Leoasanāńś, will be an emperor, ruling over the entire earth. With the said Raja Yoga relationship of the said Planets in Leoasanāńś were born H6thsh Moon, Manu, Balai, Agni Deva and many emperors. In the present Yuga so born is Yudhishtira (9th Raja of Mahabharat). Salivahanas birth and that of others will also come with this Yoga. With such Lords, placed in Paravatāńś, Manu etc. were born. The Incarnations of Lord Vishnu took place, when such Lords were placed in Devalokāńś. With such Lords, placed in Brahmalokāńś, Lord Brahma was born and, placed in Iravatāńś, the Swayambhu Manu was born. (Manu is the first of the 14 Manus, identified, as the second creator, who produced the Prajapatis. To Manu the code of laws, Manu Smriti is ascribed).
Ch. 42. Combinations for Penury
1. O Lord, you have stated many Yogas, related to acquisition of wealth. Please tell me such Yogas, causing utter poverty.
2. The native will be penniless, if Lagnas Lord is in 12th House, while 12ths Lord is in Lagna along with the Lord of a Maraka, or receives a Aspect from such a Planet.
3. The native will be penniless, if Lagnas Lord is in 6th House, while 6ths Lord is in Lagna, conjunct with, or receiving a Aspect from a Maraka Lord.
4. Should Lagna, or Moon be with Ketu, while Lagnas Lord is in 8th House, the person concerned will be penniless.
5. If Lagnas Lord along with a malefic is in 6th, 8th, or 12th House, while 2nds Lord is in an enemy Rāśi, or in debilitation, even a native of royal scion will become penniless.6. If Lagnas Lord is conjunct with the Lord of 6th, 8th, or 12th House, or with Saturn and, if Lagnas Lord is devoid of a Aspect from a benefic, the native will be penniless.
7. Should 5ths and 9ths Lords be, respectively, found in 6th and 12th House and receive a Aspect from Maraka Planets, the native will be penniless.
8. If malefics, excepting the Lords of 10th and 9th House, happen to be in Lagna, associated with, or receiving a Aspect from Maraka Planets, one will become penniless.
9. Note the Planets, that are ruling the Rāśis, occupied by the Lords of 6th, 8th and 12th House. If the said dispositors are in such evil Houses in turn and are associated with, or receive a Aspect from malefics, the native will be miserable and indigent.
10. The Lord of the Navāmśa, occupied by Moon, joining a Maraka Planet, or occupying a Maraka House, will make one penniless.
11. Should the Lord of the natal Lagna and that of the Navāmśa Lagna be conjunct with, or receive a Aspect from Maraka Planets, one will be penniless.
12. If inauspicious Houses are occupied by benefics, while auspicious Houses are occupied by malefics, the native will be indigent and will be distressed even in the matter of food.
13. A Planet, associated with one of the Lords of 6th, 8th and 12th House, being bereft of a Aspect from the Lord of a Kona, will in its Dasha periods cause harm to the natives financial aspects.
14. If the 8th/12th from Atma Karak, or 8th/12th House receive a Aspect from the Atma Karaks Navāmśa Lord and the Lord of Janma Lagna, the native will be bereft of wealth.
15. The native will be a spendthrift, if the 12th from Atma Karak receives a Aspect from the dispositor of Atma Karak, or, if 12th House receives a Aspect from the Lord of Lagna.
16-18. Now I tell you some Yogas for poverty along with conditions of their nullifications. Should Mars and Saturn be together in 2nd House, the natives wealth will be destroyed. Should Mercury give a Aspect to Mars and Saturn in 2nd House, there will be great wealth. There is no doubt in it. Sun in 2nd House, receiving a Aspect from Saturn, will cause penury, while, if Sun is in 2nd House and does not receive a Aspect from Saturn, riches and fame will be obtained. The same effects (poverty) will be declared, if Saturn is in 2nd House, receiving a Aspect from Sun.
Ch. 43. Longevity
1. O Mahārśi Parashara, you have dealt with combinations for wealth and poverty. Kindly detail methods of ascertaining the life-span of human beings. 
2-3. O Brahmin, for the benefit of mankind I narrate methods of ascertaining longevity. Knowing that longevity is difficult even for gods. Many exponents have laid down various methods of longevity calculations. Following is the summary of such schools of thought.
4-8. Pindayu. The Planets contribute to longevity, according to their being in exaltation, or debilitation and also based on their strengths and weaknesses and positions in Ashvini etc. and in the various Rāśis. First of all Pindayu is based on the positions of the Planets. O Brahmin, listen carefully to what I say: 19, 25, 15, 12, 15, 21 and 20 are the number of years, contributed by the Planets, from Sun etc., when in exaltation. These are half of the above in debilitation. And, if the Planets are in between exaltation and debilitation, the rule of three process should be used. Deduct the actual position of the Planet from its deep exaltation point. If the product is less than 6 Rāśis, deduct it again from 12 Rāśis. The product concerned should be multiplied by the number of years allotted to the Planet and divided by 12 to get the Planets actual contribution.
9. Rectifications. Excepting Venus and Saturn, the contributions, made by others, should be halved, if they are eclipsed by Sun. One third should be reduced, if the Planet is in its inimical Rāśi. This does not apply to the one in retrogression (see Vakra Charam).
10-11. Deductions for Planets in the Visible Half of the Zodiac. Full, half, one third, one fourth, one fifth and one sixth are the deductions of contributions, made by malefics, placed in the visible half of the zodiac. Benefics in such cases lose only half of what malefics lose. Should there be more than one Planet in a House, the deduction, due to the strongest, will only prevail and not deductions, due to other Planets in that particular House. Waning Moon is a benefic for this purpose.
12-13. Malefics in Lagna. In case 1st House is occupied by malefics, adopt the following procedure. Convert Lagnas Sphuta into minutes of arc and multiply it by the years etc., contributed by the occupant, and divide by 21600. The years etc. so arrived be deducted from the respective contribution, which will be the net span, donated by the Planet. If there is benefics Aspect on Lagna, containing malefics, then the loss is only half.
14-15. Lagnas Contribution. The number of years, contributed by Lagna, will correspond to the number of Rāśis it gained (from Aries), while the degrees Lagna has gained in the particular Rāśi will also correspondingly donate (30ｰ = l year). If the Lagnas Lord in the Navāmśa is stronger than Lagnas Lord, then the contribution should be computed only based on the number of Navāmśaas gained (from Aries), otherwise the computation will be for the Rāśi Lagna. 
16-17. Nisargayu. O Brahmin, now I tell you about Nisargayu. 1, 2, 9, 20, 18, 20 and 50 are the years, allotted to Moon, Mars , Mercury, Venus, Jupiter, Sun and Saturn from the period of birth.
18-19. Ańśayu. Now I will tell you about Ańśayu contributions by Lagna and Planets. The years correspond to the number of Navāmśaas, counted from Aries. Multiply the longitude in question by 108. If the product exceeds 12, expunge multiples of 12 and consider the final product in Rāśis, degrees etc., as years, months etc.
20-22. The same reductions, as per Pindayu, apply to Ańśayu as well; i.e. half for a combust Planet, one third for inimical placement and the ones, due for placements in the half of the zodiac, counted from the 12th backwards. Some scholars suggest further corrections for Ańśayu, viz. to increase threefold the contribution of a Planet in exaltation, or in own House and double the contribution, if the contributor is in his own Navāmśa, or in his own Dreshkana. If doubling and trebling is warranted, only trebling be done. In case of reductions also only halving is to be done, if both halving and reducing a third are required. That is how the final life-span of men be understood.
23. Longevity for Other Living Beings. For other living beings as well such computations can be made. The said figure should be multiplied by the figure, corresponding to its full span of life and divided by the figure, corresponding to the full span of life for human beings.
24-29. Full Life Span of Various Living Beings. Now Ill tell you about the full life-span figures for various living beings. Gods and sages enjoy endless life-span (in astronomical proportions, as against ordinary mortals). The full life-span of eagles, owls, parrots, crows and snakes is one thousand years. For falcon, monkey, bear and frog the full span of life is 300 years. Demons full life-span is 150 years, while it is 120 for human beings, 32 for horses, 25 for donkeys and camels, 24 for oxen and buffaloes, 20 for peacocks, 16 for goats and rams. 14 for swans, 12 for cuckoo, dog and dove, 8 for hens etc. and 7 for birds etc.
30-31. Choice of Longevity. I have narrated 3 different methods of longevity. Listen to me about the choice among the three systems. According to which of the three, Lagna, Sun, or Moon is stronger than the other two, Ańśayu, Pindayu, or Nisargayu should be, respectively, chosen.
32. Doubtful Cases. If two among Lagna, Sun and Moon gain equal strength, then longevity should be worked out, as per both systems and the average of both should be considered. If all the three are equally strong, the average of the three should be considered.
33-40. Other Clues to Longevity. O excellent of the Brahmins, I will now give you details of other methods in the matter of longevity, as under. This is based on the positions of Lagnas Lord, 8ths Lord, Saturn, Moon, natal Lagna and Hora Lagna. These six are grouped into three groups thus: the Lords of Lagna and of 8th House on the one hand, Saturn and Moon on the other hand and the natal Lagna and Hora Lagna on yet the other hand. Out of a group of two, if the two are in Movable Rāśis, long life is denoted. One in a Fixed Rāśi and the other in a Dual Rāśi will also bestow long life. One in a Movable Rāśi and the other in a Fixed Rāśi will give medium life. If both are in Dual Rāśis, then again medium life will be obtained. Short life is denoted, if one is in a Movable Rāśi, as the other is in a Dual Rāśi, or, if both are in Fixed Rāśis. The type of life, denoted by three, or two groups be only considered. If the three groups denote different scales, then the one, indicated by the pair of natal Lagna and Hora Lagna should be only considered. In case of three different indications, if Moon is in Lagna, or 7th House, then the one, indicated by the Saturn-Moon pair will only come to pass. 
41-44. Further Cl6thfications. If long life is denoted by all the said three groups, the span is 120 years, if by two groups, it is 108 years and, if only by one group it is 91 years. If medium life is arrived at by three groups, it is 80 years, if indicated by 2 groups, it is 72 years and, if by one group, it is 64 years. If short life is denoted by the said three groups, it is only 32 years, if indicated by two groups, the life-span is 36 years and, if by one group, the life-span is 40 years. These are rectified, as under. 
45-46. Rectifications. If the contributor is in the beginning of a Rāśi, his donation will be full and it will be nil, if he is at the end of a Rāśi. For intermediary placements rule of three process will apply. Add the longitudes of the contributors and the sum so arrived at must be divided by the number of contributors. The latest product should be multiplied by the number of basic years and divided by 30. This will yield the net longevity. 
47. Special Rule for Saturn. Should Saturn be a contributor, the class of longevity declines. Some advocate contr6thly an increase of class in this context. If Saturn is in its own Rāśi, or in exaltation, change in class will not occur. Even, if he receives a Aspect from, or is conjunct with only a malefic, no change occurs.
48. Special Rule for Jupiter. If Jupiter is in Lagna, or in 7th House and receives a Aspect from, or is conjunct with only benefics, the class of longevity will increase.
49-50. Increase and Fall in Class of Longevity. From very short life to short life, from short life to medium life, from medium life to long life and from long life to extremely long life are the increases in the classification of longevity, when Jupiter warrants an increase. The reverse is true, if Saturn warrants a fall in the span of life.
51. (Maitreya says) You have narrated various kinds of longevity computations. Please favour me by denoting subtle classes thereof and poor and long life-spans.
52. (Mahārśi Parashara replies) These are seven-fold, viz. Bala Risht, Yoga Risht, short, medium, long, super-natural (Divya) and immortality (Amritayu).
53-54. The life-span in Bala Risht is 8 years, in Yoga Risht 20 years, in short, medium and long lives, respectively, 32, 64 and 120 years. Super-natural life-span is 1000 years. Above this super-natural life-span of 1000 years it is Amritayu, which can be acquired only by those, who deserve it.
55. Limitless Longevity. Should Cancer be Lagna with Jupiter and Moon therein, while Venus and Mercury are in Kendras and others are in 3rd, 6th and 11th House, the native will obtain limitless longevity.
56. Super-Natural Longevity. One having benefics in Kendras and/or Konaas, while malefics are in 3rd, 6th and 11th House will obtain super-natural life-span. 8th House in this case should be one of the Rāśis, owned by a benefic.
57. Living until the End of the Yuga. One born in Cancer Lagna will live till the end of the Yuga, if Jupiter is in a Kendra and happens to be in Gopurāńś, while Venus is in a Kona and happens to be in Paravatāńś.
58. Living the Life-Span of a Sage. Jupiter in Leoasanāńś, being in Lagna, Saturn in Devalokāńś and Mars in Paravatāńś. If these are so, one will enjoy the life-span, as due to a sage.59. Good Yogas increase the life-span and bad Yogas decrease the same. Hence I tell you such Yogas, as to know of full, medium and short span combinations.
60. If a Kendra contains a benefic, while Lagnas Lord is conjunct with, or receives a Aspect from a benefic, or Jupiter in particular, the native will live a full span of life.
61. Should Lagnas Lord be in a Kendra conjunct with, or receiving a Aspect from Jupiter and Venus, full life-span will result.
62. If at birth three Planets are exalted, out of which the Lords of Lagna and 8th House are inclusive, as 8th House is devoid of a malefic in it, full life-span will result.
63. Long life is denoted, if three Planets are in 8th House, in exaltation, own, or friendly divisions, while Lagnas Lord is strong.
64. If Saturn, or Lagnas Lord is conjunct with any exalted Planet, long life will result.
65. Long life will be enjoyed, if malefics are in 3rd, 6th and 11th House, while benefics are in Kendras.
66. If 6th, 7th and 8th House are occupied by benefics, while malefics are in 3rd and 11th House, full life-span will follow the birth.
67. If 8ths Lord is friendly to Sun, while malefics are in 6th and 12th House, as Lagnas Lord is in a Kendra, the native will live the full span of life.
68. O excellent of the Brahmins, if a malefic is in 8th House, while 10ths Lord is exalted, one will be long-lived.
69. Long life will follow, if Lagna is a Dual Rāśi, while Lagnas Lord is in a Kendra, or in exaltation, or in a Kona.
70. Should Lagna be a Dual Rāśi, while two malefics are in a Kendra with reference to a strong Lagnas Lord, long life is indicated.
71-73. If the stronger among Lagnas Lord and 8ths Lord is placed in a Kendra, long life is indicated and, if in a Panaphara, medium life is indicated, if in Apoklima, short life will come to pass. According to Lagnas Lord being friendly, neutral, or inimical to Sun, long, medium, or short life will result.
74. Should Mars and 3rds Lord, or 8ths Lord and Saturn be combust, or be conjunct with malefics, or receive a Aspect from malefics, there will be short life.75. If Lagnas Lord is in 6th, 8th, or 12th House, conjunct with malefics and devoid of Conjunct with and/or Aspect from a benefic, short life will come to pass.
76. If malefics are in Kendras, devoid of Conjunct with, or a Aspect from benefics, while Lagnas Lord is not strong, only short life will result.
77. O excellent of Brahmins, if 12th and 2nd House are occupied by malefics and devoid of a Aspect from a benefic, or of Conjunct with a benefic, the native will be short-lived.
78. If the Lords of Lagna and 8th House are bereft of dignities and strength, short life will come to pass. If the Lords of Lagna and 8th House are helped by others, while being so, medium life-span will come to pass. 
Ch. 44. Maraka Planets
1. O Mahārśi Parashara, you have mentioned a lot about longevity. Be kind enough to throw light on Marakas, or killers. 
2-5. O Brahmin, 3rd and 8th House are the two Houses of longevity. The Houses, related to death, are the 12th from each of these, i.e. 2nd and 7th House are Maraka Houses. Out of the two, 2nd House is a powerful Maraka House. The Lords of 2nd and 7th House, malefics in 2nd and 7th House and malefics, conjunct with 2nds Lord and conjunct with 7ths Lord are all known, as Marakas. The major and sub-periods of these Planets will bring death on the native, depending on whether he is a long life, medium life, or short life person.
6-8. The Dasha of a benefic Planet, related to 12ths Lord may also inflict death. End may descend on the native in 8ths Lords Dasha. The Dasha of a Planet, which is an exclusive malefic, may also cause death.
9. Should Saturn be ill-disposed and be related to a Maraka Planet, he will be the first to kill in preference to other Planets. 
10-14. O Brahmin, I tell you further about Marakas. Narrated earlier are three kinds of life-spans, viz. short, medium and long. Short life is before 32 years, later on up to 64 it is medium life and from 64 to 100 it is long life. Beyond 100 the longevity is called supreme. O excellent of the Brahmins, it is impossible to decide upon longevity till the native is 20 years old. Till such year the child should be protected by sacred recitations, religious offerings (of Ghī etc.) to consecrated fire, as prescribed in the Vedas etc. and through medical treatments, for premature death may descend on the child due to sins of father and mother, or of its own (in the previous birth). 
15-21. I further mention about the Maraka Planets. One born with short life combinations may face death in the Dasha, denoted by Vipat star (3rd from the birth star), one of medium life may die in the Dasha, denoted by Pratyak star (5th from the birth star). In the Dasha, denoted by Vadh star (7th from the birth star), one with long life may obtain his end. The Dasha of the Lord of the 22nd Dreshkana, or 23rd, or 3rd, or 5th, or 7th asterisms may also cause death. The Lords of the 2nd and the 12th, counted from Cancer, may bring death. This is true, when Moon is a malefic. If he happens to be a benefic, there will be diseases (not death). Death may come to pass in the Dasha of 6ths Lord and in the subperiods of 6ths, 8ths and/or 12ths Lords. Should there be many Marakas and, if these Marakas are strong, there will be diseases, miseries etc. in major and sub-periods. Thus these are Marakas and are prim6thly related to bring death upon the native. According to their dispositions there may be death, or difficulties. 
22-24. Rahu and Ketu, as Marakas. If Rahu, or Ketu are placed in 1st, 7th, 8th, or 12th House, or happen to be in the 7th from a Maraka Lord, or are placed with such a Planet, they acquire powers of killing in their major, or sub-periods. For one born in Capricorn, or in Scorpio, Rahu will be a Maraka. Should Rahu be in 6th, 8th, or 12th House, he will give difficulties in his Dasha periods. He will not, however, do so, if Rahu receives a Aspect from, or is conjunct with a benefic. 
25-31. 3rd House and Death. O excellent of Brahmins, if Sun, being with strength, is in 3rd House, one will obtain his death, due to a king (legal punishments). Moon in 3rd House will cause death, due to tuberculosis, while wounds, weapons, fire and thirst will cause death through Mars in 3rd House. If 3rd House receives a Aspect from, or is occupied by Saturn and Rahu, death will be through poison, water, or fire, or fall from heights, or confinement. Death will surely come to descend through insects, or leprosy, if Moon and Gulika occupy, or give a Aspect to 3rd House. Mercury, giving a Aspect to, or occupying 3rd House, will bring death, followed by fever. Jupiter in 3rd House, or giving a Aspect to 3rd House, will cause death by swelling, or tumors. Urinary diseases will cause death, if Venus is in, or gives a Aspect to 3rd House. Many Planets, giving a Aspect to, or occupying 3rd House, will bring death through many diseases. 
32. If 3rd House is occupied by a benefic, death will be in an auspicious place (like a shrine) and, if 3rd House is occupied by a malefic, death will be in sinful places. Mixed occupation of 3rd House will yield mixed results with regard to the place of death. 
33. Consciousness will prevail at the time of death, if Jupiter, or Venus are placed in 3rd House. With other Planets in 3rd House there will be unconsciousness before death.
34. According to 3rd House being a Movable, a Fixed, or a Dual Rāśi, death will be, respectively, in a foreign place (other than native birth place), in ones own house, or on the way. 
35-36. Occupants of 8th House. Note the occupant of 8th House. If it is Sun, death will be through fire, if Moon is in 8th House, through water, if Mars , through weapons, if Mercury, through fever, if Jupiter, through diseases, if Venus, through hunger and, if Saturn, through thirst.
37. If 8th House is occupied by, or receives a Aspect from a benefic, while 9ths Lord is conjunct with a benefic, the native will die in a shrine. If 8th House is occupied by, or receives a Aspect from a malefic, while 9ths Lord is conjunct with a malefic, death will be in a place, other than a shrine.
38-39. Fate of the Human Physical System. Should there be a benefics Dreshkana in 8th House (22nd Dreshkana), the body will be burnt in fire (as prescribed in Shastras). If a malefics Dreshkana happens to be in 8th House, the body will be thrown away in water. If the Dreshkana in 8th House is owned by a mixed Planet, the dead body will only dry up. If the Dreshkana in 8th House is a serpent Dreshkana, the body will be eaten away by animals, crows etc.
40. Serpent Dreshkanaas. The 2nd and 3rd Dreshkana in Cancer, the initial one in Scorpio and the last one in Pisces are designated, as serpent Dreshkanaas.
41-42. Pre-natal Abode. O excellent of Brahmins, the stronger of the two lumin6thes, Sun and Moon, occupying a Dreshkana of Jupiter, denotes the descent from the world of gods. If the stronger of the lumin6thes occupies the Dreshkana of Venus, or Moon, the descent is from the world of the Manes, if the stronger of the two lumin6thes is in the Dreshkana of Sun, or Mars , the descent is from the world of Yama (world of the death) and, if in Dreshkana of Mercury, or Saturn, the descent is from the hell.
43-45. Ascent after Death. According to the following Planets in 12th, 7th, 6th, or 8th House, the native will attain one of the different worlds after death: Jupiter heaven, Moon, or Venus the world of Manes, Mars and/or Sun earth (rebirth), Mercury and/or Saturn hell. In case the said Houses are not occupied, the native will go to the world, indicated by the stronger of the Dreshkana Lords, related to 6th and 8th House. The relative Planets exaltation etc. will denote the high, medium and low status the native will obtain in the said world.46. Other Planets and Rāśis, becoming Marakas, are being discussed in the chapter, related to Dashas.  
Ch. 45. Avasthas of Planets 
1. O Mahārśi Parashara, you have earlier stated, that the Avasthas, or states of the Planets are to be considered in the context of the effects of the Planets. Be so kind to tell me about this. 
2. O excellent of Brahmins, various kinds of Avasthas of the Planets have been expounded. Out of these, I will give you the summary of Baal (infant) and other states of the Planets. 
3. Baal, Kumar, Yuv, Vriddh and Mrit Avastha (Baal Adi Avasthas). Infant, youthful, adolescent, old and dead are the states of the Planets, placed in the ascending order at the rate of six degrees in odd Rāśis. In the case of even Rāśis this arrangement is in reverse order. (Vriddh - Advanced, Mrit - In extremis) 
4. Results. One fourth, half, full, negligible and nil are the grades of the results, due to a Planet in infant, youthful, adolescent, old and dead Avasthas. 
5. Awakening, Dreaming and Sleeping States. If a Planet is in its own Rāśi, or in exaltation, it is said to be in a state of awakening (alertness). In the Rāśi of a friend, or of a neutral it is in dreaming state, while in an enemy Rāśi, or in debilitation it is in a state of sleeping. 
6. According to a Planet, being in Awakening, Dreaming, or Sleeping states, the results, due to it will be full, medium, or nil. 
7. Other Kinds of States. There are nine kinds of other Avasthas, viz. Deepta, Swastha, Pramudit, Shanta, Din, Vikala, Dukhita, Khal and Kop. 
8-10. If a Planet is in its exaltation Rāśi, it is in Deepta Avastha, if in its own Rāśi, it is in Swastha, if in a great friends Rāśi, it is in Pramudit, if in a friendly Rāśi, it is in Shanta, if in a neutral Rāśi, it is in Din, if a Planet is conjunct with a malefic, it is in Vikala, if is in an enemy Rāśi, it is in Dukhita, if in a great enemy Rāśi, it is in Khal and, if a Planet is being eclipsed by Sun, it is in Kop. Depending on such a state of the Planet, the House, occupied by it will obtain corresponding effects. 
11-18. Yet other Avasthas. Lajjita, Garvita, Kshudhita, Trushita, Mudita and Kshobhita are the other kinds of Avasthas, due to the Planets. Placed in 5th House, if a Planet is associated with Rahu, or Ketu, or with Sun, Saturn, or Mars , it is in Lajjita Avastha. If a Planet is in exaltation, or in MoolatriKonaa, it is Garvita. If a Planet is in an enemy Rāśi, or conjunct with an enemy, or receives a Aspect from an enemy, or even, if a Planet is conjunct with Saturn, the Avastha is Kshudhita. If a Planet is in a watery Rāśi and receives a Aspect from a malefic, but does not receive a Aspect from a benefic, the Avastha is called Trushita. If a Planet is in a friendly Rāśi, or is conjunct with, or receives a Aspect from a benefic, or is conjunct with Jupiter, it is said to be in Mudita Avastha. If a Planet is conjunct with Sun and receives a Aspect from, or is conjunct with a malefic, or receives a Aspect from an enemy, it is said to be in Kshobhita. The Houses, occupied by a Planet in Kshudhita, or in Kshobhita, are destroyed. 
19-23. The learned should estimate the effects, due to a House, in the manner, cited above, after ascertaining the strength and weakness. Weak Planets cause reduction in good effects, while stronger ones give greater effects. If a Planet, posited in 10th House, is in Lajjita, Kshudhita Avastha, or Kshobhita Avastha, the person will always be subjected to miseries. If a Planet in 5th is in Lajjita, there will be destruction of progeny, or there will be only one surviving child. Surely the wife of the native will die, if there is a Planet in 7th in Kshobhita, or in Trushita Avastha. 
24-29. Effects of Garvita, Mudita, Lajjita, Kshobhita, Kshudhita and Trushita Avastha. A Planet in Garvita Avastha will cause happiness through new houses and gardens, regalhood, skill in arts, financial gains at all times and improvement in business. A Planet in Mudita Avastha will give residences, clothes, ornaments, happiness from lands and wife, happiness from relatives, living in royal places, destruction of enemies and acquisition of wisdom and learning. A Planet in Lajjita will give aversion to God, loss of intelligence, loss of child, interest in evil speeches and listlessness in good things. A Planet in Kshobhita will give acute penury, evil disposition, miseries, financial debacles, distress to feet and obstruction to income, due to royal wrath. A Planet in Kshudhita will cause downfall, due to grief and passion, grief on account of relatives, physical decline, troubles from enemies, financial distress, loss of physical strength and an eclipsed mind, due to miseries. A Planet in Trushita Avastha will cause diseases through association with females, leading over wicked deeds, loss of wealth, due to ones own men, physical weakness, miseries, caused by evil people and decline of honour. 
30-37. Calculation of Shayan Adi Avasthas. Now I will tell you of the Avasthas, viz. Shayan, Upavesana, Netrapani, Prakasha, Gamana, Agaman, Shubh, Agama, Bhojana, Nritya Lips, Kautuka and Nidra and the Chesthas of such Avasthas. Note the number of the star, occupied by the Planet, for which an Avastha is to be calculated. Multiply that number by the number, denoted by the Planet (Sun 1 to Saturn 7). The figure so arrived at should again be multiplied by the number of the Navāmśa, where the Planet is in. Add to this the number of the birth asterism (ruling star, the one, occupied by Moon), the number of Ghatis of birth and the number of Rāśis, Lagna gained from Aries (Aries 1, Taurus 2 and so forth). This figure should be divided by 12 and the remainder will indicate the corresponding Avastha of the Planet. The sub-state in the said Avastha can be found out in the following way. Multiply the figure (Sayana 1 to Nidra 12), denoted by the Avastha concerned, by the same figure and increase it by the figure, denoted by the Anka value for the first syllable of the natives personal name. Divide the product so obtained by 12. The remainder thereof should be further increased by constant additives of the Planets in the following way: Sun 5, Moon 2, Mars 2, Mercury 3, Jupiter 5, Venus 3, Saturn 3, Rahu (Ketu) 4. The product so arrived at should be divided by 3. In the process of calculation, if it happens, that the remainder is 1, it is Aspect, if 2, it is Cheshta and, if 0, it is Vicheshta.
Notes. Shayan Adi are of supreme importance, as compared to the other kinds of Avasthas.
In place of Navāmśa, given above, some translators interpret the word Ańśa, as degree, occupied by the Planet, which is obviously not correct. In this connection the readers attention is drawn to Balaabhadrs Hora Ratna, Ch. 3, wherein the author, Balaabhadra himself, gives an example for Sun, being in the 7th Navāmśa of Leo and thus he considered only 7, as multiplier. He quotes Adhibhut Sagara, as his authority for calculation of Sayana Adi.
Agaman Avastha is known, as Gamanechch by some exponents.
Anka value is 1 for a, ka, cha, da, dha, bha and va, 2 for i, kha, ja, dha, na, ma and da, 3 for u, ga, jha, ta, pa, ya and śa, 4 for e, gha, ga, tha, pha, ra and sa, 5 for o, ca, dha, da, ba, la and ha. 
38-39. Effects of Chesht etc. If the sub-state is Aspect in an Avastha, the results, being stated for the Avastha, will be medium, the effects will be full in Chesht and negligible in Vichesht. The good and bad effects of Planets should be deciphered, based on the strength and weakness of the Planets. In exaltation the Planets reveal effects in a pronounced manner, due to Avasthas. 
40-51. Effects of Sun’s Avasthas. If Sun is in Sayana Avastha, the native will incur digestive deficiency, many diseases, stoutness of legs, bilious vitiation, ulcer in the anus and heart strokes; if in Upavesana, will suffer poverty, will carry loads, will indulge in litigations, be hard-hearted, wicked and will lose in his undertakings; if is in Netrapani, will always be happy, wise, helpful to others, endowed with prowess and wealth, very happy and will gain royal favours; if in Prakasha, will be liberal in disposition, have plenty of wealth, be a significant speaker in the assembly, will perform many meritorious acts, be greatly strong and endowed with charming beauty; if in Gamana, will be disposed to live in foreign places, be miserable, indolent, bereft of intelligence and wealth, be distressed, due to fear and will be short-tempered; if in Agaman, will be interested in others wives, be devoid of his own men, be interested in movements and skilful in doing evil deeds, be dirty, ill-disposed and will be a talebearer; if in Shubh, will be disposed to help others, be always endowed with wealth and gems, be virtuous, endowed with lands, new houses and robes, be very strong, very affectionate to his friends and very kindly disposed; if in Agama, will be distressed, due to enemies, fickle-minded, evil-minded, emaciated, devoid of virtuous acts and intoxicated with pride; if in Bhojana, will experience pains in joints, will lose money on account of others females, will have strength, declining off and on, be untruthful, will incur head-aches, eat remnant food and will take to bad ways; if in Nritya Lips, will be honoured by the learned, be a scholar, will have knowledge of poetry etc. and will be adored by kings on the earth; if is Kautuka, will always be happy, will be endowed with Vedic Knowledge and will perform Yagyas, will move amidst kings, have fear from enemies, will be charming-faced and be endowed with knowledge of poetry; if in Nidra, will have a strong tendency towards being drowsy, will live in foreign (distant) places, will incur harm to his wife and will face financial destruction. Sun in Upavesana will make one an artisan, black in complexion, devoid of learning and miserable. One will serve others. In Netrapani there will be all kinds of happiness, if Sun is in 5th, 9th, 10th, or 7th. In other Houses Netrapani of Sun will give eye diseases and enmity with all. If Sun is in Prakasha, the native will be meritorious, religious and liberal, will enjoy pleasures, be equal to a prince and will enjoy the status of Kubera, the God of wealth. However, the Prakasha of Sun, placed in 7th, or 5th will cause loss of the first child and will produce many litigations. If Sun is in Gamana, the native will incur disease of the feet and will be very mean. If in Agaman, Sun in 12th, or in 7th will destroy progeny and will give very limited wealth. If in Agama, Sun will give many miseries, an ugly appearance and foolishness. However, he will give wealth. Sun in Bhojana in 9th will cause many hindrances to spiritual and religious undertakings. In other Houses Sun in Bhojana will cause head and ear diseases, apart from joint pains. Though Mahārśi Parashara states, that the native with Sun in Kautuka Avastha will have fear from enemies, Bala Bhadr exempts such evil effect for the 6th House position. Sun in Kautuka in other Houses will give a number of daughters, two wives, itch, excellence, liberality etc. If Sun is in Nidra, the native will be predisposed to incur piles and elephantiasis, will experience a lack of peace and he will be liable to lose his first child. 
52-63. Effects of Moon’s Avasthas. If Moon is in Sayana, the native will be honourable, sluggish, given to sexual lust and he will face financial destruction; if in Upavesana, will be troubled by diseases, be dull-witted, not endowed with mentionable wealth, will be hard-hearted, will do unworthy acts and will steal others wealth; if in Netrapani, will be troubled by great diseases (long lasting in nature), be very garrulous, wicked and will indulge in bad deeds. Should Moon be in Prakasha, the native will be famous in the world, will have his virtues exposed through royal patronage, will be surrounded by horses, elephants, females and ornaments, will visit shrines. If Moon is in Gamana with decreasing rays, the native will be sinful, cruel and always troubled by afflictions of sight. If Moon is in Gamana with increasing rays, the native will be distressed, due to fear. If Moon is in Agaman, the native will be honourable, will suffer diseases of the feet, will secretly indulge in sinful acts, will be poor and devoid of intelligence and happiness; if in Shubh, will be eminent among men, honoured by kings and kings of kings, will be very beautiful, will subdue the passion of women and will be skilful in sexual acts, will be virtuous; if in Agama, will be garrulous and virtuous and, if the said Moon is of dark fortnight, the native will have two wives, he will be sick, highly wicked and violent; if in Bhojana, will be endowed with honour, conveyances, attendants, social status, wife and daughters, provided Moon is Full Purna; if in Bhojana and is of dark fortnight, auspicious effects will fail to come; if in Nritya Lips and is endowed with (fortnightly) strength, will be strong, will have knowledge of songs and will be a critic of beauty of things; if in Nritya Lips and of dark fortnight, i.e. not endowed with strength, the person will be sinful; if in Kautuka, the native will attain kingship, lordship over wealth and skill in sexual acts and in sporting with harlots. Should waxing Moon, being conjunct with Jupiter, be in Nidra, the native will be quite eminent. If waxing Moon is in Nidra, but devoid of Jupiter’s Conjunct, the native will lose his wealth on account of females and female jackals will be crying around his abode (as though it were a cemetery). 
64 75. Effects of the Avasthas of Mars . If Mars is in Sayana, the native will be troubled by wounds, itch and ulcer. If Mars is placed in Upavesana, the native will be strong, sinful, untruthful, eminent, wealthy and bereft of virtues. If Mars is placed in Lagna and happens to be in Netrapani, there will be penury; if placed in other Houses, Netrapani will confer rulership of a city. Should Mars be in Prakasha, the native will shine with virtues and will be honoured by the king. Mars in Prakasha in 5th will cause loss of children and of wife. If Mars is in Prakasha in 5th and happens to be there with Rahu, a severe (positional) fall will descend on the native. Should Mars be in Gamana, the native will be always roaming, will have fear of multiple ulcers, will incur misunderstandings with females, will be afflicted by boils, itches etc. and will incur financial decline. If Mars happens to be in Agaman Avastha, the native will be virtuous, endowed with precious gems, will adore a sharp sword, will walk with the gait of an elephant, will destroy his enemies and will remove the miseries of his people. If Mars is placed in Shubh and happens to be in exaltation, the native will be skilful in conducting wars, will hold the flag of righteousness aloft and will be wealthy; if Mars happens to be in Shubh in 5th, or 9th, the native will be bereft of learning; if Mars is in Shubh in 12th, childlessness and no wife and no friends will result; if Mars is in other Houses in Shubh, the native will be a scholar in a kings court (poet laureate), be very wealthy, honourable and ch6thtable. If Mars is in Agama, the native will be devoid of virtues and good deeds, will be distressed by diseases, will acquire diseases of the root of the ears (Karan Mularogam & Padamulam Urumulam etc.) and severe gout pains, will be timid and will befriend evil lot. If Mars is with strength, while in Bhojana Avastha, the native will eat sweet-food; if devoid of strength, will indulge in base acts and be dishonourable. If Mars is in Nritya Lips, the native will earn wealth through the king and will be endowed with fullness of gold, diamonds and corals in his house; if in Kautuka, will be curious in disposition and will be endowed with friends and sons; if in Kautuka and simultaneously exalted, will be honoured by the king and the virtuous and will be virtuous himself; if in Nidra, will be short-tempered, devoid of intelligence and wealth, will be wicked, fallen from virtuous path and troubled by diseases. Should Mars be in Upavesana in Lagna, the native will be extremely sinful and he will incur several diseases, will be indigent and not peaceful. If Upavesana occurs for Mars in 9th, the native will lose his whole wealth apart from his wife and progeny. Mars in Netrapani in Lagna will give poverty and will destroy the natives wife and progeny; if Mars is in Netrapani in other Houses, this confers on the native all kinds of wealth and happiness from wife and children. The 2nd, or 7th position of Mars in Netrapani will cause fear from lions and snakes apart from giving earnings from lands. Furthermore the natives wife will predecease him. Should Mars be in Prakasha in 5th, or in 7th, the native will lose his wife and all children. If Mars is placed in 5th in Prakasha and is conjunct with Saturn, the native will kill cows. Should Mars be in Gamana in Lagna, the native will be active in his assignments, will incur diseases of the joints, burning pains in the eyes and will obtain dental afflictions and the like, he will have fear from dogs and will adore the guise of a female. In other Houses Mars in Gamana will bring royal favours, leadership and luxuries of life. Mars in Agaman will cause piles and diseases of the rectum. If Mars is in Bhojana, or in Sayana in 5th, or in 8th, there will be untimely death for the native. In other Houses Bhojana of Mars will confer wealth. Should Mars be in Nritya Lips and happens to be in Lagna, 2nd, 7th, or 10th, the native will receive all kinds of happiness; there will be miseries in abundance, if Mars is in Nritya Lips and placed in 8th, or 9th, apart from incurring untimely death. In other Houses Nritya Lips of Mars will make the native akin to Kubera. Mars in 7th, or in 9th in Kautuka will give several diseases and death of the first child and wife. In other Houses Kautuka will confer scholarship, various kinds of wealth, two wives and more female children. In Nidra Mars in Lagna, 2nd, 3rd, 9th, 10th, or 11th will give scholarship, foolishness and poverty. 5th, or 7th placement of Mars in Nidra will give many miseries and many male children. Should Rahu join Mars in Nidra in any House, the native will have many wives, be miserable and will suffer from some diseases on the surface of the feet. 
76-86. Effects of Mercury’s Avasthas. Should Mercury in Sayana be in Lagna, the native will be lame and will have reddish eyes (like the black bee); if Mercury is in Sayana in other Houses, the native will be addicted to licentious (disregarding certain rules) pleasures and be wicked. If Mercury is in Upavesana in Lagna, the native will possess (the seven principle) virtues; if Mercury in Upavesana is in Lagna, receiving a Aspect from a malefic, or Aspects from malefics, or is conjunct with malefics, penury will result; if Mercury in Upavesana is in Lagna, receiving a Aspect from a benefic, or Aspects from benefics, or is conjunct with benefics, financial happiness will follow. If Mercury is in Netrapani, the native will be devoid of learning, wisdom, well wishers and satisfaction, but he will be honourable; if Mercury is in 5th in Netrapani, the subject will be bereft of happiness from wife and sons, will be endowed with (more) female children and will gain abundant finance through royal patronage. If Mercury is in Prakasha, the native will be charitable, merciful and meritorious, he will cross the boundaries of ocean in respect of many branches of learning, he will be endowed with the great faculty of discrimination and will destroy evil people; if in Gamana, will visit the courts of kings on many occasions and Goddess Lakshmi will dwell in his abode; if in Agaman, the same effects, due to his being in Gamana, will fructify; if in Shubh and happens to be in exaltation, will be affluent and meritorious at all times, will be equal to Kubera, or will be a king, or a minister, will be devoted to Lord Vishnu and Lord Shiva, will be virtuous and will attain full enlightenment. Should Mercury be in Agama, the native will serve base men and will gain wealth thereby, will have two sons and one fame bringing daughter. If Mercury is in Bhojana, the native will face financial losses through litigations, will physically lose on account of fear from the king, will be fickle-minded and will be bereft of physical and conjugal felicity; if in Nritya Lips, will be endowed with honour, conveyances, corals (gems etc.), sons, friends, prowess and recognition in assembly, due to his scholarship; if Mercury in Nritya Lips Avastha is in a malefics Rāśi, the native will be addicted to prostitutes and will long for licentious pleasures. If Mercury is in Kautuka in Lagna, the native will be skilful in music; if Mercury is in 7th, or 8th with Kautuka, the native will be addicted to courtezans; if Mercury in Kautuka is placed in 9th, the native will be meritorious and attain heavens after death. If Mercury is in Nidra, the native will not enjoy comfortable sleep, will be afflicted by neck, or neck joint Samadhi diseases, will be devoid of co-born, afflicted by miseries galore, will enter into litigations with his own men and will lose wealth and honour. 
87-98. Effects of Jupiter’s Avasthas. If Jupiter is in Sayana, the native will be strong, but will speak in whispers, he will be very tawny in complexion, will have prominent cheeks and will have fear from enemies; if in Upavesana, will be garrulous and very proud, will be troubled by the king and enemies and will have ulcers on the feet shanks, face and hands; if in Netrapani, will be afflicted by diseases, be devoid of wealth, fond of music and dances, libidinous, tawny in complexion and will be attached to people of other castes; if in Prakasha, will enjoy virtues, will be happy, splendorous and will visit holy places, devoted to Lord Krishna; if Jupiter in Prakasha is exalted, will attain greatness among men and will be equal to Kubera; if in Gamana, will be adventurous, happy on account of friends, scholarly and endowed with Vedic learning and with various kinds of wealth; if in Agaman, serving force, excellent women and the goddess of wealth will never leave the natives abode; if in Shubh, will attain comparability with Jupiter (God of speech) in the matter of speech, will be endowed with superior corals, rubies and wealth, will be rich with elephants, horses and chariots and will be supremely learned; if in Agama, will be endowed with various conveyances, honors, retinue (many persons will take good care of him), children, wife, friends and learning, will be equal to a king, extremely noble, fond of literature and will take to the path of the virtuous; if in Bhojana, will always beget excellent food and horses, elephants and ch6thots, while Lakshmi, the Goddess of Wealth, will never leave his house; if in Nritya Lips, will receive royal honors, be wealthy, endowed with knowledge of moral law 9tha and Tantra, will be supreme among the learned and be a great grammarian; if in Kautuka, will be curious in disposition, very rich, will shine, like Sun in his circles, be exceedingly kind, happy, honoured by the kings, endowed with sons, wealth and just disposition, will be very strong and he will be a scholar in the kings court; if in Nidra, will be foolish in all his undertakings, will suffer irredeemable penury and will be devoid of righteous acts. 
99-110. Effects of Venus Avasthas. If Venus is in Sayana, the native, although strong, will incur dental disease, he will be very short-tempered, bereft of wealth, will seek union with courtesans and be licentious; if in Upavesana, will be endowed with a multitude of nine gems (Navamin Vraja) and golden ornaments, be ever happy, will destroy enemies and will be honoured by the king, will have highly increased honors; if in Netrapani in Lagna, 7th, or 10th, there will be loss of wealth on account of afflictions of the sense of sight (heavy medical expenses, due to severe eye diseases); if Netrapani occurs, when Venus is in other Houses, the native will own large houses. Should Venus be in Prakasha in its own Rāśi, in its exaltation Rāśi, or in a friendly Rāśi, the native will sport, like a lofty elephant, will be equal to a king and be skilful in poetry and music. If Venus is in Gamana, the native will not have a long-living mother, will lament over separation from his own people and will have fear from enemies; if in Agaman, will command abundant wealth, will undertake to visit superior shrines, will be ever enthusiastic and will contract diseases of the hand and foot; if in Shubh, will earn eminence in the kings court, will be very virtuous, will destroy enemies, be equal to Kubera in wealth, will be charitable, will ride on horses and will be excellent among men; if in Agama, there will be no advent of wealth, but there will be troubles from enemies, separation from children and relatives, diseases and lack of pleasures from the wife. Should Venus be in Bhojana, the native will be distressed, due to hunger, diseases and many kinds of fear from enemies; if Venus is in Virgo in Bhojana, the native will be very rich and will be honoured by scholars. If Venus is in Nritya Lips, the native will be skilful in literature and intelligent, will play musical instruments, like lute, tabla etc., be meritorious and very affluent; if in Kautuka, will be equal to Lord Indra, will attain greatness in the assembly, be learned and will have Lakshmi always dwelling in his abode; if in Nidra, will be interested in serving others, will blame others, be heroic, garrulous and will be wandering all over the earth. 
111-122. Effects of Saturn’s Avasthas. If Saturn is in Sayana, the native will be troubled by hunger and thirst, will incur diseases in boyhood and later on he will become wealthy; if in Upavesana, will be troubled greatly by enemies, will contract dangers, will have ulcers all over the body, will be self-respected and will be punished by the king; if in Netrapani, will be endowed with a charming female, wealth, royal favour and friends, will have knowledge of many arts and will be an eloquent speaker; if in Prakasha, will be very virtuous, very wealthy, intelligent, sportive, splendorous, merciful and devoted to Lord Shiva; if in Gamana, will be very rich and endowed with sons, will grab enemy lands and will be a scholar at royal court; if in Agaman, will be akin to a donkey (foolish) and bereft of happiness from wife and children, will always roam pitiably without anybody’s patronage; if in Shubh, the native will have surprising possessions of abundant precious stones and gold, will be endowed with great judicial (political) knowledge and will be extremely brilliant; if in Agama, will incur diseases and will not be skilful in earning royal patronage; if in Bhojana, will enjoy tastes of food, will be weak-sighted and will be fickle-minded, due to mental delusion; if in Nritya Lips, will be righteous, extremely opulent, honoured by the king and brave, heroic in the field of war; if in Kautuka, will be endowed with lands and wealth, will be happy, endowed with pleasures through charming females and learned in poetry, arts etc.; if in Nidra, will be rich, endowed with charming virtues and valorous, will destroy even fierce enemies and will be skilful in seeking pleasures through harlots. 
123-134. Effects of Rahu’s Avasthas. If Rahu is in Sayana, the native will experience miseries in abundance, but, if Rahu in Sayana is placed in Taurus, Gemini, Virgo, or Aries, the native will be endowed with wealth and grains. If Rahu is in Upavesana, the native will be distressed, due to ulcers, will be endowed with royal association, be highly honourable and ever devoid of financial happiness; if in Netrapani, will be troubled by eye diseases, will have fear from wicked people, snakes and thieves and will incur financial decline; if in Prakasha, will acquire a high position, will perform auspicious acts and will obtain elevation of his financial state, will be highly virtuous, a chief in the kings court, charming, like freshly formed clouds (that will cause soon rain) and will be very prosperous in foreign places; if in Gamana, will be endowed with numerous children, be scholarly, wealthy, ch6thtable and honoured by the king; if in Agaman, will be very irritable, bereft of intelligence and wealth, crooked, miserly and libidinous; if in Shubh, will be scholarly, miserly and endowed with many virtues, wealth and happiness; if in Agama, will be always mentally distressed, will have fear from enemies and litigations with enemies, be bereft of his own men, will face financial destruction and will be crafty and emaciated; if in Bhojana, will be distressed without food and dull-witted, will not be bold in his acts and will be bereft of conjugal and progenic happiness; if in Nritya Lips, will contract a serious disease, which seems difficult to subdue, will have afflicted eyes and will have fear from enemies, will decline financially and righteously; if in Kautuka, will be devoid of a position (place), be interested in others females and will steal others wealth; if in Nidra, will be a repository of virtues, will be endowed with wife and children, be bold, proud and very affluent. 
135-146. Effects of Ketu’s Avasthas. If Ketu is in Sayana in Aries, Taurus, Gemini, or Virgo, there will be plenty of wealth; if Ketu is in Sayana in other Rāśis, increased diseases will follow. If Ketu is in Upavesana, the native will suffer from ulcers and will have fear from enemies, windy diseases, snakes and thieves. Should Ketu be in Netrapani, the native will contract eye diseases and will have fear from wicked people, snakes, enemies and people of royal family. If Ketu is in Prakasha, the native will be wealthy and righteous, will live in foreign places, be enthusiastic and genuine and will serve the king; if in Gamana, will be endowed with many sons and abundant wealth, be scholarly, virtuous, ch6thtable and excellent among men; if in Agaman, will incur many diseases, will face loss of wealth, will hurt (others) with his teeth (Danta Ghatin), be a tale bearer and will blame others; if in Shubh, will be garrulous, very proud, miserly, licentious and skilful in evil branches of learning; if in Agama, will be a notorious sinner, will enter into litigations with his relatives, will be wicked and troubled by diseases and enemies; if in Bhojana, will always be distressed with hunger, penury and diseases and will roam all over the earth; if in Nritya Lips, will be distressed, due to diseases, will have a floral mark on the eye (white of the pupil), will be impertinent and wicked and will plan evils; if in Kautuka, will seek union with dancing females (prostitutes), will suffer positional displacement, will take to evil paths and will roam all over; if in Nidra, will be endowed with wealth and corns, will be virtuous and will spend his time sportively. 
147. General Effects (up to Sloka 155). O Brahmin, if a benefic Planet is in Sayana, there will be benefic effects at all times, according to the learned.
148. If a malefic is in Bhojana, everything will be destroyed and there is no need of a second thought.
149. Should a malefic in 7th be in Nidra, auspicious effects will follow, provided, that there is no Aspect from another malefic.
150. Declare without a second thought auspicious effects, following the location of a malefic in 5th House, but only with Nidra, or in Sayana.
151. Untimely death, due to royal wrath, will come to pass, if there is a malefic in 8th House in Nidra, or in Sayana.
152. If in the case of a malefic in 8th House in Nidra, or Sayana there happens to be a benefic Aspect, or the Conjunct of a benefic, (untimely) death will be in the river Ganges, i.e. Gangetic belt, shrines etc.
153. If there is a malefic in 10th in Sayana, or Bhojana, the native will face many miseries on account of his own deeds.
154. O excellent of the Brahmins, doubtlessly a Raja Yoga will come to pass, if Moon is in 10th in Kautuka, or Prakasha.
155. Thus the good and bad effects should be guessed, assessing the strength and weakness of the Planets, concerning all the Houses. 
