
Brihat Parashara Hora Sashtra by Rishi Parashara
Page 6
Ch. 46. Dashas of Planets  
1. Maitreya said. O Venerable Mahārśi Parashara! You are omniscient. There is no subject, with which you are not conversant. Therefore now please favour me with guidance about the different kinds of Dashas (periods) of the various Planets. 
2-5. Mahārśi Parashara replied. O Brahmin! Dashas are of many kinds. Amongst them Vimshottari is the most appropriate for the general populace. But the other Dashas, followed in special cases, are Astottara, Shodshottari, Dwadashottari, Panchottari, Shatabdik, Chaturashiti-sama, Dwisaptati-sama, Shastihayani, Shat-trimshat-sama. Our ancients have described these different kinds of Dashas, based on Nakshatras. 
6-11. O Brahmin! Some Mahārśis have made a mention of Kala and Chakra Dasha, but they have recognized the Kala Chakra Dasha, as supreme. The other kinds of Dashas, propagated by the sages, are Char, Sthira, Kendra, Karak, Brahma Planet, Manduk, Shul, Yogardh, Drig, Trikona, Rāśi, Panchswara, Yogini, Pind, Nausargik, Asht Varga, Sandhya, Pachak, Tara etc. But in our view all these Dashas are not appropriate. 
Vimshottari 12-14. Beginning from Kritika, the Lords of Dashas are Sun, Moon, Mars, Rahu, Jupiter, Saturn, Mercury, Ketu and Venus in that order. Thus, if the Nakshatras from Kritika to the Janma Nakshatra are divided by nine, the remainder will signify the Lord of the commencing Dasha. The remaining Dashas will be of the Planets in the order, given above. In Kali Yuga the natural life-span of a human being is generally taken, as 120 years. Therefore Vimshottari Dasha is considered to be the most appropriate and the best of all Dashas.
15. The periods of Dashas of Sun, Moon, Mars, Rahu, Jupiter, Saturn, Mercury, Ketu and Venus are 6, 10, 7, 18, 16, 19, 17, 7 and 20 in that order.
16. To find out the remainder of the Dasha, operating at the time of birth, first find out the expired portion of the Dasha of the concerned Planet. This is done, as follows. Multiply the Dasha period of the Planet concerned by the period of the stay of Moon in Janma Nakshatra, that has expired and divide that amount by the total period of the stay of Moon in that Nakshatra. The figure in years, months etc. so arrived at will be the expired period of the Dasha. If this figure is deducted from the total period of the Dasha, we will get the Balance of Dasha at the time of birth. 
Ashtottari
17-20. Mahārśi Parashara said. O Brahmin, the sages have recommended the adoption of Ashtott6th, when Rahu not being in Lagna, in any other Kendra, or Trikona to the Lord of the Lagna. From 4 Nakshatras from Ardra commences the Dasha of Sun, from 3 after that begins the Dasha of Moon, 4 after that will bring the Dasha of Mars, 3 after that the Lord of Dasha will be Mercury, 4 there from will have Saturn, as the Dasha Lord, 3 thereafter the Lord will be Jupiter, Rahu will be the Lord of the Dasha 4 Nakshatras after that and then Venus will take over the lordship of the Dasha 3 Nakshatras from the last one mentioned above. The Lord of the Dasha at birth will be determined by counting in this order up to the Janma Nakshatra. The duration of Ashtott6th Dasha for Sun, Moon, Mars, Mercury, Saturn, Jupiter, Rahu and Venus are 6, 15, 8, 17, 10, 19, 12 and 21 in that order. Thus in this Dasha system only 8 Planets play the role of Dasha Lords, Ketu having been denied this privilege.21-22. The Dashas of the various Planets have been specified above. In the case of malefic Planets the Dasha span of one Nakshatra is ｼ of the Dasha of the Planet. It is 1/3rd in the case of benefics. Thus the expired portion of the Dasha is calculated, according to the method, followed for Vimshottari Dasha, by multiplying the Bhayat, i.e. the expired period of the stay of Moon in the Janma Nakshatra, by the Dasha portion of the Janma Nakshatra and dividing it by Bhabhog, i.e. the total period of the stay of Moon in the Janma Nakshatra. Then the Balaance of Dasha at birth can also be ascertained. If Uttarashadha happens to be the Janma Nakshatra, the duration of its first three Padas is taken, as Bhabhog and the Dasha calculations should be done accordingly. The Dasha and calculations for Abhijit Nakshatra are done by taking the 4th Pad of Uttarashadha plus the 15th part of the beginning of Shravan. For Shravan the Bhabhog would be the total of its duration in Ghatikas minus the 1/15th part of the beginning of Shravan. 
Shodshottari
23. It will be advisable to adopt the Shodshottari, if the birth is in the day in Krishna Paksh (dark half of the month), or at night in Shukla Paksh (bright half).
24-26. The Dasha may be adopted, when the Lagna is in the Hora of Moon with birth in the Krishna Paksh, or, when Lagna is in the Hora of Sun with birth in the Shukla Paksh. Count the number of Nakshatras from Pushya to the Janma Nakshatra. Divide this number by 8. The remainder will indicate the Dashas of Sun, Mars, Jupiter, Saturn, Ketu, Moon, Mercury and Venus. The Dashas of the above Planets are of 11, 12, 13, 14, 15, 16, 17 and 18 years.
Dwadashottari  
27-28. This Dasha system will be appropriate for one, whose Lagna is in the Navāmśa of Venus. Count from Janma Nakshatra to Revati. Divide this number by 8. The remainder will indicate the Dasha of the Planet concerned. The Dasha order is Sun, Jupiter, Ketu, Mercury, Rahu, Mars, Saturn, Moon. The Dashas will be of 7, 9, 11, 13, 15, 17, 19 and 21 years of the Planets.Panchottari (29-30) This Dasha is considered suitable for those, whose Lagna is Cancer and also in the Cancer Dvadashāńś. Count from Anuradha up to the Janma Nakshatra and divide the number by 7. The remainder will indicate the Dasha. The order of the Dasha Lords is Sun, Mercury, Saturn, Mars, Venus, Moon and Jupiter. The Dashas of the Planets are 12, 13, 14, 15, 16, 17 and 18 years. 
Shatabdik
(31-32) This Dasha system has been considered appropriate, if Lagna is Vargaottama. This happens, when Lagna in the Rāśi Kundali and the Navāmśa Lagna are in the same Rāśi.
(33-34) Count from Revati to the Janma Nakshatra and divide this number by seven. The remainder will indicate the Lords of Dashas in this order: Sun, Moon, Venus, Mercury, Jupiter, Mars and Saturn. Their Dashas will be of 5, 5, 10, 10, 20, 20 and 30 years.
Chaturashiti-sama
35-36. Chaturashiti-sama Dasha is considered appropriate in cases, where the 10ths Lord is placed in 10th. Count from Swati to the Janma Nakshatra and divide this number by 7. The remainder will indicate the Dasha Lords in the following order: Sun, Moon, Mars, Mercury, Jupiter, Venus and Saturn. The Dasha period of each Planet is 12 years.
Dwisaptati-sama 37-39. This Dasha system is considered suitable in cases, where the Lord of Lagna is in Lagna, or in 7th. Count from Mul to the Janma Nakshatra and divide the number by 8. The remainder will determine the Dasha Lords in the following order: Sun, Moon, Mars, Mercury, Jupiter, Venus, Saturn and Rahu. In this Dasha system all the eight Planets have Dashas of 9 years each.
Shastihayani 
40-41. This Dasha may be adopted in cases, where Sun is posited in Lagna. The order of Dasha Lords in this system is, as follows: Jupiter, Sun, Mars, Moon, Mercury, Venus, Saturn and Rahu. The following shows the Nakshatras, falling under the various Dasha Lords. The Dashas of Jupiter, Sun and Marsare of 10 years. The remaining Planets have Dashas of 6 years each. Jupiter (Ashvini, Bharani, Kritika, Punarvasu), Sun (Rohini, Mrigashira, Ardra, U.Ashadha), Mars(Pushya, Aslesha, Magha, Revati), Moon (P.Phalguni, U.Phalguni, Hast), Mercury (Swati, Vishakah, Anuradha), Venus (Jyeshtha, Mul, P.Ashadha), Saturn (Abhijit, Shravan, 2ndishtha), Rahu (Shatabhisha, P.Bhadra, U.Bhadra).
Shat-trimshat-sama
42-43. Count from Shravan to the Janma Nakshatra and divide the number by 8. The remainder 1 etc. will indicate the Dasha Lords, whose order will be, as follows: Moon, Sun, Jupiter, Mars, Mercury, Saturn, Venus and Rahu. Their Dashas will be 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7 and 8 years. If the birth is during the day and Lagna is in the Hora of Sun and, if the birth is at night and Lagna is in the Hora of Moon, adoption of this system would be preferable.
Kaala
44-49. 5 Ghatikas before the sight of the semi-disk of the setting Sun and 5 Ghatikas after that and 5 Ghatikas before and after the rising of Sun, that is 10 Ghatikas in the evening and 10 Ghatikas in the morning, respectively. The total period of both these Sandhyas (twilight) is said to be 20 Ghatikas. The 20 Ghatikas of the night have been given the name Purna and the 20 Ghatikas of the day have been given the name Mugdha. The Sandhya at the time of sunrise is called Khanda and the Sandhya at the time of Sun’set is said to be Sudh. Both of these Sandhyas are of 10 Ghatikas each. If the birth is in Purna, or Mugdha, its past Ghatikas should be multiplied by 2 and the product should be divided by 15. The figure so arrived at should be converted into years, months etc. By multiplying it by the serial number of Sun and other Planets in their normal order, we will get the Kaal Dasha of these Planets. If the birth is during Sandhya, then its past Ghatikas should be multiplied by 4 and the product divided by 15. The figure so arrived at in terms of years, months etc. should be multiplied by the serial number of Sun and the other Planets to get the Kaal Dasha of all the nine Planets. 
Chakra 
50-51. If the birth is at night, the Dasha will commence from Lagna Rāśi. If the birth is during the day, the Dasha will start from the Rāśi, in which the Lord of Lagna is placed. If the birth is during Sandhya, the Dasha will begin from the Rāśi of the second House. The Dasha of each Rāśi is 10 years. As it is the Dasha system of the 12 Rāśis in the Zodiac, it has been named, as Chakra Dasha.Kala Chakra
52-53. Mahārśi Parashara said. O Brahmin! Now, after making obedience to Lord Shiva, I shall describe the Kala Chakra Dasha. Whatever was related by Lord Shiva to Goddess Parvati, is being explained by me for the use of sages to be utilized for the welfare of the people.
54-55. By drawing vertical and horizontal lines, prepare 2 Charts, Savya and Apsavya, of 12 apartments (Kosthas) each. From the second Kostha in each Kundali fix the Rāśis Aries, Taurus, Gemini, Cancer, Leo, Virgo, Libra, Scorpio, Sagittarius, Capricorn, Aquarius, Pisces. Then Nakshatras may be incorporated in the manner, indicated hereafter. These Charts, indicative of the 12 Rāśis, are called Kala Chakra.
56-58. Write Ashvini, Bharani and Kritika in the Savya Chakra and Rohini, Mrigashira, Ardra in the Apsavya. Then incorporate the three following Nakshatras, Punarvasu, Pushya and Aslesha in the Savya and Magha, Purvaphalguni and Uttaraphalguni in the Apsavya. Then incorporate the three following, Hast, Chitra and Swati in the Savya and Vishakah, Anuradha and Jyeshtha in the Apsavya. Then incorporate Mul, Purvashadha and Uttarashadha in the Savya and Shravan, 2ndishtha and Shatabhisha in the Apsavya. Finally incorporate the last three Nakshatras, Purvabhadrapad, Uttarabhadrapad and Revati in the Savya Chakra. Now there will be 15 Nakshatras in the Savya and 12 Nakshatras in the Apsavya, (because for the 12 Rāśis there are 12 Padas of 3 Nakshatras, the Navāmśaas). The Padas of Ashvini, Punarvasu, Hast, Mul, Purvabhadrapad, Kritika, Aslesha, Swati, Uttarashadha and Revati of the Savya should be reckoned in the same manner, as the Padas of Ashvini.
59. Now I shall describe in detail, how the Deha and Jiva should be reckoned in the Padas (quarters) of the Nakshatras.
60. In the first Pad of Ashvini Aries is indicative of Deha (body) and Sagittarius is indicative of Jiva (life). And the Lords of Aries, Taurus, Gemini, Cancer, Leo, Virgo, Libra, Scorpio and Sagittarius are Lords of the Dashas in the order, as described before.
61. In the second Pad of Ashvini Capricorn is Deha and Gemini is Jiva and the Lords of the nine Rāśis from Capricorn to Gemini are Lords of the Dashas.
62. In the third Pad of the ten Nakshatras, beginning from Ashvini, Taurus is Deha and Gemini is Jiva. The Lords of the Rāśis Taurus, Aries, Pisces, Aquarius, Capricorn, Sagittarius, Aries, Taurus and Gemini are Lords of the Dashas in that order.
63-64. For the 4th Pad of the 10 Nakshatras, beginning from Ashvini, Cancer is Deha and Pisces is Jiva and the Lords of the nine Rāśis from Cancer to Pisces are the Lords of Dashas.
65. In the four Padas of the 5 Nakshatras, Bharani, Pushya, Chitra, Purvashadha and Uttarabhadrapad, Deha and Jiva are the same, as for Bharani.
66. In the first Pad of Bharani Scorpio is Deha and Pisces is Jiva and the Lords of the Rāśis Scorpio, Libra, Virgo, Cancer, Leo, Gemini, Taurus, Aries and Pisces are the Lords of Dashas in this order.
67. In the 2nd Pad of Bharani Aquarius is Deha and Virgo is Jiva and the Lords of Aquarius, Capricorn, Sagittarius, Aries, Taurus, Gemini, Cancer, Leo and Virgo are the Lords of Dashas in that order.
68. In the 3rd Pad of Bharani Libra is Deha and Virgo is Jiva and Lords of the Rāśis Libra, Scorpio, Sagittarius, Capricorn, Aquarius, Pisces, Scorpio, Libra and Virgo are the Dasha Lords in this order.
69. In the 4th Pad of Bharani Cancer is Deha and Aquarius is Jiva and the Lords of the Rāśis Cancer, Leo, Gemini, Taurus, Aries, Pisces, Aquarius, Capricorn and Sagittarius are the Dasha Lords in this order.
71-72. O Brahmin! I have thus given you the description of Savya Chakra. Now I shall give the description of Apsavya Chakra. Prepare a similar chart of 12 apartments and from the 2nd apartment onwards place the Rāśis from Scorpio onwards in the reverse order. In this chart Deha and Jiva would be the same for Rohini, Magha, Vishakah and Shravan, as for Rohini.
73-76. In the first Pad of Rohini Cancer is Deha and Sagittarius is Jiva. The Lords of the Rāśis Sagittarius, Capricorn, Aquarius, Pisces, Aries, Taurus, Gemini, Leo and Libra will be the Dasha Lords in this order. In the 2nd Libra will be Deha and Virgo the Jiva and the Lords of the Rāśis Virgo, Libra, Scorpio, Pisces, Aquarius, Capricorn, Sagittarius, Scorpio and Scorpio will be the Dasha Lords. In the 3rd Aquarius will be Deha and Virgo Jiva. The Lords of the Rāśis Virgo, Leo, Cancer, Gemini, Taurus, Aries, Sagittarius, Capricorn and Aquarius will be the Dasha Lords. In the 4th Scorpio will be Deha and Pisces Jiva and the Lords of the Rāśis Pisces, Aries, Taurus, Gemini, Leo, Cancer, Virgo, Libra and Scorpio will be the Lords.
77. In the 4 Padas of the Apsavya Nakshatras Mrigashira, Ardra, Purvaphalguni, Uttaraphalguni, Anuradha, Jyeshtha, 2ndishtha and Shatabhisha the Deha and Jiva and the Dasha Lords will be the same, as for Mrigashira.
78-81. In the first Pad of Mrigashira Cancer is Deha and Pisces is Jiva and the Lords of the Rāśis Pisces, Aquarius, Capricorn, Sagittarius, Scorpio, Libra, Virgo, Leo and Cancer will be the Dasha Lords in this order. In the 2nd Taurus is Deha and Gemini is Jiva and the Lords of the Rāśis Gemini, Taurus, Aries, Sagittarius, Capricorn, Aquarius, Pisces, Aries and Taurus will be the Dasha Lords. In the 3rd Capricorn is Deha and Gemini is Jiva and the Lords of the Rāśis Gemini, Leo, Cancer, Virgo, Libra, Scorpio, Pisces, Aquarius and Capricorn will be the Dasha Lords. In the 4th Aries will be Deha and Sagittarius Jiva and the Lords of the Rāśis Sagittarius, Scorpio, Libra, Virgo, Leo, Cancer, Gemini, Taurus and Aries will be the Dasha Lords.
82. Mahārśi Parashara said. O Brahmin! The description of the Deha and Jiva of the Padas of the Apsavya Nakshatras and the Dasha Lords is the same, as narrated by Lord Mahadeva to Goddess Parvati.
83. Maitreya said. O Venerable Mahārśi Parashara! Now please guide me about the Dasha spans of the Dasha Lords, described by you. Please also demonstrate, how the commencement of the Dasha, its expired and the remaining periods at the birth are to be calculated.
84. Mahārśi Parashara said. 5, 21, 7, 9, 10, 16 and 4 years are the Dasha spans of Sun, Moon, Mars, Mercury, Jupiter, Venus and Saturn.
85-86. The span of life of a person is determined from the Padas (Ańśaas) of the Nakshatra at the time of birth, or the time of query and the years allotted to the 9 Rāśis, commencing from it (the Pad of the Nakshatra). Some sages are of the view, that the person will enjoy full span of life (Purna Ayu), if his birth is at the commencement of the Padas, will have middle span of life (Madhaya Ayu), if the birth is in the middle of the Padas and short span of life (Alap Ayu), or will face death-like sufferings, if the birth is at the end of the Padas of the Nakshatra.
87-88. According to this principle, we should be acquainted with the Padas of the Nakshatras. Now I shall tell you, how the calculations are made, according to the proportion of the Padas of a Nakshatra. The number of Ashvini etc., whichever may be the past Nakshatras, should be divided by 3. Thereafter the remainder should be multiplied by 4. To the figure so made available the Pad of the present Nakshatra should be added. The product will be the Navāmśa from Aries onwards.
89. The number of years (Purna Ayu) are, as under. For the Ańśa in Aries 100 years, in Taurus 85 years, in Gemini 83 years, in Cancer 86 years. The number of years will be the same for Rāśis, situated the 5th and 9th to them.
90-91. Multiply the past Ghatikas, Palas etc. of the Pad of the Nakshatra, in which a person is born, by the existing Dasha years and divide it by 15. The result will indicate the expired period of the Dasha in years, months etc. By deducting it from the total number of years allotted, we get the Balaance of Dasha at birth. The Dasha should be taken, as commencing from that Rāśi.
92. Multiply the past Ghatikas, Palas etc. of the present Pad of the Nakshatra by the number of years and divide the product by the fourth part of Bhabhog. The years etc. so obtained may then be deducted from the total Dasha period. The result will be the Balaance of Dasha at birth in years, months etc.
93. The past Kalas (minutes) of the Navāmśa, in which Moon may be placed, should be multiplied by the years, allotted to the Dasha and the product should be divided by 200. The resulting years etc. will be the expired portion of the Dasha. By deducting them from the total number of years the Balaance of the Dasha at birth is obtained.
94-95. In the Savya Chakra the first Ańśa is called Deha and the last Jiva. The opposite is the case in the Apsavya Chakra. Therefore the calculations should be based on the Deha etc. in the Savya Chakra and on the Jiva etc. in Apsavya.
We give below the Savya and Apsavya Kala Chakra Charts. For example. The birth is in Mrigashira 4th Pad. It is in the Apsavya Kala Chakra. The Lord of Deha is Mars and that of Jiva is Jupiter. The Bhabhog of Mrigashira is 59/31 (59 Ghatikas 31 Palas) and Bhayat is 58/15 (58 Ghatikas 15 Palas). ｼ of the Bhabhog comes to 14/52/44. That would be the value of one Pad. Multiplying this by 3 will get Ghatikas of 3 Padas, namely 44/38/15. Deducting this from Bhayat, the past Ghatikas, Palas etc. of the 4th Pad will be 13/36/45. The full Dasha years are 100. Multiplying this by 13/36/45 we get 1300/3600/4500 = 1361/15. This divided by 15 will give the expired period at birth, namely 90 years and 9 months. See the Kala Chakra. There we count from Jiva etc. to Deha. In the 4th Pad of Mrigashira Jiva is in Sagittarius and Deha in Aries. Therefore, by deducting the total of years from Sagittarius to Gemini, namely 77, from 90 years 9 months, we get the expired period of Taurus, namely 13 years and 9 months. By deducting this from the present 16 years of Venus, we will get 2 years and 3 months, as the Balaance of Dasha at birth. Accordingly, like Vimshottari Dasha, the order of Dasha will be Taurus, Aries, Sagittarius, Scorpio etc. For Example. Suppose, that at the time of birth of a person in Kritika Nakshatra the longitude of Moon is 1r4ｰ50. This converted into Kalas will be 2090 at birth. The Dasha should be taken, as commencing from that. Divide the Kalas by 800 (1 Nakshatra). The result will be the 2nd Nakshatra, namely Bharani and the remainder will be 490. These will be the past Kalas of Kritika. There are 200 Kalas in one Pad (Navāmśa). Divide 490, the past Kalas of Kritika, by 200. We will then get 2, as past Padas and the remainder 90 will represent the past Kalas of the present Nakshatra. By multiplying this by 83, the Dasha years, we will get 7470, which, divided by 200, will indicate the expired portion of the Dasha, as 37 years, 4 months and 6 days. By deducting the years of Dehāńś, commencing from Taurus, in the order Taurus, Aries, Pisces, Aquarius (16+7+10+4 = 37), we will get 0 years, 4 months and 6 days. This will be the expired portion of Capricorn. Deducting this from 4, the Dasha period of Capricorn, we get the Balaance of the Dasha of Capricorn, namely 3 years, 7 months and 24 days. See in this connection the Savya Kala Chakra.Gati of Rāśis in the Kala Chakra 96-98. There are three kinds of movements (Gati) of the Rāśis in the Kala Chakra, namely Manduki, Markati and Leoavlokan. The movement of one Rāśi by jumping over one Rāśi is known, as Manduki Gati. Backward movement to the previous Rāśi is called Markati Gati. The movement of a Rāśi to the 5th and 9th Rāśi is said to be Leoavlokan.99-100. Movement from Virgo to Cancer and from Leo to Gemini is Manduki Gati. Movement from Leo to Cancer is Markati Gati. Movement from Pisces to Scorpio and from Sagittarius to Aries is called Leoavlokan Gati. 
Effects of Dashas of Rāśis, as a Result of these Gati 101-102. The effects of the Dasha of the Rāśis with Manduki Gati in the Savya Chakra are distress to friends, relations, parents and elders and there is likely to be cause for trouble from poison, weapons, thieves and enemies. In the Manduki Dasha of the Gati of a Rāśi from Leo to Gemini there is the likelihood of the death of the mother, or self, trouble from Government and possibility of brain fever.103. The effects of the Dasha of Rāśi with Markati Gati in the Savya Chakra are loss of wealth, agricultural products and animals, death of father, or an elderly close relation and feeling of lethargy.
104-105. The effects of the Dasha of the Rāśis with Leoavlokan Gati in the Savya Chakra are possibility of injury from animals, loss of amity with friends, distress to near relations, drowning in a well, fall from animals, possibility of harm from poison, weapons and diseases and destruction of residential dwelling.
106-108. In the Dasha of the Rāśis with the Manduki Gati in the Apsavya Chakra the effects will be distress to wife and conditions, loss of children, possibility of feverish conditions and loss of position. In the Dasha of the Rāśis with the Markati Gati there may be danger from watery places, loss of position, distress from father, punishment from Government and wandering in the forests; with the Simhaavlokan there may be destruction of the dwelling and death of father etc.
109-111. If the movement is from Pisces to Scorpio, the native may suffer from fever; if from Virgo to Cancer, there may be loss of brothers and kinsmen; if from Leo to Gemini, there may be ill health of the wife; if from Leo to Cancer, the native may die; if from Sagittarius to Aries, there may be death of uncles and similar relations. If the Rāśi is conjunct with a malefic, adverse conditions may be expected in the Dasha of the Rāśi. Favourable effects will be felt in its Dasha, if the Rāśi is conjunct with a benefic.
112-113. O Brahmin! In the Kala Chakra Dasha favourable and unfavorable effects may be predicted, after taking into account the directions of the Rāśis and Planets.
114-119. If the movement is from Virgo to Cancer, good results are realized in places, located in the East and at that time journeys to the places in the North prove fruitful. Unfavorable effects will be felt in places, located in the West and the South. It will be advisable not to undertake journeys in those directions in the Dasha of these Rāśis. If the movement is from Leo to Gemini, no journey should be undertaken to places, located in the East. However, the journeys to the South-West will prove fruitful in the Dasha of those Rāśis. If the movement is from Cancer to Leo, journeys during that period to the South will prove unfavorable and result in loss and the native has to return from the South to the West. If the movement is from Pisces to Scorpio, there will distress, if the native goes to the North. The same would happen, if the movement is from Sagittarius to Capricorn. There may be ill health, imprisonment, or death, if the movement is from Sagittarius to Aries. There may be gains, comforts and property and marriage, if the movement is from Sagittarius to Scorpio. It will not be advisable to undertake journeys to the West during the related period, if the movement is from Leo to Cancer. Favourable results should be predicted, if the Rāśis are conjunct with benefics and adverse, if the Rāśis are conjunct with malefics.
120-122. According to the above-mentioned Kala Chakra, the person, born in the Ańśaas of the various Rāśis, will be, as under. Aries Ańśa brave and a thief, Taurus wealthy, Gemini learned, Cancer king, Leo respected by king, Virgo learned, Libra minister, or adviser, Sagittarius sinful, Aquarius businessman, Pisces wealthy.
123-128. If the Deha, or Jiva Rāśis are conjunct with Sun, Mars, Saturn, or Rahu, the native will die. Worse results may be expected, if the Deha and Jiva Rāśis are conjunct with two, or all of them. If there is a malefic in Deha Rāśi, the native suffers ill health; a malefic in a Jiva Rāśi will make the native very timid. If the Deha and/or Jiva Rāśi are conjunct with two malefics, there will be distress and diseases. Three malefics in the Deha and/or Jiva Rāśi will cause premature death. Four malefics in the Deha and Jiva Rāśi will cause definite death. If both the Deha and Jiva Rāśis are occupied by malefics, there will be fear from king and thieves and death of the native. If Sun is in the Deha, or Jiva Rāśi, there will be danger from fire. Moon in the Deha, or Jiva Rāśi will cause danger from water, Marsfear from weapons, Mercury fear from windy troubles, Saturn fear from Gulma (a disease), Rahu and Ketu fear from poison. If the Deha, or Jiva Rāśis are occupied by Mercury, Jupiter and Venus, the native will be wealthy, will enjoy all kinds of comforts and will have good health. Mixed results may be expected, if the Deha and Jiva Rāśis are occupied by both benefics and malefics.
129-130. In the Dasha of the Rāśis, owned by malefics, the body and soul will be in distress. The effects will be favourable in the Dasha of the Rāśis, owned by benefics. If a malefic Rāśi is occupied by a benefic Planet, or, if a benefic Rāśi is occupied by a malefic Planet, the effects will be of a mixed nature.
Effects of Kala Chakra Dasha of the Rāśis in Lagna and other Houses.  
131-132. In the Kala Chakra Dasha of the Rāśi in Lagna the body remains healthy and the native spends a life with many kinds of comforts. If the Lagna Rāśi is a benefic one, the good effects are realized fully. If the Lagna Rāśi is a malefic Rāśi, there is likelihood of ill health. If a Planet is in exaltation or in its own Rāśi occupies Lagna, the native is respected by the king, or government and acquires wealth. 
133-134. In the Chakra Dasha of the Rāśi in 2nd the native receives good food, enjoys happiness of wife and children, gains wealth, achieves progress in the educational sphere, becomes a clever conversationalist and moves in good society. If the Rāśi be a benefic, good effects are realized in full, otherwise the effects would be of a mixed nature.
135-136. Happiness from co-borns, valor, patience, comforts, acquisition of gold, ornaments and clothes and recognition by the king, or government, are the effects in the Kala Chakra Dasha of the Rāśi in 3rd. If the Rāśi is a benefic, the good results are realized in full, otherwise adverse effects may also be experienced.
137-138. Good relations with kinsmen, acquisition of land, houses, or a kingdom, conveyances and clothes and enjoyment of sound health, are the effects of the Chakra Dasha of the Rāśi in 4th. If the Rāśi is a benefic one, the good effects are realized in full. If it is a malefic Rāśi, adverse results are also experienced.
139-140. Being blessed with wife and children, favours from Government, enjoyment of sound health, good relations with friends, achievement of fame, good progress in the educational sphere, patience and valor are the effects of the Chakra Dasha of the Rāśi in 5th. If the Rāśi is a benefic one, the good results are enjoyed in full. If the Rāśi is a malefic one, adverse effects are also experienced.
141-142. Danger from the king, fire and weapons and the possibility of suffering from diabetes, Gulma and jaundice are the effects in the Chakra Dasha of the Rāśi in 6th. If the Rāśi is a malefic one, the above adverse effects will be experienced in full. There will be some mitigation of the evil effects in the case of a benefic Rāśi.
143-144. Marriage, conjugal happiness, being blessed with children, gain of agricultural products, cows and clothes, favours and recognition from the king and achievement of fame, are the effects in the Chakra Dasha of the Rāśi in 7th. The beneficial results will be experienced in full, if the Rāśi is a benefic one. Meager good effects will be realized in the case of a malefic Rāśi.
145-146. Destruction of a residential house, distress, loss of wealth, poverty and danger from enemies are the effects of the Chakra Dasha of the Rāśi in 8th. The adverse effects will be realized in full, if the Rāśi is a malefic one. Some mitigation in evil effects may be expected in the case of a benefic Rāśi.
147-148. Felicity in respect of wife, children, house, agricultural activities, performance of good and pious deeds, progress in religious inclinations and privilege of moving in the society of great religious leaders, are the effects in Chakra Dasa of the sign in the ninth house (Dharma Bhava). These of a benefic sign. Very meager good effects will be experienced in the event of the sign being a malefic one. 
149 - 150. Acquisition of kingdom, recognition from the king, happiness from wife and children, success in ventures and performance of pious deeds are the effects in the chakra dasa of the sign in the 10th house. The good results will be realized in full in case of a benefic sign. If it is a malefic sign, the good effects will be few.
151 - 152. Felicity from wife, children and kinsmen, receipt of favors from government, acquisition of wealth and clothes and association with good people, are the effects in the Chakra Dasa of the sign in the eleventh house (Labha Bhava). The good effects will be enjoyed in full in the case of a benefic sign. Very little good will happen in the sign be a malefic one.
153 - 154. Failure in efforts and ventures, pain in the body, loss of position, poverty and unnecessary expenditures are the effects in the Kalachakra Dasa of the sign in the twelfth house (Vyaya Bhava). The adverse effects will be experienced in full in the case of a malefic sign. Some good may happen if the sign be a benefic.
Chara Dasa 
155 -156. Now I shall describe to you the Chara Dasa of the signs (Rasis) of the twelve houses. In this Dasa system the number of years of Dasa is reckoned from the Rasi up to the house in which its lord is posited. The peculiar feature of this system is that every three signs from Aries etc. have four padas. For the odd (1,3) padas, the counting is done from Rasi onwards up to the Rasi in which its lord is housed. For the even padas (2,4) this counting is done in the reverse order.
157 . In this system Mars and Ketu are both lords of Scorpio. Similarly Saturn and Rahu are lords of Aquarius. 
158-166. Now I will tell you about the working out of the Dasha years of Scorpio and Aquarius. If both the Lords of the two Rāśis, Scorpio and Aquarius, are placed in their own Rāśis, their Dasha will be of 12 years. Otherwise the Dasha will be of the number of years, indicated by the number, counted from that Rāśi to the Rāśi, occupied by its Lord. If one Planet be in his own Rāśi and the other in any other Rāśi, the Dasha will be of the number of years counted, from the above first Rāśi to the other. If the Lords are in different Rāśis, the counting is to be done up to the Rāśi, which is stronger. The Rāśi, which has a Planet, placed in it, is considered more powerful than the Rāśi without a Planet in it. If both are with Planets in them, the one with more Planets would be considered more powerful. If both Rāśis are occupied by an equal number of Planets, the strength of the Rāśi itself should be taken into account. The principle for considering the Bala of the Rāśi is, that the Fixed Rāśi is considered stronger than the Movable one and the Dual Rāśi is considered more powerful than the Fixed Rāśi. If there is equality in the strength of the Rāśis, then to determine the number of years of Dasha counting should be done up to the Rāśi with bigger number. If one Rāśi is occupied by a Planet in exaltation, the counting should be done up to that Rāśi only. In addition 1 should be added in the number of years in the case of a Rāśi with an exalted Planet and 1 should be deducted from the number of years in the case of a Rāśi with a Planet in debilitation. The prediction should be made after calculating the Dashas in this manner. 
167. If the Rāśi in 9th House is in an odd Pad, the counting should be from the Rāśi in the Lagna onwards. The counting would be in the reverse order, if the Pad is even. The Dashas of Rāśis have to be fixed, keeping this in view.
For example. In the above Libra is the Rāśi in 9th House in an odd Pad. Amongst the Lords of Lagna, Saturn and Rahu, Rahu is associated with a Planet. Therefore Rahu is more powerful than, Saturn. Therefore counting should be done up to Rahu. Aquarius is in even Pad, therefore counting has to be done from Aquarius up to Rahu in the reverse order, by which the Char Dasha for Aquarius would come to 8 years. Aries is in odd Pad. Therefore the Char Dasha for Aries will be one year. The Dasha of other Rāśis should be calculated in the same manner. 
Sthira Dasa 
168-169. Mahārśi Parashara said. Now I am going to describe the Sthira Dasha. In this Dasha system 7, 8 and 9 years are the Dasha spans of the Movable (Char), Fixed (Sthira) and Dual (Dvisva House) Rāśis. In this system the Dasha of the 12 Rāśis begins from the Brahm Planet Ashrit Rāśi. The Dashas are counted onwards from the odd Rāśis and in the reverse order from the even Rāśis.170-173. Maitreya said. O great Sage! Now please enlighten me how the Brahm Planet is picked out in a chart. Mahārśi Parashara said. From amongst the Lords of 6th, 8th and 12th the Planet, who may possess the greatest strength and is placed in Lagna, or in 7th with strength, the one, placed in an odd Rāśi within sixth House from the House concerned, is called the Brahm Planet. The Lord of 8th in 8th is also accepted, as Brahm Planet. If Saturn, or Rahu/Ketu obtain Brahmatva (qualifications of Brahm Planet), they become Brahm Planet. If a number of Planets obtain Brahmatva, the one with the largest number of degrees would become Brahm Planet. If there is p6thty in the degrees of such Planets, the most powerful amongst them would become Brahm Planet.
Yogardha Dasa
174. The spans of Dashas of the Rāśis in the Yogardha Dasha system are half of the total of the spans of Char and Sthira Dashas. The Dasha will commence from the Rāśi of Lagna, or 7th, whichever is stronger. The order of the Dashas of the 12 Rāśis will be counted onwards, if the opening Dasha Rāśi is an odd one. If it be an even Rāśi, the Dashas will be in reverse order.
Kendraadi Dasa  
175-176. In this system there are Dashas of Fixed Rāśis in the Kendra etc. from Lagna, or from 7th, whichever is stronger. If Lagna, or 7th with strength is placed in an odd Rāśi, the Kendra etc. are counted in the onward order. If it be in an even Rāśi, the counting will be in the backward, or reverse order. In them also the Dashas would be in the order of comparative strength of the Rāśis. The order of Dashas would be the same, as reckoned from the Atma Karak. The spans of Dashas would be the same, as they are in the Char Dasha. In calculating the years of Dashas of Planets, counting is done from the Planet to his own Rāśi. The years of Dashas would be the number, arrived at by counting up to the Rāśi of the Planet, which is stronger, or more in number. 
177. If a Planet owns two Rāśis, the Dasha years will be equal to the number, which is greater, when counted from the Rāśi, occupied by him.
Notes. Under this system Dashas are of two kinds, namely Lagna Kendraadi and Atma Karak Kendraadi. There are also Kendraadi Rāśi Dasha, or Kendraadi Planet Dasha in both the Dasha systems, mentioned above.
Karak Dasa
178. The system, under which the first Dasha is of the Atma Karak and the subsequent Dashas are of the remaining 7 Karakas in their order is known, as Karak Dasha. In this system the Dasha years are equal to the number of Rāśis, counted from Lagna up to the Karak concerned.
Manduka Dasa
179-180. Under the Manduka Dasha system the Dasha commences from Lagna, or 7th House, whichever is stronger. If the Rāśi of commencement is an odd Rāśi, the Dashas of 3 Movable, 3 Fixed and 3 Dual Rāśis will be counted in the onwards order. They will be in the reverse order in the case of an even Rāśi. In this system the Dasha years will be the same, as in Sthira Dasha. In this system every Dasha is of the next 3rd Rāśi.
Shula Dasa
181-182. Some sages have designed the Shula Dasha for determining the time of death. In this system the Dasha commences from 2nd, or 8th, whichever is stronger. If the Rāśi is an odd one, the order of the Dasha Rāśis will be onwards. It will be backwards in the case of an even Rāśi. The Dasha years in this system are, as adopted for the Sthira Dasha. There is a possibility, that death appears in the Dasha of the Marak Rāśi, which has greater strength.
Trikona
183-184. In this system the first Dasha commences from the strongest amongst the Rāśis in Kona (Trikona) to Lagna (1st, 5th and 9th). This system is similar to the Char Dasha. Here also the Dashas of the Rāśis will be in the onwards order in the case of odd Rāśis and in the reverse order in the case of even Rāśis. The Dasha years will be similar to that of Char Dasha. It has been named Trikona because of the commencement of the Dasha from the Rāśis in Konas.
Dirga Dasa
185-187. In this system the order of the Dashas is, as follows: the Rāśi, occupying 9th, the Rāśis, receiving a Aspect from the Rāśi in 9th, the Rāśi in 10th, the Rāśis, receiving a Aspect from the Rāśi in 10th, the Rāśi in 11th and the Rāśis, receiving a Aspect from the Rāśi in 11th. As this system is mostly based on Aspects, it has been named, as Dirga Dasha. Three different processes are adopted for the Movable, Fixed and Dual Rāśis from 9th, 10th and 11th. According to them, Rāśi, which receives a Aspect from the Movable Rāśi, is counted backwards and the Rāśi, receiving a Aspect from the Fixed Rāśi, is counted onwards. In the case of the Dual Rāśi, if it is odd, the counting is onwards and the order is backwards in case of an even Rāśi for the Rāśis, receiving a Aspect.
Notes. The intention is, that from the point of view of Aspect the process of Rāśi, receiving a Aspect, should be started from the Rāśi, which is nearest. In this connection readers may refer to Rāśi Aspectkathan Adhyaya, Ch. 8, Verse 9 and the table after that.
Lagnaadi Rāśi Dasha
188-189. In this system there are Dashas of all the 12 Rāśis, including Lagna, in every Nakshatra. Consequently the Bhayat at birth may be multiplied by 12 and then the product should be divided by Bhabhog. The Rāśi, degree etc. so available may be added to the longitude of Lagna. From the Rāśi, becoming available by doing so, will start the Dashas of the 12 Rāśis. (If that Rāśi is odd, the counting will be onwards. It will be in the reverse order, if the Rāśi is even)
190. For finding the Balaance of Dasha at birth, multiply the expired degree etc. by the Dasha years of the first Dasha Rāśi and divide it by 30. The years etc. so arrived at may be deducted from the Dasha years. The result will indicate the Balaance of Dasha at birth in years, months etc.
Panch Swar Dasha 191-194. Beginning from Akaradhi 5 Swaras (a, i, u, e, o), write underneath them the Varnas in 6 lines. Leave out the letters ňa, a and ņa, because they are not used in names. If they are found in any name, ga may be substituted for ňa, ja for a and da for ņa for working out the Dashas and making predictions. In this manner the Swar, under which the first Varna of the name of the native is found, will determine the order of the Dashas of the five Swaras. Dashas are of 12 years for all the five Swaras. In the Dasha of every Swar there will be Antar Dashas of all the five Swaras in the same order. 
Yogini Dasa
195-199. Mahārśi Parashara said. O Brahmin! I have already given you the description of Panch Swar Dasha. Now I will acquaint you with the Yogini Dasha, as described by Lord Mahadeva. There are 8 Yoginis, namely Mars, Pingal, 2ndya, Bhram6th, Bhadrika, Ulka, Siddha and Sankat.
Moon, Sun, Jupiter, Mars, Mercury, Saturn, Venus and Rahu are born from them. Add 3 to the Janma Nakshatra and divide it by 8. The remainder will indicate the Yogini Dasha of Mars, etc. The Dashas are of 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7 and 8 years. The Balaance of Dasha at birth should be worked out from the Bhayat and Bhabhog etc., as already explained earlier.
Pind, Ańśa and Nisarg
201-202. The Pind, Ańśa and Nisarg Dasha will be the same, as Pindayu, Ańśaayu and Nisargayu, the method of determination of which has already been explained previously. The order of Dashas will be, as follows. The first will be of Lagna, Sun, or Moon, whoever is stronger. The subsequent Dashas will be of Planets in Kendra to them, then of Planets in Panaphara Houses and lastly in Apoklima Houses. The Dashas and Antar Dashas of Lagna and the seven Planets will also be in the same order.
203. The effects of these Dashas will be in accordance with Ashtak Varga Bala, which subject will be dealt with later. These Dashas are also called Ashtak Varga Dashas.
Sandhya 204. Sandhya is the Dvadashāńś Ayurdaya of the Param Ayurdaya (maximum possible life-span). In Sandhya Dasha the Dasha of all the Rāśis from Lagna onwards is of 1/12 the years of Param Ayurdaya.Pachak Dasha in Sandhya Dasha
205-206. By multiplying the Dasha years of Sandhya Dasha by 6 and dividing the product by 31, the years, months etc. so arrived at may be put in one apartment of a Table. Thereafter half of these years, months etc. may be written in the next three apartments. The remaining 8 apartments may be filled in by one third of the aforesaid years, months etc. In this manner Pachak Dasha in Sandhya Dasha of every House can be worked out and predictions may be made from it.
Tar 207-209. O Brahmin! Some sages have given consideration to Tar Dasha, which is like Vimshottari. In this Dasha Janma, Sampat etc. in their order replace Sun, Moon etc., placed in Kendraas. This Dasha is applied in those cases only, where there are Planets in Kendraas. If there are a number of Planets, the first Dasha will belong to the strongest amongst them.
210. O Brahmin! I have now completed the description of the different kinds of Dashas. I will give the description of their Antar Dashas (sub-periods) later. 
Ch. 47. Effects of Dashas
1. Maitreya said. O Mahārśi Parashara! You have told me about the different kinds of Dashas. Now be kind enough to enlighten me with the effects of Dashas.2. Mahārśi Parashara replied. O Brahmin! There are two kinds of effects of Dashas: general and distinctive. The natural characteristics of the Planets cause the general effects and the distinctive effects are realized by their placements etc.
3-4. The effects of the Dashas of the Planets are in accordance with their strength. The effects of a Planet in the first Dreshkan are realized at the commencement of the Dasha. The Planet in the second Dreshkan makes its effects felt in the middle of the Dasha. The effects of the Planet in the third Dreshkan are experienced at the end of the Dasha. If the Planet is retrograde, these effects would be in the reverse order. The Dasha effects of Rahu and Ketu, who are always retrograde, will always be realized in the reverse order.
5-6. The effects are favourable, if at the commencement of the Dasha the Dasha Lord is in Lagna, in his exaltation, own, or a Shant Rāśi. The results are unfavorable, if the Dasha Lord is in 6th, 8th, or 12th House, in his debilitation, or in an inimical Rāśi.
7-11. During the Dasha of Sun there is acquisition of wealth, great felicity and honors from the Government, if at the time of birth Sun is in his own Rāśi, in his exaltation Rāśi, in a Kendra, in 11th, be associated with the Lord of 9th, or the Lord of 10th and strong in his Varga. The native will be blessed with a son (children), if Sun is with the Lord of 5th. The native will acquire elephants and other kinds of wealth, if Sun is associated with the Lord of 2nd. The native will enjoy comforts of conveyances, if Sun is associated with the Lord of 4th. He attains a high position, like that of Army Chief, by the beneficence of the king and enjoys all kinds of happiness. Thus during the Dasha of a strong (and favourable) Sun there are acquisitions of clothes, agricultural products, wealth, honors, conveyances etc.
12-15. During the Dasha of Sun there will be anxieties, loss of wealth, punishment from Government, defamation, opposition by kinsmen, distress to father, (in)auspicious happenings at home, distress to paternal and maternal uncles etc., anxiety and inimical relations with other people for no reason whatsoever, should Sun be in his Rāśi of debilitation, be weak in 6th, 8th, or 12th, or be associated with malefic Planets, or with the Lord of 6th, 8th, or 12th. There will be some favourable effects at times, if in the above situations Sun receives a Aspect from benefic Planets. The effects will always be unfavorable, when malefic Planets give a Aspect to Sun.
16-22. O Brahmin! After describing the effects of the Dasha of Sun in brief, I will now come to the effects of Vimshottari Dasha of Moon. During the Dasha of Moon from its commencement to the end there will be opulence and glory, good fortune, gain of wealth, auspicious functions at home, dawn of fortune, attainment of a high position in Government, acquisition of conveyances, clothes, birth of children and acquisition of cattle, should Moon be in her exaltation, in her own Rāśi, in Kendra, in 11th, 9th, or 5th, be associated with, or receives a Aspect from benefics, be fully powerful and is associated with the Lord of 10th, 9th, or 4th. There will be extraordinary gains of wealth and luxuries, if such a Moon is in 2nd House.
23-26. Should Moon be waning, or in her debilitation Rāśi, there will be loss of wealth in her Dasha. If Moon is in 3rd, there will be happiness off and on. If Moon is associated with malefics, there will be idiocy, mental tension, trouble from employees and mother and loss of wealth. If waning Moon is in 6th, 8th, or 12th, or is associated with malefics, there will be inimical relations with Government, loss of wealth, distress to mother and similar evil effects. If a strong Moon is placed in 6th, 8th, or 12th there will be troubles and good times off and on.
27-32. If Mars is in his exaltation, in his MulaTrikonaa, in his own Rāśi, in Kendra, in 11th, or 2nd House with strength, in a benefic Ańśa (Navāmśa) and is associated with a benefic, there will be during his Dasha acquisition of kingdom (attainment of a high administrative, or political position in Government, gain of wealth and land, recognition by Government), gain of wealth from foreign countries and acquisition of conveyances and ornaments. There will also be happiness and good relations with co-borns. If Mars with strength is placed in a Kendra, or in 3rd, there will be gain of wealth through valor, victory over enemies, happiness from wife and children. There will, however, be a possibility of some unfavorable effects at the end of the Dasha.
33. If Mars is in his debilitation Rāśi, weak, in an inauspicious House, or is associated with, or receives a Aspect from malefics, there will be in his Dasha loss of wealth, distress and similar unfavorable effects.
34-39. In order to cl6thfy the effects of the Dasha of Rahu I shall first mention the exaltation and debilitation Rāśis of Rahu and Ketu. The exaltation Rāśi of Rahu is Taurus. The exaltation Rāśi of Ketu is Scorpio. The MulaTrikonaas of Rahu and Ketu are Gemini and Sagittarius. The own Rāśis of Rahu and Ketu are Aquarius and Scorpio. Some sages have expressed the view, that Virgo is the own Rāśi of Rahu and Pisces is the own Rāśi of Ketu. Should Rahu be in his exaltation Rāśi etc., there will be during the Dasha of Rahu great happiness from acquisition of wealth, agricultural products etc., acquisition of conveyances with the help of friends and Government, construction of a new house, birth of sons (children), religious inclinations, recognition from Government of foreign countries and gain of wealth, clothes etc. If Rahu be associated with, or receives a Aspect from benefics, be in a benefic Rāśi and be in 1st, 4th, 7th, 10th, 11th, or 3rd, there will be during his Dasha all kinds of comforts by the beneficence of the Government, acquisition of wealth through a foreign Government, or sovereign and felicity at home.
40-43. If Rahu is in 8th, or 12th House, there will be during his Dasha all kinds of troubles and distress. If Rahu is associated with a malefic, or a Marak Planet, or is in his debilitation Rāśi, there will be loss of position, destruction of his residential house, mental agony, trouble to wife and children and misfortune of getting bad food. There will be loss of wealth at the commencement of the Dasha, some relief and gain of wealth in his own country and distress and anxieties during the last portion of the Dasha.
44. Now I am going to describe the effects of the Dasha of Jupiter, the great benefic and preceptor of the Gods.
45-48. If Jupiter is in his exaltation, his own Rāśi, his MulaTrikonaa, in 10th, 5th, or 9th House, in his own Navāmśa, or in his exalted Navāmśa, there will be during his Dasha: acquisition of kingdom, great felicity, recognition by Government, acquisition of conveyances and clothes, devotion to deities and Brahmins, happiness in respect of his wife and children and success in the performance of religious sacrifices (oblations. 
49-51. If Jupiter is in his debilitation Rāśi, combust, associated with malefics, or in 6th, or 8th, there will be during his Dasha loss of residential premises, anxiety, distress to children, loss of cattle and pilgrimage. The Dasha will give some unfavorable effects at its commencement only. During the later part of the Dasha there will be good effects, like gain of wealth, awards from and recognition by Government.
52. Now I will describe to you the effects of the Dasha of Saturn, who is considered the vilest and most inferior amongst all the Planets.
53-56. If Saturn is in his exaltation, in his own Rāśi, or in MulaTrikonaa, or friendly Rāśi, in his own, or exalted Navāmśa and in 3rd, or 11th, there will be during his Dasha recognition by Government, opulence and glory, name and fame, success in the educational sphere, acquisition of conveyances and ornaments etc., gain of wealth, favours from Government, attainment of a high position, like Commander of an Army, acquisition of a kingdom, benevolence of goddess Lakshmi, gain of property and birth of children.
57-60. If Saturn is in 6th, 8th, or 12th, in his debilitation Rāśi, or combust, there will be during his Dasha ill effects from poison, injury from weapons, separation from father, distress to wife and children, disaster, as a result of displeasure of Government, imprisonment etc. If Saturn receives a Aspect from, or is associated with a benefic, is placed in a Kendra, or in a Trikona, in Sagittarius, or in Pisces, there will be acquisition of a kingdom, conveyances and clothes.
61. Now I am going to describe the effects of the Dasha of Mercury, who is called a Kumar (in his teens) amongst all the Planets.
62-65. If Mercury is in his exaltation, in his own, in a friendly Rāśi, or in 11th, 5th, or 9th, there will be during his Dasha acquisition of wealth, gain of reputation, improvement in knowledge, benevolence of Government, auspicious functions, happiness from wife and children, good health, availability of sweetish preparations, profits in business etc. If Mercury receives a Aspect from a benefic, is in 9th, or is the Lord of 10th, the aforesaid beneficial results will be experienced in full and there will be great felicity all-round.
66-70. If Mercury is associated with a malefic, there will be during his Dasha punishment by Government, inimical relations with kinsmen, journey to a foreign country, dependence on others and the possibility of urinary troubles. If Mercury is in 6th, 8th, or 12th, there will be loss of wealth, due to indulgence in lascivious activities, possibility of suffering from rheumatism and jaundice, danger of thefts and malevolence of Government, loss of land and cattle etc. At the commencement of the Dasha of Mercury, there will be gains of wealth, betterment in the educational sphere, birth of children and happiness. In the middle of the Dasha, there will be recognition from Government. The last part of the Dasha will be distressful.
71. Now I will tell you about the Dasha of Ketu, who is a headless trunk (Kabandha) amongst all the Planets.
72-77. If Ketu is in a Kendra, a Trikona, or in 11th, in a benefic Rāśi, in his exaltation, or in his own Rāśi, there will be during his Dasha cordial relations with the king, desired headship of a country, or village, comforts of conveyances, happiness from children, gain from foreign countries, happiness from wife and acquisition of cattle. If Ketu is in 3rd, 6th, or 11th, there will be in his Dasha acquisition of a kingdom, good relations with friends and opportunities for the acquisition of elephants. At the commencement of the Ketu Dasha there will be Raja Yoga. During the middle portion of the Dasha there will be possibilities of fearfulness and in the last part there will be sufferings from ailments and journeys to distant places. If Ketu is in 2nd, 8th, or 12th, or receives a Aspect from a malefic, there will be imprisonment, destruction of kinsmen and residential premises and anxieties, company of menials and diseases.
78. Now I will describe the effects of the Dasha of Venus, who is the incarnate of intoxication, ecstasy, delight and pride amongst all the Planets.
79-82. If Venus is in his exaltation, in his own Rāśi, or in a Kendra, or a Trikona, there will be during his Dasha acquisition of fancy clothes, ornaments, conveyances, cattle and land etc., availability of sweet preparations every day, recognition from the sovereign, luxurious functions of songs and dances etc. by the benevolence of Goddess Lakshmi. If Venus is in his MulaTrikonaa, during his Dasha there will definitely be acquisition of a kingdom, acquisition of a house, birth of children and grandchildren, celebration of marriage in the family, attainment of a high position, like the Commander of an Army, visits of friends, recovery of lost wealth, property, or kingdom.
83-84. If Venus is in 6th, 8th, or 12th, there will be during his Dasha inimical relations with kinsmen, distress to wife, losses in business, destruction of cattle and separation from relations.
85-87. If Venus is in 4th, as Lord of 9th, or 10th, there will be during his Dasha attainment of rulership of a country, or village, performance of pious deeds, like building of reservoirs and temples and giving grains etc. in ch6thty, availability of sweet preparations every day, vigor in work, name and fame and happiness from wife and children.
88-89. Similar are the effects of Venus in his sub-periods. If Venus is Lord of 2nd, or 7th, there will be during his Dasha physical pains and troubles. To get alleviation from those troubles the native should perform Shatarudriya, or Mrityunjaya Japa in the prescribed manner and give in ch6thty a cow, or female buffalo. 
Ch. 48. Distinctive Effects of the Nakshatra Dasha, or of the Dashas of the Lords (Vimshottari) of various Houses 
1. If the Lord of 10th is placed in an auspicious House in his exaltation Rāśi etc., his Dasha effects will be favourable. The effects will be adverse, if the Lord of 10th is in his debilitation Rāśi and occupies an inauspicious House. This proves, that an inauspicious Planet in his exaltation Rāśi etc. will not produce unfavorable results, if placed in an auspicious House and a benefic, being in his debilitation Rāśi and being placed in an inauspicious House, will produce adverse effects. Now I will describe the effects of the Dasha of the Lords of various Houses, who are related to each other.2-4. There will be physical well-being in the Dasha of the Lord of Lagna, distress and possibility of death in the Dasha of the Lord of 2nd, unfavorable effects in the Dasha of the Lord of 3rd, acquisition of house and land in the Dasha of the Lord of 4th, progress in educational sphere and happiness from the children in the Dasha of the Lord of 5th and danger from enemies and ill health in the Dasha of the Lord of 6th.
5-8. There will be distress to wife and the possibility of the death of the native in the Dasha of the Lord of 7th, the possibility of death and financial losses in the Dasha of the Lord of 8th, improvement in the educational sphere, religious-mindedness and unexpected gains of wealth in the Dasha of the Lord of 9th, recognition from and awards by the Government in the Dasha of the Lord of 10th, obstacles in gains of wealth and the possibility of diseases in the Dasha of the Lord of 11th and distress and danger from diseases in the Dasha of the Lord of 12th. A Planet, placed in an auspicious House, like Trikona etc., at the commencement of the Dasha, produces favourable results in his Dasha. The Planet, placed in 6th, 8th, or 12th at that time, yields only adverse results during his Dasha. It is therefore essential, that the placement of a Planet at the time of birth and at the commencement of the Dasha should both be taken into account for the assessment of the Dasha effects.
14-17. The Dasha of 6ths, 8ths, or 12ths Lord also becomes favourable, if they get associated with the Lord of a Trikona. If the Lord of a Kendra is in a Trikona, or the Lord of a Trikona is in a Kendra, the Dasha of the Planet, conjunct with either of them, becomes favourable. The Dasha of a Planet, receiving a Aspect from the Lord of a Kendra, or Trikona is also favourable. If 9ths Lord is in Lagna and Lagnas Lord is in 9th, the Dashas of both of them will produce extremely beneficial results. There will be acquisition of a kingdom in the Dashas of Lagnas Lord and 10ths Lord, if 10ths Lord is in Lagna and Lagnas Lord is in 10th.
18-20. The Dasha of 3rds, 6ths and 11ths Lord, of the Planets, placed in 3rd, 6th and 11th and of the Planets, conjunct with the above, will prove unfavorable. The Dasha of the Planets, associated with the Lords of Marak Houses, namely 2nd and 7th, in 2nd, or 7th and the Dashas of the Planets, placed in 8th, will produce unfavorable effects. Thus the Dashas should be considered favourable, after taking into account the placement of a Planet and his relationship of one Planet with the other. (Rahu and Ketu give favourable results in 3rd, 6th and 11th). 
Ch. 49. Effects of the Kala Chakra
1-5. Mahārśi Parashara said. O Brahmin! I am now going to describe to you the effects of the Kala Chakra Dasha.During the Dasha of the Rāśi, owned, or occupied by Sun, there will be ill health, due to the blood, or bile troubles; … Moon, there will be gain of wealth and clothes, name and fame and birth of children; … Mars, there will be bilious fever, gout and wounds; … Mercury, there will be acquisition of wealth and birth of children; … Jupiter, there will be increase in the number of children, acquisition of wealth and enjoyment; … Venus, there will be acquisition of learning, marriage and gain of wealth; … occupied by Saturn, there will be all kinds of adverse happenings.The Effects of the Dashas on the Basis of the Navāmśa of each Rāśi 
6-7. In the Kala Chakra Dasha of Aries in Aries Navāmśa there will be distress, due to troubles, caused by the pollution of blood. In the Dasha of Aries in the Navāmśa of Taurus there will be increase in wealth and agricultural product. In the Navāmśa of Gemini there will be advancement of knowledge. In the Navāmśa of Cancer there will be acquisition of wealth, in the Leo Navāmśa danger from enemies, in the Virgo distress to wife, in the Libra kingship, in the Scorpio death and in the Sagittarius acquisition of wealth. Such will be the effects of the 9 Padas of Aries. In assessing the net effects the nature of the Planet, occupying the Rāśi, should also be taken into account. 
8-10. In the Dasha of Capricorn Navāmśa in Taurus there will be tendency to perform undesirable deeds along with more adverse effects. In the Aquarius Navāmśa there will be profits in business, in the Pisces success in all ventures, in the Dasha of Scorpio Navāmśa danger from fire, in the Dasha of Libra Navāmśa recognition from Government and reverence from all, in the Dasha of Virgo Navāmśa danger from enemies, in the Dasha of Cancer Navāmśa distress to wife, in the Dasha of Leo Navāmśa diseases of eyes and in the Dasha of Gemini Navāmśa obstacles in earning livelihood. Such will be the effects of the 9 Navāmśaas of Taurus. Similar interpretation should be made of further verses on this subject. 
11-12. In Gemini in the Dasha of the Taurus Ańśa there will be acquisition of wealth, in the Dasha of Aries Ańśa attacks of fever, in the Dasha of Pisces Ańśa affectionate relations with maternal uncle, in the Dasha of Aquarius Ańśa increase in the number of enemies, in the Dasha of Capricorn Ańśa danger from thieves, in the Dasha of Sagittarius Ańśa increase in the stock of weapons, in the Dasha of Taurus Ańśa injury by some weapon and in the Dasha of Gemini Ańśa enjoyment. 
13-15. In Cancer in the Dasha of Cancer Ańśa there will be distress, … Leo displeasure of the sovereign, … Virgo reverence from kinsmen, … Libra beneficence, … Scorpio creation of obstacles by father, … Sagittarius increase of learning and wealth, … Capricorn danger from water, … Aquarius increase in the production of agricultural products and in the Dasha of the Pisces Ańśa acquisition of more wealth and enjoyment. 
16-17. In Leo in the Dasha of the Navāmśa of Scorpio there will be distress and disputes, … Libra extraordinary gains, … Virgo gains of wealth, … Cancer danger from wild animals, … Leo birth of a son, … Gemini increase of enemies, … Taurus gains from sale of cattle, … Aries danger from animals and in the Dasha of Pisces Ańśa journeys to distant places. 
18-19. In Virgo in the Dasha of Aquarius Ańśa there will be acquisition of wealth, … Capricorn financial gains, … Sagittarius mingling with kinsmen, … Aries happiness from mother, … Taurus birth of children, … Gemini increase in enemies, … Cancer love with some woman, … Leo aggravation of diseases and in the Dasha of Virgo Ańśa birth of children. 
20-22. In Libra in the Dasha of Libra Ańśa there will be financial gains, … Scorpio good relations with kinsmen, … Sagittarius happiness from father, … Capricorn disputes with mother, … Aquarius birth of a son and financial gains, … Pisces entanglement with enemies, … Scorpio disputes with women, … Libra danger from water and in Dasha of Virgo Ańśa more financial gains. 
23-24. In Scorpio in the Dasha of Cancer Ańśa there will be financial gains, … Leo opposition to the king, … Gemini acquisition of land, … Taurus financial gains, … Aries danger from reptiles, … Pisces danger from water, … Aquarius profits in business, … Capricorn profits in business, … Capricorn possibility of suffering from diseases and in the Dasha of Sagittarius Ańśa financial gains. 
25-27. In Sagittarius in the Dasha of Aries Ańśa there will be financial gains, … Taurus acquisition of more land, … Gemini success in ventures, … Cancer success all round, … Leo increase in the accumulated wealth, … Virgo disputes, … Libra financial gains, … Scorpio affliction with diseases, … Sagittarius happiness from children. 
28-29. In Capricorn in the Dasha of Capricorn Ańśa there will be happiness from children, … Aquarius gain of agricultural products, … Pisces well being, … Scorpio danger from poison, … Libra financial gains, … Virgo increase in enemies, … Cancer acquisition of property, … Leo danger from wild animals and in the Dasha of Gemini Ańśa danger of falling from a tree. 
30-32. In Aquarius in the Dasha of Taurus Ańśa there will be financial gains, … Aries diseases of the eyes, … Pisces journeys to distant places, … Aquarius increase in wealth, … Capricorn success in all kinds of ventures, … Sagittarius more enemies, … Aries loss of happiness and enjoyment, … Taurus death, … Gemini well being. 
33-34. In the Pisces in the Dasha of Cancer Ańśa there will be increase in wealth, … Leo recognition by Government, … Virgo financial gains, … Libra gains from all sources, … Scorpio fever, … Sagittarius more enemies, … Capricorn conjugal disputes, … Aquarius danger from water and in the Dasha of Pisces Ańśa good fortune all-round. In this manner on the Kala Chakra, prepared on the basis of Pad of the Janmaa Nakshatra, the Dashas of the Navāmśa Rāśis and their duration can be assessed and prediction can be made for the whole life of the native. Appropriate remedial measures (recitation of Mantras, oblations etc.) should be taken to alleviate the adverse effects, caused by malefic Dashas. 
35-37. The effects of Dasha in Raja Yoga etc. have already been described in Vol. I of this book. The same should be applied in a judicious manner in the Kala Chakra. These are in brief effects of Kala Chakra Dasha. 
Ch. 50. Effects of the Char etc. Dashas  
1-3. Mahārśi Parashara said. O Brahmin! I have already described the Char etc. Dashas. Now I am going to tell you the effects of these Dashas. The effects of the Dashas of the Rāśis should be judged from the strength of the Lords of Rāśis and whether they are benefics, or malefics. If the Lord of a Rāśi possesses full strength, the effects of the Dasha of the Rāśi will be realized in full. The effects of the Dasha will be of medium nature, if the strength is medium. If the Lord of Rāśi possesses little strength, the effects will be experienced accordingly. 
4-10. If there are malefics in the 8th, the 5th and the 9th from a Dasha Rāśi, the effects of the Dasha of that Rāśi will be distressful. If there are malefics in the 3rd and the 6th from a Dasha Rāśi, the effects of the Dasha will be victory over enemies and happiness. If there are benefics in the 3rd and the 6th from the Dasha Rāśi, there will be defeat in its Dasha. If there are benefics, or malefics in the 11th from the Dasha Rāśi, there will be conquests and happiness in the Dasha. If the Dasha Rāśi is occupied by, or is owned by a benefic, the effects of its Dasha will be beneficial. If a Dasha Rāśi, owned by a benefic, is occupied by a malefic, favourable effects will be experienced in the first part of the Dasha and they will be adverse in the latter part. If a Dasha Rāśi, owned by a malefic is occupied by a benefic, the effects of the Dasha will be the same. A Dasha Rāśi, owned and occupied by a malefic will always yield unfavorable results. The reverse will be the case in the case of the Dasha Rāśi, owned and occupied by a benefic. If a Dasha Rāśi, owned by a benefic, is occupied by both benefic and malefic Planets, the effects of Dasha will be adverse in its first part and favourable in the latter part. 
11-17. The assessment of the effects of the Dasha of the Dasha Rāśi should be made after taking into account the disposition of the Planets in the Rāśi at birth and the disposition of Planets during the Dasha. If the Dasha Rāśi is well disposed both at the time of birth and during its Dasha, the beneficial results will be realized in full. If it is ill-disposed during the Dasha, the effects will be of mixed nature. If the Dasha Rāśi is ill-disposed both at the time of birth and during its Dasha, only evil effects will be experienced. 
18-19. The effects of the Dasha will be favourable, if it is occupied by a benefic and there is also a benefic in the Rāśi previous to it. If the Rāśi is occupied by a malefic, the effects will be of adverse nature. If there are benefics in 5th and 9th, the effects of its Dasha will be favourable. The reverse will be the case, if 5th and 9th are occupied by malefics. 
20-21. Aquarius, Taurus, Leo and Scorpio are Badhaka Houses for the four Movable Rāśis: Aries, Cancer, Libra and Capricorn. In other words the 11th Rāśi to a Movable Rāśi is its Badhaka House. If there is a malefic in the House, occupied by its Lord, or in Badhaka House of that Rāśi, there will be occasions of great sorrow, imprisonment and diseases during the Dasha. 
22. The Dasha of a Rāśi will be favourable, if it is occupied by its own Lord, or an exalted Planet. The Dasha of a Rāśi, not occupied by any Planet, will be adverse. 
23-25. There will be great danger, imprisonment during a journey, displeasure of Government and danger from enemies in the Dasha and Antar Dasha of the Rāśi, from which its Badhaka House, 12th, 6th and 8th are occupied by Rahu. There will be loss, due to the displeasure of the king and danger there from in the Antar Dasha of the Rāśi, that is occupied by Sun, Mars, Rahu and Saturn. There will be the possibility of death, if the 5th and the 9th from the Antar Dasha Rāśi are occupied by a debilitated, or malefic Planet. 
26-28. There will be enjoyment, acquisition of chiefship of a town, or village, birth of a son, financial gains, well-being, dawn of fortune, attainment of the position of a Commander of an Army and progress all-round, if there is an exalted Planet in the Trikona from the Antar Dasha Rāśi. There will be in his Dasha financial gains, well-being and birth of a son, if the Planet, who is the Lord of the Dasha, happens to be in a benefic Rāśi and receives a Aspect from Jupiter. 
29-32. Taurus, Libra, Capricorn, Aquarius and Gemini are the inimical Rāśis of Sun. The inimical Rāśis of Moon and other Planets may be reckoned similarly. If a Planet is in an inimical Rāśi, his Dasha will be full of adversities. The effects of the Dasha of Rāśis and Planets should be judged after taking into account the above rules. 
33-34. The Dashas of that Planet will be favourable, who is Raja Yoga Karak, who is disposed between two benefics (that is there are benefics in the 2nd and the 12th Houses to that Planet) and who has benefics in the 2nd, 3rd and 4th Houses from him. A malefic Planet becomes favourable, if he is disposed between benefics. 
35-36. The whole of the Dasha of a Planet, who is related to a friendly and benefic Planet at the commencement and the end of the Dasha, will be favourable. In an unfavorable Dasha the Antar Dasha of a benefic (Planet, or Rāśi) becomes favourable. The Dasha of a Planet, or Rāśi, who has benefics in the 5th, or the 9th from it, is also favourable. In this manner the effects of the Dasha should be judged, after taking into account the dispositions of the Planet, or Rāśi at the commencement and at the end of the Dasha. 
37-39. The Dasha of the Planets and Rāśis, who have benefics in the Trikona from them is favourable. If the Dasha of a benefic Rāśi commences in a benefic Rāśi, it will be very favourable. If an evil Dasha commences in a benefic Rāśi, it is also favourable. Therefore the commencement of a Dasha should always be kept in view in assessing the results of the Dasha. There will be loss of fortune, if at the commencement of the Dasha there is a malefic Rāśi, or, if the Lord of the Dasha Rāśi is in debilitation. 
40-41. There will be loss of fortune, wealth and agricultural products and infliction with disease during the Dasha of the Rāśi, occupied by a debilitated Planet, or, if there is a debilitated Planet in the 5th from it, or in the 9th from it, or whose Lord is debilitated, or related to a debilitated Planet. 
42. Four Rāśis from Aquarius and four Rāśis from Scorpio belong to Rahu and Ketu, respectively. If Rahu and Ketu are in any one of the aforesaid Rāśis, the Dasha will be productive of beneficial results. 
43-45. If a Planet, whose Dasha is otherwise considered favourable, is placed in a Marak House, or, if the Rāśi, in which his Dasha comes to an end, receives a Aspect from Venus, or Moon, there will be in his Dasha displeasure of government and loss of wealth. 
46-47. There will be loss of everything, imprisonment, death, exile from the country and great distress at the end of the Dasha of Rahu. The above effects will definitely be realized, if there are malefics in the 5th and the 9th from Rahu. Beneficial and adverse effects should be predicted in this manner. 
48-50. The same would be the effects in the Dasha of the Rāśi, occupied by malefics, like Rahu etc. The association of a Marak Planet with the Rāśi at the time of commencement of its Dasha is not productive of good effects. If such a Planet is Rahu, there will be imprisonment, or loss of wealth. 
51-52. The natural characteristics of the House, occupied by Rahu, are harmed at the commencement of the Dasha. If such a House is 2nd, there will be loss of wealth. If Moon and Venus are in 12th, there will be losses, due to the displeasure of government. If Mars and Ketu are so disposed, there will be death, or danger from fire. There will be acquisition of a kingdom, if Venus and Moon are in 2nd at the commencement of the Dasha. This means, that the effects of the House, in which Moon and Venus are placed at the commencement and end of a Dasha, are strengthened. Thus their disposition in 6th, 8th and 12th will produce only adverse effects. 
53-55. Similarly the sages have described the effects of the House with Argal. If there is an auspicious Argal causing benefic, or malefic Planet of a Rāśi and Lagna receives a Aspect from him, that Rāśi will prevail. Here Lagna is the secondary condition. If the Planet, causing uninterrupted Argal, gives a Aspect to a Rāśi, that Rāśi will prevail. In other words good effects will be derived in the Dasha of that Rāśi. The Dasha of the Rāśi, which does not receive a Aspect from an auspicious Argal, or the Dasha of a Rāśi with Vipreet Argal will not be favourable. The Dasha of that Rāśi, which receives a Aspect from a benefic, will be favourable. 
56-59. Financial gains will be derived in the Dasha of the Rāśi, which is occupied by its benefic Lord, or by an exalted Planet, who receives a Aspect from him. There will be loss of wealth, if such a Planet is in the 12th House to the Rāśi (or House). There will be destruction of all good effects, distress to children and father and mental agony in the Dasha of the Rāśi, if there are malefics in the 5th and the 9th from the Rāśi. Evil effects will be experienced in the Dasha of the Rāśi, which is occupied by 8ths Lord, 12ths Lord, Sun, Mars, or Saturn. 
60-63. The Dasha of the Rāśi will cause distress to children, exile to a foreign country and continuous disturbances in life, if Rahu and Ketu are in the Trikona to the Rāśi. There will be danger from enemies, from the king and disease in the Dasha of the Rāśi, which is so posited, that the 6th and the 8th from it are occupied by malefic, debilitated, or combust Planets. There will be destruction of house, land and agricultural fields, if there is a malefic, or debilitated Planet in the 4th from the Rāśi. There will be loss of house, due to negligence, if such a Planet is Mars. There will be heart pain and danger from government, if the Planet is Saturn and there will be losses all round and danger from poison and thieves, if the Planet is Rahu. 
64-66. There will be pilgrimage to holy places in the Dasha of the Rāśi, who has Rahu in the 10th to it. There will be gain of earnings, religious rites, gain of wealth, renown for good deeds and success in efforts and ventures in the Dasha of the Rāśi, which is so posited, that the 10th, the 11th and the 9th from it are occupied by benefics. There will be birth of children, happiness from wife and recognition by the Government in the Dasha of the Rāśi, from which the 5th, the 7th and the 9th are occupied by benefic, or exalted Planets. During the Dasha of the Houses (Rāśis), occupied by 5ths, 11ths, 10ths, 4ths, 9ths and Lagnas Lord, there will be growth of these Houses. The good effects will be in proportion to the strength of the Houses and the Planets, occupying them. 
67-70. In the Dasha of a Rāśi (House) there will be well-being, increase in opulence and glory and devotion to deities and Brahmins, if it is occupied by Jupiter, Venus, or the Lord of a Trikona. There will be acquisition of more conveyances and cattle etc. in the Dasha of the Rāśi (House), which is so posited, that the 4th from it is occupied by an exalted Planet, or Lord of a Trikona. Moon there will give things, like grains, Ghī etc. Full Moon will favour with a treasure and jewels etc. Venus there, will provide enjoyment from music etc. 
71-72. There will be enjoyment of the palanquin-like conveyance in the Dasha of the Rāśi (House), from which the 4th is occupied by Jupiter. There will be success in all ventures, great opulence and glory, acquisition of a kingdom during the Dasha of a Rāśi (House), which has the Yoga of the Lord of Lagna, 9ths Lord, 10ths Lord, an exalted Planet, or benefics. The effects of the Dashas of various Houses should be judged in this manner. 
73-77. The effects of the Dashas of each Rāśi, or Planet (Nakshatra Dasha) depend on their 18 different kinds of conditions. They are deep exaltation, exaltation, dispositions on their either side, MulaTrikonaa, own, Adhimitr, Tatkalik Mitras, neutral, enemy, Adhisatrus Rāśi, deep debilitation, debilitated, or enemy Varga, own Varga, disposition in a Kendra, disposition in a Trikona, defeated in war between Planets, deep combustion. 
78-83. Acquisition of kingdom, enjoyment and acquisition of more property are the effects of the whole Dasha of the Planet, who is in deep exaltation and is fully equipped with all the six kinds of strength, great opulence and glory with some possibility of affliction with disease are the effects of the Planet, placed in his Rāśi of exaltation. The Dasha of a Planet in deep debilitation is called Rikt. Diseases, loss of wealth and danger of death are the effects of the Dasha of such a Planet. The Dasha of the Planet, who is in a condition in between deep exaltation and deep debilitation is known, as Avrohini (descending). The Dasha of the Planet in exaltation, or in a friends Rāśi is called Madhya (of middle order). This Dasha also yields moderately good effects. The Dasha of a Planet, placed in a condition in between deep debilitation and deep exaltation, is called Rohini (ascending). The Dasha of a Planet, placed in between the debilitated and enemy Navāmśa is called Adham (evil). Dangers of various kinds, distress and sorrows are the results of the Dasha of such a Planet. These Dashas give results, according to their nomenclature. 
84-87. The Dashas of other Planets become auspicious and augment the fortune, if the Lord of 9th and Jupiter are in any way related with Yoga, Kendra, or the House concerned etc. The Planet with Yoga of good fortune at birth produces good effects, when he is free from retrogression and becomes direct. The weakness, inabilities and Yogas of other Planets should also be taken into account in judging their effects. All those Dashas give full, medium and little effects in accordance with the disposition of the Planets in the Kendra, Panaphara and Apoklima. 
88-89. The Planets in Shirshodaya, Ubhayodaya and Prishthodaya Rāśis, yield their results, respectively, at the commencement, in the middle and at the end of the Dasha. All the Planets yield auspicious results in the Antar Dasha of Naisargik (natural, constant) and Tatkalik (according to position) friends. The results will be adverse in the Antar Dasha of inimical Planets.
Antar Dashas of Rāśis 
90-96. There are Antar Dashas of the 12 Rāśis, commencing from the Rāśi, in which the Lord of the Dasha is placed. There will be auspicious results, like acquisition of kingdom in the Antar Dasha of a Rāśi, which is occupied by its own Lord, or a friendly Planet. There will be inauspicious results, like loss of wealth, disputes, danger from diseases etc. in the Antar Dasha of the Rāśi, which may be 6th, 8th, or 12th, or is occupied by a malefic, debilitated Planet, or a Planet, placed in an inimical Rāśi. The Rāśi, which contained more auspicious marks in the Ashtak Varga will yield benefic effects in its Antar Dasha. Adverse will be the effects of the Antar Dasha of the Rāśi, which contains more inauspicious marks. For assessing the results the Rāśi, from which the Dasha commences, should be treated, as Lagna and the Houses thereafter should be assumed to have the characteristics, as if they are so from Lagna. Thus the 2nd House from that Rāśi will be the House of the wealth, the 3rd of co-borns and so on. There will be gains, or losses of Dhatus etc., assigned to the Rāśis and the Planets, in the Antar Dasha of the Rāśis concerned. In judging the effects of the Antar Dashas of the Planets their benefic and malefic nature, relations with the malefic, or benefic, Aspects on them and their disposition in 6th, 8th, or 12th etc. should all be kept in view. 
97. The results of the Antar Dashas Pratyantar Dashas of the Rāśis should be assessed in the manner, explained in this chapter. 
