
Brihat Parashara Hora Sashtra by Rishi Parashara
Page 2
Ch. 11. Judgment of Houses
1. O Mahārśi Parashara, I have come to know of the evils and antidotes thereof from you. Please tell me, what is to be deduced from each House.2. Indications of 1st House. Mahārśi Parashara replies. Physique, appearance, intellect (or the organ of intelligence, i.e. brain), complexion of the body, vigor, weakness, happiness, grief and innate nature are all to be guessed through the ascending Rāśi.
3. Indications of 2nd House. Wealth, grains (food etc.), family, death, enemies, metals, precious stones etc. are to be understood through 2nd House.
4. Indications of 3rd House. From 3rd House know of the following: valor, servants (attending etc.), brothers, sisters etc., initiatory instructions (Upadesha), journey and parents death.
5. Indications of 4th House. Conveyances, relatives, mother, happiness, treasure, lands and buildings are to be consulted through 4th House.
6. Indications of 5th House. The learned should deduce from 5th House amulets, sacred spells, learning, knowledge, sons, royalty (or authority), fall of position etc.
7. Indications of 6th House. Maternal uncle, doubts about death, enemies, ulcers, step-mother etc. are to be estimated from 6th House.
8. Indications of 7th House. Wife, travel, trade, loss of sight, death etc. be known from 7th House.
9. Indications of 8th House. 8th House indicates longevity, battle, enemies, forts, wealth of the dead and things, that have happened and are to happen (in the past and future births).
10. Indications of 9th House. Fortunes, wife's brother, religion, brothers wife, visits to shrines etc. be known from 9th House.
11. Indications of 10th House. Royalty (authority), place, profession (livelihood), honour, father, living in foreign lands and debts are to be understood from 10th House.
12. Indications of 11th House. All articles, sons wife, income, prosperity, quadrupeds etc. are to be understood from 11th House.
13. Indications of 12th House. From 12th House, one can know about expenses, history of enemies, ones own death etc.
14-16. Prosperity, or Annihilation of a House. Predict prosperity of the House, which is conjunct with, or aspected by a benefic. Also, when its Lord is in Yuvavastha, or Prabuddhavastha, or in Kismaravastha, or in 10th House, the Houses well-being is indicated. The House, which is not aspected by its Lord, or, whose Lord is with a malefic Planet, or with one of the Lords of evil and such other Houses (i.e. 3rd, 6th, 8th, 11th and 12th), or is defeated in a war between Planets, or is in one of the three Avasthas, viz, Vriddhavastha, Mritavastha and Suptavastha. 
Ch. 12. Effects of 1st House  
1-2. Physical comforts. Should Lagna Lord be conjunct with a malefic, or be in 8th, 6th, or 12th, physical felicity will diminish. If he is in an angle, or trine there will be at all times comforts of the body. If Lagna Lord is in debilitation, combustion, or enemy Rāśi, there will be diseases. With a benefic in an angle, or trine all diseases will disappear. Lagnas angles (i.e. 4th, 7th, or the 10th), or its trine (5th, 9th), containing a benefic, is a powerful remedy for all, related to health.3. There will not be bodily health, if Lagna, or Moon be aspected by, or conjunct with a malefic, being devoid of a benefics Aspect.
4. Bodily Beauty. A benefic in Lagna will give a pleasing appearance, while a malefic will make one bereft of good appearance. Felicity of the body will be enjoyed, if Lagna is aspected by, or conjunct with a benefic.
5-7. Other Benefits. If Lagna Lord, Mercury, Jupiter, or Venus be in an angle, or in a trine, the native will be long lived, wealthy, intelligent and liked by the king. Fame, wealth, abundant pleasures and comforts of the body will be acquired, if Lagna Lord is in a Movable Rāśi and be aspected by a benefic Planet. One will be endowed with royal marks (of fortune), if Mercury, Jupiter, or Venus be in Lagna along with the Moon, or be in angle from Lagna. If Mercury, Jupiter, or Venus be in 4th, 7th, or 10th from Lagna, or be in the company of Moon in Lagna, the native will enjoy royal fortunes.
8. Coiled Birth. If there be a birth in one of Aries, Taurus and Leo Lagnas, containing either Saturn, or Mars, the birth of the child is with a coil around a limb. The corresponding limb will be in accordance with the Rāśi, or Navāmśa, rising.
9. Birth of Twins. The native, who has Sun in a quadruped Rāśi, while others are in Dual Rāśis with strength, is born, as one of the twins.
10. To Be Nurtured by Three Mothers. If Sun and Moon join in one and the same House and fall in one Navāmśa, the native will be nurtured by three different mothers for the first three months from its birth and will later on be brought up by its father and brother.
11. Important. The learned in Jyotishya should base the effects on Moon also, as are applicable to Lagna. Now explained are clues to know of ulcers, identity marks etc. on ones person.
12-14. Decanates and Bodily Limbs. Head, eyes, ears, nose, temple, chin and face is the order of limbs, denoted (by the v6thous Houses), when the first decanate of a Rāśi ascends. In the case of the second decanate ascending the order is neck, shoulder, arm, side, heart, stomach and navel. The order for the third decanate ascending is pelvis, anus/penis, testicles, thigh, knee, calf and foot. The portion already risen indicates left side of the body (while the one yet to rise, i.e. the invisible half, denotes the right side of the body).
15. Limbs Affected. The limb, related to a malefic by occupation, will have ulcers, or scars, while the one, related to a benefic, will have a mark (like moles etc).
Also see Sloka 6, Ch. 4 of Saravali, which states, that a malefic, or a benefic, if be in own Rāśi, or Navāmśa, the effects will be right from birth. In other cases it will be in the course of ones life, that these effects will come to pass)
Ch. 13. Effects of 2nd House  
1-2. Combinations for Wealth. O excellent of the Brahmins, listen to me, speaking on the effects of 2nd House. If the Lord of 2nd is in 2nd, or is in an angle, or in trine, he will promote ones wealth (or monetary state). Should he be in 6th/8th/12th, financial conditions will decline. A benefic in 2nd will give wealth, while a malefic instead will destroy wealth.
3. One will be wealthy, if Jupiter is in 2nd, as the Lord of 2nd, or is with Mars.
4. If 2nd Lord is in 11th, while the Lord of 11th in 2nd, wealth will be acquired by the native. Alternately these two Lords may join in an angle, or in a trine.
5. If the Lord of 2nd is in an angle, while 11th Lord is in a trine thereof, or is aspected by, or conjunct with Jupiter and Venus, the subject will be wealthy.
6-7. Yogas for Poverty. One will be penniless, if the Lord of 2nd House is in an evil House, while the Lord of 11th House is also so placed and 2nd House is occupied by a malefic. There will be penury right from birth and the native will have to beg even for his food, if the Lords of 2nd and 11th House are both combust, or with malefics.
8. Loss of Wealth through the King. Should the Lords of 2nd and 11th House be relegated to 6th, 8th, or 12th House, while Mars is in 11th House and Rahu is in 2nd House, the native will lose his wealth on account of royal punishments.
9. Expenses on Good Accounts. When Jupiter is in 11th, Venus is in 2nd and a benefic is placed in 12th House, while 2nds Lord is conjunct with a benefic, there will be expenses on religious, or ch6thtable grounds.
10. Fame etc. If 2nds Lord is in own Rāśi, or is exalted, the native will look after his people, will help others and also will become famous.11. Effortless Aquisition. If 2nds Lord is conjunct with a benefic and is in a good division, like Paravatāńś, there will be effortlessly all kinds of wealth in the natives family. (Paravatāńśdau of the text denotes Paravat, or such other higher Vargaas: 2nds Lord should be in Paravatāńś, or in Devalokāńśa, Brahmalokāńśa, Sakravahanāńś, or Sridhamāńś in the Dash Varga scheme)
12. Eyes. If 2nd Lord is endowed with strength, the native will possess beautiful eyes. Should the said Planet be in 6th, 8th, or 12th House, there will be disease, or deformity of eyes.
13. Untruthful Person. If 2nd House and its Lord are conjunct with malefics, the native will be a talebearer, will speak untruth and will be afflicted by windy diseases.
Ch. 14. Effects of 3rd House  
1. O Brahmin, I now tell you about 3rd House. Should 3rd House be conjunct with, or aspected by a benefic, the native will be endowed with co-born and be courageous.
2. If 3rds Lord along with Mars aspects 3rd House, the native will enjoy good results, due to 3rd House. Alternatively these two Planets may be in 3rd itself.
3. Destruction at once of co-born will come to pass, if the said 2 Planets are together with a malefic, or in a Rāśi, owned by a malefic.4-4. Female and Male Co-born. If 3rds Lord is a female Planet, or, if 3rd House be occupied by female Planets, one will have sisters, born after him. Similarly male Planets and male Rāśis denote younger brothers. Should it be of mixed nature, co-born of both sexes will be obtained. These effects be declared after assessing the strength and weakness of the concerned.
5-6. Should 3rds Lord and Mars be together in 8th House, destruction of co-born will result. Happiness in this respect will come to pass, if Mars, or 3rds Lord is in an angle, or in a trine, or in exaltation, or friendly divisions.
7-11. Number of Brothers and Sisters. If Mercury is in 3rd House, while 3rds Lord and Moon are together, as the indicator (Mars) joins Saturn, the effects are: there occurred the birth of an elder sister and there will be younger brothers. Furthermore, the third brother will die. Should Mars be conjunct with Rahu, while 3rds Lord is in his debilitation Rāśi, there will be loss of younger brothers and/or sisters, while three elder brothers and/or sisters were attained by the native. If 3rds Lord is in an angle, while the significator (Mars) is exalted in a trine and be conjunct with Jupiter, 12 will be the number of total co-born. Out of these two elders and the 3rd, the 7th, the 9th and the 12th of the younger co-born will be shortlived, while six of the said twelve will be longlived.
12-13. There will be 1 co-born, if 12ths Lord (some texts read, as 11ths Lord) joins Mars and Jupiter, while 3rd House is occupied by Moon. If Moon is lonely placed in 3rd House with Aspect of male Planets, there will be younger brothers, while the Aspect of Venus denotes younger sisters.
14. Adverse Planets. Sun in 3rd House will destroy the preborn. The afterborn will be destroyed, if Saturn is found in 3rd House. In the same situation Mars will destroy both the preborn and later-born.
15. After estimating the strength and weakness of such Yogas, the effects, related to brothers and sisters, be announced.
Ch. 15. Effects of 4th House
1. O excellent of the Brahmins, thus have been briefly told the effects of 3rd House. Now listen to the results, related to 4th House.
2. Housing Comforts. One will have residential comforts in full degree, if 4th is occupied by its Lord, or by Lagnas Lord and be aspected by a benefic.
3. Miscellaneous. Should 5ths Lord be in his own House, or in own Navāmśa, or in exaltation, the native will be endowed with comforts, related to lands, conveyances, houses etc. and musical instruments.
4. Housing Comforts. If 10ths Lord joins 4ths Lord in an angle, or in a trine, the native will acquire beautiful mansions.
5. Relatives. Should Mercury be in Lagna, while 4ths Lord, being a benefic, is aspected by another benefic, the native will be honoured by his relatives.
6. Long-living Mother. If 4th House is occupied by a benefic, while its Lord is in his exaltation Rāśi, as the indicator of mother is endowed with strength, the native will have a long-living mother.
7. Happiness of Mother. The natives mother will be happy, if 4ths Lord is in an angle, while Venus is also in an angle, as Mercury is exalted.
8. Quadrupeds. Sun in 4th, Moon and Saturn in 9th and Mars in 11th House; this Yoga will confer cows and buffaloes on the native.
9. Dumbness. Should 4th House be a Movable one, while its Lord and Mars are together in 6th, or 8th House, the native will be dumb.
10-14. Conveyances. If Lagnas Lord is a benefic, while 4ths Lord is in fall, or in 11th House and the significator (Venus) is in 12th House, the native will obtain conveyances in his 12th year. Should Sun be in 4th House, as 4ths Lord is exalted and be with Venus, one will acquire conveyances in his 32nd year. It will be in the 42nd year, that one will be endowed with conveyances, if 4ths Lord joins 10ths Lord in his (4th Lords) exaltation Navāmśa. An exchange between 11ths and 4ths Lords will confer conveyances in the 12th year. A benefic, related to 4th House (and to its Lord), will bring with him auspicious effects (regarding conveyances), while a malefic will produce only malefic effects (in respect of conveyances). Should a benefic be in 4th, aspect 4th, or in conjunct with the Lord of 4th, or a Aspect on the Lord of 4th House, then the native will be happy with conveyances and be free from accidents and dangers. A malefic, replacing the said benefic, will cause losses, concerning vehicles and reduce one to severe accidents.
Ch. 16. Effects of 5th House
1-3. O Brahmin, now I tell you the effects, related to 5th House. If the Lords of Lagna and 5th are in their own Rāśis, or in an angle, or in a trine, one will enjoy thorough happiness through his children. Should 5ths Lord be in 6th, 8th, or 12th House, there will be no offspring. Should the Lord of 5th be combust, or be with malefics and be weak, there will be no children; even, if per chance issues are obtained, they will only quit the world soon. The Conjunct of 5ths Lord with Lagnas Lord in a good House will ensure early obtainment of children apart from happiness through them. If they join in an evil House, they will prove a defect in this respect.
4. If 5ths Lord is in 6th House, as Lagnas Lord is conjunct with Mars, the native will lose his very first child, whereafter his female will not be fertile to yield an offspring.
5. Should 5ths Lord be in fall in 6th, 8th, or 12th House, while Mercury and Ketu are in 5th House, the natives wife will give birth to one child only.
6. If 5ths Lord is in fall and be not in Aspect to 5th, while Saturn and Mercury are in 5th, the natives wife will give birth to one child only.
7. Should 9ths Lord be in Lagna, while 5ths Lord is in fall and Ketu is in 5th along with Mercury, obtainment of progeny will be after a great deal of ordeal.
8. If 5ths Lord is in 6th, 8th, or 12th House, or be in an inimical Rāśi, or be in fall, or in 5th itself, the native will beget issues with difficulty.
9. Should 5th House be owned by Saturn, or Mercury and be occupied, or aspected by Saturn and Mandi, one will have adopted issues.
10. Should Sun and Moon be together in a Rāśi and in the same Navāmśa, the native will be brought up by three mothers, or two fathers.
11. Adopted issue is indicated, if 5th is tenanted by six Planets, while its Lord is in 12th House and Moon and Lagna are endowed with strength.
12. There will be many children, if 5ths Lord is strong, while 5th is aspected by strong Mercury, Jupiter and Venus.
13. If 5ths Lord is with Moon, or is in her Decanate, the native will beget daughters.
14. If 5ths Lord is in a Movable Rāśi, while Saturn is in 5th, as Rahu is with Moon, the child (so born) is of questionable birth.
15. Undoubtedly the native is born of others loins, if Moon is in the 8th from Lagna, while Jupiter is in the 8th from Moon. Malefics Aspect, or Conjunct is essential in this Yoga.
16. If 5ths Lord is exalted, or be in 2nd, 5th, or 9th House, or be conjunct with, or aspected by Jupiter, obtainment of children will be there.
17. One will obtain children, that will indulge in mean deeds, if 5th is occupied by three, or four malefics, while 5ths Lord is in fall. A benefic (including Mercury) in 5th is excluded in the said combination.
18. If 5th is occupied by Jupiter, while its Lord is with Venus, one will obtain an offspring in his 32nd, or 33rd year.
19. Should 5ths Lord be in an angle along with Jupiter, the Karak, one will beget a child at the age of 30, or 36.
20. If Jupiter is in 9th House, while Venus is in the 9th from Jupiter along with Lagnas Lord, one will beget a child at the age of 40.
21. The native will at the age of 32 lose his child, if Rahu is in 5th, 5ths Lord is in Conjunct with a malefic and Jupiter is in debilitation.
22. There will be loss of children at 33 and 36, if a malefic is in the 5th from Jupiter, while another is in the 5th from Lagna.
23. Should Mandi be in Lagna, while Lagnas Lord is in fall, grief on account of loss of child at the age of 56 will come to pass.
24-32. Number of Children. There will be 10 sons, if 4th House and 6th House are occupied by malefics, while 5ths Lord is in deep exaltation, joining Lagnas Lord, as Jupiter is with another benefic. Nine will be the number of sons, that one will beget, if Jupiter is in deep exaltation, as Rahu is with 2nds Lord and 9th is occupied by its own Lord. There will be eight sons, if Jupiter is in 5th, or 9th House, while 5ths Lord is endowed with strength and 2nds Lord is in 10th House. Saturn in 9th House, while 5ths Lord is in 5th itself, gives 7 sons, out of which twins will be born twice. If 5ths Lord is in 5th in Conjunct with 2nds Lord, there will be birth of 7 sons, out of which 3 will pass away. Only one son is denoted, if there be a malefic in 5th House, while Jupiter is in the 5th from Saturn, or vice versa. If 5th House has a malefic in it, or, if Saturn is in the 5th from Jupiter, the native will beget offspring only through his second, or third wife. Should 5th be occupied by a malefic, while Jupiter is conjunct with Saturn in 5th House, as Lagnas Lord is in 2nd House and 5ths Lord is conjunct with Mars, one will live long, but lose his children one after the other, as they are born.
Ch. 17. Effects of 6th House
1. O Brahmin, following are the effects, produced by 6th House, relating to diseases, ulcers etc. Listen to this attentively.
2. Ulcers/Bruises. Should 6ths Lord be in 6th itself, or in Lagna, or 8th, there will be ulcers, or bruises on the body. The Rāśi, becoming 6th House, will lead to the knowledge of the concerned limb.
3-5. Relatives Affected. The Karak of a relative, or the Lord of such a House, joining 6ths Lord, or being in 6th, or 8th House, indicates ulcers/bruises to such a relative, like father. Sun with such lordship and in such a House denotes such affectation of head, Moon of the face, Mars of the neck, Mercury of the navel, Jupiter of the nose, Venus of the eyes, Saturn of the feet and the Rahu and Ketu of the abdomen.
6. Facial Diseases. Should Lagnas Lord be in a Rāśi of Mars, or of Mercury and has a Aspect on Mercury, there will be diseases of the face.
7-8. Leprosy. Mars, or Mercury, having ownership of the ascending Rāśi and joining Moon, Rahu and Saturn, will cause leprosy. If Moon is in Lagna, which is not however Cancer, and be with Rahu, there will occur white leprosy. Saturn in place of Rahu will cause black leprosy, while Mars similarly will afflict one with blood-leprosy.
9-12. Diseases in General. When Lagna is occupied by the Lords of 6th and 8th House along with Sun, the native will be afflicted by fever and tumors. Mars, replacing Sun, will cause swelling and hardening of the blood vessels and wounds and hits by weapons. Mercury so featuring will bring in bilious diseases, while Jupiter in similar case will destroy any disease. Similarly Venus will cause diseases through females, Saturn windy diseases, Rahu danger through low-caste-men and Ketu navel diseases. Moon in Conjunct with the Lords of 6th and 8th House will inflict dangers through water and phlegmatic disorders. Similar estimates be made from the respective significators and Houses for relatives, like father.
13-19 TIMING OF ILLNESS. The native will be afflicted by illness throughout life, if Saturn is with Rahu, while 6th Lord and 6th House are conjunct with malefics. One will suffer from (severe) fever at the age of 6 and at the age of 12, if Mars is in 6th, while 6th Lord is in 8th. If the Moon is in Sagittarius/Pisces, while Jupiter is in 6th from Lagna, one will suffer from leprosy at the age of 19 and 22. If Rahu is in 6th, Lagna Lord is in 8th and Mandi is in an angle, consumption will trouble the native at the age of 26. Spleen disorders will be experienced at the age of 29 and 30, if the Lords of 6th and 12th are in exchange of their Rāśis. Saturn and Moon together in 6th will inflict blood-leprosy at the age of 45. If Saturn is with an inimical planet, while Lagna Lord is in Lagna itself, windy disorders (like rheumatism) will trouble the native at the age of 59.
20-22. Unfortunate years. Should Moon be conjunct with 6th Lord, while the 8th Lord is in 6th and the 12th Lord is in Lagna, the native will be troubled by animals at the age of eight. O Brahmin, if Rahu is in 6th, while Saturn is in 8th from the said Rahu, the child will have danger through fire at the age of 1 and 2, while in 3rd year birds will bring some evils.
23-25. Unfortunate years (continued). Danger through water will have to be feared during 5th and 9th years, if Sun is in 6th, or 8th, while Moon is in 12th from the said Sun. Saturn in 8th, as Mars is in 7th, all cause small-pox in 10th year and in 30th year of age. If 8th Lord joins Rahu in an angle/trine from 8th House and be in 8th in Navamsa, the subject will be troubled by swelling of blood vessels, urinary disorders etc. during the 18th year and the 22nd year.
26. Loss through enemies. Loss of wealth will come to pass during the 31st year, if 11th and 6th Lords exchange their Rāśis.
27. Inimical sons. Ones own sons will be his enemies, if 5th Lord is in 6th, while 6th Lord is with Jupiter. Simultaneously 12th Lord should be in Lagna.
28. Fear from dogs. There will be fear from dogs during the 10th and 19th year, if the Lagna Lord and the 6th Lord are in exchange.
Ch. 18. Effects of 7th House  
1. O excellent of the Brahmins, listen to me, detailing the effects of the 7th House. If 7th Lord is in his own Rāśi, or in exaltation, one will derive full happiness through his wife (and marriage).2. Sick wife. Should 7th Lord be in 6th, 8th, or 12th, the wife will be sickly. This however does not apply to own House, or exaltation placement, as above.
3. Excessive Libidinousness/Death of Wife. If Venus is in 7th, the native will be exceedingly libidinous. If Venus conjunct a malefic in any House, it will cause loss of wife.
4-5. The 7th lord. Should 7th Lord be endowed with strength and be conjunct with, or be aspected by a benefic, the native will be wealthy, honourable, happy and fortunate. Conversely, if 7th Lord is in fall, or is combust, or is in an enemy Rāśi, one will acquire sick wives and many wives.
6. Plurality of wives If 7th Lord is in a Rāśi of Saturn, or of Venus and be aspected by a benefic, there will be many wives. Should 7th Lord be particularly in exaltation, the same effects will come to pass.
7-8. Miscellaneous matters. The native will befriend barren females, if Sun is in 7th. Moon therein will cause association with such female, as corresponding to the Rāśi, becoming 7th. Mars, placed in 7th, will denote association with marriageable girls (those with menses), or with barren females. Mercury indicates harlots, mean females and females, belonging to traders community. Wife of a Brahmin, or a pregnant female will be in the natives association, if Jupiter is in 7th. Base females and females, having attained their courses, are denoted by Saturn, Rahu/Ketu in 7th.
8-9. Mars denotes a female with attractive breasts. Saturn indicates sick and weak spouse. Jupiter will bring a spouse with hard and prominent breasts. Venus will bring one with bulky and excellent breasts.
10-13. Malefics in 12th and 7th, while decreasing Moon is in 5th denote, that the native will be controlled by spouse, who will be inimical to the race (or family). If 7th House is occupied, or owned by Saturn/Mars, the native will beget a harlot, as his spouse, or he will be attached to other illegally. Should Venus be in a Navamsa of Mars, or in a Rasi of Mars, or receive a Aspect from, or be conjunct with Mars, the native will kiss the private parts of the female. If Venus is so related to Saturn, the native will kiss the private parts of the male.
14-15. Worthy spouse. The native will beget a spouse endowed with (the seven principal) virtues, who will expand his dynasty by sons and grandsons, if the 7th Lord is exalted, while 7th is occupied by strong Lagna Lord and a benefic.
16. Evils to spouse. If 7th House, or its Lord is conjunct with a malefic the natives wife will incur evils, especially, if 7th House, or its Lord is bereft of strength.
17. Loss of spouse. If 7th Lord is devoid of strength and is relegated to 6th, 8th, or 12th, or, if 7th Lord is in fall, the natives wife will be destroyed (i.e. she will die early).
18. Lack of conjugal felicity. If Moon is in 7th, as 7th Lord is in 12th and the Karaka (indicator Venus) is bereft of strength, the native will not be endowed with marital happiness.
19-21. Plurality of wives. One will have two wives, if 7th Lord is in fall, or in a malefic Rāśi along with a malefic, while 7th House, or the 7th Navamsa belong to a eunuch planet. If Mars and Venus are in 7th, or, if Saturn is 7th, while the Lord of Lagna is in 8th, the native will have 3 wives. There will be many wives, if Venus is in a Dual Rāśi, while its Lord is in exaltation, as 7th Lord is endowed with strength.
22. Timing of marriage (upto Sloka 34). If 7th Lord is in a benefics House (or in 9th, as Subha Rāśi so means), while Venus is exalted, or is in own Rāśi, the native will marry at the age of 5, or 9.
23. If Sun is in 7th, while his depositor is conjunct with Venus, there will be marriage at 7th, or 11th year of age.
24. Venus in 2nd, while 7th Lord is in 11th will give marriage at the age of 10, or 16.
25. Marriage will take place during the 11th year, if Venus is in an angle from Lagna, while Lagna Lord is in Capricorn, or Aquarius.
26. The native will marry at 12, or l9, if Venus is in an angle from the Lagna, while Saturn is in 7th counted from Venus.
27. Should Venus be in 7th from Moon, while Saturn is in 7th from Venus, marriage will be in the 18th year.
28. Marriage will be in the 15th year, if 2nd Lord is in 11th, while Lagna Lord is in 10th.
29. An exchange between the Lords of 2nd and 11th will bring marriage 13 years after birth.
30. Ones 22nd/27th year will confer marriage, if Venus is in 7th from the 8th House (i.e. 2nd from Lagna), while his depositor is conjunct with Mars.
31. Should 7th Lord be in 12th, while the natal Lord is in 7th in Navamsa, marriage will be in 23rd/26th year of age.
32. Either the 25th year, or the 33rd year will bring marriage, if 8th Lord is in 7th, as Venus is in Navamsa Lagna.
33. Should Venus be in 9th from 9th (i.e. in 5th House), while Rahu is in one of the said Houses (i.e. in 5th/9th), marriage will take place during 31st, or 33rd year.
34. The native will marry at 30, or 27, if Venus is in Lagna, while the 7th Lord is in 7th itself.
35-39. Timing of wife's death. Loss of wife will occur in the 18th year, or 33rd year of age of the native, if 7th Lord is in fall, while Venus is in 8th. One will lose his spouse in his 19th year, if 7th Lord is in the 8th, while 12th Lord is in 7th. The natives wife will die within three days of marriage due to snake bite, if the native has Rahu in 2nd and Mars in 7th. If Venus is in 8th, while his depositor is in a Rāśi of Saturn, death of wife will take place during the natives 12th, or 21st year of age. Should the ascendat Lord be in his Rāśi of debilitation, as 2nd Lord is in 8th, loss of wife will occur in the 13th year of age.
40-41. Three marriages. Should Moon be in 7th from Venus, while Mercury is in 7th from Moon and 8th Lord is in 5th (from the Lagna), there will be marriage in 10th year followed by another in the 22nd year and yet another in the 33rd year.
42. Death of wife. lf 6th, 7th and 8th are in their order occupied by Mars, Rahu and Saturn, the natives wife will not live (long).
Ch. 19. Effects of 8th House  
1. Long Life. O excellent of the Brahmins, listen to me speak on the effects of 8th House. If 8ths Lord is in an angle, long life is indicated.
2. Short Life. Should 8ths Lord join Lagnas Lord, or a malefic and be in 8th itself, the native will be short lived.
3. Saturn and 10ths Lord about Longevity. Similarly consider Saturn and 10ths Lord in the matter of longevity. 10ths Lord is in 8th along with a malefic Planet and/or Lagnas Lord.
4-7. Long Life. There will be long life, if 6ths Lord is in 12th, or, if 6ths Lord is in 6th, as 12ths Lord is in 12th, or, if 6ths Lord and 12ths Lord are in Lagna and 8th. If the Lords of 5th, 8th and 1st House are in own Navāmśaas, own Rāśis, or in friendly Rāśis, the native will enjoy a long span of life. Should the Lords of Lagna, 8th and 10th House and Saturn are all disposed severally in an angle, in a trine, or in 11th House, the subject will live long. Like these, there are many other Yogas, dealing with the issue of longevity. The strength and weakness of the Planets concerned be estimated in deciding longevity.8-13. Short Life. Ones span of life will be between 20 and 32 years, if Lagnas Lord is weak, while 8ths Lord is an angle. The native will only be short-lived, if 8ths Lord is in fall, while 8th House has a malefic in it and 1st House is bereft of strength. Death will be instant at birth, if 8th House, 8ths Lord and 12th House are all conjunct malefics. Malefics in angles and/or trines and benefics in 6th and/or 8th House, while 1st House has in it 8ths Lord in fall: this Yoga will cause immediate end. If 5th and 8th House and 8ths Lord are all conjunct malefics, the life span will be very brief. Within a month of birth, death will befall the child, if 8ths Lord is in 8th itself, while Moon is with malefics and be bereft of beneficial Aspect.
14-15. Long Life (again). One will be long-lived, if Lagnas Lord is in exaltation, while Moon and Jupiter are, respectively, in 11th and 8th House. If Lagnas Lord is exceedingly strong and receives a Aspect from a benefic, which is placed in an angle, the person concerned will be wealthy, virtuous and long-lived.
Ch. 20. Effects of 9th House
(1) Combinations for Fortunes. O Brahmin, now listen to the effects of 9th House. One will be fortunate (or affluent), if 9ths Lord is in 9th House with strength.
(2) Should Jupiter be in 9th House, while 9ths Lord is in an angle and Lagnas Lord is endowed with strength, one will be extremely fortunate.
3. Fortunate (Affluent) Father. If 9ths Lord is with strength, as Venus is in 9th, while Jupiter is in an angle from 1st House, the natives father is fortunate.
4. Indigent Father. If 9ths Lord is debilitated, while the 2nd and/or the 4th from 9th House is occupied by Mars, the natives father is poor.
5. Long-living Father. Should 9ths Lord be in deep exaltation, while Venus is in an angle from 1st House and Jupiter is in the 9th from Navāmśa Lagna, the father of the native will enjoy a long span of life.
6. Royal Status for Father. If 9ths Lord is an angle and receives a Aspect from Jupiter, the natives father will be a king endowed with conveyances, or be equal to a king.
7. Wealthy and Famous Father. Should 9ths Lord be in 10th House, while 10ths Lord receives a Aspect from a benefic the natives father will be very rich and famous.
8-9. Virtuous and Devoted to Father. Should Sun be in deep exaltation, as 9ths Lord is in 11th House, the native will be virtuous, dear to the king and devoted to father. If Sun is in a trine from Lagna, while 9ths Lord is in 7th in conjunct with, or receiving a Aspect from Jupiter, the native will be devoted to his father.
10. Fortunes etc. Acquisition of fortunes, conveyances and fame will follow the 32nd year of age, if 9ths Lord is in 2nd, while 2nds Lord is in 9th.
11. Inimical to Father. There will be mutual enmity between the father and the native, if Lagnas Lord is in 9th House, but with the Lord of 6th. Further, the natives father will be of contemptible disposition.
12. Begged Food. If 10ths Lord and 3rds Lord are bereft of strength, while 9ths Lord is in fall, or combust the native will go begging for his food.
13-25. Combinations for Fathers Death. The father of the native would have passed away prior to the natives birth, if Sun is in 6th, 8th, or 12th House, as 8ths Lord is in 9th House, 12ths Lord is in 1st House and 6ths Lord is in 5th House. Should Sun be in 8th House, while 8ths Lord is in 9th, the natives father will pass away within a year of his birth. If the Lord of 12th House is in 9th House, while 9ths Lord is in its debilitation Navāmśa, the natives father will face his end during the 3rd, or the 16th year of the native. Death of father will occur in the 2nd, or the 12th year, if Lagnas Lord is in 8th House, as 8ths Lord is with Sun. Should Rahu be in the 8th from 9th, as Sun is in the 9th from 9th, death of father will take place in the 16th, or the 18th year of the native. If Saturn is in the 9th from Moon, as Sun is with Rahu, the natives father will die in the 7th, or the 19th year of the native. The native in his 44th year will lose his father, if 9ths Lord is in 12th, as 12ths Lord is in 9th. If Lagnas Lord is in 8th House, as Moon is in Sun’s Navāmśa, the native in his 35th, or 41st year will lose his father. One will lose his father in the 50th year, if Sun, being the Lord of 9th, is conjunct Mars and Saturn. If Sun is in the 7th from 9th House, as Rahu is in the 7th from 3rd House, the 6th, or 25th year of the native will be fatal for father. If Saturn is in the 7th from 8th House, as Sun is in the 7th from Saturn, the ages of 21, 26, or 30 will be fatal for the father. If 9ths Lord is in its debilitation Rāśi, while his depositor is in 9th House, the native will lose his father at the age of 26, or 30. Thus the Jyotishyais may know the effects.26. Fortunes. One will enjoy abundant fortunes, if Venus is in deep exaltation and be in the company of 9ths Lord, as Saturn is in 3rd.
27-28. Fortunate Periods. Abundant fortunes be acquired after the 20th year, if 9th has Jupiter in it, as its Lord is in an angle from Lagna. Should Mercury be in his deep exaltation, as 9ths Lord is in 9th itself, abundant fortunes will be earned after the 36th year.
29. Should Lagnas Lord be in 9th, as 9ths Lord is in Lagna and Jupiter is in 7th, there will be gains of wealth and conveyances.
30. Lack of Fortunes. If Rahu is in the 9th from 9th House, as his depositor is in 8th House and 9ths Lord is in fall, the native be devoid of fortunes.
31. Food by Begging. Should Saturn be in 9th House along with Moon, as Lagnas Lord is in fall, the native will acquire food by begging.
32. O Brahmin, these are the effects related to 9th House. I have explained briefly. These may be estimated with the help of the state of the Lords of Lagna and 9th House and in other manners as well. 
