 
Garga Hora 
The classic Garga Hora by Sage Gargacharya is one of the ancient scriptures which explains the principles of astrology in brief sutras. 
Page 1
SUTRAS 1-150 
1. Jupiter in his own house along with Saturn and Mercury will bestow long life. Such native often will beget wealth. 
2. Should Venus be in Pisces along with Jupiter and the Moon, the native will acquire kingly fortunes and will have many sons and family. 
3. Should the Ascendant be in a malefic Rāśi, while the Lord thereof occupies the 7th house and Jupiter is posited in the 8th along with the Sun, the child will die at the age of eight. 4. If Mercury and Mars be together in the Ascendant, or 6th, or 8th, the native will either be a thief, or will indulge in awful acts. Such a person will have defect in his hands and legs. 5. Mercury in the Ascendant, or 6th, or 8th can cause death at the age of 4. Even if the native is dipped in nectar, it will be of no avail. 
6. Mars and Jupiter in exchange in Rāśi will inflict death at the age of 12. Even though Lord Siva may desire to save the person, it is rare to escape death in such a case. 7. Should Jupiter occupy a house of Mars identical with 2nd, 6th, or 8th from Lagna, this child doubtlessly will face death in its sixth year. 8. If Rahu occupies the Ascendant at birth, while the Moon is in the 6th/9th, the child will die within 20 days of birth. Similar effects will prevail, if Rahu is in the 4th from Lagna, while the Moon occupies one of the angles. 
9. Death will be inflicted by Rahu in the 7th from Lagna, while the Moon is in the Ascendant. Even nectar will not be useful to him and the death will come to pass in the 10th year of the child. 
10. If the Moon is in the 12th from Lagna, while malefics are in the 6th house, the native will be short lived. He will suffer from stomach disorders. 
11. If Rahu occupies the 9th, or the 10th, the native will die at 16, though Indra, Lord of Lords, may try to protect him. 
12. Death will come to pass at the age of 20, if Saturn and the Sun are in exchange Rāśi. 13. If Rahu is in the Ascendant, while the Moon is in the 6th (or both of them being together in the 6th) will promote diseases in the rectum, indigestion and deficiency of a limb. 14. Death will be caused due to leprosy, or tuberculosis, if the Sun is in 8th, while Saturn is in 6th. 
15. If the Sun is in the Ascendant at birth, the native will be subjected to mental worries and will have no place of his own. 
16. The child will die instantly, if Rahu is in the Ascendant, or in 8th and is in aspect to the Moon. Even Indra cannot save such child. 
17. The native will have a life-span of 100 years, if two Angles are occupied by Jupiter and Venus, while the Sun is in 12th and Mercury is in Lagna. 
18. There will be no Arishtas (evils), if Jupiter is in an Angle, or in a Trine, or in own House/exaltation House, as the Lagna. This will be so throughout the life. 
19. There will be no evils whatsoever, if one of Jupiter, Venus and Mercury is in an Angle and with positional strength. 
20. There is no evil whatsoever, if Saturn happens to be in the Ascendant, 3rd, or the 6th and be at the same time in Libra, Aquarius, or Capricorn. 
21. If the 2nd from the Ascendant is tenanted by Rahu, Mercury, Venus, Saturn and the Sun together, the mother will die soon. Alternatively it can be the father of the child. 
22. if the Sun is in Leo, or in Aries identical with the 6th, or the 11th and is aspected by a friendly planet, the evils, if any are simply counteracted. 
23. Should Rahu be in the Ascendant identical with Aries, Taurus, or Cancer and be in aspect to a benefic planet, no evil exists in the horoscope. 
24. RajaYoga is caused, if Saturn and the Moon are in the Lagna, while its trines are occupied by the Sun and Jupiter. Mars should be simultaneously in the 10th house. 
25. Should the Sun be in the 9th in Leo, the native will not have a surviving co-born. If however, one exists, he becomes a king. 
26. If Rahu is in Karma Sthana i.e. the 10th house, identical with own house and in the company of Mars, Mercury and Venus, the native will sometimes prosper and yet sometimes will have downfall. 
27. The subject is born in a mean descent, if malefics are in the 2nd, Rahu is in the 3rd and Jupiter is in the 5th. 
28. If the Sun etc. (i.e. other malefics) are in the 4th, 5th and 9th, the native will lose his first issue, while the later ones may survive. 
29. Should malefics be in the 2nd along with Mars and Saturn, while Rahu is in the 3rd, the co-born will not survive. 
30. Chatra Yoga is formed, if all planets are in the Ascendant, 2nd, 7th and 12th, he will become a leader of his race. 
31. If the Ascendant is occupied by Venus, 12th by Mercury and the 2nd by a malefic, a RajaYoga is formed and the native becomes a king. 
32. If the Ascendant is occupied by Venus, 12th by Mercury and the 2nd by a malefic, a RajaYoga is formed and the native becomes a king. If the Sun is in the 12th, the subject will be subjected to penury. 
33. The relatives of the native will perish, if the 12th and the 7th are occupied by malefics, while the 2nd by benefics. 
34. There is a RajaYoga, if the Moon and Saturn are in the 2nd, while Jupiter occupies Aries and Rahu with Venus is in the 10th. 
35. Should malefics be in the 2nd, 8th and 12th, the native will lose his eyes in his 8th, or 12th year of age. 
36. The co-born will not survive, if Mars is in the 8th house. Similar effects prevails, if he joins Rahu and Saturn in the 7th house. 
37. The results concerning Karma Sthana (i.e. 10th house) will be meagerly felt, if Mars aspects the 10th house occupying Aries, or Scorpio, while Mercury is associated with malefics. 
38. The native will head many people, if Jupiter is in Leo, while Venus is in virgo, Saturn is in Gemini and Mars in the 4th identical with own house. 
39. Should Saturn be in Virgo along with the Moon, while Mars is in the sign Capricorn, Rahu in Aquarius and, Jupiter in Leo, the native will destroy the band of his enemies. One born with such planetary array will not be an ordinary man. He will advance his family to a good state and enjoys RajaYoga. 
40. The native will indulge in notorious acts at the age of 20 (i.e. from his 20th year), if Venus is in Sagittarius, the Sun in Aquarius and Mars in Pisces simultaneously. 
41. Should a malefic be in the 11th house, while the 5th is occupied by Venus and the Moon, the native’s first issue will be a female and such female’s mothers will be subjected to many troubles. 
42. There will be destruction of relatives, if the 4th is occupied by Rahu, the 2nd by Jupiter and the 6th, or the 9th by Mercury. 
43. Should the 9th be occupied by Jupiter, Mercury, Venus and the Moon, the subject acquires success in all his undertakings and will be honoured by a king. 
44. If both malefics and benefics occupy severally the 6th, 8th, 5th, 9th and the 12th, the native will be honoured by the king. But he will face many hardships in life. 
45. If the 5th, 6th, 8th and 9th are occupied by, respectively, Mars, Rahu, Venus and the Sun, the native will protect his own people. 
46. If the Ascendant is occupied by Saturn and the Moon, while Venus is posited in the 8th, the subject will be highly libidinous. Though he will be honoured by a King, he can not enjoy any kind of happiness. 
47. If the Moon is in Capricorn at birth along with debilitated Jupiter, or with an inimical planet and aspected by Saturn, the native will be a source of evil to his own co-born. 
48. Should Rahu be in Gemini, while Mars is in Leo and Jupiter in Scorpio, the native will be equal to a king. 
49. If at birth Saturn occupies Aquarius, Mars Capricorn and the Moon Aries, while the 2nd house is occupied by the Sun, the subject will enjoy paternal wealth, or his own wealth. 
50. If Mercury and the Sun occupy the 10th, while Rahu is in the 6th, the native will lord over many. 
51. If the Sun is in the 10th in Leo, or Saturn in Libra identical with the 6th, or the Moon and Mercury in the 9th in Gemini, a RajaYoga is formed. 
52. Jupiter in Lagna, while Venus is in the 12th holding the other planets in between indicates RajaYoga, this is to the advantage of the native’s family to become strong (in all respects). 
53. The native doubtlessly becomes a king, if Jupiter is in the 8th and Venus is in the 3rd. All others should be between them. 
54. One born in Libra Lagna with exalted Saturn, while Jupiter is in Taurus, the Moon in Gemini, Mars in Capricorn, Venus in Leo and Mercury in Virgo along with the Sun, will have RajaYoga; he will maintain justice, good deeds and auspiciousness in his life. He will however cause Balarishta in the 8th, or the 12th year. The native will, however, later on prove inauspicious for the elder brother, or sister. 
55. If Libra happens to be the 2nd house, or an angle and is occupied by a malefic, the native only faces sheer poverty. He will not prove a good augury for his own people. 
56. Should the Moon be in the 10th, while Venus is in the 7th and malefics in the 4th, the native’s dynasty ends with him and there will be no further descent in his race. 57. The mother of the native will not survive, if Saturn is in the 2nd, Rahu in the 3rd and Jupiter is in Pisces. 
58. Should Mars be in the 7th, while Venus is in the 8th followed by the Sun in the 9th, the native will be short lived. 
59. If Jupiter is in the Ascendant, while Mars is not in the 7th and Venus is not in the 8th and the Sun is not in the 9th an auspicious Yoga is caused. Such a native will live a long lease of life, will have many co-borns, will head many people (i.e. employ many and feed them), will be happy, will lead himself and his co-born to a prosperous level, be free from proud conduct and be pleased in all aspects of life. 
60. If Saturn is in Cancer, while Rahu is in Taurus, the native will be very liberal, will enjoy numerous Yogas, i.e. will reach a very high state in life, will be famous, will be chief in his race and will marry many women. If, however, the said Saturn is lonely and aspects the 5th, there is only one marriage. 
61. The native will meet with his end, if Jupiter and Rahu are together in the Ascendant, or the 4th. The end will be in the 13th year even, if Lord Siva may try to save him. (That is, death in 13th year is certain). 
62. If Mars occupies the 8th, while the Sun is in fall in the 5th, or the 9th and Jupiter must be in accelerated motion. The native is blessed by Lakshmi, the Goddess of Wealth. 
63. Should Venus be in Pisces along with Mercury, while the Ascendant, 2nd and 3rd are, respectively, tenanted by the Sun, Moon and Mars, a Raja Yoga is constituted. One born under this kind of planetary array will respect Gods and preceptors. He will achieve such fame in his own native country and abroad as well, that cannot be achieved by others. 
64. It the 12th is occupied by Jupiter, while the 2nd house has Saturn, Sun, Mars and Mercury, the father of the native will pass away at the time of marriage of the native. 
65. If Jupiter is in the 3rd, while the planet Venus is in the 11th the native will be famous among his relatives and will shine, like a lamp among the men of his race. 
66. If Venus in the Ascendant is unaspected by anyone, while the Moon is in the 2nd and Jupiter is in the 3rd, the native cannot enjoy any paternal earnings. 
67. Should Mars and Saturn be in Leo, while Venus is in Virgo and Rahu is in Gemini, the child will lose its mother (early). 
68. Should Mars and Saturn be in Leo, while Venus is in Virgo and Rahu is in Gemini, this will cause poverty in childhood and happiness in the later part, if the Moon join Mars. 
69. If Lagna happens to be a malefic sign and is occupied by the said malefic Lagna Lord himself, while one among the 4th, 7th and the 10th being a malefic sign is occupied by its own malefic lord, the child will live only up to six. He will prove inauspicious to its mother. Additionally, there will be destruction of maternal relatives, if the 6th house is unaspected by Jupiter. 
70. The child, who has the Sun in Leo, a malefic in Virgo and Rahu in a malefic’s house will only live for six years. 
71. The longevity is only for 19 years, if the Moon is in the 8th, malefics in angles and Rahu in the 10th at birth. 
72. If a benefic planet is exalted in an angle, the native will acquire a large kingdom and will protect his family. 
73. Death of the father is imminent, if a child is born with Rahu in the Ascendant and the Sun in the 7th, while Mars is between Lagna and the 7th. 
74. A child, who has malefics posited in the 7th, 12th, 3rd and 8th, will always have an ailing physique. 
75. Should malefics be in the Lagna, 12th and 8th simultaneously, the child will be deprived of its mother instantly, while its father will leave this world in its 4th, or 10th year of age. 
76. 1st 
77. Sūrya, Candra: will have many sons, will not be happy in regard to parents, will be subjected to mental worries. 
78. Sūrya, Mangal: will be unhappy about his father, will be wicked, will always wander from place to place, will be meanly disposed. 
79. Sūrya, Budha: will not have conveyances, will be wickedly disposed, will have ill-reputed history, will commit sinful acts, be forsaken by friends and relatives. 
80. Sūrya, Guru: will have little intelligence, will look ugly, will be a dunce, will be ungrateful, thievishly disposed and jealous. 
81. Sūrya, Śukra: will hate scholars, will not have many children, will be cruel, angrily disposed, will trouble others, be fierce and dejected. 
82. Sūrya, Śani: will be a simpleton, be sick, be given up by his relatives and will not possess good qualities. 
83. Candra, Mangal: wicked, poor, talkative and not virtuous. 84. Candra, Budha: will have good speech, will be rich, beautiful, passionate, modest and will be addicted to other women. 
85. Candra, Guru: will be good-looking, long-lived, very famous, will have attractive eyes and hair on the head. 
86. Candra, Śukra: will be interested in good affairs, will have very beautiful face, will be affluent, interested in being virtuous and dear to king. 
87. Candra, Śani in the 1st Bhava: will earn money in bad ways, will know only bad things, be mean-minded, be attached to others money, be won by unsocial elements. 88. Mangal, Budha in the 1st Bhava: can easily dupe others, will be an able speaker, interested in living in foreign countries and will have bad notions. 
89. Mangal, Guru in the 1st Bhava: will be hard-hearted, will have few sons, will entertain others and will be interested in doing bad acts. 
90. Mangal, Śukra in the 1st Bhava: will have phlegmatic imbalances, will undertake futile jobs, will cheat others, will be ungrateful, will have a valorous son and will not achieve success in any of his undertaking. 
91. Mangal, Śani in the 1st Bhava: will be interested in committing sinful acts, will defy others, be interested in speaking harshly and be fiercely disposed. 
92. Budha, Guru in the 1st Bhava: will be beautiful in appearance, be fortunate, splendorous, rich and pleasing. 
93. Budha, Śukra: will be connected with royal duties, will be worth praising by kings, will be interested in various Śāstras, be rich and truthfully disposed. 
94. Budha, Śani in the 1st Bhava: will be expert in carrying out the orders of the king, will possess a bad wife, be indigent and will face obstructions from the public. 
95. Guru, Śukra in the 1st Bhava: will be dear to king, be inclined to earn more wealth, will have more knowledge in policies, be very rich and be an exponent of Śāstras to a great proportion. 
96. Guru, Śani in the 1st Bhava: will be very wealthy, highly educated, be not cunning, will face many risks and be untruthful. 
97. Śukra, Śani in the 1st Bhava: will be foolish, ungrateful and always attached to his men. 
98. Sūrya, Candra, Mangal in the 1st Bhava: will be liked by his elders, be defective limbed, be a liar and be cruel, blameworthy and foolish. 
99. Sūrya, Candra, Budha in the 1st Bhava: He will be foolish. 
100. Sūrya, Candra, Guru in the 1st Bhava: Will have all auspiciousness, be inclined to be virtuous, be intelligent, rich, very powerful on others and be always happy. 
101. Sūrya, Candra, Śukra in the 1st Bhava: will have auspicious events, be famous, prestigious, wealthy, chief among men and be justly disposed. This position bestows an early marriage and an amiable wife. 
102. Sūrya, Candra, Śani in the 1st Bhava: will have a fearful body (i.e. be fierce in appearance), be short lived, sick, sinful, capable of promoting quarrels and will be forsaken by relatives. 
103. Sūrya, Mangal, Budha in the 1st Bhava: will be very industrious, will always be troubled, be inimically disposed to others, be ungrateful and subjected to phlegmatic and windy diseases. 
104. Sūrya, Mangal, Guru in the 1st Bhava: will always be proud, be highly egoistic, will possess a fleet of horses and will be keen in imparting vices to others. 
105. Sūrya, Mangal, Śukra in the 1st Bhava: will be chief, justly disposed, will have good qualities and be dear to his relatives. 
106. Sūrya, Mangal, Śani in the 1st Bhava: will acquire a wife to promote monetary state, be short-lived, be subjected to many diseases, untruthful and foolish. 
107. Sūrya, Budha, Guru in the 1st Bhava: will be skilful, will advance through his undertakings, will befriend many and be an expert in war. 
108. Sūrya, Budha, Śukra in the 1st Bhava: will be modest, valorous, chief among Brahmins and be happy. 
109. Sūrya, Budha, Śani in the 1st Bhava: will be exposed to penury and diseases, will not have good qualities, be unjust and be forsaken by his own men and others as well. 110. Sūrya, Guru, Śukra in the 1st Bhava: will be leader of men, be fond of acquiring many children and will be free from enemies and such other troubles. 
111. Sūrya, Guru, Śani in the 1st Bhava: will have more enemies, will have to spend on bad missions, will like to commit sins, be defective in some limb and be weak. 
112. Sūrya, Śukra, Śani in the 1st Bhava: will undertake mean professions to earn money, will suffer poverty, will have vices, be fond of wandering and will earn his food by performing Homas etc. 
113. Candra, Mangal, Budha in the 1st Bhava: will own a fine house to live in, be very wealthy, justly disposed, be free from enemies and will earn knowledge in Śāstras. 
114. Candra, Mangal, Guru in the 1st Bhava: will be happy, very prestigious, be attached to his work, be virtuous, will have many friends and will be a great person. 
115. Candra, Mangal, Śukra in the 1st Bhava: will be subjected to much grief, will have vices, will have highly placed relatives, be very intelligent and be bright in appearance. 116. Candra, Mangal, Śani in the 1st Bhava: will be ever modest, be fond of guests, be interested in donation-giving, be very wise and will stand to gain a lot. 
117. Candra, Budha, Guru in the 1st Bhava: will be a king, will possess attractive physique, be very valorous and be always happy. 
118. Candra, Budha, Śukra in the 1st Bhava: will be very efficacious, attached to the virtuous, will have no knowledge of arts (practical, or fine, which are Śani, Budha in the 1st Bhava: in number, such, as music, dance etc.) and will be versed in justice. 
119. Candra, Guru, Śukra in the 1st Bhava: will marry a highly placed lady, will have rich food to eat, be very happy and will donate liberally. 
120. Candra, Guru, Śani in the 1st Bhava: will not be so efficacious (here Hora Ratna states, that the native will have appealing physique), be firm, will be eloquent, inimically disposed to the public, will have knowledge of poison (i.e. will deal with poison) and will have interest in bad deeds. 
121. Candra, Śukra, Śani in the 1st Bhava: will have sons and money, will maintain fasten and other religious observations, will have many plans in mind about things to be done, be bright and will have good mind. 
122. Mangal, Budha, Guru in the 1st Bhava: will always be modest, will gain several ways from foreign countries, be famous and be favorably disposed towards his dependants. 
123. Mangal, Budha, Śukra in the 1st Bhava: will have broad eyes and face, will have properly combed hair, be sweet in speech, truthful in disposition and will be easy to be approached. 
124. Mangal, Budha, Śani in the 1st Bhava: will be unjust, regardless of law, will have bad wife, have few sons and will kill animals. 
125. Mangal, Guru, Śukra in the 1st Bhava: will be good natured, will be endowed with virtues, wealth and children and will be respectful towards Brahmins and Gods. 
126. Mangal, Guru, Śani in the 1st Bhava: will be phlegmatic, wicked, be won by his wife, be troubled by hunger and be a talebearer. 
127. Mangal, Śukra, Śani in the 1st Bhava: will have a surprising body, be fierce, will not have any code of conduct, be inimical to his own men and be confused. 
128. Budha, Guru, Śukra in the 1st Bhava: will consider money, as most important, be beautiful, attached to women, friendly and very valorous. 
129. Budha, Guru, Śani in the 1st Bhava: will be subjected to phlegmatic diseases, fond of meat etc., will have hard teeth and coarse hair, be hard-hearted and will create terror among the people. 
130. Budha, Śukra, Śani in the 1st Bhava: will have swarthy body, be windy in temperament, be libidinous, torturous and very argumentative. 
131. Guru, Śukra, Śani in the 1st Bhava: will stick to religious observations, with delight in the contemplation of Supreme Spirit, will advocate final Emancipation effectively and be devoid of fear of tens of millions in kind. 
132. Sūrya, Candra, Mangal, Budha in the 1st Bhava: will be very sickly, will not be good-natured, will be interested in sinful acts, be ungrateful and will suffer from physical ailments. 
133. Sūrya, Candra, Mangal, Guru in the 1st Bhava: will be interested in bad acts, sick, sinful thankless, devoid of learning, ugly and fearful. 
134. Sūrya, Candra, Mangal, Śukra in the 1st Bhava: will wander purposelessly, will cheat others, be interested in blaming and be timid. 
135. Sūrya, Candra, Mangal, Śani in the 1st Bhava: will be interested in being just and be virtuous, will be ugly, forsaken by servants and will cheat others. 
136. Sūrya, Candra, Budha, Guru in the 1st Bhava: will be very timid, be a cheat, be attached to relatives and hardhearted. 
137. Sūrya, Candra, Budha, Śukra in the 1st Bhava: will like bad odour, be indigent, foolish, will not have friends and will be defeated by enemies. 
138. Sūrya, Candra, Budha, Śani in the 1st Bhava: will be foolish, night blind, will be interested in residing in bad places and be very poor. 
139. Sūrya, Candra, Guru, Śukra in the 1st Bhava: will be untruthful, will have few sons, will speak harshly, will be won over by enemies and will be subjected to grief. 
140. Sūrya, Candra, Guru, Śani in the 1st Bhava: will be dull-witted, have control over his senses, be skilful in taking things from others and be honoured for his deeds. 
141. Sūrya, Candra, Śukra, Śani in the 1st Bhava: will be auspicious, be dejected with people, will be very fair in complexion, will not have much money, will be hard in disposition. 
142. Sūrya, Mangal, Budha, Guru in the 1st Bhava: will be very valorous, will have voice, resembling that of a crow, be unkind, will have less money and will have physical deficiencies out of sickness etc. 
143. Sūrya, Mangal, Budha, Śani in the 1st Bhava: will have interest in sexual affairs, be expert in gambling, be unkind, more phlegmatic in temperament and be not bright in appearance. 
144. Sūrya, Mangal, Guru, Śukra in the 1st Bhava: will be troubled by sickness, will have vices, be very miserable and unkind. 
145. Sūrya, Mangal, Guru, Śani in the 1st Bhava: will have fearful eyes, will spend in bad ways, will wear rags and will be dejected with his wife, but attached to his son. 146. Sūrya, Mangal, Śukra, Śani in the 1st Bhava: will not be efficacious, be always insulted and be fickle-minded. 
147. Sūrya, Budha, Guru, Śukra in the 1st Bhava: will have ugly eyes, be unkind and disturbed. 
148. Sūrya, Budha, Guru, Śani in the 1st Bhava: will do irreligious things in times of danger, will serve mean people, be ill-natured, shameless and will face troubles from the king. 
149. Sūrya, Budha, Śukra, Śani in the 1st Bhava: will be given to anger, will have wicked wife, will always be a servant and be forsaken by his relatives. He will be inimical to all. 
150. Sūrya, Guru, Śukra, Śani in the 1st Bhava: will promote quarrels, be wicked, be immodest and will always move with sinful persons.  


*****************************************


Garga Hora 
Page 2
SUTRAS 151 TO 300
151. Candra, Mangal, Budha, Guru in the 1st Bhava: will possess a very dark and long body, will be interested in fighting, will suffer from bloody disorders and will poorly dress himself. 
152. Candra, Mangal, Budha, Śukra in the 1st Bhava: will not have sons and wealth, will have ugly ears, teeth and eyes, be a voracious eater, be ascetic and wicked. 153. Candra, Mangal, Budha, Śani in the 1st Bhava: will have uneven legs, ugly hair and ugly teeth. 154. Candra, Mangal, Guru, Śukra in the 1st Bhava: will have un ugly physique, ugly nails and ugly sides, will indulge in acceptable deeds and will be a tale-bearer. 155. Candra, Mangal, Guru, Śani in the 1st Bhava: will be very famous, be helpful to others, be free from enemies, be attached to his sons and affectionate to his preceptors. 156. Mangal, Budha, Guru, Śukra in the 1st Bhava: will be endowed with sons and a fleet of horse, be interested in Śāstras, will destroy sinners, be quite famous and be pure-hearted. 157. Mangal, Budha, Guru, Śani in the 1st Bhava: will be foolish, be phlegmatic and windy, dear to preceptors and be not proud. 158. Mangal, Budha, Śukra, Śani in the 1st Bhava: will have horrible notions, be long-bodied, will wear twisted hair, as an ascetic, be not virtuous, subject to skin afflictions and will suffer from itches. 159. Mangal, Guru, Śukra, Śani in the 1st Bhava: will be a bald-headed, fearless, learned, black in complexion and be in auspicious. 160. Budha, Guru, Śukra, Śani in the 1st Bhava: will be very efficacious, will have good (i.e. beautiful, or strong) nails, be tall, patient, will have beautiful hands and be fair complexioned. 161. Sūrya, Candra, Mangal, Budha, Guru in the 1st Bhava: will be very wealthy, be interested in Śāstras, be dear to elders and be attached to his sons. 162. Sūrya, Candra, Mangal, Budha, Śukra in the 1st Bhava: will be important by virtue of his good qualities, be good looking, be devoted to help the public and liberal in giving donations. 163. Sūrya, Candra, Mangal, Budha, Śani in the 1st Bhava: will beat (or kill) firmly, be unkind, will be strong bodied and be bereft of wisdom. 164. Sūrya, Candra, Mangal, Guru, Śukra in the 1st Bhava: will be firm in disposition, very efficacious, cruel, be a poet, be famous and dejected. 165. Sūrya, Candra, Mangal, Guru, Śani in the 1st Bhava: will have wounded body, will eat voraciously, be unjustly disposed, be very splendorous and be highly given to sexual feelings. 166. Sūrya, Candra, Mangal, Śukra, Śani in the 1st Bhava: will have interest in others wealth, will have long penis, will be full of veins, will have foul smell in the body and be cruel. 167. Sūrya, Candra, Budha, Guru, Śukra in the 1st Bhava: will be endowed with sons, learning, wealth and relatives and will have attractive eyes, ears, teeth and nose. 168. Sūrya, Candra, Budha, Guru, Śani in the 1st Bhava: will have sickly body, will be bilious and phlegmatic in temperament and will always move in forests. 169. Sūrya, Candra, Budha, Śukra, Śani in the 1st Bhava: will have own business, will have income through arts, be liberal in giving away gifts and will be endowed with all pleasures. 170. Sūrya, Candra, Guru, Śukra, Śani in the 1st Bhava: will be free form grief and fear, be inactive, or foolish due to some sin, or blemish and will be highly pious. 171. Sūrya, Mangal, Budha, Guru, Śukra in the 1st Bhava: will consider justice, as the most supreme aim, will have virtues, be truthful, be dear to the virtuous and will have pleasing looks. 172. Sūrya, Mangal, Budha, Guru, Śani in the 1st Bhava: will be subjected, troubles by abundantly, labouring, will be extremely emaciated, skilful in spending, expert in guess, be devoid of wealth, be phlegmatic, expert in promoting quarrels and will cheat. 173. Sūrya, Mangal, Guru, Śukra, Śani in the 1st Bhava: will be worshipped by Lord Indra (i.e. so superior a person), will eat and drink abundantly, will be interested in possessing conveyances, will possess attractive eyes and be unkind. 174. Sūrya, Budha, Guru, Śukra, Śani in the 1st Bhava: will consider piousness, as supreme, be a good singer, be very strong, very happy and truthful. 175. Candra, Mangal, Budha, Guru, Śukra in the 1st Bhava: will be interested in comforts will always be pure and clean, will be interested in listening to auspicious stories, will have a beautiful body and be the leader of men. 176. Candra, Mangal, Budha, Guru, Śani in the 1st Bhava: will have good knees and feet, will follow elders in respect of fame, wealth and happiness, be interested in performing sacrifices, worship etc. 177. Candra, Mangal, Budha, Śukra, Śani in the 1st Bhava: will have more gains, will be subjected to fear, will contact be venereal diseases due to sexual union with poor women and will wander. 178. Candra, Mangal, Guru, Śukra, Śani in the 1st Bhava: will be endowed with happiness, will have a fleet of horses, will have many friends, be proud, dear to good people and will befriend elders. 179. Candra, Budha, Guru, Śukra, Śani in the 1st Bhava: will have loss of horses, will practice self restraint, will present an artificial disposition (while inwardly he will be of a different nature), will be pious and will have parents with him. 180. Mangal, Budha, Guru, Śukra, Śani in the 1st Bhava: will consider money, as the most important aim, will have knowledge of Śāstras, will win his five senses and will be pious to the Almighty. 181. Sūrya, Candra, Mangal, Budha, Guru, Śukra in the 1st Bhava: will be helpful to others, wicked, cruel, will be subjected to grief and be virtuous. 182. Sūrya, Candra, Mangal, Budha, Guru, Śani in the 1st Bhava: will be subjected to great penury, be devoid of enemies, be extreme in nature, will be forsaken by his caste, will have defect in limbs, be very sickly broken-hearted and modest. 183. Sūrya, Candra, Mangal, Guru, Śukra, Śani in the 1st Bhava: will be hard hearted and will always be insulted by others. 184. Sūrya, Candra, Budha, Guru, Śukra, Śani in the 1st Bhava: will be interested in committing sinful acts and will have many kind of diseases. 185. Candra, Mangal, Budha, Guru, Śukra, Śani in the 1st Bhava: will have vices and various diseases. 186. 2nd 187. Sūrya, Candra in the 2nd Bhava: will not have money, will be ungrateful, will always possess bad disposition, will not be splendorous, will be subjected to diseases and fear. 188. Sūrya, Mangal in the 2nd Bhava: will suffer from penury, be shameless, unkind and sinful. 189. Sūrya, Budha in the 2nd Bhava: His body will be full of boils and wounds, he will not have any property, will be bad in disposition, will be bereft of servants, be troubled by others and will be subjected to much grief. 190. Sūrya, Guru in the 2nd Bhava: will be immodest, will be troubled, interested in committing sinful acts, be eloquent in speech and will contact difficulties in foreign countries. 191. Sūrya, Śukra in the 2nd Bhava: will be cruel in nature, attached to basemen, will have many enemies, will instil fear in others and be not bright in appearance. 192. Sūrya, Śani in the 2nd Bhava: will contact many diseases, will approach others in vain, be unkind, be not angry and will not join the virtuous. 193. Candra, Mangal in the 2nd Bhava: will be ruled by the public, will have a dejected wife, will look old, be ungrateful, be a servant, be wicked and bright in appearance. 194. Candra, Budha in the 2nd Bhava: will be very rich, be free from vices and dear to the king. 
195. Candra, Guru in the 2nd Bhava: will be a king, will be splendorous, be interested in virtues, will destroy enemies, will have many sons and be liked by the public. 
196. Candra, Śukra in the 2nd Bhava: will have virtue, as his wealth, will be either a king, or a minister, will have many friends and will be attached to his son. 197. Candra, Śani in the 2nd Bhava: will not have any wealth, will follow bad course, will be troubled by enemies, be argumentative in nature and his relatives will perish. 198. Mangal, Budha in the 2nd Bhava: will lose wife and wealth, be subjected to blemish, will contact diseases, will not possess good qualities and will not patronize his relatives. 199. Mangal, Guru in the 2nd Bhava: will be sickly, be unwise, ill-natured, will have few sons and will be blamed in arguments. 
200. Mangal, Śukra in the 2nd Bhava: will be sickly, be unwise, ill-natured, will have few sons and will be blamed in arguments. 201. Mangal, Śani in the 2nd Bhava: will have wealth, grains, pearls and such other precious stones, will acquire few sons and be untruthful. 202. Budha, Guru in the 2nd Bhava: will have knowledge of Supreme Spirit, will head a town, or be equal to a king, be wealthy, will have virtues worth respect and will be expert in mathematics. 203. Budha, Śukra: will acquire a fleet of horses and elephants, be very wealthy, wise, virtuous, truthful and will be dear to Brahmins. 204. Budha, Śani in the 2nd Bhava: will be devoid of wealth, fierce, wicked and will join bad elements. 205. Guru, Śukra in the 2nd Bhava: will be chief among kings, will be endowed with honour, wealth and army, will honour good deeds, will live by praise and valour and will be successful. 206. Guru, Śani in the 2nd Bhava: will be troubled by kings, be quite sickly, greedy, be free from enemies and be not happy in any respect. 207. Śukra, Śani in the 2nd Bhava: will be bereft of sons and money, be dirty in appearance, cruel and will perform bad acts. 208. Sūrya, Candra, Mangal in the 2nd Bhava: will not be wealthy, be troubled by others, be not efficacious, be cruel and will be troubled by fear. 209. Sūrya, Candra, Budha in the 2nd Bhava: will be timid by nature, be indigent, will have a bad wife and will experience grief by his own bad acts. 210. Sūrya, Candra, Guru in the 2nd Bhava: will have gad sons, will torture others, be sensuous, ungrateful and will instil fear in elders. 211. Sūrya, Candra, Śukra in the 2nd Bhava: will indulge in enmity with friends, will have conveyances, will not have much wealth, will look ugly, will depend on elders and be given to anger. 212. Sūrya, Candra, Śani in the 2nd Bhava: will be ungrateful, be interested in visiting foreign countries, interested in gambling, will face troubles, be not virtuous and be with little wealth. 213. Sūrya, Mangal, Budha in the 2nd Bhava: will be a dunce, a spendthrift, be truthful, will have a prodigal son, be shameless and be devoid of friendliness. 214. Sūrya, Mangal, Guru in the 2nd Bhava: will be devoid of wealth, be wicked, will have a lean body and will earn enmity in service. 215. Sūrya, Mangal, Śukra in the 2nd Bhava: will not have common sense, will be forsaken by many, will prove a bad servant, be interested in battle and will lose property. 216. Sūrya, Mangal, Śani in the 2nd Bhava: will have a polluted physique, be devoid of qualities and wealth, be fond of promoting quarrels, be sick at all times and will be condemned by good people. 217. Sūrya, Budha, Guru in the 2nd Bhava: will have many wounds and boils in the body, be blamed, wicked, be troubled by people and will wound other’s feelings. 218. Sūrya, Budha, Śukra in the 2nd Bhava: will be always insulted, will look, like a lion, be sensuous, miserly, will face ups and downs and be a simpleton. 219. Sūrya, Budha, Śani in the 2nd Bhava: will derive help from his own people, will be indigent, be fierce, be not virtuous and be a simpleton. 220. Sūrya, Guru, Śukra in the 2nd Bhava: will be dull-witted, not learned, unwise, will lose property, be defeated and be a miser. 221. Sūrya, Guru, Śani in the 2nd Bhava: will be given to much anger, be troubled by diseases, be interested in promoting quarrels, be devoid of righteous deeds and be very indigent. 222. Sūrya, Śukra, Śani in the 2nd Bhava: will be interested in acts, which are not righteous, be wicked, immodest, troubled and will indulge in gad acts. 223. Candra, Mangal, Budha in the 2nd Bhava: will be subject to vicissitude, be harsh in speech, be scandalous in money matters, be childless, ge fiver to much anger, will suffer from diseases and be forsaken by his relatives. 224. Candra, Mangal, Guru in the 2nd Bhava: will be poor in status, be devoid of wife, issue and wealth, be very greedy and will suffer from diseases. 
225. Candra, Mangal, Śukra in the 2nd Bhava: will be troubled by diseases caused due to phlegmatic disorders, will not respect his preceptors, be very justly disposed and will be banned from the purview of Śāstras. 226. Candra, Mangal, Śani in the 2nd Bhava: will be naturally wicked, be fond of alcohol, be interested in gambling, be a dejected soul and be forsaken by his relatives. 227. Candra, Budha, Guru in the 2nd Bhava: will be a king, will be insulted much, be beautiful land will be endowed with learning and riches. 228. Candra, Budha, Śukra in the 2nd Bhava: will be affluent, will have a number of friends, will be learned in Śāstras, be virtuous, be very learned and be always affectionate. 229. Candra, Budha, Śani in the 2nd Bhava: will be efficacious and helpful, be a spendthrift, be subjected to grief on account of his wife, ge a donor and will cheat others. 230. Candra, Guru, Śukra in the 2nd Bhava: will be happy, will have good ideals, be a king, be very famous, be very wise and will have a questionable (mean) profession. 231. Candra, Guru, Śani in the 2nd Bhava: will be free from anger, will be interested in good conduct, be sweet in disposition, will be attractive and will be affectionate to his son. 232. Mangal, Budha, Guru in the 2nd Bhava: will be devoid of ideals, will not have any wealth, be very wicked, be attached to other’s wives, will wander aimlessly and will be tortured by his libidinous disposition. 233. Mangal, Budha, Śukra in the 2nd Bhava: will consider justice, as the most supreme ideal, be an agriculturist, will pull carts, will own fleet of quadrupeds and will have many friends. 234. Mangal, Budha, Śani in the 2nd Bhava: will be very angrily disposed, will be fond of meat and flesh, will be interested in possessing weapons, will torture others, will spend much and be a source of grief to his own people. 235. Mangal, Guru, Śukra in the 2nd Bhava: will be and expert artisan, will take to righteous path, will perform penance, will possess attractive body and be fearless. 236. Mangal, Guru, Śani in the 2nd Bhava: will possess good robes, will enjoy much of pleasures, will be interested in women, will be an able speaker, be interested in Śāstras, be very wealthy and very attractive. 237. Budha, Guru, Śukra in the 2nd Bhava: will be a king, will own a fleet of superior class of elephants and horses, be very affluent and be attached to his relatives. 238. Budha, Guru, Śani in the 2nd Bhava: will become superior by his righteous acts, be famous, be useful (to others), be very kind and be garrulous. 239. Budha, Śukra, Śani in the 2nd Bhava: will have a strong and prominent belly, will be interested in various sciences and to be truthful, be a drunkard, but will be piously attached to Lord Krishna. 240. Guru, Śukra, Śani in the 2nd Bhava: will be endowed with sons and wealth, will be a scholar, be justly disposed, be happy, be very affectionate and splendorous. 241. Sūrya, Candra, Mangal, Budha in the 2nd Bhava: will be attached to evil countries (or places), will indulge in unethical acts, will derive happiness from his wicked wife and will incur grief through his sons. 242. Sūrya, Candra, Mangal, Guru in the 2nd Bhava: will not be of good disposition, will not be virtuous, will be untruthful, will be very phlegmatic in temperament and libidinous. 243. Sūrya, Candra, Mangal, Śukra in the 2nd Bhava: will always be worried, be dirty, will instil fear in others, be ungrateful, be troubled and be not famous. 244. Sūrya, Candra, Mangal, Śani in the 2nd Bhava: will have shaky teeth and long stomach, will not be so freely, will speak doubtfully (not confident), be unwise and be not successful in his mission. 245. Sūrya, Candra, Budha, Guru in the 2nd Bhava: will eat anything available, will be troubled due to excess of the three humours, will be very greedy and will befriend very bad elements. 246. Sūrya, Candra, Budha, Śukra in the 2nd Bhava: will have diseases related to penis (i.e. urinal diseases, venereal diseases, bladder etc.), will be of mean disposition, will have few sons, will have daughters and be not virtuous. 247. Sūrya, Candra, Budha, Śani in the 2nd Bhava: will suffer headache and from windy and phlegmatic diseases and be not attached to his own people. 248. Sūrya, Candra, Guru, Śukra in the 2nd Bhava: will not be sharp, will be dejected with people, will be troubled, blame -worthy and timid. 249. Sūrya, Candra, Guru, Śani in the 2nd Bhava: will have plenty of hair on the head, will not be dear to the virtuous, elders, Brahmins etc., will grow by eating food given by others and will have trouble from kings. 250. Sūrya, Candra, Śukra, Śani in the 2nd Bhava: will be devoid of sons, will grow fat by excess work, will have mean ideals and be bereft of pleasures. 251. Sūrya, Mangal, Budha, Guru in the 2nd Bhava: will be devoid of good disposition, be fierce, be devoid of sons, will be interested in women, will have diseased eyes, be spendthrift and have mental worries. 252. Sūrya, Mangal, Budha, Śukra in the 2nd Bhava: will be sinful, be forsaken by his virtuous wife, will be devoid of good relatives and be interested in sexual acts. 253. Sūrya, Mangal, Budha, Śani in the 2nd Bhava: will be troubled by wounds, will have fear, be very proud, be very sinful and be not well-taught. 254. Sūrya, Mangal, Guru, Śukra in the 2nd Bhava: will have good speech and eyes, will be a tale-bearer, will not show interest in giving donations/gifts, be not grateful and will suffer from great blemishes. 255. Sūrya, Mangal, Guru, Śani in the 2nd Bhava: will be very famous, will have big bones and long hair, will live in foreign countries, will have more enemies, will be friendly, will always be angry, be troubled, wicked, cruel, shameless and be forsaken by his wife. 256. Sūrya, Mangal, Śukra, Śani in the 2nd Bhava: will have many troubles, be not virtuous, be devoid of happiness and knowledge of Śāstras and will befriend only sinners. 257. Sūrya, Budha, Guru, Śukra in the 2nd Bhava: will be sickly be emaciated, be less truthful, be dull-witted and interested in bad tales. 258. Sūrya, Budha, Guru, Śani in the 2nd Bhava: will not have wealth, will be greedy, will look ugly and will have diseased eyes, will not have happy relations, will be interested in sexual affairs and be sickly disposed. 259. Candra, Mangal, Budha, Guru in the 2nd Bhava: will be dear to sages/good people, be interested in Śāstras and Puranas, be devoted to Brahmins and will be pleasing to look at. 260. Candra, Mangal, Budha, Śukra in the 2nd Bhava: will be interested in visiting shrines, religious observations and Śāstras, will be worshipped and be equal to a king. 261. Candra, Mangal, Budha, Śani in the 2nd Bhava: will consider money the most important, will have agricultural profession, will own a fleet of horses, will acquire gold, will be famous, will be a poet, will be interested in giving donations/gifts and will be attractive in appearance. 262. Candra, Mangal, Guru, Śukra in the 2nd Bhava: will be devoid of learning, will be calculative, will be a scholar and dear to Brahmins. 263. Candra, Mangal, Guru, Śani in the 2nd Bhava: will be successful, will have virtuous children, be affluent, be honoured even by kings, will observe religious regulations, will have various kinds of horses, robes and things, be free from diseases and be virtuous. 264. Candra, Budha, Guru, Śukra in the 2nd Bhava: will be interested in performing sacrifices of religious nature and serving the virtuous, be an able speaker, be very wealthy and be interested in Śāstras. 265. Candra, Budha, Guru, Śani in the 2nd Bhava: will be dear to Brahmins, will possess attractive body, will speak smilingly, be always happy and be dear to the king. 266. Candra, Budha, Śukra, Śani in the 2nd Bhava: will be a chief with the king, will be respected even by his enemies, will have much wealth and donate liberally. 267. Candra, Guru, Śukra, Śani in the 2nd Bhava: will be chief among many men, be respected by kings, be minister, be always happy and be famous. 268. Mangal, Budha, Guru, Śukra in the 2nd Bhava: will be favourable to Brahmins, be famously valorous, be skilful in achieving royal missions patient and happy in all respects. 269. Mangal, Budha, Guru, Śani in the 2nd Bhava: will be related to foreign countries, will have income, be attached to the virtuous, will have gardens and wills and will be on king’s mission. 270. Mangal, Budha, Śukra, Śani in the 2nd Bhava: will have a modest wife, will have attractive body, be attached to the virtuous and will have abundant grains and money. 271. Mangal, Guru, Śukra, Śani in the 2nd Bhava: will have abundant corns, will acquire knowledge of Śāstras, be happy, be chief amongst poets and will be principled. 272. Budha, Guru, Śukra, Śani in the 2nd Bhava: will be skilful in all kinds of arts, will destroy enemies, will be famous and be attached to wealth. 273. Sūrya, Candra, Mangal, Budha, Guru in the 2nd Bhava: will be worried, very greedy, not wise and will have small body. 274. Sūrya, Candra, Mangal, Budha, Śukra in the 2nd Bhava: will be subjected to troubles due to excessive mundane attachment, be not splendorous, be windy in temperament and interested in committing sinful acts. 275. Sūrya, Candra, Mangal, Budha, Śani in the 2nd Bhava: will be a night-blind, be libidinous, will lose his property, will be inimical to many and be dull-witted. 276. Sūrya, Candra, Mangal, Guru, Śukra in the 2nd Bhava: will be without any assignment, be not rich, be without good robes, be troubled by diseases and interested in living in foreign countries. 277. Sūrya, Candra, Mangal, Guru, Śani in the 2nd Bhava: will be inimical even to friends, be not helpful to others, will be very poor, will have poor (unrewarding) profession and be not valorous. 278. Sūrya, Candra, Mangal, Śukra, Śani in the 2nd Bhava: will be interested in association with wicked people, will be troubled by wounds and boils, be very sinful and be much angrily disposed. 279. Sūrya, Candra, Budha, Guru, Śukra in the 2nd Bhava: will be egoistic, impatient, unkind and unjust. 280. Sūrya, Candra, Budha, Guru, Śani in the 2nd Bhava: will be very greedy, short tempered, devoid of desires, be unjust and timid. 281. Sūrya, Candra, Guru, Śukra, Śani in the 2nd Bhava: will be poor, be troubled out of fear, be very sinful, devoid of desires, interested in virtues and will have attractive eyes and legs. 282. Sūrya, Mangal, Budha, Guru, Śukra in the 2nd Bhava: will be blame-worthy, ungrateful, will do others’ jobs, will give high importance to wife and will not be masculine in disposition. 283. Sūrya, Mangal, Budha, Guru, Śani in the 2nd Bhava: will face obstacles (in his undertakings), will cheat, be ungrateful, will undertake to do inimical acts and will have and inimical wife. 284. Sūrya, Budha, Guru, Śukra, Śani in the 2nd Bhava: will not have people of his own, who will have their money (i.e. his own people will be devoid of money), will have vices, will not be kind at all and will be inimical to Śāstras. 285. Candra, Mangal, Budha, Guru, Śukra in the 2nd Bhava: will be interested in getting the jobs of his relatives done, be very wealthy, learned in Vedas (Śāstras etc.) and be pure. 286. Candra, Mangal, Budha, Śukra, Śani in the 2nd Bhava: will have good friends, be modest, be disinterested, will not have food to eat and will suffer from lung disorders. 287. Candra, Budha, Guru, Śukra, Śani in the 2nd Bhava: will be devoted to elders and Brahmins, be good looking, be liberal and skilful in divine undertakings, viz. Puja etc. 288. Mangal, Budha, Guru, Śukra, Śani in the 2nd Bhava: will be given to anger to a small extent, will be very interested in friends and Śāstras and be adventurous. 289. Sūrya, Candra, Mangal, Budha, Guru, Śukra in the 2nd Bhava: will be very much worried, be devoid of truth and wealth, wicked and attached to bad elements. 290. Sūrya, Candra, Mangal, Budha, Guru, Śani in the 2nd Bhava: will not attain crops, will have no sons, be very wicked, attached to undesirable learning etc. and will befriend bad elements. 291. Sūrya, Candra, Mangal, Budha, Śukra, Śani in the 2nd Bhava: will be given to anger chiefly, will prove an evil to friends, be chief among men and be a big cheat. 292. Sūrya, Candra, Mangal, Guru, Śukra, Śani in the 2nd Bhava: will be proud, will dislike to listen to religious stories, will be fickle-minded in speech and will be subjected to much grief. 293. Sūrya, Candra, Budha, Guru, Śukra, Śani in the 2nd Bhava: will not attain fame, will not be rich, be blameworthy, be chief and be free from expenses. 294. Sūrya, Mangal, Budha, Guru, Śukra, Śani in the 2nd Bhava: will not successfully perform his own profession, will be foolish, sick and be troubled. 295. Candra, Mangal, Budha, Guru, Śukra, Śani in the 2nd Bhava: The native will have the seas, as boundaries of his kingdom, will hold the flag of virtue aloft and be very famous. 296. Sūrya, Candra, Mangal, Budha, Guru, Śukra, Śani in the 2nd Bhava: will be endowed with wealth, horses and elephants galore and be highly virtuous.  297. 3rd  
298. Sūrya, Candra: will have affectionate wife and affectionate relatives, will be attached to others, will observe religious fasting etc., will have knowledge of Śāstras, will possess sweet voice, will be a poet and will have increasing fame. 299. Sūrya, Mangal: will be equal to a king, will have lands, be interested in possessing conveyances, will have attractive eyes, will be courteous to guests and will acquire many sons. 300. Sūrya, Budha in the 3rd Bhava: will have many sons and grandsons, will be widely famous, be very valorous, will win his five senses and be dear to people. 
 
