
Saravali 
Page2
Ch. 8. Conception 
1-3. A Female Menstruation. Without the knowledge of conception time one cannot understand the effects of the various divisions, like Rāśi. That is why I explain below about conception, which is the cause of births of all animals. As a result of Moon's transit in Anupachaya Rāśis and in aspect of Mars, a female obtains her menses. The Moon is water and Mars is fire. Water produces blood and fire produces bile. When blood is enraged by bile, the women gets her menstruation. 4-7. The menstruation so caused makes the female capable of conception. If the Moon is in Upachaya, it makes the menses defunct for conception. However, if the Moon in Upachaya is aspected by Jupiter, or her friends, or especially Venus, the woman affectionately cohabits with the male. If the Moon is aspected by Mars, the female unites with a person other than husband. The Sun, if aspecting the Moon, indicates a king, while Saturn aspecting denotes a servant. Similar inferences should be made, if the Moon is aspected by malefics only, without aspect of benefics. If the Moon is aspected by malefics, like Mars, then the female gives up her home and becomes a prostitute. 
8-10. The 7th House from Lagna at the time of copulation indicates the disposition of the couple. If there is a malefic's aspect to the Lagna at the time of copulation, the couple unites angrily and with quarrel. Should it be benefic's aspect, then the sexual enjoyment will be (pleasing), as enumerated by Vatasyayana Mahāŗşi. If there be both malefic and benefic aspects on the 7th, the sexual act is mixed in nature. According to one's past deeds, to ripe its fruits the semen enters the womb and conception ensues. 
11-12. Occurrence of Pregnancy. If the transit Sun and Venus be in Upachaya Rāśis with strength with reference to the male partner's nativity and occupy even Navamsas, there is scope of pregnancy to be caused by the particular intercourse. Similar effects follow, if strong Moon and strong Mars be in Upachaya Rāśis in transit with reference to the female's horoscope and be in even Navamsas. Alternatively Venus, Sun, Mars and Moon should be in Upachaya Houses in own Amsas, or Jupiter be in Lagna, 5th, or 9th with strength to cause pregnancy. 
13. Disposition of Fetus. The child in the womb will be according to the mental disposition of the couple and their desires and according to Tridoshas (bile, phlegm and wind) prevailing. 
14-15. Sex of the Child. Should Lagna, Moon, Jupiter and the Sun be strong and be in male Rāśis and male Navamsas, birth of a male child be predicted. If they are in even Rāśis and even Amsas, predict female child. If strong Jupiter and Sun be in male Rāśis, male child will be born. Female child should be expected, if Venus, Moon and Mars are in even Rāśis. 
16. Twin Birth. If the Sun and Jupiter be in Gemini, or Sagittarius in aspect to Mercury, birth of two male children be predicted. Two female children will be born, if Venus, Mars and the Moon be in Pisces, or Virgo in aspect (of) Mercury. 
17. Male Birth. If Saturn is in odd House other than Lagna, a male child will be born. Such Yogas and strengths at the time of Adhana should be properly assessed to predict birth of male, or female child. 
18-20. Birth of Hermaphrodite. Birth of a hermaphrodite should be declared, if the Sun and the Moon be in odd Rāśis and be in mutual aspect, or, if Mercury and Saturn be in mutual aspect from odd Rāśis, or, if Mars aspects the Sun, who is in an even Rāśi, or, if the Moon is in Lagna in odd Rāśi. These are the views of sages. If Mars aspects Mercury in odd Rāśi and simultaneously the Moon in even Rāśi, same effect follows. Alternatively if Lagna, Moon and Mercury be in odd Rāśi and odd Navāńśa and aspected by Venus and Saturn, eunuch birth is indicated. 
21-22. One Male Child and One Female Child to be Born. Should Lagna and Moon be in even Rāśis and be aspected by a strong planet, then there are twins in the womb (one male child and one female child). Similar results follow, if the Moon and Venus are in even Rāśis, or Common Signs and be strong. 
23-26. Birth of Triplets. The following Yogas prevailing at the time of Adhana lead to births of triplets. Mercury remaining in Gemini Navāńśa aspecting a planet, who also falls in Common Navāńśa (a), Mercury remaining in Gemini Navāńśa aspecting a Sign, which ascends (b), Mercury in Virgo Navāńśa aspecting a planet falling in Common Navāńśa (c), Mercury in Virgo Navāńśa aspecting a Common Sign, which ascends (d), Mercury in Gemini Amsa aspecting a planet in Gemini Amsa, or Sagittarius Amsa (e), Mercury in Gemini Navāńśa aspecting the Lagna, which falls in Gemini Navāńśa, or Sagittarius Navāńśa (f), Mercury in 7th aspecting a planet in Kanya, or Meena Navāńśa, or aspecting such Lagna Navāńśa (g). Combinations (a) and (b) lead to birth of triplets - one female and two males. Combinations (c) and (d) cause birth of triplets consisting of two females and one male. Combinations at (e) and (f) cause three male children, while the ones at (g) indicate three female children. 
27. Mother, Father, etc. If births take place in day-time, Venus indicates mother, while the Sun indicates father. In the case of nights the Moon and Saturn, respectively, play these roles. Similarly the Moon denotes mother's sister and Saturn paternal uncle for day-time births, while Venus and the Sun take over these portfolios, respectively, in the case of night births. 
28. Effects of such Planets. If the planets denoting father and paternal uncle are in odd Bhavas, their well-being is assured. If the planets denoting mother and maternal aunt are in even Bhavas, their well-being is to be predicted. 
29-31. Process of Growth of Embryo and Lords thereof. The embryo in the womb improves, as under. First month coagulated blood, second mass of flesh, third limbs, fourth bones, fifth skin, sixth hair, seventh movement, eighth feeling of hunger and thirst, ninth excitement and tenth riped, like a fruit and ready for coming out of the womb. These ten months are ruled, respectively, by Venus, Mars, Jupiter, the Sun, the Moon, Saturn, Mercury, Lord of Nisheka Lagna, the Moon and the Sun. The dispositions of these Lords indicate good, or bad of the respective processes. 
32-33. Miscarriage. Should a planet be affected by celestial portents, or defeat by malefic at the time of intercourse, miscarriage may take place in the month ruled by the planet concerned. The Ascendant ruling at the time of intercourse can also become cause of miscarriage. If Saturn and Mars be in the said Ascendant, or the Moon be in a House of Mars, or Saturn, the results mentioned will come to pass. 34. Comfortable Carrying. Should the Adhana Ascendant be occupied by Moon, or should there be benefics in the 5th, 9th, 7th, 2nd, 10th, 4th and malefics relegated to 3rd and 11th aspected by the Sun, the carrying female is safe. 
35-41. Adversities to the Pregnant Woman. If at the time of Adhana the Sun and the Moon are hemmed between two malefics, while the Ascendant has no benefic aspect, the female concerned dies. The same effect prevails, if the said Ascendant and the 7th are occupied by malefics and be without benefic aspect, or, if the said Ascendant is occupied by Saturn and weak Moon aspected by Mars. Again similar effects shall come to pass, if weak Moon and the Sun are in 12th, Mars in 4th, while Venus is between two malefics. Both the child in the womb and its mother leave this world, if malefics occupy the 4th from the said Ascendant, or from the Moon, while Mars is in the 7th, or Lagna. The same result follows, if Mars is in 4th, Sun in 12th and the Moon be decreasing and be with malefic aspect. If the Sun is in Lagna, while the Moon is weak, or, if Mars is in Lagna, while malefics are in 12th and 2nd without benefics' aspect, death occurs of the mother along with child. The Sun in the 7th at Adhana, while Mars is in Lagna, takes away the child along with its mother through instruments. 
42-43. Progress of Pregnancy. Should there be aspects from Mercury, Jupiter, Venus, or the Sun to the Lagna, the process of pregnancy goes on well. The embryo develops according to the state of the Lords of various months (in transit). In the third month the pregnant woman develops tastes to eat various things according to the disposition of the various monthly Lords and Lagna Lord and the Yogas caused to them. 
44-45. Time of Delivery. If at the time of Nisheka (i.e. Adhana) the Sun is in a Movable Sign, delivery takes place in the 10th month, if he is in a Fixed Sign, delivery in 11th month is indicated and in a Dual Sign it is in 12th month. If a Movable Rāśi ascends at Adhana, delivery takes place in 10th month, a Fixed 11th and Dual 12th. 46-47. The matter of delivery can be guessed through the Vargas of Nisheka Lagna. The natal Moon can be in the 10th from Adhana Moon. This view is held by many Acharyas. According to Badarayana the natal Ascendant will be in the 7th from Adhana Lagna and natal Moon will be in the 7th from Adhana Moon. Since there are several views on this, I explain below a view, which is acceptable to all. 
48. View Acceptable to all about Natal Moon. Note the Dwadasamsa of the Moon at the time of Adhana. When Moon is so many Signs away from her Adhana position (in a month, when delivery is normally possible), delivery will take place. 
49. Should a Navāńśa of Saturn rule the Nisheka Lagna and Saturn be in the 7th, the delivery takes place after three years. If Cancer be the Navāńśa Lagna with the Moon in the 7th (from Rāśi Lagna), delivery occurs after twelve years. 
50. Fraction of Day, or Night for Delivery. According to Nisheka Lagna being a day Sign, or night Sign, delivery will be after so much of fraction of night, or day having passed. 
51-52. Thus should be understood the possible time of birth in day, or night and the Lagna at birth. In similar manner the difference between sunrise and birth, i.e. natal Ascendant and (week)day, fortnight, Muhurta month etc. should be guessed. Such details relating to birth should first be ascertained and then predictions should be issued with reference to nativity by astrologers. 
53-55. Yogas for Eye Defects. If at the time of Adhana (or at birth) the Sun and Moon are in Leo identical with Lagna, the child born will be blind. There should be aspect of Mars and Saturn on Leo. A bubble on the eye should be predicted, if Mars and Mercury aspect the said Sun and Moon in Leo Lagna. I shall further explain Yogas affecting the eyes. Should the 12th be occupied by waning Moon, left eye is destroyed and, if by the Sun, it is the right eye. If, however, benefics aspect (the said 12th and the Sun/Moon), then by (suitable) efforts the eye can be repaired. 
56. If malefics are in Rāśi Sandhi and the Moon is in Taurus aspected by Mars, Saturn and the Sun, the native born will be dumb. If, however, there is benefic's aspect, the person speaks later on. 
57. If malefic planets are in Rāśi Sandhis, while there is no benefic aspect on the Moon, the native born is dullwitted. Should Saturn and Mars be in a Navāńśa of Mercury, the birth is with teeth. 
58. Should Mercury be in 5th, or 9th from the Ascendant, while all other planets are devoid of strength, the child has 2 faces, 4 hands and 4 legs. 
59. If the last portion of Capricorn rises with aspect from Saturn and the Luminaries, the native is short-statured. The same effect prevails, if the Moon is in Cancer identical with Ascendant and aspected by Mars and Saturn. 
60. If Pisces rises at birth with aspect from Mars, Saturn and the Moon, the child born is lame. If there is a benefic's aspect to the said combination, then relief can be expected after making efforts. 
61. Should Mars be in the Ascendant and fall in the ascendental decanate, or a trinal decanate, receiving the aspect of malefics, while benefics are devoid of strength, the child in the womb develops no head, no legs and no hands, respectively. 
62. Whatever is stated in this Ch., should be suitably applied to natal Ascendant, if applicable. And the rules stated elsewhere in regard to nativity may be used with reference to Ādhāna also, if need be. 
Thus ends the 8th Ch. entitled Ādhānādhyāya in Saravali of Kalyana Varma. 
Ch. 9. Conditions at Birth 
1. To know the time of delivery I have explained the Ādhāna Ch. Now I explain the natal Ch., as below. 
2. If natal Lagna is in Sīrshodaya Rāśi, birth is with head foremost and a Prishtodaya Rāśi at birth indicates birth with legs foremost. The birth is with hands in such a position, if an Ubhayodaya Rāśi ascends. Should Lagna enjoy benefic aspect, delivery would have been comfortable, otherwise difficult. 
3-4. The place of delivery will correspond to the Rāśi Lagna, or Navāńśa Lagna at birth. If it is a Dual Rāśi, or Navāńśa, delivery will be on the way. A Fixed Rāśi/Ańśa indicates delivery in one's own place. Should the Navāńśa be of the same Rāśi, the delivery is in one's own house, otherwise it is otherwise. The delivery will be in the house of father, or mother according to the indicator concerned being strong. 
5-7. If benefic planets are in full, then the birth is in an enclosed place, under a tree, or on the banks of a river. Should all planets be together and not aspect Lagna, or the Moon, then the birth is in a thick forest. If a watery Sign is on the Ascendant and aspected by Full Moon from a watery Sign being 4th, or 10th, birth is in water (river etc.) and similar results be predicted, if Lagna and 4th are occupied by benefics and Full Moon is in watery Sign, or in own House. 
8-11. If Scorpio, or Cancer ascends with Saturn and is aspected by Moon, birth is in a deep place. This view is held by Yavanas and Maniththa. Should Saturn be in watery Rāśi rising and aspected by Mercury, birth is in playground. If the planet aspecting is the Sun, it is temple and the Moon aspecting indicates barren lands. Should an Aranya Rāśi (for example Leo) be on the Lagna, the birth is in hills, forest, fortress etc. Should a human Rāśi be ascending and is aspected by Mars, it is burial ground, if by Mercury, sculpture home and, if by the Sun, cowshed, royal palace, or temple. If the aspect is from Venus and Mercury, it indicates pleasing location and, if from Venus and Jupiter, it is Brahmins' place, or where sacred rites are performed. 
12. Should Jupiter be exalted in 10th (Libra Lagna), delivery is in a 2-, 3-, or 4-storied building. If benefic planets are in Saturn's Rāśi, or Navāńśa, coinciding with the 4th, or 10th, the delivery is in a veranda, or balcony. 
13. To know the direction of the delivery room proceed thus. One of the Dual Signs ascending denotes the quarter (of the direction), in which the room is situated. The other Signs from Aries on indicate the directions of the room. 
14. Should there be a (strong) planet in the Angle of a Sign, the direction, represented by that Sign will prevail. If Sagittarius ascends with strength, it is 3-storied building, while Capricorn denotes a spacious house. 
15. If Venus is strong at birth, it is a new and painted house. Jupiter in strength denotes a strong house, while Mars indicates a burnt house. The Sun stands for house constructed of wood. It is a new house, if the Moon is strong. Saturn in strength indicates an old house. 
16-17. The direction of the planet occupying an Angle denotes the direction of entry for the lying-in-chamber. The planet, that is conjunct with the planet denoting house of birth, indicates the direction, in which another house related to delivery is located. The Sun indicates temples, the Moon watery places, Mars fire-houses, Jupiter treasury, Venus parks etc., Saturn filthy corner and Mercury bedroom etc. 
18-20. Now explained is the situation of the cot, on which the delivery took place. The 3rd, 6th, 9th and 12th indicate the four legs of cot. The first two relate to southern side legs and the other two denote the northern side legs. If the Ascendant is aspected by a benefic, the kind of cloth relating to that benefic was spread on the delivery cot. The Ascendant leads to know the direction, in which the mother was having her head. The depression in the cot corresponds to the Common Sign occupied by malefics. 
21-23. If the Moon is in her debilitation Sign identical with the 4th, or Ascendant, the birth is on the ground. The number of attendants can be known by the number of planets posited between the Moon and Lagna. The number of attendants inside the chamber is known by the number of planets posited in the invisible half and the number of attendants outside the chamber will correspond to the number of planets in the visible half. If the concerned planets are benefic, the attendant ladies are with attractive features, beautiful and bedecked with ornaments. Malefics similarly indicate, that such females are ugly, unfortunate and dirty. If the planets are of mixed disposition, but with strength, the attending women are in between the said two accounts. All these should be accordingly understood. 
24-25. Out of the 12 Rāśis the one occupied by the Sun will indicate the portion of the delivery chamber, where light is kept. If it is Fixed Sign, the light burns steadily and, if it is a Moving Sign, it is unsteady. The portion, that expired in Lagna is indicative of the content, to which the wick has burnt already. The quantity of oil in the lamp will correspond to the waxing, or waning state of the Moon. 
26-27. There were many lights, if the Sun is aspected by Mars. Should other planets be all weak, light was obtained by burning grass. Should the Moon be in a Navāńśa of Saturn, or be in watery Navāńśa, or in the 4th House and be in aspect to, or in the company of Saturn, delivery was in a place of darkness. There is no doubt about this. 
28-30. Should the Ascendant be without the aspect of the Moon, the birth is behind the father, i.e. the father was absent from the place. If the Sun is in the 9th identical with a Movable Rāśi, the father was in a foreign place. The Sun in the case of day birth and Saturn in the case of night birth, if aspected by Mars, delivery is out of father's sight. If the said Sun, or Saturn be in a Movable Sign, death of father (in a distant place) should be declared. If the 5th, 6th and 7th from the Sun are aspected, or occupied by malefics, the father was under confinement. Movable, Fixed and Common Signs here indicate confinement, respectively, in foreign place, own place and on the way. 
31. Should the 7th House and the Trines be occupied by malefics, the delivery is not without trouble. Benefics in 10th and 4th cause easy delivery in a large room apart from giving wealth. 
32-33. The following lead to birth outside wedlock: Moon, or Lagna sans Jupiter's aspect; Luminaries being together without Jupiter's aspect; Luminaries along with malefics not receiving the aspect of Jupiter; Sun, Moon and Jupiter simultaneously in fall, while Saturn is in Lagna and Lagna, Moon and Venus not being in aspect to Jupiter. 
34-36. If the Moon is in 4th, or 7th along with malefics, it is evil to mother. The native's mother dies (immediately after delivery), if there are malefics in 7th from Moon and aspected by Mars. Sun in 10th from the Moon along with malefics indicate death of the mother. The same effect prevails, if Sun is in 5th, or 9th from Venus (?) and with Saturn's company, or aspect. If birth takes place during night-time, while Saturn occupies 5th, or 9th from the Moon, the mother soon leaves the world. For a day birth, if Mars is 5th, or 9th from Venus and aspected by malefics, the mother dies (early). 
37-40. If Mars and Saturn join in 5th, or 9th from Ascendant, while the Moon is in 7th, the child is forsaken by the mother. Jupiter's aspect in that case bestows happiness and long life. The child given up dies, if the Moon is in Lagna and Mars in 7th in aspect to malefics. Mars and Saturn in 11th bring similar effects. Should a benefic aspect such combinations, the child is rescued by the respective relative. Both malefics and benefics aspecting indicate death in the hands of others. Saturn and Mars joining in the same Ańśa indicate, that the child will be forsaken by the mother. Mars in 7th from the Ascendant in aspect to Saturn produces similar effects. 
41. The child acquires the qualities corresponding to the benefic's aspects. Should the Sun be strong, it resembles the father. If the Moon be so, resemblance is that of the mother. 
42. When Leo, Aries, or Taurus rises with Mars, or Saturn, there will be coil around the limb, as indicated by the Navāńśa Lagna Rāśi. 
43-44. If the Lagna falls in a decanate of Mars, or Saturn, while malefics, or Moon occupy Lagna, with benefics relegated to 2nd, or 11th denote, that the child was born with navel cord coiled around. Should the Sun be in a Quadruped Sign, while others with strength remain in Dual Signs, it indicates, that twins were born coiled by same navel cord. 
45-46. The physical appearance will correspond to the Navāńśa Lagna, or the strongest of planets. It may also correspond to the Lord of the Navāńśa occupied by the Moon. If many are strong, appearance and complexion will be mixed. Race, caste and country of birth should be considered, while estimating features and character of a person. 
47. Sages say, that the nature of the native will correspond to the Trimsāńśa occupied by the Sun at birth. 
48. Other information must be understood according to the friendship, enmity and debilitation, exaltation, or placement in between of the planets at birth. 
49. If weak Moon be with malefics, mother's death takes place, while the Sun being so causes father's death. These planets indicate sickness (to the concerned parent), if aspected by both benefics and malefics. Benefics, however, cause auspiciousness. 
50. The Moon, being bright, if be in her exaltation Rāśi, or in her own Rāśi along with Jupiter and Venus in aspect to Mercury, or the Moon in 5th is capable of giving extreme auspiciousness in respect of the native's mother. The Sun so placed proves auspicious for father. 
Thus ends the 9th Ch. entitled Janma Vidhanādhyāya of Kalyana Varma's SARAVALI 
Ch. 10. Evils at Birth 
1. In the absence of knowledge of longevity, attempts to know other information are futile. So I explain below Arishtas (evils) in order to determine longevity. 
2. Male planets are strong in odd Rāśis, bright lunar half and day-time. Female planets are strong in even Rāśis, dark lunar half and night-time. 
3. There are three kinds of evils, explained by astrological expounders. These are preordained, accidental and Yogaja (arising of planetary combinations). The third kind is dealt with below, while others are explained later on. 
4. Should Jupiter be in 8th and in a House of Mars and aspected by Sun, Moon, Mars and Saturn, the child dies in 3 years. 
5. If Saturn is retrograde in a House of Mars, while Moon is in 6th, 8th, or an Angle and aspect Mars, the child born lives for two years. 
6-7. If Saturn joins Sun and Moon at birth, the life-span is only nine years, according to Brahmasaunda. Should Mars, Sun and Saturn be in Taurus identical with 8th, the native lives for one month even though Lord Yama may try to save him. 
8-9. Even, if there be a single malefic in 8th House, owned by Venus and aspected by other malefics, the native lives for one year only in spite of the fact, that he may drink nectar. If Venus is in 12th, 6th, or 8th, owned by Sun, or Moon and is aspected by all benefics, the life-span is six years. 
10-11. If Mercury occupies Cancer identical with 6th, or 8th from Ascendant and is aspected by the Moon, life is only up to 4. The efficacious Raja Yogas expounded by Yavanas may produce persons of high descent. Even such children are subject to premature end in this case. 
12-13. If the birth star is identical with the one, in which Ketu rises, the native lives only for two months. Should the Sun be in 10th House identical with that of Mars, or Saturn and aspected by strong malefic, the native faces immediate death. 
14-15. Should the Ascendant fall in Nigala, Sarpa, Pakshi, or Pasa decanate and be occupied by malefic planets, without the aspect of the decanate Lord concerned, the native lives up to 7 years only. If Rahu is in an Angle and aspected by malefics, the longevity is only 10, while, according to some, it is 16. 
16-17. If malefics are Angles and Trines, while benefics are relegated to 6th, 8th and 12th, one born at the time of sunrise dies at once. If the three planets, viz. the Lords of Navāńśa Lagna, Moon Sign and natal Ascendant, are combust, the person lives just for a few years. 
18. If the 6th is occupied by the Ascendant Lord, death occurs in the year corresponding to Rāśi concerned. If the occupant is the Lord of rising decanate, death occurs in the month corresponding to Rāśi concerned and, if it is Lord of Navāńśa Lagna, the Rāśi concerned causes death in so many days. 
19. If Saturn is in the Ascendant in aspect to malefics, longevity is only 16 days. If Saturn in the Ascendant is in the company of malefics, death occurs in a month and, if he is alone in the Ascendant without malefic connections, the child lives for one year. 
20-22. If weak Moon is in the Ascendant excepting Cancer, Taurus and Aries and is aspected by malefics, the child passes away (soon). The Moon in 6th, or 8th, if aspected by malefics, causes death in one year, while, when aspected by benefics, she kills in the 8th year. Should the aspect be from both benefics and malefics, the life-span is only 4. This should be decided according to the strength of such bodies. 
23-24. Should benefics be in 6th, or 8th and be aspected, or conjoined with retrograde malefic, without the aspect of benefic, the child lives only for one month. If malefics are in 12th, 2nd, 6th and 8th, without connection of benefics, the child dies in 6, or 8 months. 
25-26. If the Lords of Lagna and the Moon Sign are together in 6th, 8th, or 12th and be combust, the child dies in the year corresponding to the Rāśi. Should the Lord of the Ascendant be in 7th, defeated by a malefic and be without a benefic's aspect, death occurs in a month. Similar clues should be drawn from Moon and her dispositor. 
27-28. If Moon is conjoined with Mars and Sun and be in 2nd, or 5th unaspected by benefics, the child doubtlessly dies in the 9th year. Sages declare, that, if the Ascendant Lord is in 8th in aspect to all the malefics, who are with strength, the child dies in the fourth month. 
29-30. If the Lord of Moon Sign, the Sun and his son are in 8th, the child dies in the year corresponding to the Rāśi concerned. Should the Moon be with malefics, be in 12th, 8th, 6th, or Ascendant and be not aspected by benefics, while benefics are non-angular, the child dies at once. 
31-32. If malefics are in the oriental half of the Zodiac (from 10th to 4th Bhava Madhya) with benefics relegated to the occidental half, birth in Scorpio Ascendant causes what is Vajra Mushti Yoga. One born in such a Yoga does hardly live. According to Yavanas, if weak Moon is in Lagna, while malefics are angular, or in 8th, (instant) death is caused. 
33-34. One born in twilight does not live long, if the Ascendant falls in lunar Hora, while malefics are posited in the end of the Rāśis, which are angular, along with the Moon. Should the Moon be amidst two malefics and be in 7th, 4th, or 8th, even Gods cannot save one from (instant) death. 
35-36. If the Moon is hemmed between two malefics, be in the Ascendant, 7th, or 8th and be in aspect to weak benefics, (infant) death follows. Should malefics be in 7th and 8th and be aspected by malefics, the child dies along with its mother. If there be aspect from benefics in such a case, the mother becomes sick (there will not be immediate death). 
37-38. If the Moon be eclipsed and be in the Ascendant along with malefics, while Mars is in 8th, the child quits the world along with its mother. The mother dies of weapons along with the child, if it be a solar eclipse with Sun and malefics in the Ascendant, while Mars is in 8th. Should weak Moon be in the Ascendant and malefics be angular, or in 8th, without benefic's aspect, death is imminent. This view is of Satyācārya. 
39-40. The undermentioned combinations cause death soon. Sun in 7th, while Saturn, or Mars is in Ascendant. Sun in Ascendant, while Saturn, or Mars is in 7th. Saturn, or Mars joining Moon and she not aspected by benefics. Malefics in Ascendant, 8th, 7th, 4th and 10th, the Moon be decreasing in 12th. 
41-42. Moon, Sun, Saturn and Mars are capable of inflicting infant death, if they are together in Ascendant, 12th, 9th, or 8th, unaspected by Jupiter. If Ascendant is tenanted by Sun, or Moon, while malefics are in Trines, or 8th and be not aspected by, or conjoined with benefics, according to Yavanas, infant death is caused. 
43-44. Venus joining the Sun and Saturn causes instant death. This combination doubtlessly gives death in the 9th year, if aspected by Jupiter. Death in childhood occurs, if Moon is conjoined with Mars, Sun and Saturn, provided unaspected by benefic planets. 
45-46. If Sun is aspected by Mars and Saturn in the case of a day birth, it soon leads to death of the father. The Sun joining malefics (for day birth) also indicates the same effect. The child's father and paternal grandfather will face early death, if Sun is in Ascendant along with Mars and Saturn, but unrelated to Mercury, Jupiter and Venus. 
47-48. If Sun is hemmed between two malefics, or is conjoined with malefics, one born during day-time loses his father early without any doubt. The child's father at once quits the world, if planet Sun has Mars and Saturn in 8th from him unaspected by benefics. 
49-50. If at birth Sun is in a Movable Rāśi along with malefics, the father of the child dies of poison, weapons etc. Malefics (or even a malefic) in 8th, 9th, or 7th from Moon can cause death of the child along with its mother. 
51-52. The father of the child was away at the time of birth, if Sun is in a Movable Sign, in case of day birth and aspected by Mars. Saturn in a Movable Rāśi and in aspect to the Sun in the case of night birth denotes same results. 
53-54. In the case of night birth, if Saturn is in a Movable Sign along with Mars, the father undoubtedly dies in a distant place. If Sun joins Mars and Saturn in any Rāśi, the father dies before the birth of the native. 
55-56. If malefics are disposed in Ascendant, 8th, 7th, 6th and 12th, the child dies along with its mother. There is no doubt in it. Should only 6th and 8th be occupied by malefics, the mother does not die, but the child dies. The reverse is true, if malefics are in Ascendant, 8th and 7th. 
57-67. Mars, or Saturn in 12th can deprive the native of his eyes. Saturn right and Mars left eye. The native becomes blind, if Sun and Moon are in 12th, while 6th and 8th are occupied by malefics. Even, if one among the Sun and the Moon is in 12th, damage to eye is indicated (Sun affects the right eye, while Moon affects the left one). If Rahu is in Ascendant, while Sun is in 7th, the native is blind by birth. Should 2nd and 12th be occupied by Moon and Sun, while malefics are in 8th and 6th, the person born is blind. If Moon is in 6th, Sun in 8th, Saturn in 9th and Mars in 2nd, simultaneously, the native is blind. Should Moon be in the company of Mars and Saturn and be posited in 8th, or 6th, the native looses his eyesight due to bilious and phlegmatic imbalances. Should the said Moon be conjunct other malefics, apart from Mars and Saturn, in this combination, if the House involving Moon is the 8th, the damage is to the right eye and, if it be the 6th, the left eye is damaged. Should, however, this combination be aspected by benefics, the damage is not at birth, but will be later on. If Moon is in 8th, or 12th along with Saturn and be aspected by malefics, eyesight is lost due to windy and phlegmatic complaints (here also 8th indicates right, while 12th the left eye). And, if benefics aspect the said Moon in 8th/12th, the loss is not at birth, but in the course of time. If Moon is thus associated with Saturn and Sun (in several ways), damage to eyes is to be predicted. 
68-70. YOGAS ADVERSE FOR EARS. Moon in 11th, 3rd, or Ascendant along with malefics causes defects of the ears. If she is aspected by malefics, the effect is along with birth (i.e. immediate). Should 9th and 5th be aspected, or occupied by malefics, ear defects at the time of birth exist. Malefics in 9th affect the right ear, while in 5th they damage the left ear. Benefics aspecting, or occupying these Houses cause on the other hand good in respect of ears. 
71-73. Whatever Rāśi is indicative of a disease shall be treated, as the limb to be afflicted by such disease. The Moon Sign can also be similarly considered. Benefics cause birth marks on the right, or left side of the body, according to their occupation. Should malefics aspect these benefics, loss of concerned limb should be expected. Malefics and benefics according to their association with Moon and the visible and invisible halves (counted from Lagna) cause bad and good results in this respect. 
74-76. DEATH IN FEW DAYS. The Sun and the Moon in the 3rd House identical with Pisces cause illness from birth and the child lives only for three days. If the Moon is in the 10th from the Ascendant, while the Sun singly, or with all others is in the 3rd asterism from that occupied by the Moon, the child lives only for one night. The life span is just one week, if the Sun and Mars are in the 7th from the Moon. 
77-82. EFFECTS OF TIME OF STARTING OF DISEASES. The following combinations prevailing at the time of a disease cause death in so many days, as indicated: 1) Malefics in 4th and 8th from Lagna-10 days. 2) Malefics in 2nd and 12th from Lagna10 days. 3) The Sun in 5th, while Moon is in 9th from the Ascendant12 days. 4) The Moon in Angle, while the Sun is in 4th, or 8th 3 nights. 5) The Moon in the 4th, while the Sun is in the 6th 18 days. 6) The Sun in the 5th, or 9th from the Moon20 days. 7) The Sun in the Ascendant, or the 8th and in aspect to Saturn and Mars will finally inflict death on the patient. 
83-88. Mars in Lagna, or other Angles, while Jupiter is not so causes death. The Sun in Lagna, Jupiter non angular and malefics in the 8th cause immediate death. Similar results should be predicted, if the Moon is in the Ascendant, while Jupiter is in a place other than Angles and malefics are in the 8th. Malefics in the 7th from the rising decanate, while the Moon is in the Ascendant will also cause death at birth. (In this case, the Moon shall be in the rising decanate, while malefics shall occupy the l9th decanate). A majority of planets in the 8thprimarily maleficsindicate longevity ranging from seven days to one month. A dead child is born, if Saturn is in the Ascendant, while Mars is in the 8th, with Jupiter being not in an Angle. 
89-9O. MALEFICS IN RISING DECANATE AND TRINES THEREOF. Saturn in the rising decanate, while a malefic is in the 5th and another in the 9ththe latter two should be exactly on trinal decanates, as Saturn isindicates disease. Mars in the place of Saturn in the said combination denotes (infant) death, while the Sun so placed indicates disease, deformity, or death. 
91. DEATH. If at birth Mars is in the Ascendant, while Venus is in an Angle, Mars causes death, when he resumes the same point in the next round in his transit. 
92. If Jupiter is in a Trine, Ascendant Lord in the Ascendant and Mars in an Angle to one of them, it can cause immediate death. 
93-97. EXCEEDINGLY LONG LIFE. The native lives for 108 years, if the 8th House is not occupied, while Ascendant is free from malefic residence and Jupiter is in an Angle. A span of over 108 years is granted, if Jupiter and Venus are in an Angle, while there are no malefics in Trines and the 8th. Predict 120 years of life, if Venus is in the Ascendant, Jupiter is in an Angle other than the Ascendant and the 8th House is not occupied by malefics. Similar span of life is given, if Jupiter is in Cancer Ascendant along with Venus, or the Moon, while the 8th House is not occupied. If Angles, Trines and the 8th House are not occupied by malefics, one's longevity is comparable to that of Gods. 
98. ELAPSED LONGEVITY. Weak Moon along with malefics, if posited in the 8th, 7th, 12th, 1st, 5th, or 9th and unaspected by benefics will only grant elapsed longevity, i.e. immediate death. 
99. TIMING INFANT DEATH. When the child with powerful infant mortal combinations is in its first year, death will come to pass, if the Moon with strength passes over the natal position of another qualified planet, or on its own natal position (i.e. Janma Rāśi), or natal Ascendant. In all these cases, the Moon should be aspected by malefics. 
100-103. DEATH IN CHILDHOOD. Any one group of the following planets joining in one House will cause death in five years: d) The Sun, the Moon, Mars and Jupiter, 2) Mars, Jupiter, Saturn and the Moon, 3) The Sun, Saturn, Mars and the Moon. Even, if a child is on the God's laps, it will die in 11th year, if the Sun conjunct Mercury is aspected by malefics. Death within 7 years of age will occur, if the Sun is in the Ascendant along with Mars and Saturn, while declining Moon is in the 7th House in a House owned by Venus, provided this combination is not aspected by Jupiter. Should the Sun and the declining Moon be in Angles and be conjunct with, or in aspect to Mars and Saturn, the child has a longevity of only 4 years. In these cases, i.e., where child mortality is indicated, there is no use of making any calculations. 
104. DEATH IN THIRD YEAR. If waning Moon, or Lagna Lord be in the Marana Pada and aspected by all the malefics, but not benefics, the length of life is only 3 years. 
Notes: Marana Pada has been interpreted, as 8th House by some. But it actually means the Rāśi counted so many Signs away from the Rāśi, in which the 8th Lord is, as he is away from the 8th. Note how many Signs away the 8th Lord is from the 8th. So many Rāśis away from the 8th Lord's Rāśi is Marana Pada. 
105-107. If all benefic planets are in the visible half of the Zodiac, while malefics are relegated the invisible half Rahu be specifically in the Ascendantat the time of birth, the longevity is only 3 years. Should Rahu be in the 7th House in exclusive aspect to the Luminaries and be unaspected by others, death before the age of 12 is denoted. 
108-110. If Rahu is in Aquarius, Leo, or Scorpio identical with the Ascendant and is aspected by malefics, the life span is only 7. If Dhuma Ketu rises followed by fall of meteor and strong gale and, if birth occurs in Raudra Muhurta, or Sarpa Muhurta, the subject invites early death. 
111-114. FATEFUL DEGREES OF THE MOON. The Moon is capable of inflicting death, if she is in any of the following degrees at birth: Aquarius 21, Leo 5, Taurus 9, Scorpio 23, Aries 8, Cancer 12, Libra 4, Capricorn 20, Virgo 1, Sagittarius 18, Pisces 10 and Gemini 22. If the Moon is in such degrees at birth, death is indicated in the corresponding year and the native cannot be protected by even God Yama. 
115-118. Assess the strengths of Ascendant, Angles etc., at birth. Jupiter is life spirit of all natives. The time of death should be known through Jupiter. If he is in the 3rd, 4th, 5th, 7th, 9th, 10th and 11th, or Ascendant, he proves fatal at the age of 5 10, 46, 20. 30, 40 and 50, respectively. 
Thus ends the 10th Ch. entitled Evils at Birth in Kalyana Varma's SARAVALI 
Ch. 11. Evils and the Moon 
1-2. I now explain the combinations, that are capable of nullifying the said evils, for these are important in the Science of Horoscopy and initially explained below are the Yogas to counteract the evils emanating from, or afflicting the Moon, as done by expounders, like Lord Brahma. 
3-4. If the Moon is Full and is aspected by all heavenly bodies, all evils are countered, just as lawbreakers are destroyed by the king. Venus aspecting the Full Moon, while the latter is in friendly divisions is capable of obstructing evils, just as abdominal remedies are able to cure windy diseases. 
5-6. Should the Moon be in her deep exaltation and be aspected by Venus, evils are countered, just as phlegm and bile are controlled by induced vomiting. If the Moon be in the divisions of benefic planets and be aspected by benefics, she will not prove evil though she may be waning, just as nutmeg bark treats dysentery. 
7-8. Benefics in the 7th, 8th and 6th from the Moon remove all adversities, just as madness is removed by Kalyana Grita. Same is the case, if the Moon is conjunct benefics and be in the decanates owned by benefics, just as saline water controls ear diseases. 
9-10. Should the full Moon be in a benefic's Dwadasamsa, all evils are removed, just as butter-milk checks piles. If the Moon occupies a benefic's Rāśi and receives the Lagna Lord's aspect, adversities for short-life are counteracted, as even a noble housewife can destroy the fame of the descent, if she seeks union with other men. 
11-12. Even though the Moon may be in a House owned by a malefic, or in such Vargas, she does not prove evil, if aspected by her dispositor. This is comparable-to a miser protecting his money. If the dispositor of the Moon is strong and be in aspect to benefics, or friendly planets, the Moon is not capable of harming, in comparison to a timid person, who cannot face others even though he may be in war field. 
13-14. If the Lord of the Moon Sign is in Lagna and is aspected by all planets, all evils are removed, just as the ointment of holy fig and bamboo bark removes whiteness. The Moon in her exaltation, own, friendly, or benefic Vargas, aspected by benefics, but not malefics counteracts all-evils, as the Sun does remove fog. 
15. Just as quartan fever is removed by inhaling Agashya flower, all evils are checked by Mercury and Venus in the 12th of Moon, malefics in the 11th and Jupiter in the 10th. 
16-17. Should the Moon be in the 6th, 3rd, 10th, 11th, or 4th from the natal Ascendant and be aspected by benefics, evils are removed, as though a king destroys his opponents. The Lord of the Moon Sign is singly capable of removing all evils, if he is with full strength and aspected by benefics, similar to an inebriated tiger throwing away a thousand deer. 
Thus ends the 11th Ch., entitled “Evils and the Moon” in Kalyana Varma's Saravali. Ch. 12. Evils Canceled at Birth 
1. A very brilliant Jupiter (i.e. not being devoid of rays) is capable of counteracting all evils, if he is in the Ascendant, just as a single sincere Prostration before Lord Vishnu, the wearer of Sudarshana Chakra, relieves one of the greatest sins. 
2. Benefics with strength and malefics without it remove all evils, if Ascendant falls in a benefic's House and is aspected by benefics, just as those, who worship planets will have no sins left to their liability. 
3-5. If malefics occupy the Rāśis and Amsas of benefics (i.e. such benefic divisions) and be in aspect to benefics, evils are removed, just as a dejected lady remains away from her husband. Should Rahu be in the 3rd, 6th, or 11th from the Ascendant and be aspected by benefics all evils are destroyed, as though wind carries away a heap of cotton with it. If all planets be in direct motion and in Seershodaya Signs, all blemishes are removed, just as ghee is burnt out in fire. 
6-7. A benefic planet victorious in planetary war at birth and essentially aspected by another benefic, destroys all evils, just as a gale can uproot trees. If a planet has a halo (in the sky) and is aspected by a malefic, evils are countered, just as the solar eclipse day bath in Kurukshetra does. 
8-9. If there is a pleasant breeze at the time of birth and the sky is with pleasing clouds and the heavenly bodies be with splendour, the evils disappear in a fillip, just as rains settle dust. If birth takes place, when Agasthya and others of Saptharshis (Alfa Carini, or Great Bear) rise, all evils are destroyed, just as darkness disappears, when the Sun rises. 
10-11. Rahu in the Ascendant identical with Aries, Taurus, or Cancer protects the native from the clutches of all evils, just as a pleased king forgives the crimes of a person. If all the planets (not of course the nodes) arc in their own decanates, all evils are removed, just as the Sun removes darkness. 
12. If at birth many planets are capable of giving benefic results, even then there is no blemish, just as the king gets success in journey undertaken, when the Moon is in a Trine to the Sun. 
13. Should Jupiter and Venus be in Angles, evils arising out of the various Rāśis (i.e. Bhavas) and of the Moon are countered. And the native lives for hundred years. 
14. If Jupiter and the Moon be in Cancer, identical with 4th, 10th, or the Ascendant, Mercury and Saturn be in Libra, while others are in the 11th, 3rd and 6th, one has illimitable longevity. 
15. I have thus explained the Yogas, that are capable of countering the evils, as laid down by our great ancestors May the astrologers please the king with the knowledge of these. 
Thus ends the 12th Ch. entitled “Cancellation of evils at birth” in Kalyana Varma's Saravali.  
