
Saravali 
Page 1
Ch. 1. Birth of Horāśāstra 1. Glory to the Sun-God, whose very breathing causes Creation in this world, with whose rising all the animals (living beings) wake up (from the sleep of their ignorance), whose state at the head (zenith) accentuates all activities (throws the brightest light on one's wisdom) and whose setting (absence, weakness) causes all to sleep. Such Sun-God has his efficacy spread (all over). 
2-4. Varaha Mihira in his Horāśāstra, i.e. Bŗhat Jataka, stated briefly the essence of the teachings of the learned sages viz. ten divisions of the Zodiacal Sign, Raja Yogas, longevity, effects of planetary periods etc. This could not be done elaborately by him and hence I am conveying in this work such useful essence, as called out from Yavanas etc., rejecting other unuseful portions, which may be appended to the said Brihat Jataka. 
5. I, Kalyana Varma, whose fame on account of patronizing Gods and administering villages and cities is brilliant, like that of a female swan in the cage of the universe, who is the king of Vyagrapada region, present this Saravali, an astrological treatise, with a chaste heart. 
6. Saravali is a river with chilly water, which has taken its birth in the mountain called Kalyana Varma, to ward off the thirst for astrology of those interested. 
Thus ends the 1st Ch. Birth of Horāśāstra in Kalyana Varma's Sāravalī 
Ch. 2. Meaning of Horā 
1-5. The Creator Brahma has written on the foreheads of all living beings their fates, which are deciphered by the astrologers through their pure insight. The first and last letters in the word Ahorātra are removed and the word Horā is thus born and has come to exist. The Zodiac and the planets are therein, as discussed. Some scholars say Horāśāstra is indicative of effects of one's Karma, i.e. fate. Some call Lagna, or half of a Rāśi, as Horā. In practice the science relating to horoscope is called Horāśāstra. Horā is capable of analyzing the destiny. Barring this Horāśāstra there is no device to help one earn money, to help, as a boat, to cross the ocean of unexpected situations and to serve, as an advisor in journey. 
Thus ends the 2nd Ch. Meaning of Horā in Kalyana Varma's Sāravalī 
Ch. 3. Rāśi Description 
1-2. At the time of Pralaya (Destruction) the Universe plunged into darkness and was flooded with water, when all of a sudden the Sun-God with his brilliant rays appeared in the Universe. He created all the planets and the 12 months. 
3-4. Description of the 12 Rāśis. The names of the 12 Rāśis are Aries, Taurus, Gemini, Cancer, Leo, Virgo, Libra, Scorpio, Sagittarius, Capricorn, Aquarius and Pisces. The Sign Aquarius resembles a man holding a pot, while Gemini is compared to a couple holding Veena and mace. A pair of fish is the imagination about Pisces. Sagittarius is compared to a man having a hip, like that of a horse and holding an arch in his hands. Deer-faced Sign is Capricorn. Virgo resembles a virgin sitting in a boat with a lamp in her hands. A male holding Scales in his hand represents Libra. The other Signs are identical with their names. 
5-6. The Limbs of KalaPurusha and their Use. The Signs Aries etc. represent the limbs of Kalapurusha, as under: Aries head, Taurus face, Gemini arms, Cancer heart, Leo stomach, Virgo hip, Libra space below navel and private parts, Scorpio private parts, Sagittarius thighs, Capricorn knees, Aquarius ankles, Pisces feet. If at birth one has benefic planet in a particular Sign, the particular limb will be strong. A malefic makes such a limb weak. 
7. Synonyms of Rāśis. Kriya, Tavuru, Jutuma, Kulira, Leya, Pathona, Jook, Kaurpika, Tauksha, Akokera, Hridaya Roga and Anthya are the other names given, respectively, to Rāśis from Aries onwards. 
8. Synonyms for Houses. Riksha, Rāśi, Kshetra, Bha and Bhavana are identical names given to a House by the sages. 
9-10. Zodiacal Halves, their Lords and Effects. The Rāśi Chakra with 12 Rāśis is called Bhagana. Six Signs counted from Leo to Capricorn consist of Solar Half and the Sun rules this Half-Zodiac. Six Signs in the reverse order from Cancer to Aquarius are Lunar Half and ruled by the Moon. Barring Cancer and Leo, planets from Mars to Saturn get one Rāśi each in each Half. If at birth more planets occupy the Solar Half, the native is brilliant and, if more planets are in Lunar Half, he is soft, good and lucky. 
11. The Rulers of Rāśis and Navāńśas. Mars, Venus, Mercury, Moon, Sun, Mercury, Venus, Mars, Jupiter, Saturn, Saturn and Jupiter are the Lords, respectively, of Aries to Pisces. The Navāńśas for these Rāśis are calculated from Aries, Capricorn, Libra and Cancer in their order. 
12. Sub-Divisions Essential. The effects of a horoscope should be predicted according to the divisions of Houses. Without knowing the strength of such Lords, one cannot lay even a step forward in the direction of astrology. 
13. Vargothamamsa. The first Navāńśa of a Movable Rāśi, the 5th one in a Fixed Rāśi and the 9th one in a Common (Dual) Rāśi are called Vargothamamsa. Should the natal Lagna be in such Vargothama Navāńśa, the native becomes an important person in his circle. The rulers of Dwadasamasas start from that Rāśi itself. 
14. Lords of Decanates and Horas. The Lords of decanates are first Lord of the same Rāśi, second Lord of the 5th Rāśi therefrom and third Lord of the 9th from the Rāśi in question. The first Hora of an odd Rāśi belongs to the Sun, while the second one is ruled by the Moon. In the case of an even Rāśi the first Hora is ruled by the Moon and the second by the Sun. 
15. Lords of Trimsamsas. In odd Signs 5, 5, 8, 7 and 5 degrees are Trimsamsas of Mars, Saturn, Jupiter, Mercury and Venus, respectively, while the arrangement is reverse in even Signs. 
16. Lords of Sapthamsas. The Sapthamsas for the 12 Rāśis from Aries onwards are, respectively, counted from Aries, Scorpio, Gemini, Capricorn, Leo, Pisces, Libra, Taurus, Sagittarius, Cancer, Aquarius and Virgo. The Lords thereof are those, in whose Rāśis they fall. 
l7. The total of the number of Horas and that of decanates is sixty (24+36) in the entire Zodiac. The figure is increased by 72, if the total of Horas + Navāńśas is required, i.e. 60+72=24+108=132. Each Rāśi has 1800 Kalas (30°, each of 60'). 18. Different Vargas. To know any kind of Varga (Hora, Navāńśa, Drekkana etc.) adopt the following method. Convert the longitude into minutes of arc and multiply by the Varga figure concerned. Divide the product by 1800. The resultant figure will reveal the required Varga. 19. The malefic and benefic effects of such Vargas are explained in detail in the Nashta Jataka chapters (at the end). 
20-21. Rāśis Benefic and Malefic, Gandanta and its Effects. From Aries onwards alternatively the Rāśis are known, as malefic and benefic on the one hand and male and female on the other hand. These are also classified, as Chara (Movable), Sthira (Fixed, Immovable) and DvisvaBhava (Ubhaya, Dual, Common) Rāśis. The ending portions of Cancer, Scorpio and Pisces are called Gandanta. It is said, that one born in Gandanta will not survive. He will either lose his mother, or he will end the dynasty, i.e. he is the last of his descent and will not have any children. If, however, he survives, he becomes a king with many elephants and horses. 
22. Directions of Rāśis. The four Rāśis from Aries onwards indicate East, South, West and North, while the remaining Rāśis repeat in the same way. A journey undertaken by a person towards the direction indicated by the Lagna, or the Moon (at the commencement of journey) yields fruitful results. 
23. DigBala and KalaBala. Human Signs, quadruped Signs, Scorpio and watery Signs are, respectively, strong in the directions commencing from the East. Further during night-time quadruped Signs, day-time human, or biped Signs and the second half of Capricorn, Scorpio, Cancer and Pisces are strong at the time of daybreak and of nightfall. 
24. Gemini, Cancer, Capricorn Aries, Taurus and Sagittarius are night Signs. Leo, Libra, Scorpio, Aquarius, Pisces and Virgo are day Signs. The Signs Cancer, Capricorn, Aries, Sagittarius and Taurus are called Prishtodaya, which rise with hind part. Sīrshodaya Signs (rising with head) are Leo, Libra, Scorpio, Virgo, Aquarius and Gemini. The Sign Pisces is Ubhayodaya (rises with both head and hind part). 
25. Strength of Rāśi. If a Rāśi is aspected by its Lord, or by a planet, that is friendly to its Lord, or by Mercury, or by Jupiter, it is said to be strong. Planets other than the above do not lend strength by aspect. 
26-27. Synonyms of 12 Bhavas. Lagna Thanu and Sakthi, Second Artha and Dhana, Third Sahaja and Parakrama, Fourth Bandhava and Griha, Fifth Putra and Pratibha, Sixth Ari and Vrana, Seventh Stri and Kama, Eighth Vinasa and Dehavivara, Ninth Punya and Guru, Tenth Karma and Mana, Eleventh Aya and Bhava, Twelfth Vyaya. 
28-31. Additional Synonyms. The 4th (Veśma) and the 8th are called, as Caturaśra Houses. The 9th is known, as Tapa, i.e. penance. The 4th has names, like耠Sukha (happiness), Jala (water), Patala (nether-world), Bandhu (relatives) and Hibuka. The other names given to the 10th House are Karma (deed), Agna (command), Gagana (sky, zenith) and Meshurana. The 5th and 9th are Trines. The 5th is the only House connected with Dhī, while the 9th is Tritrikona, the Trine of Trine. The 7th House is called Dyuna, Astha (setting), Jāya and Jamitra. The 6th is Shatkona, 3rd is Duschikya and 12th Rippha. Kutumba is the 2nd. 32. Kendra, Apoklima and Panaphara, Effects thereof. The adjoining Houses with reference to Angles (Kendras) are Panaphara. The Houses next to Panapharas are Apoklimas. The planets in Angles give effects in one's boyhood. The effects of planets in Panapharas are felt in the middle age, while the planets in Apoklima give result at the conclusion of the native's life. 
33. Upachaya and Anupachaya. The 6th, 10th 11th and 3rd are called Upachaya Houses, while the 1st, 2nd, 4th, 5th, 7th, 8th, 9th and 12th are Anupachayas. 
34. Moolatrikonas of Planets. Leo, Taurus, Aries, Virgo, Sagittarius, Libra and Aquarius are the respective Moolatrikonas for the planets from the Sun onwards. 
35-36. Exaltation and Fall. Aries, Taurus, Capricorn, Virgo, Cancer, Pisces and Libra, respectively, are the Signs of exaltation for the Sun, Moon, Mars, Mercury, Jupiter, Venus and Saturn. These are deeply exalted at 10, 3, 28, 15, 5, 27 and 20 Degrees in the respective Rāśis. The Rāśis opposite exaltation are the places of debilitation for the planets concerned. And the respective degrees are of deep fall. 
37-38. Long, Medium and Short Ascensions of Signs. Pisces, Taurus, Aries and Aquarius are Signs Of short ascension. Gemini, Sagittarius, Cancer and Capricorn are of medium ascension. The long ascension Signs are Scorpio, Virgo, Leo and Libra. The head and other organs of the native will be similar to the Sign ascending at birth and other relative Signs. The planets occupying such Houses will also influence the form and shape of the various organs. 
39. Favourable Directions for Journeys. The direction ruled by the Lord of a Rāśi becomes Plava direction for that Rāśi. This is Yavana's school of thought. If the king undertakes his journey towards such direction, indicated by the Rāśi concerned, he attains quick success. 
40-4l. Colours of Rāśis. From Aries onwards the following 12 colours are allotted to the various Rāśis, respectively, red, white, green, pink, brown, gray, variegated, black, golden, yellow, deep-brown and white. If an idol of the Lord of the Ascendant is made in the colour allotted and is worshipped, the native will destroy his enemies, just as Lord Indra destroyed the demons. 
Thus ends the 3rd Ch. Rāśi Description of Kalyana Varma's Saravali 
Ch. 4. Planetary Characters 
1-2. Kalapurusha's Soul etc. and their Use. The Sun is the soul of the Zodiac personified, the Moon mind, Mars strength, Mercury speech (voice), Jupiter intelligence, Venus comforts, Rahu ego and Saturn grief. If at birth planets indicative of soul etc. are strong, these significations will equally be strong. If these planets are weak, the effects are only meager. But in the case of Saturn it is different. 
3-6. The counting of limbs according to the decanate rising at birth should be identified, as under. If the first decanate rises, count from head. If second, from neck and, if 3rd, from pelvis. The 6 Rāśis backwards from the Ascendant denote the left side of the body, while the 6 forward Rāśis from Lagna indicate the right side of the body. Should the first decanate of a Sign ascend, the lapsed part of the Ascendant denotes left side of the head and the part to rise yet indicates the right side of the head, the 2nd and 12th denote right and left eyes, respectively, 3rd and 11th right and left ears, 4th and 10th right and left nose, 5th and 9th right and left cheeks, 6th and 8th right and left chins and the 7th left side of the face (area yet to rise) and the 7th right side of the face (portion already descended). If the 2nd decanate rises, neck, shoulder, arms, side, heart, stomach and navel are to be understood in the same order. Should the third decanate rise, pelvis, anus, penis, testicle, thigh, knee, calf and feet will be counted in the same order. The decanates occupied by malefics denote wounds etc., while the ones by benefics indicate marks (moles) on the limbs concerned. Should these planets be in their own Rāśi, or Amsa at birth, then the wound, or mole are right from birth. Otherwise these will be caused later on (in appropriate periods). 
7. Planetary Portfolios and their Use. The Sun and the Moon are said to be the kings. Mercury is the prince, Mars Army chief, Jupiter and Venus ministers, while Saturn is servant. The native acquires such qualities, as of the strongest planet. 
8. Planetary Directions. The Sun, Venus, Mars, Rahu, Saturn, the Moon, Mercury and Jupiter are, respectively, the Lords of the directions commencing from the East. 
9. Planetary Nature. Jupiter, Mercury and Venus are benefics in nature. Saturn, Mars and the Sun are natural malefics. Mercury in the company of malefics and the waning Moon are also considered malefics. 
10-11. Synonyms of Planets. Heli and Bhanu are the other names given to the Sun. The Moon is called Sasi. Krūradrik, Bhomisuta, Āra, Rakta and Vakra are indicative of Mars. Hemna, Vid, Gna and Bodhana denote Mercury. Īdya, Ijya, Angira and Jiva are the Jupiter's names. Āsphujit, Sita and Bhrigu means Venus. Manda, Kona, Yama and Krishna are Saturn's synonyms. For these planets there are various other names, which should be elicited from other texts. 
12-13. Planetary Colours, Deities and their Use. From the Sun onwards the respective hues of the planets are copper-red, white, blood-red, green, yellow, variegated and black. The deities for these planets are, respectively, Fire, Water, Kartikeya, Vishnu, Indra, Sachi Devi and Brahma. The planets from the Sun onward should be worshipped by the Mantras concerned and, if trips to the respective directions are undertaken one can gain gold, gems, elephants etc. 
14. Sex, Caste and Elements. The Moon and Venus are females. Mercury and Saturn rule neutrals. Males are Jupiter, the Sun and Mars. Brahmins are ruled by Jupiter and Venus. The Sun and Mars preside over the royal lot. The Moon rules Vaisyas. Saturn rules those of mixed breed, while Mercury presides over Sudras. The five primordial compounds, viz. Fire, Earth, Ether, Water and Air are, respectively, ruled by planets from Mars onwards. 
15. Planetary Tastes and Abodes. The planets from the Sun on are attributed tastes, as acrid, saline, bitter, mixed, sweet, sour (acidulous) and astringent. Their abodes, respectively, are temples, water resorts, fire houses, sports ground, treasury, bed-room and dirty places. 
16. Planetary Robes and Substances. From the Sun onwards the apparels attributed are coarse, new, burnt, water-soaked, neither new nor old i.e. recent, durable and a rag. Similarly copper, gem (?), gold (?), metal allay, silver (?), pearl (?) and iron are in their order denoted by the Sun etc., ending with Saturn. 
17. Periods and Ritus of Planets. Ayana, Muhurta, Ahoratna, Ritu (season), month, fortnight and year are, respectively, ruled by the planets from the Sun to Saturn. The seasons, viz. Sisira, Vasanta, Grishma, Varsha, Sarat and Hemanta are, respectively, ruled by Saturn, Venus, Mars, Moon, Mercury and Jupiter. 
18. Use of these. In the matter of winning enemies, delivery of child, or such questions materialization of the objective concerned will be, as per the period allotted to the Lagna Lord. This should be understood according to the Ascendant passed. 
19-20. Lords of Vedas and Worlds. Jupiter rules Rig Veda, Venus Yajur Veda, Mars Sama Veda and Mercury Atharva Veda. Jupiter denotes the Heavens, the Moon and Venus the world of the Manes, the Sun and Mars the World of mortals and Mercury and Saturn Hell. 
21. Description and Nature of the Sun. The Sun has curly hair, sharp mind, prominent appearance, majestic voice and is not very tall. His eyes are honey-coloured. He is courageous, steady and of a complexion, which has a mix of red and green. His feet are not conspicuous (small in size). He is bilious and has sturdy bones. He is great and majestic. He has fiery rays and square body and wears saffron-coloured apparels. 
22. Description and Nature of the Moon. She has an auspicious appearance. Her eyes are beautiful. She has mellifluous voice. She is fair in complexion, has an emaciated body, is youthful, tall, curly and short hair, is learned, soft, of Sattvik disposition, beautiful, phlegmatic, amicable to friends, has pure (excellent) blood, is kind, fond of old ladies, fickle-minded, very fortunate and wears clean apparels. 
23. Description and Nature of Mars. The planet Mars is short, his eyes are reddish-brown in colour. He has a strong body. He is as bright, as burning fire. He is not steady in disposition. He has marrow in bones and flesh. He wears red-coloured apparels. He is more intelligent and is courageous. He is an accomplished speaker. He causes injury. He has short and shining hair. He is bilious in disposition and is Tamasic. He is adventurous and wrathful and is skillful in hurting. He is blood-red in appearance. 
24. Description and Nature of Mercury. Mercury's eyes are reddish and broad. He speaks sweetly. His complexion is of green grass. He has strong skin. He is an extremely Rajasic planet. He is clear in his speech and is pure. He has a mixture of the three humours, i.e. phlegm, bile and wind. He remains delighted and has moderate beauty. He is skillful and sinewy. He is agreeable to all in dressing and speech and wears green robes. 
25. Description and Nature of Jupiter. The eyes of Jupiter are somewhat reddish-brown. He is learned in Vedas. His voice resembles that of a lion. He is firm and prominently Sattvik. His physical complexion is akin to pure yellow metal. He has broad and prominent chest. He is always fond of virtues and is modest. He has firm and large eyes and is of forgiving disposition. He wears yellow apparels, is phlegmatic, fat and pre-eminent. 
26. Description and Nature of Venus. The planet Venus is beautiful, has long hands, broad chest and face, is very seminal, splendourous, has dark, short and extended hair, is of complexion, which is a mix of yellow and green, is sensuous, windy and phlegmatic, very fortunate, wears multi-coloured apparels, is of Rajasic disposition, sportive, intelligent, broad-eyed and has prominent shoulders. 
27. Description and Nature of Saturn. Saturn has red and depressed eyes, emaciated body, prominent veins, is indolent, black-bodied and windy in temperament. He is a talebearer. He is muscular, unkind, foolish, has large nails and teeth, is very dirty, impure, Tamasic in disposition, fierce, short-tempered and old (worn out). He adores black apparels. 
28-29. Natural Friendship, Neutrality and Enmity between Planets. The Sun's friends are Jupiter, Mars and the Moon. The Moon's friends are the Sun and Mercury. The Sun, the Moon and Jupiter are friendly to Mars. Venus and the Sun are Mercury's friends. The Sun, Moon and Mars are friendly disposed to Jupiter. Saturn and Mercury are friends of Venus. Mercury and Venus are Saturn's friends. The Sun's enemies are Venus and Saturn. The Moon has no enemies. Mercury is inimical to Mars, while the Moon is Mercury's enemy. Venus and Mercury are the enemies of Jupiter. The Moon and the Sun are enemies of Venus. Saturn's enemies are the Sun, the Moon and Mars. If a planet is neither a friend, nor an enemy of another one, there exists neutrality among them. 
30. Temporary Friendship and Enmity between Planets. If a planet is in the 12th, 4th, 2nd, 10th, 11th and 3rd from another planet, then there is temporary friendship between the two. If the position is in the 6th, 7th, 8th, 1st, 5th, or the 9th, then there is temporary enmity among them. (This may be applied to a birth horoscope, horary horoscope, or any such other context) 
31. Five Kinds of Considerations of Relationship. Should there be temporary friendship and natural friendship between two planets, then they become extremely friendly. If there is natural neutrality and temporary friendship, there exists only friendship between two planets. If there is natural enmity and temporary friendship, they are neutral in relationship. Should they be naturally neutral and temporarily inimical, they are only inimical. If there is enmity both naturally and temporarily, then they are greatly inimical to each other. 
32-33. Planetary Aspects. Planets lend ¼ aspect on the 3rd and 10th, half aspect on the 4th and 8th, ¾ aspect on 5th and 9th and full aspect on the 7th from their positions. Saturn has special full aspect on the 3rd and 10th, Jupiter on the 5th and the 9th and Mars on the 4th and 8th. All planets aspect the 7th fully. 34. Planetary Strengths. To assess the auspicious and inauspicious effects of a planet, its directional, positional, temporal and motional strengths are important, for without these it is considered to be weak. 
35. Directional and Positional Strengths. Jupiter and Mercury have directional strength, while in the Ascendant (East), the Sun and Mars in the 10th (South), Saturn in the 7th (West) and the Moon and Venus in the 4th (North). If a planet is in exaltation, Mulatrikona, own House, friendly House, or own Navāńśa and aspected by a benefic, it assumes strength. The Moon and Venus are strong in even Rāśis, while the rest are so in odd Rāśis. This is called positional strength. 36. Temporal and Motional Strengths. The Sun, Jupiter and Venus acquire strength during day-time, while Saturn, the Moon and Mars become strong during night-time. Mercury acquires vigour at all times. The Hora Bala goes to Hora Lord, Masa Bala (Masa - month) to the Lord of the month, Dina Bala to the Lord of the week-day of birth and Abda (year) Bala is credited to the Lord of the year of birth. Malefics get strength in Dark Half, while benefics become strong in Bright Half. The planet, that is victorious in war, that is in its retrograde motion, or, that is not combust become strong. The Luminaries get strength in northern course. This is how Satyacharya detailed motional strength. 
37. Ayana Bala. Venus, Mars, the Sun and Jupiter are strong in Uttarayana, while the Moon and Saturn are strong in Dakshinayana. Mercury is strong in both the cases. This is called Ayana Bala. 
38. Drekkana Bala. Male planets are strong in the first decanate, female planets in the third decanate and neutral planets in the second decanate of a Rāśi. Planets are strong, only when they are away from the Sun, as per Yavanas. 
39. Tribhaga Bala, or Triamsa Bala. The Moon, Venus and Mars get this strength in the first, second and third parts of the night, respectively. This is similarly enjoyed by Mercury, the Sun and Saturn in day-time, while Jupiter has it always, irrespective of day, or night. 
40. Naisargika Bala (Natural Strength). Saturn, Mars, Mercury, Jupiter, Venus, Moon and Sun are stronger than the other in the ascending order. Should there be similarity in other strengths, then the one with greater natural strength prevails. 
Thus ends the 4th Ch. Planetary Characters of Kalyana Varma's Saravali 
Ch. 5. Miscellaneous Matters 
1. After discussing the Ch. Rāśi Prabheda (Ch. 3) and Graha Yoni Bheda, or Graha Gunadhyaya (Ch. 4) I now explain Misrakadhyaya (Miscellaneous Ch.), which is the most supreme of all. 
2-4. Avasthas, or States of Planets. Planets have nine states of being, viz. Dīpta (radiant), Svastha (confident), Mudita (rejoiced), Santa (peaceful), Sakta (strong), Nipīdita (oppressed), Bhita (alarmed), Vikala (mutilated) and Khala. A planet in its exaltation is said to be in Dīptavastha. In its own House, it is in Svasthavastha, friendly House Muditavastha, in beneficial Vargas Santavastha, with bright rays Saktavastha, in combustion Vikalavastha, if defeated in planetary war, Nipīdita, in malefic Vargas Khalavastha and, if in fall, in Bhitavastha. 
Notes. There are 27 Graha Samayas, i.e. planetary conditions. These will help us know, as to what a planet is doing at a particular moment with reference to either birth, or query. Such positions reveal specific results. How to calculate these positions and the effects thereof are noted below. Find out the number of Signs from Aries to Ascendant. Again find out in what number of Sign is the planet, for which (Samaya) is required, counted from Aries. Multiply these figures mutually and again the latest product be multiplied by the total number of Dasa period years of the planet, as per Vimsottari Dasha scheme. Divide this by 27 and the remainder indicates Graha Samaya (some scholars, however, advise, that the planet's position is to be counted from Lagna instead of Aries. It is wrong counting the planet's position from Lagna, as the Sloka clearly says, vide Jyotisharnava Navanītam). Let us assume, that in Virgo Lagna chart the Moon is in Sagittarius. Hence we count six Signs from Aries through Virgo Ascendant and get 6. Again from Aries to Sagittarius we get 9. Multiply 9 by 6 to get 54. The Dasha period of the Moon is 10. When we multiply 54 by 10, we get 540. This, when divided by 27, yields no balance and hence the 27th Samaya is denoted. 
Now the scheme of Samayas and their effects (1-27). Snana: good family, children, respect, success and position. Vastradharana: precious stones, money, position and clothes. Pundradharana: dear to people, gains in foreign countries, hard work and honour. Upadesa: lands, conveyances and happiness. Siva Pūja: fond of lands, royal wrath, expenses and litigations. Āposana: wealth, fond of wicked people. Vishnvarchana: bile, grief, highly learned. Vipraradhana: fortune, gains from lands, success over enemies, rich relatives. Namaskara: soft-spoken, conveyances and capability to speak on either side in arguments. Adri Pradakshina: bilious diseases, dysentery, litigations and penalties. Vaisyadeva: position with king, good family, perennial progress. Athithi Satkara: cheat, jimminks and monetary gains. Bhojana: sick, dismissed from the circle, cheating. Ambhapana: bad meal, bad acts. Ahamkara: egoism and enmity with people. Tambūla: good position, high learning, money and fame of high order. Nripalapa: respect, pious disposition, diviee cows. Kirītadharana: big position in Army, learned, wealthy. Ekanta Sambhashana: lazy, soft-spoken. Ālasya: abundant education, lazy, careless. Sayana: very short-tempered, sick, disputes in family. Amritapana: foolish, harmful, blaming elders, destruction (some texts prescribe good results, which only seem to be sensible). Madhupana: health, good children, beautiful wife, rich food. Dhanarjana: respect, much wealth, skilful. Bhikshatana: loss, bad teaching. Nidra: long-lasting diseases, drunkard. Sambhoga: attached to base women, cunning and revengeful. 
5. Effects of a Radiant Planet. Should a planet be in Dīpta state at birth, the native burns his enemies with the fire of his valour. He gathers all kinds of wealth. His (band of) elephants soak the surface of the earth with the juice, or ichor exuding from their temples. (That is the native will own a large number of elephants. See the simultaneous literary ability of Kalyana Varma. A number of such comparisons can be found in this work) 
6. Effects of a Confident Planet. Should a planet be in Svastha state at birth, the native acquires gold, family etc. He will be a justice in a king's employ. He will own houses and will amass grains. His family will prosper. 
7. Effects of a Rejoicing Planet. If a planet is in Mudita state at birth, the native will be pleasingly disposed, will have wife, gold, diamonds etc., will win the entire band of his foes and will enjoy all kinds of comforts in life. 
8. Effects of a Peaceful Planet. If a planet is in Santa, or peaceful state at birth, the native will have peaceful mind, comfort and wealth. He will be a king's minister, will be learned, helpful to others, religious and fortunate. 
9. Effects of a Śakta Planet. If a planet is in Śakta state at birth, the native will have wife, clothes, scents, garlands etc. He will be famous, liked by all and have his name spread all-over. 
10. Effects of a Hurt Planet. If a planet is in Pīdita (hurt, oppressed) state at birth, the native will be subjected to grief and sickness and will have enemies. He will be deprived of his own people and wander from one country to the other. 
11. Effects of an Alarmed Planet. Should a planet be in Bhita state at birth, the native, even, if he were a king with varied paraphernalia, will be troubled by enemies. He will lose his men. He will be defeated and will become poor. 
12. Effects of a Mutilated Planet. If a planet is in Vikala state at birth, the native will be deprived of his place, or position, dirty-hearted, poor and will wander here and there. He will be frightened by his enemies. 
13. Effects of a Planet in Khalavastha. Should a planet be in Khalavastha, the native will grieve in sorrow, due to maintaining his wife (the native cannot maintain even his wife), will lose all his wealth, will have an impure mind and be never free from miseries. 
14. Retrogression in Exaltation. If a planet is retrograde, while in exaltation, it produces no effect (nothing good will happen). This is the view held by some. Even, if it is in exaltation by its entry in retrograde motion from the next Sign (for example Jupiter entering Cancer from Leo), the effect is same, for it takes unduly long time in such traversion. 
15. Different Effects. A planet in exaltation is considered highly strong. It is medium in strength in its Mulatrikona Rāśi, or own House. Its strength is only nominal, if it be aspected by a friendly planet, or be in a friendly Rāśi. 
16-17. The elders among Yavanas say, that the Moon is of medium strength for ten days commencing from Sukla Padyami, i.e. first of Bright Lunar Half. During the following ten days (from the 11th day, or Ekadasi of Bright Lunar Half through the 5th day, or Panchami of Dark Lunar Half, or Krishna Paksha) she is exceedingly strong. And during the third ten-day period (from the 6th day, or Shashti of Dark Lunar Half through the New Moon day, or Amavasya) she has very little strength. If at birth the Moon has brilliant rays, is bright circled and full, it makes the native an unencounterable king. 
18. Good Results in Mid-Life. If at birth the Lord of Moon Sign, or the Lord of the Ascendant, or Jupiter be in Kendra, the native is happy in the middle of his life. 
19-20. The effects revealed by various Rāśis will correspond to the strengths of their Lords. Should two planets have identical strength, the one with higher Naisarga Bala will prevail. According to Chudamani Acharya the Ascendant's strength equals that of its Lord. 
21-24. Swakshetra, Mulatrikona etc. In Leo up to 20°, it is the Sun's and the rest is his own House. The Moon's exaltation zone is the first 3° of Taurus, with the remaining portion being her Mulatrikona. Up to 12° in Aries Mars is in Mulatrikona, the rest is his own House. Mercury in Virgo has the first 15°, as exaltation, the next 5 (15°1'-20°), as Mulatrikona and the remaining portion is termed, as own House. In Sagittarius first 10° is Jupiter's Mulatrikona, with the rest being own House. The first 5° in Libra is Mulatrikona of Venus and the balance his own House. Aquarius is Mulatrikona for Saturn in the initial 20° portion and the last 10° in Aquarius is his own House. 25. Effects of Exalted Planets etc. If a planet is exalted, it gives auspicious results to full extent. It is futile, if in debilitation. The results are limited in an enemy's camp. The auspicious effects given by a planet are ¼ in a friendly House, ½ in own House and ¾ in Mulatrikona Rāśi. 26. Inauspiciousness of Planets. A planet is fully inauspicious, if it is in its debilitation; it is somewhat better in inimical House. Its inauspicious effects are nil, if it is exalted, ¾ in friendly House, ½ in own House and ¼ in Mulatrikona Rāśi. 27. The planetary combination, that produces Utpata, the planet, that is combust by the Sun, with less brilliance, which is in debilitation, in enemy's camp, or, that is defeated in planetary war: such a planet not only loses its potence to be auspicious, but also becomes capable of bestowing malefic effects in full. 
28-30. Effects According to Exaltation etc. A planet in exaltation gives all kinds of wealth. It confers ministership, or leadership over Army, if in Mulatrikona Rāśi. If it is in own House, it gives happiness, money, grains, wealth etc. In a friendly House, it gives fame, splendour, abundant good fortune, long-lasting wealth and also wealth through king. A planet, that is in its own Hora, makes one courageous. 
31-33. A planet in its own decanate confers virtues, while the one in own Navāńśa makes one famous. Courage, wealth and fame are bestowed by a planet occupying its own Sapthamsa. One becomes devout and helpful, if a planet is in its own Dvadasamsa. A planet in own Trimsamsa gives happiness and good qualities. When a planet is aspected by a benefic planet, the native becomes wealthy, famous, fortunate, chief of all, beautiful and happy. 
34-35. If a planet is with Ojha, or Yugma Bala (strength by being in male, or female Rāśis), the native is worshipped by the public, expert in arts, pleased, immune to sickness and prone to fear of other Worlds. A planet with positional strength gives perennial happiness, friendship, courage, fixity of mind and independent profession, or work. 
36-38. A planet with directional strength takes the native to the direction ruled by it and gives clothes, jewels, conveyances etc. And the native is happy in such a direction. A planet with Ayana Bala similarly takes the native to its direction and confers various kinds of wealth apart from fame. In both the cases, the planets should not be combust, or debilitated. If a planet has Cheshta Bala, it sometimes gives kingdom, sometimes respect, sometimes money and yet sometimes increases the fame of the native. 
39. Effects of Retrograde Planets. A benefic, if retrograde, is strong and is capable of conferring kingdom. If a malefic is retrograde, it causes grief and purposeless wandering. 
40. Auspicious Planets. A planet with clear rays, or, that is conjunct with the Moon, or, that has won in a planetary war, is capable of bestowing complete happiness and kingdom, that cannot be seized. 
41. Diva Bala and Ratri Bala. A planet, that has Diva Bala, or Ratri Bala, is capable of conferring lands, elephants etc. Such a native defeats his enemies with courage and achieves kingdom and wealth. 
42. Effects of Lord of Year etc. The Lords of the year, month, week and Hora improve two-fold in their Dasas happiness, wealth and fame. That is the Lord of the month gives two-fold results, as against year Lord, the week Lord two-fold of month Lord and the Hora Lord two-fold of week Lord. 
43. Effects of Paksha Bala. A planet with Paksha Bala destroys enemies and confers diamonds, robes, conveyances, wife, gold, land and fame. 
44. Effects of a Planet with all Sources of Strengths. Should a planet have all kinds of strengths stated so far and be bright with unobscured rays, it confers kingdom exceeding the desires of the native. 
45. Benefic Planets with all-round Strength. If at birth benefic planets possess all-round strength, the native will have good habits, be truthful, upright, beautiful, splendourous and be an expert in all deeds, respectful towards the wise and Gods and will be blessed with scents, garlands, robes, ornaments etc. 
46. Malefics with all-round Strength. Should malefics be with such all-round strength at birth, the native will be a miser, will do bad acts, be selfish, jealous of virtuous people, intent on promoting quarrels, wicked, torturous, dirty, ungrateful, slanderous and ugly. 
47-50. Planetary Stages and Effects thereof. It is boyhood, if a planet is in its own House, or friendly House. In Mulatrikona Rāśi, it is in youth and in adolescence in exaltation. It is said to be in old stage, if it occupies an inimical House. A planet in debilitation is in extrimis. The corresponding effects are felt in the respective planetary Dashas, i.e. periods. The results for such stages are, respectively, happiness, virtue, kingdom, sickness with debts and death, or expenses. 
51-52. Effects of Planets in Odd and Even Rāśis. A planet in odd Rāśi with strength makes the native courageous and a warrior. If it is weak in odd Rāśi, the native is cruel and dull-witted. A planet in even Rāśi gives soft nature, fear for quarrels, love for water, flowers and clothes, good fortune, health and protection of own men. 
Thus ends the 5th Ch. Miscellaneous Matters in Kalyana Varma's Saravali 
Ch. 6. (Yoga) Karakas 
1. Karaka Planets. Planets posited in own House, Mulatrikona, or exaltation and simultaneously in Angles become mutual Karakas, or significators. Such kind of Yoga Karakas (co-workers) are counted only in regard to Lagna's Angles. This view is held by Acharya Hari. 
2. For example Saturn in Libra, while Cancer Ascendant containing Jupiter and the Moon and Mars with the Sun in Aries become mutual Karakas. 
3. Planets posited in exaltation, friendly Rāśi, own Rāśi, or Amsa also become Karakas. The Sun in the 10th, as above, becomes greatly significant. This is Chanakya's opinion. 
4. Planets though not in Vargas, like own House, become Karakas, if they are in Lagna, 4th, 10th, or even the 11th. But this view is not acceptable to great sages. 
5-6. Effects of Karakas. Even though a person may be born in base strata, he will become chief, if he has Karaka Grahas. One born in royal family without doubt becomes a king in such a case. While analyzing the Yogas, such Karakatwas are along important and effects should be declared only on that basis. 
Thus ends the 6th Ch. entitled Karakadhyaya in Kalyana Varma's Saravali 
Ch. 7. Planetary Indications 
1. Lord of Week-Day etc. The Sun, the Moon, Mars, Mercury, Jupiter, Venus and Saturn rule the week-days etc. Whichever planet becomes the Lord of the first week-day in the month of Aswina in the year of Aswina, will become the Lord of month and year. 
2-3. The fourth planet counted from the Lord of the first year rules the second year. Similar counting of fourth Lords for the subsequent years should be made to know the Lords thereof. There are 24 Horas (planetary hours) in each day (from one Sun-rise to the next). The first Hora is ruled by the Lord of the week day, while the subsequent ones are ruled by the Lords of the sixth week-days thereof. Thirty (Savana) days make one (Savana) month. To know the Lord of the week-day in particular month, the months past should be multiplied by 30, increased by one and divided by 7. The remainder represents the Lord of the week-day counted from the earlier week-day Lord. 
4. A Savana month has 30 days and each month, viz. Chaitra, Vaisakha etc., commences with the first day of Bright half and ends with the 30th Thiti (Amavasya). 
5-6. Bhava Effects. The good effects relating to a Bhava can be better reaped, if an enterprise relating to that Bhava is started in an Ascendant ruled by the Lord of that Bhava, or, when the Lord thereof is in an Upachaya House, or on the week-day, Hora, year, or month ruled by that Bhava Lord. The good effects will be 25% by year Lord, 50% by month Lord, 75% by Lord of week and 100% by Hora Lord. 
7-13. Planet's Rulerships. The Sun rules snakes, wool, hills, gold, weapons, poison, fire, medicines, kings, Aryas (foreigners in general), river banks, forest, wood and Mantras. The Moon indicates poets, flowers, eatables, beads, silver, conch, salt, water, arrow, robes, ornaments, females, Ghī, sesamum, oil and sleep. Mars rules blood, copper, Army, red cloth. Mercury minerals, earth, king, destruction, swooning, bile and thieves. Mercury rules Veda, writing, sculpture, medicines, expertise, ministership, speech, jokes, birds, couples, fame, Vanaspathi (a large forest tree, which bears fruit apparently without any blossoms) and gold. Jupiter rules auspiciousness, virtue, physical stoutness, prowess, preceptorship, deputation, city, state (province), gold, bed, conveyance, position, grains, residence and sons. Venus rules diamonds, ornaments, marriage, scents, friends, wreaths, females, cow dung, diagnosis (apart from meaning diagnosis also indicates end, purity, rope to tying up a calf etc.), education, sexual enjoyment and gold. Saturn is Karaka for lead, zinc, black metals, inferior grains, dead relatives, fools, servants, mean women, salable goods, poor people and self-restraint (apart from meaning self-restraint also means investing with sacred thread, which is in vogue to give “second birth” to Brahmins). 14-15. Planetary Places. The Sun rules Kalinga (a Coromandel district), the Moon Yavana (Greek, Mohamedan, or European countries), Venus plain river banks, Jupiter Sindhu (Indus), Mercury Magadha (southern part of Bihar), Saturn Saurashtra (Gujarat), Mars Ujjain and the nodes Dravida country (five tribes: Dravida, Karnataka, Gūrjara, Maharashtra and Tailanga). 
Thus ends the 7th Ch. entitled Karakadhyaya in Kalyana Varma's Saravali.  Next > 
