
Saravali 
Page 10
Ch. 46. Female Horoscopy 
l. Whatever horoscopic effects have been stated for males are equally applicable to females too. Explained in this Ch. are rules peculiar to the fair sex. 
2. IMPORTANT HOUSES. From the 8th House, her widowhood can be deduced, while the Ascendant deals with her physique, the 7th House with her husband's good fortunes and the 5th House with her offspring. 
3-4. THE MOON AND ASCENDANT. If the Moon and the Ascendant are both disposed in even Signs, the female will be virtuous and extremely good-looking. Should these two be in aspect to auspicious planets, she will be endowed with ornaments and virtues. In case these two occupy odd Signs, she will be akin to a male in appearance and in disposition. With these two receiving aspects of malefics, she will be sinful and bereft of virtues. 
5. TRIMSAMSA POSITIONS. Note the stronger of the Moon and the Ascendant. Whoever of the two is placed in the Trimsamsa of Mars, Venus, Mercury, Jupiter, or Saturn, such effects will come to pass, (as detailed below). 
6-10½. EFFECTS OF THE MOON/ASCENDANT IN VARIOUS TRIMSAMSAS. If it is a Sign owned by Mars, the Trimsamsa of Mars denotes a harlot, that of Venus a female devoid of virtuous history, that of Mercury one with cunning disposition, that of Jupiter a chaste lady and that of Saturn one in servitude. Should a Sign of Mercury house the Moon/the Ascendant in the Trimsamsa of Mars, the female will be cunning, in the Trimsamsa of Venus one with high degree of lust, in the Trimsamsa of Mercury a chaste girl, in the Trimsamsa of Jupiter a virtuous housewife and in that of Saturn impotent. If it is a Sign of Venus, the Trimsamsa of Mars denotes a female with wicked nature, Venusian Trimsamsa one with fame for her virtues, Mercurian Trimsamsa skillful, Jupiterian Trimsamsa a virtuous female and Saturn's Trimsamsa a woman given in marriage, as a second wife. In the Sign owned by the Moon the Trimsamsa of Mars bestows her freedom not due to a housewife, Venusian Trimsamsa will make her unchaste, Mercurian Trimsamsa will bestow skill in arts, Jupiterian Trimsamsa will make her quite virtuous and in Saturn's Trimsamsa she will betray her husband. In Leo the Trimsamsa of Mars will make the female garrulous, Venusian Trimsamsa chaste, Mercurian Trimsamsa male-natured, Jupiterian Trimsamsa a queen and Saturn s Trimsamsa fallen. 
11-13. TRIMSAMSA EFFECTS (continued). In a Sign of Jupiter the Trimsamsa of Mars will make her a gentlewoman with many (of the seven principal) virtues, the Trimsamsa of Venus a female with evil speech, the Trimsamsa of Mercury one with knowledge, the Trimsamsa of Jupiter one with many virtues and the Trimsamsa of Saturn a female desiring limited physical union. Lastly in a Sign owned by Saturn, a Trimsamsa of Mars will make one servant, that of Venus intelligent, that of Mercury cruel and devoid of conduct, that of Jupiter a chaste lady and that of Saturn himself one addicted to base men. 
14. BEASTLY LUST OF A FEMALE. When Venus and Saturn are in mutual aspects in the case of a birth in Taurus, or Libra Ascendant with Saturn's Navāńśa, the female concerned burnt with sexual lust will unite with a woman playing the role of a male. Venus and Saturn should simultaneously be in exchange in Navāńśas owned by them. 15-17. THE 7th HOUSE. Should the 7th House be vacant, her husband will be a contemptible fellow. With the said House bereft of aspect of a benefic, he will be bereft of strength. He will be disposed to living in other places, if the 7th House is a Movable Sign. He will be a eunuch with Mercury, or Saturn in the 7th House. She will be discarded by her husband, if the Sun is in her 7th House. Mars in the said House will cause early widowhood, while Saturn in the 7th with malefic aspects will make her old soon. Again she will be given up by her husband with malefics being weak and combust in the 7th receiving aspects from malefics. Benefics and malefics combust in the 7th will give away the woman native in second marriage. 
18. UNCHASTITY. If Venus and Mars exchange their divisions, the female will go after other males. If the Moon be simultaneously in the 7th House, she will join others with consent of her husband. 
19. MOTHER AND DAUGHTER. If a Sign of Mars, or Saturn be ascending with Venus and the Moon in it in aspect to malefics, the female along with her mother may be deemed unchaste. 
20. MISCELLANEOUS. If the 7th House falls in a Navāńśa of Mars and be in aspect to the Moon (Saturn, according to some texts), the female will have a diseased vagina. A Navāńśa of Venus denotes a fortunate female, who will be dear to her husband. 
21-24. EFFECTS OF RULERS OF 7th•HOUSE/NAVĀŃŚA. If the 7th House, or its Navāńśa be ruled by Saturn, the female's husband will be old and foolish. The ruler ship of Mars in such a case will give a husband, who will be addicted to other women and be irascible. If Venus heads the 7th House, or its Navāńśa the husband will be very beautiful and be fortunate. The husband will be skillful and knowledgeable, if Mercury be such a planet. A sexually tormented husband, who will, however, be soft in disposition will be bestowed by the Moon in such circumstances. The husband will be virtuous and be a conqueror of the five senses, if Jupiter rules the 7th House, or its Navāńśa. Leo, as the 7th House, or the 7th Navāńśa will indicate an industrious and a very intelligent husband. Thus the effects relating to the rulership of the 7th House and 7th Navāńśa be declared in respect of males. 25-26. EFFECTS OF PLANETS IN THE ASCENDANT. She will be jealously disposed and be happy with Venus and the Moon in the Ascendant. Mercury replacing Venus in the said Yoga will make the female happy, skillful in arts, virtuous and modest. If Mercury and Venus are together in the Ascendant, the female will be beautiful, fortunate and skillful in arts. Benefics in the Ascendant will endow a female with servants, happiness and robes, while malefics give adverse effects in regard to these. 
27. EFFECTS OF THE 8th HOUSE. Malefics in the 8th will cause widowhood. This will occur in the Dasa periods of the Lord of the Navāńśa occupied by the 8th Lord. A benefic in the 2nd will, however, cause the female's death in this Yoga, instead of widowhood. 
28. LIMITED PROGENY. If the 5th House be one of Virgo, Scorpio, Taurus and Leo receiving the aspect of a benefic, there will be limited number of children Alternatively, the said 5th House may be conjunct a benefic, or the Moon. 
29. FEMALE WITH MASCULINE DISPOSITION. Should Mercury, Venus and the Moon be in the Ascendant and be weak, while Saturn has moderate strength, as the rest are strong, the female concerned will be akin to a male in appearance and in acts. The Ascendant should in this case necessarily be an odd Sign. 
30. TAKING TO RELIGIOUS ORDER. A female will be initiated into a religious order, if a malefic is in the 7th House, while the 9th House is occupied by any planet. The order will relate to the planet in the 7th House. 
31. VEDIC EXPONENT. If strong Mercury, Jupiter, Venus, or the Moon be in the Ascendant identical with an even Sign, the female will be a teacher/exponent of Vedas (or be a follower of Vedanta Philosophy). And she will be an expert in interpretation of various Shastras. 
32. APPLICATION. Whatever has been stated in this Ch. should be wisely applied to females relating to their births, selection of grooms, marriage and query. These effects are applicable to their husbands also. 
Thus ends the 46th Ch. entitled ‘ FEMALE HOROSCOPY” in Kalyana Varma's Saravali. Ch. 47. Aphorisms of Death 
1. REASONS OF DEATH. If the 8th House is occupied by any planet from the Sun to Saturn, the reason for death in the same order will be fire, water, weapon, fever, indigestion (or constipation), thirst and hunger. According to the 8th House being a Movable, Fixed, or Dual Sign, the place of death will be a foreign place, own place, or on the way. 
2. Death may be due to the imbalance of that humour belonging to the planet aspecting the 8th House. If there is no planet in the 8th House, the aspecting one may indicate the kind of death. If many are thus related, the strongest one will prevail. 
3. DEATH BY DROWNING, FALL ETC. If the 10th and 4th are occupied by the Sun and Mars, the native will die due to fall from hills. If the 10th, 7th and 4th Houses are occupied by Mars, Mercury and Saturn, it may be due to fall in a well. Death due to imprisonment will follow, if the Luminaries are placed in Virgo in aspect to malefics. The end will be by drowning, if Pisces is occupied by the Sun and the Moon. 
4-5. DEATH BY FIRE ETC. If the Moon and Saturn, respectively, are in Capricorn and Cancer, death will be due to affliction of stomach. If the Moon be hemmed between malefics and occupies a Sign of Mars, fire/weapons will cause death. Death will be certainly inflicted by dryness of blood, if the Moon is in Virgo hemmed between malefics. 
6-7. DEATH BY HANGING ETC. If the Moon in Capricorn, or Aquarius be hemmed between benefics, death will be due to hanging, fire, or fall, which is doubtless according to Chanakya. The same effect will come to pass, if the 5th and 9th Houses are occupied by malefics in aspect to malefics. If the drekkana of the 8th House be one of Pasa, Sarpa and Nigala, death will be reticent. 
8. DEATH DUE TO A FEMALE. If the Sun be in Pisces Ascendant, while the Moon is in the 7th (in Virgo), or in the 2nd in Aries, or in the 5th in Cancer, a female will be reason for the native's end. 
9. DEATH DUE TO A TRIDENT'S HIT. If the 4th House is occupied by Mars, or the Sun, while Saturn is conjunct weak Moon in the 10th House and malefics are in the Ascendant and its Trines, hit of a trident will cause the end. 
10. DEATH BY HIT OF WOOD. If the Sun is in the 4th, while the Moon devoid of strength is in the 10th along with Mars, or in aspect to Saturn, the native will be hit by a log. 
11. DEATH BY HIT OF A CLUB etc. If weak Moon, Mars, Sun and Mercury along with Saturn are in the 10th, 8th, 4th and Ascendant (in any way), the subject will have his end due to a club beat. If these planets fill the 10th, 9th, 5th and Ascendant, death will be by smoke, fire, confinement, or a blow of fist. 
12. DEATH DUE TO ROYAL WRATH. If the 4th, 7th and 10th Houses are occupied by Mars, the Sun and Saturn, death will be due to weapon, fire, or royal wrath. 
13-14. DEATH DUE TO INSECTS, INTOXICANTS AND MACHINERY. One's end will be due to insects, if the 10th, 4th and 2nd Houses at his birth are occupied by Mars, the Moon and Saturn. If the 10th House is constellated by the Luminaries and Mars, the native will end his life on account of intoxicants, or fall from height. Machinery will be the source of one's death, if the 7th House is occupied by Mars, as the trio of weak Moon, Saturn and the Sun afflict Ascendant by occupation. 
15-16. DEATH IN FILTHY SURROUNDINGS. One will die amidst ordure, if Mars is in Libra, the Sun in Aries/Scorpio and the Moon in Capricorn/Aquarius. The Sun, weak Moon and Mars in the 8th, 10th and 4th Houses, will kill one amidst excrement. So says Siddhasena. 
17-18. DEATH BY THIRST, WEAPONS AND BIRDS. If the 8th House contains both the weak Moon and Saturn in aspect to strong Mars, the subject will die due to spleenary disorders, colics, thirst, or weapons. The Sun and Mars in the 7th, while Saturn occupies the 8th and the Moon the 4th, one's death will be caused by birds. 
19. If the Ascendant, 8th, 5th and 9th Houses are occupied by the Sun, Mars, Saturn and the Moon, death will be due to fall from a hill, hit of a weapon, or fall of a wall etc. 
20. Yavanas indicate, that the place of death will correspond to the Navāńśa Lagna Lord. The aphorisms stated in this Ch. should be suitably interpreted according to other aspects and other conjunctions. 
21. The duration of the state of loss of consciousness (or insensibility, delusion, pain etc.) will correspond to the portion elapsed in the radical Ascendant. The duration will remain doubled and trebled according to the Ascendant Lord, or a benefic aspecting the Ascendant. 
22. KHARA DREKKANA. The 22nd decanate from the Ascendant will denote the nature of one's death. For example, by the nature of its Lord, (i.e. the humour, place etc.) 
23-24. EFFECTS OF ARIES DECANATES AS RELATED TO DEATH. If the first decanate of Aries be the 22nd decanate from the Ascendant and be in aspect to a malefic the native's death will be due to water (i.e. drowning etc.), snake, poison, or bilious imbalances. If the 2nd decanate of Aries be so related, water, insects, ice and forests will cause death. The 3rd decanate of Aries denotes tanks, well etc. 
25-26. DECANATES IN TAURUS. If the first decanate of Taurus be the 22nd decanate at birth, death will be caused by animals, like ox, horse, donkey, camel etc. The second decanate in Taurus denotes the end due to bilious/windy complaints, fire and thieves. The concluding decanate of Taurus leads to one's death in journey, or due to fall from the back of a horse, or due to hit by weapon in battle. 
27-28. DECANATES IN GEMINI. If the first decanate of Gemini be the 22nd decanate at birth, one's end will be due to tuberculosis, or pulmonary disorders. The second decanate in Gemini identical with 22nd decanate denotes death through a buffalo, or through poison, or delirium. If the 3rd decanate in Gemini becomes the 22nd decanate the end will be through forest tribes, quadrupeds in general, or elephants in particular. 
29-30. DECANATES IN CANCER. If the 22nd decanate is the first decanate of Cancer, the reason of death will be a crocodile (or a shark), wine, thorn, or dreams. The second decanate will cause end by beating, or by consuming of poison. The terminating decanate indicates death by respiratory diseases, urinary diseases (viz. gleet, diabetes etc.), spleenary disorders, affliction to blood, or by swooning caused by excessive labor. 
31-32. DECANATES IN LEO. The 22nd decanate identical with the first decanate of Leo will cause one's end due to water, poison, or diseases of the foot. The second decanate of Leo indicates death by diseases caused by water, or movements in forests. The last decanate thereof will bring one's end through poison, weapons, calumny, or fall from heights. 
33-34. DECANATES IN VIRGO. Should the death decanate be the first decanate in Virgo, one's life will end due to diseases of the head, or by wind, (gale, hurricane, or outburst of violent wind etc.,) The middle decanate in Virgo will cause death by snake-bites, or in hills, forts, forests etc., or by the son of a king. The concluding decanate in Virgo will bring death by camels, asses, weapons, water, deep pits, females and unhealthy eating and drinking. 
35. DECANATES IN LIBRA. When the 22nd decanate at birth is held by the first decanate of Libra, death will be through a female, or quadrupeds, or fall from heights. The middle decanate of Libra denotes end on account of stomachial diseases, while last decanate indicates snakes, or animals living in water, as a source of death. 
36-37. DECANATES IN SCORPIO. The first decanate in Scorpio, if designated, as the 22nd decanate at birth, poison, weapons, females, (unhealthy) food and drinks will bring one's death. The second decanate in Scorpio indicates death through robes, weights, falls and diseases. The last decanate of Scorpio will inflict death by being stoned, or by breakage of shank bones. 
38-39. DECANATES IN SAGITTARIUS. The first decanate of Sagittarius being the 22nd decanate at birth, denotes, that death will be due to various windy disorders, or due to diseases of the anus. The second decanate will cause one's end to poison, or faults of elders, or windy diseases. The concluding decanate will inflict death in water, or through abdominal disorders. 
40-41. DECANATES IN CAPRICORN. The opening decanate of Capricorn will bring death through royal torture, or through tigers. The middle decanate will inflict death on account of damage to thighs, or through creatures/animals living in water, poison, snake, fire, weapons, robbers, fever and living beings other than human beings. The last decanate will bring end through a female. 
42-43. DECANATES IN AQUARIUS. The first decanate in Aquarius will bring death through females, water, hills, elephants and stomachial disorders. The middle decanate denotes one's end through miseries caused by a female, venereal diseases etc., while the third decanate will cause death through copulation, facial diseases and quadrupeds. 
44-15. DECANATES IN PISCES. If the first decanate of Pisces be related to death, it will be due to diarrhea, spleenary, or urinary disorders affliction to stomach/thighs, females, elephants, or planetary evils. If the second decanate be so related, one's end of life will come through a tragedy in a boat and the third one denotes death due to dreaded diseases. 
Thus ends the 47th Ch. entitled “APHORISMS OF DEATH” in Kalyana Varma's Saravali. Ch. 48. Lost Horoscopy 
1. When the time of birth, or time of conception is unknown, through horary method the lost birth details can be traced. 
2. The effects of ten divisions (Dasa Vargas) will help to arrive at the natal Ascendant. These ten divisions are explained infra, the first being the effects of Ascendant. 
3-6. EFFECTS OF BIRTH IN ARIES ASCENDANT. One born in Aries Ascendant will be highly susceptible to fire, be interested in visiting foreign places, be miserly in disposition, emaciated, not happy, be jealous, stammering in speech, troubled by bilious and windy diseases and complaints of heat, be skillful in performance, timid, religious, not very intelligent and will destroy others' wealth. He will be fickle-minded. He will enjoy pleasures, be famous, will have bad (ugly) nails, be bereft of brothers, be discarded by his father, will walk fast, will have inactive (or unlucky) children, be endowed with various kinds of wealth and be, virtuous. His wife will belong to a base family, be virtuous and be reproached even by her own people. The native will derive happiness and wealth in undesirable manners. 
7-9. EFFECTS OF BIRTH IN TAURUS ASCENDANT. One born in Taurus Ascendant will be brave, will endure miseries, be happy, will destroy his enemies, will have the tendency of gathering wealth right from boyhood, will have broad and strong forehead, nose, cheeks and lips, be industrious, fortunate, devoted to parents, liberal, will have many expenses, be very short-tempered, be phlegmatic and windy in humour, be the father of (many) daughters, will insult his own men, be devoid of religion, be interested in women, fickle minded, be fond of food and drinks and be endowed with various kinds of robes and ornaments. 
10-13. EFFECTS OF BIRTH IN GEMINI ASCENDANT. One born in Gemini Ascendant will have a dear wife, be fond of ornaments, charitable, respectable, will have two mothers, will be favourable even to his enemies, be interested in music, fine arts, Vedas, Shastras, amusement, poetry etc., gentle, fond of beautification, be conceit, truthful, impatient, will have evil sons, be crafty, will have a few relatives, will possess limbs of irregular sizes, will have round eyes, be fierce in appearance, will destroy even fearful enemies and will be endowed with lands, jewels, gold etc. 
14-17. EFFECTS OF BIRTH IN CANCER ASCENDANT. One born is Cancer Ascendant will be timid, will have many residences, be fickle minded, learned, intelligent, enduring, troubled by diseases of the anus, will destroy his enemies, be crooked in disposition, sensuous, will honour Brahmins and Gods, be religious, very phlegmatic, will possess a physique, akin to that of a female, be honoured for his virtues, will be preceded by sisters in birth, be bereft of relatives, will have a few children, will have a censured family and a vile wife, will enjoy others' wealth, be firmly obstinate, will live in foreign places, be valorous in his deeds, be courageous, will earn through water (i. e. products related to water, sea travel etc.) and be endowed with wife, ornaments, robes and happiness. 
18-21. EFFECTS OF BIRTH IN LEO ASCENDANT. One born in this Ascendant will be fond of eating meat, will earn wealth and honour through the king, be bereft of religion, be dutiful in family affairs, will have a face, resembling that of a lion, will hold a high rank of office, be majestic, strong, bold, will speak sparingly, be a miser, will trouble others, be desirous of (eating or) worldly enjoyments, will wander in hills and forests, be irascible, be firm in friendship, be careless, inaccessible (or inviolable), will destroy his enemies, will have famous sons, will honour the virtuous, be rich through agriculture etc., interested in business and will spend heavily on prostitutes, dancers and his own wife and will suffer dental diseases. 
22-25. EFFECTS OF BIRTH IN VIRGO ASCENDANT. One born in Virgo Ascendant will be gentle, skillful in training (or teaching others), music, poetry and fine arts be a sweet speaker, be affectionate, interested in charitability and serving others, will sport with virgins, be endowed with goodness, merciful, will enjoy others' wealth, will wander, will have a female's disposition, be modest, be a liar, will attempt to enlarge his landed properties, be fortunate, sensuous, famous, virtuous, beautiful, will honour elders, be sinful, inimical to brothers, will have (more) daughters, be phlegmatic and windy in humour and will be away from base and inimical people. 
26-29. EFFECTS OF BIRTH IN LIBRA ASCENDANT. One born in Libra Ascendant will have a crooked physique, be bereft of virtues, be fickle minded, will have increasing and decreasing wealth, be bereft of physical happiness, be phlegmatic and windy in humour, be fond of promoting quarrels, will have a long face and a long physique, be virtuous, learned, very miserable, very intelligent, will injure others' honour, will possess beautiful and black eyes, will honour guests, Gods and Brahmins, will perform Yagnas etc., will respect preceptors (or elders), be respectable, will help the helpless, be truthful, will have a beautiful body, will be affectionate to brothers, be pre-eminent, chaste, will yet help sinners, will have mean profession, be charitable, be religious and baseminded. 
30-33. EFFECTS OF BIRTH IN SCORPIO ASCENDANT. One born in Scorpio Ascendant will have fleshy and broad limbs, (as though) perfected by exercises, be clever, crooked in innate disposition, valorous, attached to his mother inclined to quarrel, generous, will have majestic and tawny eyes, a prominent chest, a sunken belly and depressed nose, be adventurous, firm, fierce, trustworthy, amusing, be troubled by bilious complaints, will have a big family, will betray his preceptors (or elders) and friends, be engaged in attracting other women, will have an attractive face, will serve a king, will have enemies, be pious, will give his money to others, will possess an amiable wife, be religious, affectionate and base. 
34-37. EFFECTS OF BIRTH IN SAGITTARIUS ASCENDANT. One born in Sagittarius Ascendant will have big teeth and prominent forehead, will patronize dependents, be courageous, strong, just, will have very fat thighs and belly, be skillful in Shastras, be of high intelligence, be irascible, short tempered even with mighty men, be important among the men of his race, will destroy enemies, be famous through battles, will fault his relatives, be interested in fine arts etc., will have own profession, will do good to his men, be splendourous, be afflicted with facial and eye diseases, will earn wealth through royal favours and be virtuous. 
38-41. EFFECTS OF BIRTH IN CAPRICORN ASCENDANT. One born in Capricorn Ascendant will have an emaciated body, be timid, will have a face, akin to that of a deer, be troubled by windy diseases, will have a bright and elevated nose, be not mighty, will have many sons, be hairy-bodied, will have broad feet and hands, be devoid of conduct and virtues, be tormented by thirst (or morbid heat), be dear to the fair sex, will wander in hills and forests, be valorous, will have knowledge of Shastras, Vedas, fine arts, music and musical instruments, will have little strength, be a householder, be hostile, wicked, ill disposed to relatives, splendourous, will have a wicked wife, will not be a talebearer, be wealthy, virtuous, will serve a king, be very liberal, happy and fortunate. 
42-45. EFFECTS OF BIRTH IN AQUARIUS ASCENDANT. One born in Aquarius Ascendant will indulge in mean acts, be principal among the men of his race, be foolish, will have blown and sharp nose, be base, irascible, indolent, inclined to enmity, dissatisfied, harsh, be fond of gambling and of base females, will not be helpful to relatives, be agitated, will have checkered prosperity, will acquire wealth, be a talebearer, be crafty, will suffer penury, will face loss of relatives, be prohibited (in social circles), be not agreeable, will acquire great wealth and will honour elders. At birth Aquarius is not an auspicious Ascendant for ever, according to Satyacharya. Yavanas go a step further, stating, that even Aquarius Vargas are not auspicious (at birth), while Chanakya does not consider such divisions inauspicious. 
46-49. BIRTH IN PISCES ASCENDANT. One born in Pisces Ascendant, will be fortunate, will have well blown nose and unblown (not wide open) eyes, will be interested in profane knowledge and poetry, be respectable, famous, will have exposed lips and teeth, be tormented by leprosy, will have an afflicted face, be courteous, trustworthy, will be endowed with goats, she-goats etc., will have pure conduct, will have knowledge of Vedas, be courageous, will have (more) daughters, be modest, gently disposed, be mighty, will have knowledge of music and sexual union, be virtuous, liberal, will gain through brothers and will have good relatives. 
If the ascending Sign, or the Lord of the Ascendant is strong, the effects stated will fully come to pass (in regard to all Ascendants). 
Thus ends the 48th Ch. entitled “LOST HOROSCOPY (through rising Signs)” in Kalyana Varma's Saravali. Ch. 49. Effects Of Horas 
1-2 HORAS IN ARIES. If the first Hora of Aries ascends at birth, the native will roll his eyeballs unnecessarily, be cruel, rich, very bright in appearance, will have a fierce wife, be tall, irascible and be a leader of thieves. 
If the second Hora of Aries ascends at birth, the native will be a thief, be careless, will have afflicted foot, fingers etc., large eyes and tall stature and be very intelligent. 
3-4. HORAS IN TAURUS. If the first Hora of Taurus ascend at birth, the native will be dark in complexion, will have broad eyes, fore face and chest, be eminent, disposed to carnal pleasures and will have strong bones and strong physique. 
If the second Hora of Taurus ascend at birth, he will have broad, long and round (i.e. muscular) limbs, be liberal, will have attractive hair, thin waist and eyes, akin to that of an ox. 
5-6. HORAS IN GEMINI. If the first Hora of Gemini be the Ascendant, the native will have a long waist, be very skillful, will have a moderate physique and soft hair and feet, be courageous and fond of sexual union, be wealthy and learned. 
Born in the second Hora of Gemini, one will have beautiful and large eyes, be sensuous, soft, be a gifted speaker and be attached to others' housewives. 
7-8. HORAS IN CANCER. If the birth be in the first half of Cancer, one will be endowed with elevated body, (i.e. be prominent in appearance), a beautiful head, eminence and intelligence, be weak sighted, will have limbs moving off and on, be crafty, dark in complexion, ungrateful and will have broken teeth. 
If the birth be in the second half of Cancer, he will be fond of gambling and travels, will have a broad chest, be quite truthful, irascible and will have a harsh physique. 
9-10. HORAS IN LEO. One born in the first Hora of Leo will have blood-red eyes, be bold, be endowed with a large and long physique, be crooked, happy and decidedly firm in his undertakiugs. 
One born in the later half of Leo will be fond of women, sweets, foods, drinks and robes, will move frequently, will have a harsh physique, be liberal, fond of travels, will have a few sons, will enjoy pleasures and be firm in friendship. 
11-12. HORAS IN VIRGO. If the birth be in the initial half of Virgo, the native concerned will have a soft and beautiful body, be a sweet speaker, be fond of music, females and sexual union, be sweet, fortunate and excellent. 
Born in the second half of Virgo one will be short-statured, will have knowledge of Hatha Yoga and Vedas, will possess a big head, be agreeable, argumentative, learned in service, drawing and writing, will have checkered prosperity and (yet) be happy. 
13-14. HORAS IN LIBRA. If the first Hora of Libra ascends at birth one will have a round face, elevated nose and back and large eyes, be sportive, will have a strong body and strong bones, be wealthy and will be affectionate to his men. 
If the second Hora of Libra ascends at birth, he will be very wealthy, will have firm wealth, will be endowed with black and curly hair, be crafty, round-eyed, will have a strong lower body and attractive skin and will have defective feet. 
15-16. HORAS IN SCORPIO. One born in the first half of Scorpio will have blood-red eyes, be adventurous in acts, be valorous in battle, wicked, fond of females and be rich. 
If born in the second half of Scorpio, one will have broad, well grown, long and fleshy limbs, will serve a king, will have many debts and many friends and will possess blown eyes (expanded, as a flower). 
17-18. HORAS IN SAGITTARIUS. One born in the first half of Sagittarius will possess a wide and split face and chest, with eyes and neck contracted (i.e. small), will be discarded by elders in boyhood and be pious. 
If the later half of Sagittarius rises, one will possess eyes akin to the petals of a lotus and long arms, will have knowledge of Shastras, be good in appearance, will speak sweetly, be fortunate and famous. 
19-20. HORAS IN CAPRICORN. If the first half of Capricorn be on the Ascendant, the native will be dark in complexion, will possess eyes, like that of a deer, be fortunate, will conquer women, be beautiful, crafty, opulent, will eat purified food, will do good acts and will have elevated nose. 
If born in the second half of Capricorn one will have blood-red eyes, be indolent, be interested in long travels, be foolish, dark in complexion, will have a hairy physique, be clever and fierce. 
21-22. HORAS IN AQUARIUS. One born in the first half of Aquarius will be endowed with a female and with friends, be a person of tastes, or feelings (or be an alchemist), be soft in disposition, will have a few sons, be virtuous, valorous, will be endowed with physical complexion akin to copper, be radiant and interested in travels. 
If born in the second half of Aquarius, one will have copper-brilliant eyes, be emaciated, firm, very insignificant in appearance, indolent, not outspoken, very dejected, miserly and very crafty. 
23-24. HORAS IN PISCES. One born in the first 15 degrees of Pisces will be short-statured, be endowed with broad and beautiful body, a large fore face, large face and broad chest, be dear to women, be very famous, skillful and valorous. 
If born in the second Hora of Pisces, one will be liberal, will have an elevated nose, be skillful, intelligent, will possess charming eyes be dear to king and will speak affably. 
25. The (good effects) due to a Hora will come to pass in full measure, if either the Sun, or the Moon is strong in aspect to the Ascendant Lord, or, if the Ascendant Lord is himself in an Angle. 
Thus ends the 49th Ch. entitled “EFFECTS OF HORAS (lost horoscopy)” in Kalyana Varma's Saravali. Ch. 50. Effects Of Decanates 
1-3. DECANATES IN ARIES. One born in the first decanate of Aries will be charitable, be a thief, be splendourous, will have checkered prosperity, be fierce in battle (or in quarrels), pleasing in appearance and will inflict punishment on relatives. 
If born in the second decanate of Aries, he will be attached to females, will wander, be interested in carnal pleasures and music, be intelligent, be endowed with friends and wealth, be good-looking and will have an eye on women's property. 
If born in the third decanate of Aries, he will be virtuous, will fault others, be fickle minded, mighty, will serve a king, be attached to his own men, be very righteous and honourable, but not learned. 
4-6. DECANATES IN TAURUS. If the birth be in the first decanate of Taurus, one will be fond of food and drinks, be tormented due to separation of his wife, endowed with robes and ornaments and will act according to the desires of his wife. 
If the birth be in the second decanate of Taurus, one will be beautiful, liked by women, will have large lips, be endowed with beauty and wealth, firmly wealthy, intelligent and attached to mean women. 
If the birth be in the third decanate of Taurus, one will be skillful, be not very fortunate, be valorous, dirty and will repent after spending money. 
7-9. DECANATES IN GEMINI. One born in the first decanate of Gemini will have broad and excellent limbs, be wealthy, lofty, deceiving, virtuous, sportive, honoured by the king and be a good speaker. 
One born in the second decanate of Gemini will be miserly, dreaming, conquered by the fair sex, self respected, endowed with co-born, fickle-minded, sportive and tormented by many diseases. 
One born in the third decanate of Gemini will hate women, will have a large head, will have enemies, be lofty, will possess rough nails and will not have firm wealth. 
10-12. DECANATES IN CANCER. One born in the first decanate of Cancer will honour Brahmins and Gods, be fickle-minded, fair in complexion, will help others, be intelligent, pleasing in appearance, will possess a fortunate wife and be himself fortunate. 
One born in the second decanate of Cancer will be miserly, dreaming, conquered by the fair sex, self-respected, endowed with co-born, fickle minded, sportive and be tormented by many diseases. 
One born in the third decanate of Cancer will lose his firmness to females, be wealthy, intent on living in foreign places, fond of wine, be virtuous, will have liking for forests wine, have diseased eyes and will like garlands etc. 
13-l5. DECANATES IN LEO. One born in the first decanate of Leo will be liberal, will maintain people, will conquer his enemies, will have abundant wealth, many wives and good friends, will serve many kings and be very mighty. 
One born in the second decanate of Leo will perform beneficial acts, be liberal, firm, fond of quarrels, happy, will follow the rules of Vedas and be intelligent. 
One born in the third decanate of Leo will be a miser, will steal others' wealth, be free from sickness, hard-hearted, very intelligent, roguish, will have a narrow physique, be pre-eminent and will have many children. 
16-18. DECANATES IN VIRGO. One born in the first decanate of Virgo will be dark in complexion, will speak affably, be modest, lofty, beautiful, will gain wealth through females, be ominous and will have a long head and honey coloured eyes. 
One born in the second decanate of Virgo will be bold, will live in foreign places, be skillful in fine arts, fables and battles, be garrulous, will honour Vedic teachings and be dear to forest tribes. 
Birth in the third decanate of Virgo indicates one enjoying music and other's wealth. He will be dear to king, short in stature and will be endowed with large head and large eyes. 
19-21. DECANATES IN LIBRA. If the Ascendant be in the first decanate of Libra, one will be akin to Cupid in physical charm, be skillful, will enjoy travels, be dark in complexion, fond of arts and business, will fulfill appointed tasks and be very learned. 
If the Ascendant be in the second decanate of Libra, one will have eyes of the lotus-kind, be charming, affable in speech, valorous, famous and will perform acts to increase the reputation of one's race and family. 
If the Ascendant be in the third decanate of Libra one will be fickle minded, crafty, ungrateful, crooked, will lose friends and wealth and will not be very intelligent. 
22-24. DECANATES IN SCORPIO. If birth be in the first decanate of Scorpio, the native will be fair in complexion, firm in disposition, fierce in temperament, interested in battle, broad-eyed, fat and broad physiques and fond of promoting quarrels. 
One will be fond of purified food, be skillful, will have rolling eyes, be gold-coloured in complexion, splendourous, endowed with other's wealth, virtuous and skillful in arts, if the Ascendant be in the second decanate of Scorpio. 
One born in the third decanate of Scorpio will be devoid of beard, mustache etc., be torturous, will have tawny eyes and large belly, be an assailant, will incur loss of brothers and will possess long hands and brave heart. 
25-27. DECANATES IN SAGITTARIUS. One born in the first decanate of Sagittarius will have a round face and round eyes, be chief among his men, will advance due to his own efforts, will have good conduct and be soft in disposition. 
If the birth be in the second decanate of Sagittarius, one will be expert in Shastras, be a good speaker, will perform hundred yagnas (i.e. many sacrifices), will have knowledge of Mantras, be excellent in disposition and will visit many shrines. 
If born in the third decanate of Sagittarius, one will be chief of his relatives, be skillful, will always take to virtuous path, be sensuous, will enjoy other women, be charming, famous and successful. 
28-30. DECANATES IN CAPRICORN. One born in the first decanate of Capricorn will have long hands, be dark in complexion, charming, famous, crafty, sparing in speech, be conquered by ladies, will perform superior acts and be wealthy. 
One born in the second decanate of Capricorn will have a small face, be fickle minded, will steal the wealth of other women, skillful, be a fortune-teller, be liberal and will suffer from diseases of the feet. 
One born in the third decanate of Capricorn will be garrulous, dirty, emaciated, long-limbed, devoid of father and will be reduced to evils in foreign places. 
31-33. DECANATES IN AQUARIUS. One born in the first decanate of Aquarius will be endowed with wife, honour and fame, be very efficacious, lofty, devoted to his duties, wealthy and will serve a king. 
If born in the second decanate of Aquarius, one will be a miser, be skillful, sweet, fair complexioned, tawny and broad eyed, will earn wealth through amusement, will speak unhesitatingly, be intelligent and will be endowed with many friends. 
If born in the third decanate, one will be tall in stature, crafty, valorous, emaciated, short-armed, be endowed with sons and wealth, hard-hearted, will tell many lies, be crooked in nature, will have afflicted eyes and will have knowledge of sexology. 
34-36. DECANATES IN PISCES. If the Ascendant is in the first decanate of Pisces, one will have honey coloured and tawny eyes, be fair in complexion, very learned, will perform virtuous deeds, be happy, will undertake trips by sea etc. and be modest. 
If it be the second decanate of Pisces, one will be skillful in serving the fair sex, will eat purified food, will enjoy others' wealth, be sensuous, dear to females and virtuous people and be an excellent person. 
If born in the last decanate of Pisces one will be dark in complexion, be skillful in arts, will have wide feet, will be generous with friends and will consume purified food and drinks. 
37. Thus spoke of the decanates the preceptors well-versed in that branch. Should the Sign holding the decanate be strong, or be aspected by its Lord, these effects will mature in full. 
Thus ends the 50th Ch. entitled “EFFECTS OF DECANATES (lost horoscopy)” in Kalyana Varma's Saravali. Ch. 51. Effects Of Navāńśas 
1. A native's complexion, disposition and appearance can be deduced based on the rising Navāńśa at birth. The effects being stated infra will depend on the stronger of the two, viz. the Moon's Navāńśa dispositor and the Navāńśa Lagna Lord. 
2-10. EFFECTS OF NAVĀŃŚAS IN ARIES. Following are the effects of births in the nine Navāńśas in Aries Ascendant: Effects of Aries Ascendant, First Navāńśa: The native will have a face, resembling that of a he-goat, with nose and shoulders not being very prominent. He will have a fierce voice, ugly appearance and narrow eyes. His body will be thin, but free from defects. Effects of Aries Ascendant, Second Navāńśa: The native will be dark in complexion, will have broad shoulders and long arms. small forehead, strong collar bones, sharp sight and prominent face and nose. He will be an affable speaker and will possess weak legs. Effects of Aries Ascendant, Third Navāńśa: The native will suffer loss of hair, be fair in complexion, will have irregular (defective) arms, charming eyes and nose, will be a scholar in direct poetic ability and will have weak thighs. Effects of Aries Ascendant, Fourth Navāńśa: The native will have an erratic sight, be irascible, short-nosed, wandering-natured, will have rough legs and coarse hair, be bereft of co-born and emaciated. Effects of Aries Ascendant, Fifth Navāńśa: The native will be fierce and will have eyes, resembling that of a supreme elephant, a fat nose, thick eye brows, wide fore face, fat body and coarse hair. Effects of Aries Ascendant, Sixth Navāńśa: The native will be dark in complexion, soft in disposition, will have eyes, akin to that of a deer, be tall in stature, will have irregular (defective) stomach and hands, be a eunuch, be timid and garrulous. Effects of Aries Ascendant, Seventh Navāńśa: The native will have complexion akin to green sprout, be fickle-minded, will possess white eyes, will marry an unchaste lady, be malicious and will have a broad physique. Effects of Aries Ascendant, Eighth Navāńśa: The native will have a face, akin to that of a monkey, be a good speaker, will have an afflicted and tawny body, will suffer from secret diseases, be torturous, be a liar, be fond of friends and be fierce. Effects of Aries Ascendant, Ninth Navāńśa: The native will be tall, emaciated, wandering, will have defective fore face and ears, will have a face, akin to that of a horse, will possess many names and be crooked. 
11-19. EFFECTS OF NAVĀŃŚAS IN TAURUS. Following are the effects due to births in the Navāńśas belonging to Taurus Ascendant: Effects of Taurus Ascendant, First Navāńśa: The native will have an even and dark coloured physique, be hard-hearted, will perform obsequies in the beginning and ending parts of his life, be base, will indulge in unnatural acts and will have crooked sight. Effects of Taurus Ascendant, Second Navāńśa: The native will be endowed with majestic looks, be indolent, will have a bent body, be not very intelligent, will indulge in hostile acts and be a great liar. Effects of Taurus Ascendant, Third Navāńśa: The native will be erratic in sight, be fierce, will have a short nose, be wandering natured, will have coarse legs and hair will have soft limbs, be beautiful, will have broad eyes and big limbs, be interested, in Sacrifices etc. and will have stiff legs and hands. Effects of Taurus Ascendant, Fourth Navāńśa: The native will be short in stature, will be wandering natured, be easily irritable, will have eyes, akin to that of a he-goat, be tawny in complexion, be poor and will steal others' wealth. Effects of Taurus Ascendant, Fifth Navāńśa: The native will be vicious, will have a well-elevated nose, will appear, like a giant ox, will have crooked hair, be sportive, will have large shoulders and hips. Effects of Taurus Ascendant, Sixth Navāńśa: The native will have beautiful eyes and hair, be firm, be endowed with a fair complexioned physique, will speak sweetly, be pre-eminent, be fond of amusements, be emaciated and skillful. Effects of Taurus Ascendant, Seventh Navāńśa: The native will be interested in females, who lost their sons, will have somewhat elevated nose and prominent eyes, will possess a strong physique, will hate his own men and will have stout feet and exquisite hair. Effects of Taurus Ascendant, Eighth Navāńśa: The native will have eyes, akin to that of a tiger and charming teeth, be unconquerable, will possess a full-blown nose, will work sparingly, will have curly and bluish hair and sharp nails and be garrulous. Effects of Taurus Ascendant, Ninth Navāńśa: The native will be honourable, will not be very strong, be timid, given to anger, will possess an even and charming body, be a rogue (or cheat), will gather money, be famous, will have a thin lower body and will prattle. 
20-28. EFFECTS OF NAVĀŃŚAS IN GEMINI. Following are the effects of births in the nine Navāńśas of Gemini Ascendant: Effects of Gemini Ascendant, First Navāńśa: The native will have hair on the shoulders, will possess charming and dark eyes and an elevated nose, be akin to green (Durva) grass in complexion and will possess thin legs and thin hands. Effects of Gemini Ascendant, Second Navāńśa: The native will have a pot-like head, will do dirty acts, be fond of torturous deeds, will have depressed nose, will speak much, will work much and will lead in strife and quarrels. Effects of Gemini Ascendant, Third Navāńśa: The native will be fair in complexion, will possess blood-red eyes, charming nose and even physique be very intelligent, will have a long face and dark eye-brows and be a skillful speaker. Effects of Gemini Ascendant, Fourth Navāńśa: The native will possess charming eye brows and forehead, be lustful, will possess a physique with the splendour of a blue lotus, will be broad-chested and white teethed, be soft in speech and will have attractive hair. Effects of Gemini Ascendant, Fifth Navāńśa: The native will have a broad face, strong chest and big head, be wicked, cunning and will possess charming and friendly looks. Effects of Gemini Ascendant, Sixth Navāńśa: The native will possess eyes with the hue of honey, be garrulous, will possess a broad fore face, even body and charming lips, be a rogue, be fickle-minded and be strong. Effects of Gemini Ascendant, Seventh Navāńśa: The native will possess a copper coloured physique, copper red and prominent eyes and a broad chest, be skillful in teaching and arts and be jocular in disposition. Effects of Gemini Ascendant, Eighth Navāńśa: The native will be dark in complexion, be great, intelligent, soft in disposition, sweet in speech, will have a broad and tall physique and large and black eyes and will be an expert in arts. Effects of Gemini Ascendant, Ninth Navāńśa: The native will have round and dark coloured eyes and charming body, be successful, very intelligent and be fond of sexual cohabitation, poetry and worldly knowledge. 
29-37. EFFECTS OF NAVĀŃŚAS IN CANCER. Following are the effects for births in various Navāńśas related to Cancer Ascendant: Effects of Cancer Ascendant, First Navāńśa: The native will have a clean, charming and fair coloured physique, beautiful hair, broad belly, impressive face, prominent eyes, thin body and thin shoulders. Effects of Cancer Ascendant, Second Navāńśa: The native will be blood red in complexion, be fierce in quarrels, will like fine arts, will possess face and eyes, akin to that of a cat, will be well disposed to sacrify for others and will have weak knees and shanks. Effects of Cancer Ascendant, Third Navāńśa: The native will be fair in complexion, will possess beautiful eyes, be an eloquent speaker, will have a soft body, akin to that of a female, be intelligent be a sparing and light worker and be indolent. Effects of Cancer Ascendant, Fourth Navāńśa: The native will be black in complexion, will have pressed eyebrows, be graceful in appearance, will have charming eyes and nose, be courageous, liberal, will perform acts prescribed for superior caste-men and be crafty. Effects of Cancer Ascendant, Fifth Navāńśa: The native will possess voice akin to the sound of bell, crooked, or stooping face, allied eyebrows and very long arms, be interested in worship, be bereft of dutifulness, will injure others and be not very intelligent. Effects of Cancer Ascendant, Sixth Navāńśa: The native will have a long and broad physique, charming eyes and great courage, be fair in complexion, be a good speaker and will possess beautiful nose and big teeth. Effects of Cancer Ascendant, Seventh Navāńśa: The native will have scattered hair, big body and sinewy knees, will be disposed to protect others' families and will be akin to a crow in appearance. Effects of Cancer Ascendant, Eighth Navāńśa: The native will have a head with bell shape, charming face, shoulders and limbs, will be a degraded artisan (i.e. an infamous worker), will have the gait of a tortoise and crooked nose and be dark in complexion. Effects of Cancer Ascendant, Ninth Navāńśa: The native will be fair complexioned, will possess eyes resembling fish, be great, be soft-bellied, broad-chested, will have prominent chins and lips, large, but weak knees and similar ankles. 
38-46. EFFECTS OF NAVĀŃŚAS IN LEO. Following effects will mature in the various Navāńśas prevailing in Leo Ascendant at birth: Effects of Leo Ascendant, First Navāńśa: The native will have an even belly (like a lion), be fierce, will have sharp and blood-red nose and a big head, be valorous and will possess a prominent and fleshy chest. Effects of Leo Ascendant, Second Navāńśa: The native will have a prominent and broad fore face, a square body, broad eyes, broad chest, long arms and big nose. Effects of Leo Ascendant, Third Navāńśa: The native will have hairy and broad arms, eyes, akin to that of (Greek) partridge (said to live on moon-beams), be fickle-minded, charitable, will have an elevated nose, pure white physique and round neck. Effects of Leo Ascendant, Fourth Navāńśa: The native will have (ash-coloured) body akin to ghee, large and black eyes, soft hair, peculiar voice, big hands and legs and stomach, resembling that of a frog. Effects of Leo Ascendant, Fifth Navāńśa: The native will have a bell-shaped head with limited hair, charming nose and eyes, hairy body and long belly, be fierce and will have unsightly teeth and strong and broad cheek. Effects of Leo Ascendant, Sixth Navāńśa: The native will have limited, but soft hair on his physique, white and large eyes, be tall in stature, dark in complexion, will have proven skill (only) among females, be swaggering and be learned. Effects of Leo Ascendant, Seventh Navāńśa: The native will have a long face, be sinewy, will have a prominent physique, be unfortunate in the matter of wife (or females in general), dark-complexioned, fierce, hairy-bodied and be cunning and harsh in speech. Effects of Leo Ascendant, Eighth Navāńśa: The native will be endowed with excellent speech, firm limbs, charming and majestic looks, be undutiful, poor and crafty. Effects of Leo Ascendant, Ninth Navāńśa: The native will have a face akin to a donkey's, will possess dark eyes, long arms, charming legs and be troubled by breathing disorders. 
47-55. EFFECTS OF NAVĀŃŚAS IN VIRGO. The various Navāńśas emanating from Virgo Ascendant at birth will give the following effects: Effects of Virgo Ascendant, First Navāńśa: The native will possess eyes, akin to that of an antelope, be a good speaker, be charitable, will enjoy sexual pleasures, be very rich, dark in complexion and large hearted. Effects of Virgo Ascendant, Second Navāńśa: The native will have a charming face, charming eyes and fair complexion, be soft, argumentative, fickle minded and long-bellied. Effects of Virgo Ascendant, Third Navāńśa: The native will have blown nose, prominent feet, long arms, pure speech, fair complexion and be friendly. Effects of Virgo Ascendant, Fourth Navāńśa: The native will be learned, will be sportive with the fair sex, be beautiful, sweet, blood red in complexion, sharp, intelligent, emaciated and will have charming eyes and face. Effects of Virgo Ascendant, Fifth Navāńśa: The native will have large lips and hands, big body, broad chest, strong ankles and will depend on others. Effects of Virgo Ascendant, Sixth Navāńśa: The native will have charming appearance, impressive speech, splendourous body, be an exponent of Shastras, be very intelligent, skillful in writing and fine arts, be good hearted and will take pleasure in walking, or roaming. Effects of Virgo Ascendant, Seventh Navāńśa: The native will have a small face, elevated nose, compact arms, very fair complexion, prominent belly, hands and legs and will have fear for water. Effects of Virgo Ascendant, Eighth Navāńśa: The native will be very beautiful, fair in complexion, tall in stature, will have charming eyes, be fierce, honourable and will have long and stout arms and brown hair. Effects of Virgo Ascendant, Ninth Navāńśa: The native will be famous, will have charming physique, broad eyes, incomparable vigour, be skillful, be with stooping shoulders and be learned a writer. 
56-64. EFFECTS OF NAVĀŃŚAS IN LIBRA. The various Navāńśas out of Libra Ascendant at birth will produce following effects: Effects of Libra Ascendant, First Navāńśa: The native will be fair complexioned, broad eyed, praiseworthy, long-faced, skillful in business, happy and famous. Effects of Libra Ascendant, Second Navāńśa: The native will have squint and round eyes, elevated (ill formed) teeth, depressed waist, charming neck, large (physical) heart, ugly body and compact brows. Effects of Libra Ascendant, Third Navāńśa: The native will be fair in complexion, will have a face, akin to that of a horse, be thin-bodied, famous, long-haired and long-nosed and will have beautiful legs. Effects of Libra Ascendant, Fourth Navāńśa: The native will have weak hands, be timid, will have ill-formed teeth (some placed over others), weak body, rolling eyes, small nails, dark complexion and be devoid of virtues and be miserable. Effects of Libra Ascendant, Fifth Navāńśa: The native will have majestic looks, be firm disposition, be not proud, rough haired, even-eyed and will possess a beautiful nose. Effects of Libra Ascendant, Sixth Navāńśa: The native will have fleshy limbs, be fair in complexion, will have broad eyes, beautiful nose and white nails, be diplomatic and be learned in Shastras. Effects of Libra Ascendant, Seventh Navāńśa: The native will be blood-red in complexion, be intelligent, will have long physique and long arms and a big head, be miserly, fierce and intelligent. Effects of Libra Ascendant, Eighth Navāńśa: The native will have elevated shoulders and prominent neck, will enjoy pleasures, will have a coarse physique, long and dark brows, be a polite speaker and will have a beautiful chest and bruised head. Effects of Libra Ascendant, Ninth Navāńśa: The native will have charming eyes, pleased mind, be fair complexioned, even and beautiful bodied, be skillful, fond of arts, be charitable and jocular. 
65-73. EFFECTS OF NAVĀŃŚAS IN SCORPIO. The Ascendant Scorpio will produce various following effects according to the nine Navāńśas thereof. Effects of Scorpio Ascendant, First Navāńśa: The native will be short in stature, will have prominent lips and nose, charming forehead, strong and fair complexioned body with belly, akin to that of a frog and will act, as a marriage broker (ascertaining genealogies and negotiating marital alliances). Effects of Scorpio Ascendant, Second Navāńśa: The native will be fair in complexion, will possess a strong and broad chest and shoulders and reddish eyes, will conquer his enemies be valorous and will have abundant hair. Effects of Scorpio Ascendant, Third Navāńśa: The native will be learned, will have strong shoulders and arms and beautiful hair, be endowed with clear speech, fair complexion and charming lips. He is born of a virgin. Effects of Scorpio Ascendant, Fourth Navāńśa: The native will be intent upon joining others' wives, will induce others to be active, be valorous, tall, dark in complexion, dark-haired and dark eyed. Effects of Scorpio Ascendant, Fifth Navāńśa: The native will be majestic, will possess copper-red eyes, depressed nose, be courageous, proud, will perform fearful acts, be famous and will have a strong physique. Effects of Scorpio Ascendant, Sixth Navāńśa: The native will be impudent, intelligent of a high order, will have elevated nose and great strength, will be endowed with knowledge of justice (or be diplomatic), be skillful, will possess less hair and compact brows. Effects of Scorpio Ascendant, Seventh Navāńśa: The native will have a split face, strong body, teeth in various sizes, depressed belly, squint sight and be very splendourous. Effects of Scorpio Ascendant, Eighth Navāńśa: The native will have blown nose, be dark in complexion, devoid of virtues, dirty in appearance, will possess stiff hair and be foolhardy. Effects of Scorpio Ascendant, Ninth Navāńśa: The native will have a fair coloured physique, be beautiful, like a deer, will possess calm and tawny eyes and similar hair and strong body and be amiable to elders. 
74-82. EFFECTS OF NAVĀŃŚAS IN SAGITTARIUS. The native born in Sagittarius Ascendant, but in its various Navāńśas will obtain following effects: Effects of Sagittarius Ascendant, First Navāńśa: The native will have charming big nose, will possess sight, akin to that of a goat, be a gifted speaker, will have charming teeth and hair, be fair in complexion, will have inset testicles and be fierce. Effects of Sagittarius Ascendant, Second Navāńśa: The native will have a prominent head, be firm in disposition, will have large eyes, strong waist and knees, ugly nose, tall stature and firm cheeks. Effects of Sagittarius Ascendant, Third Navāńśa: The native will have skill in educating and in fine arts, be majestic, just, fond of females, intelligent and jocular. Effects of Sagittarius Ascendant, Fourth Navāńśa: The native will be skillful, be tawny in complexion, will possess round eyes, fair-coloured physique and a belly akin to tortoise, be intelligent, wandering-natured, will have charming hair and charming appearance. Effects of Sagittarius Ascendant, Fifth Navāńśa: The native will have large ears, eyes and face, will possess a (majestic) physique, like a lion, widely spread eye brows, strong shoulders and arms, hairless physique and firm disposition. Effects of Sagittarius Ascendant, Sixth Navāńśa: The native will have beautiful and large eyes, broad forehead and broad face, be a poet, be mean and interested in scholarly discussions. Effects of Sagittarius Ascendant, Seventh Navāńśa: The native will be dark in complexion, soft in disposition, will keep up his promise, will have a prominent head, will be interested in accumulating savings, be tall in stature, will possess broad eyes and be liberal. Effects of Sagittarius Ascendant, Eighth Navāńśa: The native will be flat-nosed, broad headed, inimical, erratic sighted, garrulous and be dear to elders. Effects of Sagittarius Ascendant, Ninth Navāńśa: The native will be fair in complexion, will have a face, akin to that of a horse and broad and dark eyes, will speak sparingly, be truthful, miserable and will possess crooked walking limbs. 
83-91. EFFECTS OF NAVĀŃŚAS IN CAPRICORN. The various Navāńśas resulting in the Ascendant Capricorn will emanate the following effects: Effects of Capricorn Ascendant, First Navāńśa: The native will have intersticed and outwardly visible teeth, be dark in complexion, will speak with broken words, or be stammering, will have coarse hair, be famous, be interested in music and amusement, be emaciated and will have fluctuating wealth. Effects of Capricorn Ascendant, Second Navāńśa: The native will be indolent, crafty, crooked nosed, fond of music, broad bodied, be interested in many females, will prattle much and be skillful. Effects of Capricorn Ascendant, Third Navāńśa: The native will have lust for music, be famous, fair complexioned, be endowed with superior looks and charming nose, will be fond of many friends and relatives and achieves fulfillment of desires. Effects of Capricorn Ascendant, Fourth Navāńśa: The native will have round eyes with a mix of blood-red and black hue, large forehead, emaciated body and thin arms, scattered hair, intersticed teeth and broken speech. Effects of Capricorn Ascendant, Fifth Navāńśa: The native will have prominent neck, nose and belly, will enjoy pleasures, be attached to women, be dark in complexion, will have round knees and arms and will attain successful beginnings in his undertakings. Effects of Capricorn Ascendant, Sixth Navāńśa: The native will possess a splendourous body, will attire charmingly, be libidinous, will possess small and even teeth, be a good speaker and will have big cheeks and large forehead. Effects of Capricorn Ascendant, Seventh Navāńśa: The native will be dark in complexion, be indolent, be an eloquent speaker, be short-haired, big-bodied, be harsh in disposition, will possess soft hands and legs, be intelligent and very virtuous. Effects of Capricorn Ascendant, Eighth Navāńśa: The native will be endowed with majestic sight and charming nose, reddish face, uneven nails and hair, grotesque body and forehead protruding, like a pot. Effects of Capricorn Ascendant, Ninth Navāńśa: The native will have broad chest and large eyes, high intelligence, fully developed face, interest in musical studies, be endowed with sweetness and strength, be gentle and diplomatic. 
92-100. EFFECTS OF NAVĀŃŚAS IN AQUARIUS. The various Navāńśas ascending, while Aquarius is on the East will produce following effects: Effects of Aquarius Ascendant, First Navāńśa: The native will be dark in complexion, be soft in disposition, will have an emaciated body and prominent cheeks, be learned in poetry and Shastras, be libidinous, interested in carnal pleasures and be splendourous. Effects of Aquarius Ascendant, Second Navāńśa: The native will possess coarse skin, nails, sight and hair, be kind to the helpless, be gentle, be tall in stature, foolish and will have a ‘distinct' head. Effects of Aquarius Ascendant, Third Navāńśa: The native will have a compact body (limbs sticking close to each other), be fond of females, will possess the splendour of lapis lazuli, be learned in the meanings of Shastras and will act accordingly. Effects of Aquarius Ascendant, Fourth Navāńśa: The native will be fond of women, be fair in complexion, will have a split face, will destroy enemies, be majestic, courageous and be fond of pleasures and sexual enjoyments. Effects of Aquarius Ascendant, Fifth Navāńśa: The native will be learned in clear meanings of Shastras and in fine arts, will have coarse hair on legs, concealed (not prominent) neck and ears and be dark in complexion. Effects of Aquarius Ascendant, Sixth Navāńśa: The native will have a face, resembling that of a tiger, be bold, short-haired, will have unchanging aims, will kill living beings viz. tiger, deer, snake etc. and be dear to king. Effects of Aquarius Ascendant, Seventh Navāńśa: The native will have eyes and face, resembling that of a goat, be fierce in disposition, be delighted in village life, insulted by females, will suffer diseases of bilious imbalances and be endowed with strength and courage. Effects of Aquarius Ascendant, Eighth Navāńśa: The native will possess an undiminishing strength, firm be disposition and affection, be a warrior with the king, or be a king himself, be beautiful and will have strong teeth and broad eyes. Effects of Aquarius Ascendant, Ninth Navāńśa: The native will be dark in complexion, will possess unclean and elevated teeth, be disunited from his wife, children and wealth, be an affable speaker and be famous and skillful. 101-109. EFFECTS OF NAVĀŃŚAS IN PISCES. Should Pisces ascend at birth, the various Navāńśas thereof will yield following specific effects: Effects of Pisces Ascendant, First Navāńśa: Though the native may be white in complexion, his body will reveal the splendour of blood-red hue; he will be soft in disposition, be akin to a female in mental make up, (i.e. will act, like a female), be fickle-minded and will have a short neck and emaciated waist. Effects of Pisces Ascendant, Second Navāńśa: The native will have a big nose, be skillful in his assignments, will eat meat and the like, be endowed with a charming physique, will wander in forests and hills and will have a big head. Effects of Pisces Ascendant, Third Navāńśa: The native will be white in complexion, be crafty, will possess beautiful eyes, be beautiful, righteous, learned, courteous, modest and charming in appearance. Effects of Pisces Ascendant, Fourth Navāńśa: The native will have praiseworthy attributes, will fall into adversity, will serve aged people, be skillful in his assignments, learned, very strong versed in justice and will have elevated nose. Effects of Pisces Ascendant, Fifth Navāńśa: The native will be tall in stature, dark in complexion, be valorous, be not peaceful, will have a small nose and charming eyes, be fond of torturing others, be impatient, will possess beautiful teeth and prattle. Effects of Pisces Ascendant, Sixth Navāńśa: The native will be self-respected, righteous, excellent, strong, miserable, crafty, unsteady and be a minister. Effects of Pisces Ascendant, Seventh Navāńśa: The native will be self-respected, will show interest in other religions, be excellent, be a minister, strong, miserable, cruel and unsteady. Effects of Pisces Ascendant, Eighth Navāńśa: The native will be tall in stature, will have a big head, be emaciated, indolent, will have uneven (or dirtied) eyes and hair, will have foolish children (or a few children), be interested in earning money and be skillful in war (or quarrels). Effects of Pisces Ascendant, Ninth Navāńśa: The native will be short, soft in disposition, courageous, broad chested, broad eyed, big nosed, be bright, will have a broad physique, be intelligent, virtuous and famous. 
110. ABOUT OTHER DIVISIONS. The effects described in regard to individual Signs apply to Dwadasamsas of each Sign as well. Regarding effects for various other divisions not explained, the effects related to Sapthamsas will apply. 
Thus ends the 51st Ch. entitled “EFFECTS OF NAVĀŃŚAS (lost horoscopy)” in Kalyana Varma's Saravali. Ch. 52. Lost Horoscopy 
1. THE NATAL AYANA. If the Ascendant at the time of query (related to tracing the lost birth data) be within the first 15 of a Sign, the birth was in Uttarayana and beyond these degrees Dakshinayana. 
2-3. BIRTH RITU ETC. The strongest of the planets in the Prashna Lagna indicates the Ritu (season) at birth. Should there be none in the Ascendant, the Lord of the ascendental decanate is the ruler of Ritu at birth. Should there be a clash in the Ayana and Ritu arrived at, the Ritu Lords arrived should be interchanged thus: the Moon for Venus, Mercury for Mars and Jupiter for Saturn. The respective month of the Ritu is decided depending on the first, or second half of the decanate being Ascendant. The degrees elapsed in the decanate will be to the knowledge of the natal Tithi. Some say, that this will lead to locating the natal Sun. 
4-9. OTHER NATAL FACTORS. The query Ascendant be multiplied by 2 and divided by 5 to get the natal Jupiter's placement. This should be adjusted to actual placement guessing the native's age approximately, by increasing, or decreasing multiples of 12. If the query Ascendant is in a day Sign, declare birth during night. Otherwise, the contrary prevails. The degree elapsed in the query Ascendant will lead to the knowledge of elapsed portion of night, or day, as the case may be. Out of the query Ascendant, the 5th and the 9th therefrom will indicate the natal Rāśi (Moon Sign), the strongest of the three prevailing. The parts of the body, viz. head etc. touched by the querist at the time of query will also indicate the Moon Sign at birth. Alternatively the distance between the query Ascendant and the query Moon may be added to the query Moon to get the position of the natal Moon. This does not apply to the Moon in Pisces at the time of query, (i. e. the natal Moon is in Pisces itself). The Navāńśa Lagna at the time of query may also be the natal Ascendant. The number of decanates between the query Ascendant and query Sun, when added to the query Sun, will yield the natal Ascendant. The longitude of the planet in the query Ascendant should be multiplied by the figure indicated by Chayangula (length of shadow) at that time. This should be divided by 12, the remainder of which will indicate natal Ascendant. 
10-11. POSITION OF THE QUERIST. The following positions of the querist will indicate the natal Ascendant. Standing, lying on the bed, sitting, or getting up will, respectively, denote the first, 4th, 7th, or 10th from query Ascendant becoming natal Ascendant. 
12. PERSONAL NAME. The name formally given by parents to the native will indicate the natal star. Multiply the Matras (units) of the given name by 2 and add to it the Chayangula length. Divide this by 27 and the remainder, when counted from Dhanishta will lead to the knowledge of birth star. 
13-15. ANOTHER METHOD. Note the longitude of the query Ascendant. It should be multiplied by 10, if the Ascendant is Leo, or Taurus, by 8 in case of Gemini, or Scorpio by 7 in case, or Aries, or Libra, by 5 in case of Virgo and Capricorn, while for the rest of the Signs by the number denoted, when counted from Aries. (That is 4 for Cancer, 9 for Sagittarius, 11 for Aquarius and 12 for Pisces). If the Ascendant is occupied by Jupiter, the Ascendant converted into minutes of arc be multiplied by 10, if occupied by Mars by 8, if by Venus by 7 and, if by others by 5. Both the products so multiplied be added together. This product by multiplied again by 10 to know the year, Ritu and month; by 7 to know the Tithi and by 5 to arrive at Navāńśa Lagna and Ishta Ghati (birth time) and be, respectively, divided by their individual dividers (i.e. 120 for year, 2 for Ritu, 15 for Tithi and the like). Addition, or reduction of 9 may be made in case of anomalistic answers. 
16. I have explained lost horoscopic rules, as expounded by Yavana, Bhadasana etc. But some of their rules are ambiguous. The student better understand using his judgement. 
17-21. LOST HOROSCOPY BASED ON MOON. Just as the ascending degree helps trace back the lost details, the Moon Sign may also be used. If the Moon Sign at the time of query be a night Sign, natal Moon was in a day Sign and vice versa. Note in what quarter of the Sign is the Moon at the time of query. Proportionately understand the natal Moon during day, or night, as the case may be. Multiply the query Moon by the same Rāśi multiplication factor, as explained supra and, if necessary by planetary multipliers, as applicable. Multiply the resultant product (arrived by adding the two) by 7 and divide by 27. The remainder will represent the birth star counted from Aswini. In case of rectification by adding 9 the counting is from Moola and, if subtraction of 9 is done count from Makha. The pre-division product (i.e. the product before dividing by 27, as above) should be processed variously, as suggested earlier to know the Ritu, month, Tithi etc. at birth. 
Thus ends the 52nd Ch. entitled “LOST HOROSCOPY” in Kalyana Varma's Saravali. Ch. 53. AshtakaVarga 
1. In order to evaluate the auspicious and inauspicious effects in day-to-day life due to planetary transits, Yavanacharyas have explained AshtakaVarga (which are detailed below). 
2. THE SUN'S ASHTAKAVARGA. The Sun contributes benefic dots in his Ashtaka Varga, as under. From his own self in the 1st, 2nd, 4th, 7th, 8th, 9th, 10th and 11th Signs; from Mars and Saturn in similar Signs; from the Moon in the 3rd, 6th, 10th and 11th Signs; from Jupiter in the 5th, 6th, 9th and 11th Signs; from Venus in the 6th, 7th and 12th Signs; from Mercury in the 3rd, 5th, 6th, 9th, 10th, 11th and 12th Signs and from the Ascendant in the 3rd, 4th, 6th, 10th, 11th and 12th Signs. 
3. THE MOON'S ASHTAKA VARGA. The Moon contributes benefic points in her AshtakaVarga, as under. In the 3rd, 6th, 7th, 8th, 10th and 11th Signs from the Sun; in the 1st, 3rd, 6th, 7th, 10th and 11th Signs from her position; in the 2nd, 3rd, 5th, 6th, 9th, 10th and 11th Signs counted from Mars; in the 1st, 3rd, 4th, 5th, 7th, 8th, 10th and 11th Signs counted from Mercury; in the 1st, 4th, 7th, 8th, 10th, 11th and 12th Signs from Jupiter; in the 3rd, 4th, 5th, 7th, 9th, 10th and 11th Signs counted from Venus; in the 3rd, 5th, 6th and 11th Signs from Saturn and in the 3rd, 6th, 10th and 11th Signs counted from the ascending Sign. 
4. THE ASHTAKAVARGA OF MARS. Mars in his AshtakaVarga drops auspicious points in the various Signs from the various planets and Ascendant, as denoted below. From the Sun in the 3rd, 5th, 6th, 10th and 11th Signs; from the Moon in the 3rd, 6th and 11th Signs; from his own position in the 1st, 2nd, 4th, 7th 8th, 10th and 11th Signs; from Mercury in the 3rd, 5th, 6th and 11th Signs; from Jupiter in the 6th, 10th, 11th and 12th Signs; from Venus in the 6th, 8th, 11th and 12th Signs; from Saturn in the 1st, 4th, 7th, 8th, 9th, 10th and 11th Signs and from the ascending Sign in the 1st, 3rd, 6th, 10th and 11th Signs. 
5. THE ASHTAKAVARGA OF MERCURY. Auspicious points are contributed by Mercury in his AshtakaVarga, as under: From the Sun in the 5th, 6th, 9th, 11th and 12th Signs; from the Moon in the 2nd, 4th, 6th, 8th, 10th and 11th Signs; from Mars and Saturn in the 1st, 2nd, 4th, 7th, 8th, 9th, 10th and 12th Signs, from his own self in the 1st, 3rd, 5th, 6th, 9th, 10th, 11th and 12th Signs; from Jupiter in the 6th, 8th, 11th and 12th Signs; from Venus in 1st, 2nd, 3rd, 4th, 5th, 8th, 9th and 11th Signs and from the ascending Sign in the 1st, 2nd, 4th, 6th, 8th, 10th and 11th Signs. 
6. THE ASHTAKAVARGA OF JUPITER. Jupiter's AshtakaVarga gains auspicious points, as under. From the Sun in the 1st, 2nd, 3rd, 4th, 7th, 8th, 9th, 10th and 11th Signs; from the Moon in the 2nd, 5th 7th, 9th and 11th Signs; from Mars in the 1st, 2nd, 4th, 7th, 8th 10th and 11th Signs; from Mercury in the 1st, 2nd, 4th, 5th, 6th, 9th, 10th and 11th Signs; from his own self in the 1st, 2nd, 3rd, 4th, 7th, 8th, 10th and 11th Signs; from Venus in the 2nd, 5th, 6th, 9th, 10th, 11th Signs; from Saturn in the 3rd, 5th, 6th and 12th Signs and from the ascending Sign in the 1st, 2nd, 4th, 5th, 6th, 7th, 9th, 10th and 11th Signs. 
7. THE ASHTAKAVARGA OF VENUS. Mark benefic dots in the following places. From the Sun in the 8th, 11th and 12th Signs; from the Moon in the 1st, 2nd, 3rd, 4th, 5th, 8th, 9th, 11th and 12th Signs; from Mars in the 3rd, 4th, 6th, 9th, 11th and 12th Signs; from Mercury in the 3rd, 5th, 6th, 9th and 11th Signs; from Jupiter in the 5th 8th, 9th, 10th and 11th Signs; from his own self in the 1st, 2nd, 3rd, 4th, 5th, 8th, 9th, 10th and 11th Signs; from Saturn in the 3rd, 4th, 5th, 8th, 9th, 10th and 11th Signs and from the ascending Sign in the 1st, 2nd, 3rd, 4th, 5th, 8th, 9th and 11th Signs. This is called the AshtakaVarga of Venus. 
8. THE ASHTAKAVARGA OF SATURN. Saturn's AshtakaVarga is prepared by inserting benefic dots in places, as denoted below. From the Sun in the 1st, 2nd, 4th, 7th, 8th, 10th and 11th Signs; from the Moon in the 3rd, 6th and 11th Houses; from Mars in the 3rd, 5th, 6th, 10th 11th and 12th Signs; from Mercury in the 6th, 8th, 9th, 10th, 11th and 12th Signs; from Jupiter in the 5th, 6th, 11th and 12th Signs; from Venus in the 6th, 11th and 12th Signs; from his own self in the 3rd, 5th, 6th and 11th Signs and from the ascending Sign in the 1st, 3rd, 4th, 10th and 11th Signs. 
9-10. The places mentioned above are auspicious for the various planets and the others are inauspicious. Planets transiting Signs with more benefic dots will reveal auspicious results, while inauspicious results will come to pass in case of transits in Signs with less benefic dots. Benefic results will be predominant, if these Signs happen to be exaltation, own, friendly etc. and malefic effects will be ordinary. Similarly in debilitation/inimical Signs, malefic results will be more and benefic effects will be ordinary. In giving transit effects, the Sun and Mars will be effective, while in the beginning of the Sign, Jupiter and Venus, while in the middle of the Sign and lastly Saturn and the Moon, while in the end of the Sign. Mercury is effective in his transit through the whole Sign. 
Thus ends the 53rd Ch. entitled “ASHTAKAVARGA” in Kalyana Varma's Saravali. Ch. 54. Effects Of AshtakaVarga 
1. Draw 13 horizontal lines intersected by 9 parallel (horizontally) lines (thus getting 96 squares) noting the names of the 12 Signs from Aries onwards in a rightward manner and the names of the 7 planets and Ascendant in the left hand side vertical columns. Mark the benefic dots for each planets' AshtakaVarga and malefic points (where benefic points are absent), as per the positions told earlier. 
2. GENERAL EFFECTS. If a planet is associated with 8 Bindusin the Sign occupied by it, even an ordinary person will become a king; with 7 Bindusfulfillment of all desires; with 6 Bindusfame and financial gains; with 5 Bindus happiness and friendship; with 4 Bindus eradication and misery; with 3 Bindusloss of money; with 2 Bindusworries; with 1 Bindubodily emaciation and with the complete absence of Bindus there will be evils at all times. 
3 EFFECTS OF THE SUN'S A.V. The association of the Sun with particular number of Bindus (auspicious points) in the Sign occupied by him will lead to respective effects, thus; with 8 Binduswealth from the king; 7 Bindustranscendental beauty, happiness and riches; 6 Bindusincrease of valour and fame; 5 Bindusinflux of money; 4 Bindus neither gainful nor losing; 3 Bindusfatigue due to (frequent) travels (or difficulties on account of travels, proneness to accidents and the like); 2 Bindusfear of diseases; 1 Bindudifficulties; and absence of Bindusdeath (or troubles of a very severe nature). 
4. EFFECTS OF THE MOON'S A.V. Note the Bindus in the Sign occupied by the Moon. If she be associated with 8 Bindus, the native will enjoy affluence and pleasures; 7 Bindus financial gains through robes, food, scented articles etc., 6 Bindusacquaintance with the virtuous; 5 Bindusacquisition of courage and intelligence due to association with Brahmins (or the learned); 4 Bindusequilibrium of happiness and grief; 3 Bindusenmity with relatives; 2 Bindusseparation from kith and kin and deprival of wealth; 1 Bindu evils and absence of auspicious pointsgrief and difficulties following excitement. 
5. EFFECTS OF THE A.V. OF MARS. If Mars be associated with various benefic points, as denoted below in the Sign tenanted by him, the results due will be: 8 Bindus acquisition of wealth and land and victory over foes; 7 Bindus increase of fortunes and splendour; 6 Bindusroyal favours; 5 Bindusincrease of fame; 4 Bindusequality of wealth and calamity; 3 Bindusseparation from co-born and conjugal partner; 2 Bindustroubles from king, fire and bilious disorders; 1 Binduulcer and stomachial diseases and absence of Bindus diseases of the eye and difficulties comparable to death. 
6. EFFECTS OF MERCURY'S A.V. The effects of Mercury's association with various auspicious points in the Sign occupied by him will be: 8 Bindushonour from the ruler; 7 Binduswealth, knowledge and happiness; 6 Bindussuccess in all undertakings; 5 Bindusnew acquaintances; 4 Bindus unemployment; 3 Bindusmental worries on account of financial losses; 2 Bindusenmity with wife, children and friends causing loss of courage and wisdom; 1 Binduevils of all kinds and absence of Bindus will bring about death. 
7. EFFECTS OF JUPITER'S A.V. Based on the number of auspicious points, the Sign occupied by Jupiter will produce the following effects: 8 Bindusspotless fame, happiness and growth of wealth; 7 Bindusfortunes and happiness; 6 Bindusacquisition of robes, conveyances, gold etc.; 5 Bindus destruction of enemies and success in undertakings; 4 Bindus no loss, no gain; 3 Bindusloss of hearing, sight and masculine vigour; 2 Bindusincurring royal wrath; 1 Bindudistress due to diseases and absence of Bindusdestruction of relatives, wealth and progeny. 
8. EFFECTS OF A.V. OF VENUS. The association of Venus with various number of Bindus will generate the under mentioned effects: 8 Bindusenjoyments of all kinds and acquisition of robes, wife, scents, food, drinks etc.; 7 Bindus plentifulness of ornaments and pearls; 6 Bindusacquisition of a girl of choice; 5 Bindusassociation with friends; 4 Bindus equality of inauspicious and auspicious results; 3 Bindus enmity with people of his community and senior members of the village; 2 Bindusdisplacement; 1 Binduphlegmatic disorders and absence of Bindusbecoming a synonym of all kinds of evils. 
9. EFFECTS OF SATURN'S A.V. If Saturn is associated with a certain number of Bindus, the effects due will be: 8 Bindus lordship over villages, towns and people; 7 Bindus acquisition of female servants, asses and elephants; 6 Bindus gains from thieves, hunters and Army heads; 5 Bindusadvent of wealth, corn and happiness; 4 Bindushappiness caused by association with others; 3 Bindus destruction of progeny, wife, attendants and money; 2 Bindusimprisonment, emotions and diseases; 1 Bindu/absence of Bindusloss of wealth, family etc. 
10-12. May the astrologers be pleased with the Science of Astrology thus described by Kalyana Varma. Ancestors, like Paulasa, Vasishta, Romasa, Yavana, Badarayana, Sakthi, Atri, Bharadwaja, Viswamitra, Guna, Agnikesa, Garga, Parashara, Jeevasarma and a host of others have authored elaborate texts on astrology. The science of astrology thus deals with the good and bad in stock for an individual with Chitragupta (the official record keeper of Yamathe God of Deathnoting down the virtues and vices of mankind). 
Thus ends the 54th Ch. entitled “EFFECTS OF ASHTAKAVARGA” in Kalyana Varma's Saravali. Ch. 55. Manifold Births 
1. Acharya Kanaka's school of thought dealing with ‘Manifold Births' is narrated in this Ch. for the pleasure of the astrologers and the common folk. 2. Lord Brahma created this Universe at a time, when Cancer was ascending with its Lord and in aspect to Jupiter, while the other 5 planets were in their own Signs. Should one have a similar radix, he will rule over the three worlds enjoying the company of the celestial dames. 
3. The Science of astrology delineates the immovable and the movable through respective differences of time, omens, form etc. 
4-5. If all the malefics be with strength, while benefics be bereft of it, one of the Viyoni (Viyoni Rāśis are Rāśis other than Gemini, Virgo, Libra, Aquarius and the first half of Sagittarius) be Signs ascending with Mercury and Saturn be in Angles, or in aspect to the Ascendant, the birth will be of a creature other than human being. The birth will correspond to the Dwadasamsa of the Ascendant, or of the Moon prevailing at Adhana, or in the radix. 
6-9. The sages have explained the hue, form etc. of the manifold births based on planetary conjunctions and aspects, which I narrate below. The Zodiac personified signifies the several limbs of non-human species, as under: Ariesface, Taurusneck, Gemini and Piscesshoulders and forelegs, Cancer and Aquariusback, Leo and Capricornforelegs, Virgo and Sagittariushind legs, Libraanus and Scorpio tail and genital organ. The right side limbs are denoted by Signs Gemini to Libra, while left side by Signs Scorpio to Pisces. 
10-12. The strongest Sign, or the strongest Navāńśa ascending will indicate the hue of such birth. If the Ascendant has a strong planet in it, the hue of the animal and the wounds on its body will correspond to such planet. If a planet is in its own Rāśi/Navāńśa, such effects will be unmixed, while the one in other's Sign/Navāńśa, will give a rough version of the hue. The animal will have a mark on its back corresponding to the hue of the planet in the 7th House, or the one aspecting the 7th House. If there are many related thus, the hues of the mark will be equally many, the prime effects being from the strongest of the lot. 
13-14 The hue of the animal based on the occupant of the Ascendant will be: Jupiteryellow, Moonwhite, Venus variegated, Sun/Marsred, Saturn black, Mercury grass-green. If the planet aspecting the Ascendant be in its own Sign and other's Navāńśa, or vice versa, the hue obtainable will be golden. 
15-16. The planet in the Ascendant will be capable of giving such hue corresponding to the phenomena it is influenced by, viz. Parigha, rainbow, cloud, Parivesh etc. Otherwise, the planet will give the hue due to its nature alone. 
17-18. If the Ascendant has in it a bird decanate (the first ones of Aquarius and Leo and the second ones of Gemini and Libra), or a Movable Navāńśa (Aries Navāńśa and the Navāńśas angular thereof), or Gemini Navāńśa/Virgo Navāńśa and be in aspect to Saturn birds residing on lands will be born. In a similar case, the aspect of the Moon denotes births of birds dwelling in water. If a water resorting Sign be on the Ascendant in aspect to a strong planet, birds related to water will be born. Similarly land-resorting Signs in aspect to strong planets indicate birds of land. The hue of the bird will correspond to the planet concerned. 
19. Birth of trees is indicated, if the Ascendant, Sun, Jupiter and the Moon are devoid of strength, while others are with strength. Land resorting Signs in the Ascendant indicate trees growing on land, while water resorting Signs indicate plants etc. coming out of water. 
20-21. If the Lord of rising Navāńśa be the Sun, trees (or plants in this context) with hard, or strong trunk/stem will be born. The Moon denotes ones milky and soft; Jupiter fruitful, Marsbitter and thorny, Saturnunproductive and useless (to mankind); Venusthe ones yielding flowers and Mercuryunfruitful. 
22-23. If the said Lord of Ascendant in Navāńśa be a natural malefic being in the company of a benefic, a sub-standard tree on excellent land is denoted, while in the case of a benefic being Ascendant Lord in Navāńśa and being in the company of a malefic, the reverse is truei.e. an excellent tree on waste land. If there is a mix in the above planetary description, both the land and the born will be of a mixed nature Watery planets indicate plants growing in water, while land-resorters denote trees etc. growing on earth. 
24. Note how many Signs away is the Navāńśa Lagna Lord from the ascending Sign. So many will be the trees in number to be born. Similarly infer by the number denoted between Navāńśa Ascendant and the planet's Navāńśa position. 
25-26. Manifold birth is indicated, if benefics are in their own Navāńśa being bereft of strength, while malefics with strength are in their own/other malefics' Navāńśas. Such birth is destroyed, if the said Navāńśa Lord occupies a weak planet's Sign, is defeated in planetary war, conjunct with, or aspected by a malefic. 
21. Explained now is four kinds of manifold births, viz. those born of seeds (like plant, tree etc.), those born of womb (like quadrupeds etc.), those born in dirty places (like mosquitoes etc.) and those born of eggs (snakes, birds and the like). These are based on planetary Yogas etc. at birth. 
28-29. A quadruped is born, if the Sun is in a quadruped Sign, while a weak planet is in a weak Sign. I have explained the relative rules in a brief and general manner. Now told are something surprising (more interesting) and detailed. 
30-35. Should the Sun, the Moon and the Ascendant be strong in a Dwadasamsa related to a Viyoni Sign, the birth will correspond to such Dwadasamsa. If the Moon is in Aries Dwadasamsa in Aries Ascendant, birth of goats, rams etc., will take place. The other Dwadasamsas related to Aries Ascendant will give following effects: Taurus cow, buffalo; Gemini akin to a human being (like monkey, ape etc.); Cancer crab, tortoise etc., Leo tiger etc., Virgo human beings; Libra resembling human beings, Scorpio snakes etc. Sagittarius asses, horses etc., Capricorn, Aquarius and Pisces Crocodile/human•being/fish etc. Similarly one can guess about trees, grass etc. Just as the various Dwadasamsas of Aries have been described, the effects for other Signs can also be understood. 36-37. The Dwadasamsa effects of the manifold births will depend on the first Dwadasamsa of a Sign and the remaining Dwadasamsa should be understood based on the first division cited. Just as a Dual Rāśi with male Navāńśa causing birth of twins in the case of human beings, in the case of other births male planets in the first Dwadasamsa being in Dual Sign etc., the number of births be decided. 38-40. In case of a living being yielding multiples at a time (like snake, hen, bitch etc.) the number of births will depend on Dwadasamsas past. Male/female should be decided by the Dwadasamsas distributed in such Signs. If the Ascendant is tenanted by the Moon/Saturn/Mercury, tortoises etc. will yield such number equaling the Dwadasamsas elapsed. Venus, Mars, Moon, or Saturn being with strength will denote Sattva, Rajas and TamoGunas of the births according to the Amsas. 
41. If a (qualified) planet occupies other Navāńśas than of its own, the birth will be unnatural. 
42-44. Should Scorpio ascend with a biped Navāńśa birth of snakes, rats, insects, mongoose, scorpions, snakes without poison, deer, cows etc. will take place. 
45-46. The divisions of Sagittarius with aspect from Jupiter denote birth of horses, asses, camels, buffaloes etc. 
47-48. Capricorn and its divisions indicate birth of forest animals, like tiger, rhinoceros, swine, wolf elephants (Sarabha apart from meaning an elephant also denotes a fabulous 8 legged animal said to be stronger than even a lion), eagles and the like. 
49. Pisces (and its divisions) enjoying Jupiter's aspect relates to creatures living in deep waters, like giant fish, whale etc. 
50. Aries (and its divisions) with the aspect of Mars portends births of goat, ram etc., while Taurus (and its divisions) with aspect from Venus denotes cow, bull, buffalo etc. 
51. Thus have to be deduced the possibilities of births of the various creatures depending on the rising Sign with aspect of its own Lord and the divisions of the rising Sign. 
52. If a Sign resorting to towns/villages (like Gemini) Ascendant with Navāńśa of Leo/Scorpio/Capricorn, such animals, though wild, as bred in villages, or townships (like elephant, bear etc.) will take their birth. 
53. In the process, Navāńśas of land-resorting Signs will indicate births of animals moving on land and water-resorting Signs, animals/creatures dwelling in water. 
54. If Libra be the Ascendant in aspect to Venus, a decanate of Libra denotes birth of parrots, flaming, partridge etc. 
55. Peacock, cock/hen, francoline partridge, turtledove and birds living on (only) rain drops, are born, if Leo rises with Sun's aspect and with various own divisions. 
56. If a Fixed Sign with aspect to Saturn obtaining various divisions of the same classifications rises, “births” of temples, houses, choultries etc. begin. The colour, structure etc. will have to be guessed with the help of aspecting planets, as explained earlier. 
