 
Saravali 
Kalyana Varma, the famous author Saravali belonged to the 10th century AD. He was the king of a place called Vyaghrapada, believed to be somewhere in Madhya Pradesh. From the verses in this work it is obvious that he has studied the works of Parashara, Varahamihira and Yavana etc before him, and as he felt that they were too brief, he decided to elaborate the principles.
Saravali indeed is a monumental work and the study of it is a must for the serious students of astrology.
Saravali page and chapter index
Page 1
Chapters
1. Birth of Horāśāstra Author's prayer and introduction 
2. Meaning of Horā 
3. Rāśi Description 
Description of the 12 Rāśis, limbs of Kalapurusha and their use, synonyms of Rāśis and Houses, zodiacal halves, their Lords and effects. Rāśi and Navāńśa rulers, importance of sub-divisions, Vargothamamsa, Lords of decanates, Horas, Trimsamsas and Sapthamsas, different Vargas, benefic and malefic Rāśis, Gandantha, directions of Rāśis, DigBala and KalaBala, day and night Signs, Sirodara & Prishtodara Signs, strength of Rāśi, synonyms of Bhavas, additional synonyms, Kendra, Apoklima and Panaphara, Upachaya and Anupachaya, exaltation and fall, long, medium and short ascensions of Signs, favourable Rāśis for journey and colours of Rāśis 
4. Planetary Characters 
Kalapurusha's soul etc., limbs from decanates, planetary portfolios, directions and nature, synonyms of planets, planetary colours, deities, sex, caste, elements, robes, substances, periods and Ritus, Lords of Vedas and Worlds, description and nature of the planets from the Sun to Saturn, planetary friendship permanent and temporary, five kinds of consideration of these, planetary aspects and strengths, directional and positional strengths, temporal and motional strengths, Ayana, Drekkana, Tribhaga and Naisargika Balas 
5. Miscellaneous Matters 
States of planets, effects of various states, retrogression in exaltation, good results in mid-life, Swakshetra, Mulatrikona etc., effects thereof, inauspicious planets, exalted, retrograde, auspicious planets, Nathonnatha Bala, Lords of year etc., Paksha Bala, planets with all kinds of strengths, benefics and malefics with such strengths, planetary stages and planets in odd, or even Signs 
6. (Yoga) Karakas 
Planetary coworkers and effects thereof 
7. Planetary Indications 
Lord of weekday etc., Bhava effects, planetary rulerships, or Karakatwas and planetary places  
Page 2
8. Copulation (Conception), Menstruation, occurrence of pregnancy, disposition of fetus, birth of twins, male, hermaphrodite, one male child and one female child, triplets etc., parents, process of growth of embryo, miscarriage, comfortable carrying, adversities to the pregnant woman, progress of progeny, time of delivery, natal Moon, belated progeny, eye defects, dumbness, dullwitted, teethed at birth, peculiar birth, short stature, lame by birth and birth sans legs, hands and head 
9. Conditions at Birth 
Kinds of delivery, place of delivery home, position of cot, delivery on ground, number of attendants, position of light, birth out of fathers sight, birth out of wedlock, evils to mother, resemblance, rounded by coil, features, characteristics and nature, death of parents and happiness to parents 
10. Evils at Birth 
Need to assess longevity, strength of male/female planets, kinds of evils, longevity curtailed to minimum, Yogas adverse for eyes and ears, death in few days, effects of time causing a disease, malefics and decanates, death, exceedingly long life, elapsed longevity, timing infant death, death in childhood, death in 3rd year, fateful degrees of the Moon etc. 
11. Evils and the Moon 
Combinations to counteract lunar evils 
12. Evils Canceled at Birth  
Page 3
Evils relating to longevity nullified 
13. Lunar Yogas 
Sunapha, Anapha, Durudhura, Kemadruma, different permutations, other kinds of Sunapha etc., results of Sunapha, Anapha, Durudhura by Mars etc., lunar Yogas from the Sun, Moon in invisible and visible halves and Dhana Yogas 
14. Yogas from the Sun 
Vasi, Vesi and Ubhayachari, effects of Vasi and Vesi by different planets and effects of Ubhayachari 
15. Conjunction of Two Planets 
16. Conjunction of Three Planets 
17. Conjunction of Four Planets 
18. Conjunction of Five Planets 
19. Conjunction of Six Planets 
20. Combinations for Renunciation 
21. Nabhasa Yogas  
Page 4
32 kinds of Nabhasa Yogas, rules for their formation and effects thereof 
22. Effects of the Sun 
The Sun in 12 Rāśis and special effects, when in aspects to other planets 
23. Effects of the Moon in Various Rāśis The Moon in the 12 Rāśis and special effects, when in aspects to others planets
24. Effects of the Moon in Various Navāńśas  and in aspect to other planets 
Page 5  
25.Effects of Mars in Various Rāśis Mars in 12 Signs and special effects in case of aspects from others 
26. Effects of Mercury in Various Rāśis 
Mercury in 12 Rāśis and special effects in case of aspects to other planets 
27. Effects of Jupiter in Various Signs 
Effects for Jupiter's position in different Signs and aspects from other planets 
28. Effects of Venus in Various Signs 
Effects for Venus' positions in different Signs and aspects from others 
29. Effects of Saturn in Various Signs 
Effects for Saturn's position in different Signs and aspects from others  
Page 6 
30. Effects of Planets in Bhavas. Sun to Saturn in the 12 Houses and individual results 
31. Two Planets in Angles 
Effects of all possible 2-planet conjunctions in the Ascendant, 4th, 7th and 10th  
Page 7
32. Ninth House and Effects thereof 
The 9th House, Jupiter in the 9th and aspects thereto by individual planets/two planets, affliction to the 9th, the Sun and others in the 9th with others, 3 planets in the 9th, 4 planets in the 9th, special effects 
33. Tenth House and Effects thereof 
The 10th House, individual planets in the 10th from the Moon, two planets in the 10th from the Moon, three planets in the 10th from the Moon, four planets in the 10th from the Moon, malefics in the 10th from the Moon, livelihood, Signs and profession, planets in the 10th and source of gain 
34. Different Houses and Worldly Affairs 
Several planets aspecting the Ascendant, general aspects to the Ascendant, unaspected Ascendant, planetary conjunctions in the Ascendant, AdhiYoga from the Ascendant, principles related to the 2nd House, 3rd House, 5th House, number of children, various kinds of progeny, as per Hindu Dharma Shastras, sons and daughters, childlessness, loss of children, 6th House, 7th House, 11th House, 12th House, miscellaneous matters  
Page 8
35. Raja Yogas 
36. Planetary Rays 
Computation of rays of planets contributed at birth and effects of total number of rays 
37. Pancha Maha Purusha Yogas  
Page 9
Malavya, Ruchaka, Sasa, Hamsa and Bhadra Yoga formation and effects 
38. Effects of Natural Constituents and Primordial Compounds 
Satva, Rajo and Tamo Gunas, Akasa, Jala, Vayu, Agni and Prithwi Tatwas, births in such Tatwas, Windy, Bilious and Phlegmatic temperaments, Luminaries in Pancha Maha Purusha Yogas 
39. Obstruction to Rajayogas 
40. Calculation of Longevity 
Selection of system for longevity, Amsayurdaya calculations, additions for Ascendant's contribution, rectification for planetary contributions, reductions for Amsayurdaya calculations, Vyayadi Harana, Pindayu, Ascendant's contribution in Pindayu, reduction for rising planets, Naisargikayurdaya, full span of life, unlimited longevity, span of full life for various animals 
41. Moola Dasa 
Order of the scheme, Satya's view, auspicious periods, inauspicious periods, effects of the Moon, aspects to the Moon at the commencement of a Dasha, major Lord's placement at the commencement of a Dasha, special effects based on Navāńśa, Lagna Dasha, Naisargika Dasha, effects of adverse and favourable planet's Dasha, different kinds of Dashas of the Luminaries based on their dispositions, other placements of planets 
42. Effects of Sub-Periods Distribution of sub-periods to planets in Moola Dasa, Dasa-Bhuktis thereof, special considerations 
43. Evil Effects of Dasa 
44. Antidotes for Evil Dashas 
45. Effects of Planetary Dignities 
Effects of exalted planets, planets in Moolatrikona, own Signs, friendly Signs, debilitation Signs, inimical Signs, effects in Navāńśa, more planets in exaltation, in Moolatrikona, in own Signs, friendly Signs, inimical Signs and debilitation  Page 10
46. Female Horoscopy 
Important Houses, the Moon and the Ascendant, Trimsamsa positions, Moon/Ascendant in various Trimsamsas of various Signs, beastly lust of a female, unchastity, mother and daughter to be unchaste, miscellaneous, rulers of the 7th Sign and 7th Navāńśa, planets in the Ascendant, 8th House, female with masculine disposition, religious order, Vedic exponent, application of rules 
47. Aphorisms of Death. Reasons of death, death by drowning/fall, fire, hanging, due to a female, trident's hit, hit by wood, by a club, due to royal wrath, due to insects, intoxicants and machinery, in filthy surroundings, by thirst, weapons and birds, 22nd decanate, 22nd decanate related to the 36 decanates of the Zodiac and reasons of death therefrom 
48. Lost Horoscopy 
Effects of births in the 12 different Ascendants in the context of lost horoscopy 
49. Effects of Horas 
24 halves of the 12 Signs and effects thereof in the context of lost horoscopy 
50. Effects of Decanates 
36 decanates of the Zodiac and effects thereof in the context of lost horoscopy 
51. Effects of Navāńśas 
108 Navāńśas of the Zodiac and effects thereof in the context of lost horoscopy 
52. Lost Horoscopy 
The natal Ayana, other natal factors, position of the querist, personal name, another method, lost horoscopy based on the Moon at query 
53. Ashtakavarga 
Planetary BhinnashtakaVargas, method of preparation of A.V. charts 
54. Effects of Ashtakavarga 
Effects of the A.V. of planets from the Sun to Saturn 
55. Manifold Births

