
Saravali 
Page 9
Ch. 38. Effects of Natural Constituents and Primordial Components
1. Mars denotes one's prowess, Mercury greatness (or physical weight), Jupiter voice, Venus splendour (or friendship) and Saturn complexion (physical brightness). 
2. EFFECTS OF SATTVA GUNA. If Sattva is predominant in a native, he will be highly merciful, will possess many wives and attendants, will be firm in disposition, will be a sweet and truthful speaker, will honour Gods and Brahmins and will be of forgiving temperament. 
3. EFFECTS OF RAJOGUNA. One with predominant RajoGuna will be valorous, be skillful in fine arts and literature, be fond of uniting with women, be skillful, showy, jocular, spirited and be interested in music and gambling. 
4. EFFECTS OF TAMOGUNA. With TamoGuna predominant, the native will be foolish, indolent, will cheat others, be irascible, miserable, be a talebearer, be devoid of good conduct, unkempt. blind due to lasciviousness, miserly and careless. 
5. PRIMORDIAL COMPOUNDS (PANCHA BHUTAS). According to the strengths of Jupiter, Venus, Saturn, Mars and Mercury, the native will acquire the effects of the five Tatwas, viz. Ether, Water, Air, Fire and Earth. The strongest of the planet will impart corresponding temperament, viz. windy, bilious, or phlegmatic. If many planets attain strengths, these derivations will be mixed. 
6. EFFECTS OF AKASA TATWA (ETHER). One with predominant characteristics of Ether will be skillful in grammar and meanings, be an expert in justice, be bold, know ledgeable, will have a broad face and peculiar physical joints, weak hands and feet and be quite tall. 
7. EFFECTS OF JALATATWA (WATER). The native with predominant Watery nature will be quite charming, will endure heavy loads, will speak sweetly, be tremulous in appearance, will have many friends, be a king and will not be lastingly bold. 
8. EFFECTS OF VAYU TATWA (AIR). One of predominant Airy nature will have an emaciated body, be easily given to anger, be deeply merged in his work, be of wandering disposition, be liberal, fair in complexion and be an inviolable king. 
9. EFFECTS OF FIERY TATWA. One with predominant Fiery character, will be valorous, be hunger-stricken, be very sharp, learned, emaciated, fair in complexion, inimical, will have beautiful arms, will be a voracious eater and be tall. 
10. EFFECTS OF PRITHVI TATWA (EARTH). One with Earthy nature will emanate the good smell of camphor, of jasmine and of blue lotus from his person, will enjoy abundantly, will possess voice, akin to that of a (roaring) lion, or clouds, be firm in disposition and be endowed with prowess. 
11. BIRTH WITH AKASA TATWA. One born with the reflection of AKASA TATWA (ether) will be endowed with a physique with the brightness of crystal and of a gem. Just as wealth confers happiness this reflection will make one achieve effects of TriVargas (i.e. the three objects of worldly existence, viz. Dharma, or moral merits, Artha, or attainment of riches, or worldly prosperity and Kama, or desire of sensual enjoymentthese three ends form the well known triad excluding Moksha, or final emancipation). 
12. BIRTH WITH JALA TATWA (water). One born with the reflection of watery tatwa will be glossy, will have the complexion of white Durva grass, will receive protection as, if from the mother and will prosper. 
13. BIRTH WITH VAYU TATWA (air). One born with the reflection of Vayu Tatwa will be akin to black clouds (that are going just to cause heavy rains), will emanate foul smell, be very foolish, will have a dirty and coarse physique, be subjected to great miseries and will experience poverty, diseases, evils and financial destruction. 
14. BIRTH WITH AGNI TATWA. One born with the reflection of Agni (fiery) Tatwa will be bright, as the burning flame, will confer severe punishments, will conquer all his enemies and the earth by his own valour, will possess jewels, gold etc., will attain success in all his undertakings and will be free from diseases and grief. 
15. BIRTH WITH EARTHY TATWA. One born with the reflection of Prithwi (earth) Tatwa will emanate smell from the body akin to the smell coming out of earth, when sprinkled with fresh drizzles. He will have charming teeth, nails, hair and body. He will attain merits and happiness and be dear to all. 
16-17. SIGNS OF PREDOMINANT WINDY TEMPERAMENT. One with predominant windy temperament will be benumbed with cold and shivering, will speak much and will walk fast, be fond of moving in boats, be valorous, spiteful, sickly, unfortunate, unjust, will not be very friendly disposed, will have knowledge of music, be emaciated, be skillful in acquiring friends, will fly in the skies in dreams, be devoid of courage and gratitude, will have rough hair, will have splay feet and crooked arms, be irascible, will have lost splendour and will face financial losses. 
18-19. SIGNS OF PREDOMINANT BILIOUS TEMPERAMENT. One with predominant bile will emanate foul smell from his person, be less distressed, greatly intelligent, be easily satisfied, will have large transparent nails, large eyes, hands and feet, will resemble an old man, will suffer morbid heat, be a scholar, be fearless, fond of cold articles, will not fear even at the hands of his enemies, will be affectionate to all and will be fond of food. His dreams will be about gold, sun. light, forest-conflagration, kimsuka (a kind of tree, which yields charming red blossoms, which however have no fragrance), precious stones, karnikara (the pericarp of a lotus, alternatively a kind of flower with excellent hue, but no smell and hence disliked), red lotus, eunuch, blood and lightning. 
20-21. SIGNS OF PREDOMINANT PHLEGMATIC TEMPERAMENT. One with predominant phlegmatic temperament will be wealthy, will have clung joints, be courageous and strong, will have a bright and charming physique, be a recipient (of gifts, benefits etc.), be Sattvik, will have voice akin to the sound of a drum and roaring clouds, be enduring, fair in complexion, will have reddish eyes, will enjoy sweet drinks, (sometimes) will be highly inimical, be grateful, be friendly to all and will honour elders. His dreams will be seas, rivers, coral stones, lakes, swan, conch, stars, lily, snowfall etc. These effects are attributed by the sages. 
22. LUMINARIES IN MAHAPURUSHA YOGAS. Though Mars etc. may be strong in the respective cases of Pancha Mahapurusha Yogas (vide Sloka 2 of this Ch.), if the Sun and the Moon are weak, the person will not attain kinghood, but in the period of the concerned planet will be endowed with children and wealth. 
Thus ends the 38th Ch. entitled “GUNA TATWA PHALA” in Kalyana Varma's “SARAVALI”. Ch. 39. Obstructions To RajaYogas 
1. Earlier, the Yogas of kinghood have been explained. There can be some factors, which prevent the effects of such Yogas, which I explain in this Ch.. 
2. Out of Mars, Saturn, Jupiter and the Sun, if two, or more be in fall and one of them simultaneously be in the Ascendant, as the Moon is in Scorpio, the RajaYogas will become futile. 
3. The RajaYogas in the horoscope are only name sake, if the Moon being weak is in the last Navāńśa of a Movable Sign, or in the 8th Navāńśa of a Fixed Sign, or in the first Navāńśa of a Common Sign and is without aspect from any other planet. 4. Same effects will come to pass, if all malefics occupy Angles identical with debilitation/inimical Signs, while benefics are shunted to the 12th, 6th and 8th Houses. 
5. If the Ascendant is in Vargothama position without aspect to any planet, the RajaYogas will only be a failure. 
6. Even a hundred kingly Yogas will be of no avail, if Aquarius rises, while 3 heavenly bodies are in their Signs of fall. 
7. If there is no benefic in an Angle, or with the Moon, while 4 planets are either in fall, or in combustion, or in inimical Signs, the RajaYogas are marred. 
8. Should the Sun be in his own Navāńśa, while the Moon is in combustion and in aspect to malefics without the aspect of benefics, the native will enjoy rulership (with the help of other Raja Yogas) only to relinquish the kingdom soon and will become miserable. 
9. Should the Moon lend her inimical aspect to the Ascendant Lord, while the Sun, Mars and Saturn are in their order in the 3rd, 6th and 7th, the RajaYogas will become ineffective. Benefics should in this case be not in Angles, but suffer combustion. 
10. If five heavenly bodies are in fall at birth the RajaYogas will not come to pass. 
11. If meteor, noise of contending winds in the sky (or earth quake, or thunder), Vyatipata, or Upaketu be seen at the time of birth, the good RajaYogas stand nullified. 
12. If Trisankhu Nakshatra (Trisankhu was a monarch of the solar race, who remained suspended with his head towards the earth, as a constellation in the southern hemisphere) rises at the time of one's birth, while the Ascendant is occupied by Saturn, as there is fall of a comet, the Raja Yogas do not come to pass. 
13. If the planets capable of causing Raja Yoga are inclined to enter in war, or are becoming splendourless, or about to lose their strength, the RajaYogas will stand canceled. 
14. If weak Moon is in her deep degree of debilitation the RajaYogas get destroyed, just as a king going against an astrologer. 
15. The Sun in the 10th degree of Libra will destroy all RajaYogas, just as miserliness eclipses all the good attributes of a person. 
16. This Sloka is repeated in the original. The meaning is identical with that of Sloka 15 above. 
17. Even though other planets may be in their Mulatrikona, exaltation, or own Signs, while the Sun is singly in deep fall, the RajaYogas will be unavailable. 
18. If Jupiter occupies Capricorn, as Ascendant, while the Moon is not in Cancer, the native will become miserable, just as a penniless lewdster in the place of a courtesan. 
19. If in the formation of Kemadruma Yoga, the Moon is without the aspect of another planet, the RajaYogas lose their existence and the native will be devoid of good conduct. 
20. If 3, or more planets be in fall even the son of an emperor ruling over the entire earth will take to begging, be miserable, be dirty and penniless. 
21. If 5 planets occupy inimical Signs, or are in combustion, while the Sun, or the Moon is not in exaltation, the kingly Yogas will become ineffective. 
22. If Venus occupy his debilitation Navāńśa, even a vast kingdom is deprived from the native. 
23. RajaYogas have been explained earlier. The combinations marring such kingly states are given in this Ch.. The stronger one of these two will only prevail. 
24. RAJA YOGA. The Sun in Virgo, Mars in Scorpio along with Jupiter, as the Moon is in Aries: this configuration will produce a king the dust of whose elephants will darken the-skies. 
Thus ends the 39th Ch. entitled “OBSTRUCTIONS TO RAJAYOGAS” In Kalyana Varma's Saravali. Ch. 40. Calculation of Longevity 
1. The people all over remain perplexed over the question of longevity. So I narrate the relative principles based on the Shastras here under. 
2-3. SELECTION OF SYSTEM FOR LONGEVITY COMPUTATION. Out of the triothe Sun, the Moon and the Ascendant, if the Ascendant is the strongest, Amsayurdaya should be resorted to. Pindayu is the best, if the Sun is predominant, while Nisargayu is the apt choice with Moon prevailing. If the three in question are bereft of strength, then Jeevasarma's system can be used. 
4. AMSAYURDAYA CALCULATIONS. The longitudes (counted from Aries first point) of the (seven) planets and the Ascendant should be divided by 200 to get the number of years. The quotients in later processes should be multiplied by the respective multipliers to get months, days and Ghatis. 
5. ADDITIONS FOR ASCENDANT'S CONTRIBUTION. If the Ascendant is strong the number of years equal to the Rāśis it has traversed should be added. Months etc. thereof should be guessed by rule of three method. 
6. RECTIFICATIONS FOR PLANETARY CONTRIBUTIONS. The contribution made by a planet, that is in Vargothama, own Sign, own decanate, or own Navāńśa should be doubled. If it is retrograde, or in exaltation the figure should be trebled. 
7. If a planet's contribution gets doubled by virtue of position in own Sign, own decanate etc. (as per Sloka 6 above) and further warrants trebling by virtue of retrogression/exaltation, the trebling should also be done. So say the learned. 
8. According to Chudamani Acharya, if a planet is in Angle contributions by each rectification shall be considered. If it is in Panaphara (2nd, 5th, 8th and 11th) only two multiplications be done. If it is in Apoklima (3rd, 6th, 9th and 12th) only one (i.e. the highest) should be taken. 
9. According to Varaha Mihira, if many multiplications are warranted, only the highest be considered. But this view is not acceptable to ancestors. 
10. REDUCTIONS FOR AMSAYURDAYA CONTRIBUTIONS. If a planet is in its inimical Sign, a third of the earlier (final) figure should only be taken. If it is combust in the Sun, only half need be computed. The contributions by Venus and Saturn do not suffer reductions on account of their combustion. 
11-12. VYAYADI (CHAKRARDHA) HARANA. A malefic in the 12th loses all his contribution. If in the 11th half, in the 10th a third, in the 9th a fourth, in the 8th one fifth and in the 7th one sixth of the contribution suffers. Benefics in these places lose just half of what malefics lose. Further, if there are two, or more planets in one and the same House, only the strongest suffers reduction. 
13-15. PINDAYU. In this system the planets from the Sun onwards through Saturn contribute, respectively, 19, 25, 15, 12, 15, 21 and 20 in their order, when they are in (deep) exaltation. From the longitude of the planet (for which the contribution is being computed) deduct its highest exaltation degree (counted from Aries first point). In case the minuend is greater than the subtrahend, then increase the former by 12 Signs i.e. 360 degrees). Multiply the latest product by the number of years allotted for the planet and divide by 12 to get years. Dividers for months equal to Amsas (or degrees i e. 30) and for days Vikalas (i.e. 60). 
16. In the case of Pindayurdaya also the same multiplications and rectifications apply. Leaving aside a retrograde planet, one in inimical Sign loses a third, while the one in fall retains only half of the contribution. The planet in exaltation retains the entire contribution. 
17. ASCENDANTAL CONTRIBUTION IN PINDAYURDAYA. If the Navāńśa Lagna Lord is strong, then the years contributed will equal the Navāńśas past, If, however, the Lagna Rāśi Lord is stronger, then the Rāśis past up to Lagna (counted from Aries) will be the number of years. 
18-19. REDUCTION FOR RISING PLANETS. If malefics occupy the Ascendant, convert the Ascendant into degrees, minutes etc. Multiply this by the number of years contributed by the malefics in question. Then divide the product by 21,600. Respective products should be reduced from the earlier contributions of each of the malefics occupying the Ascendant. (This will be the net contribution by each malefic in case he occupies the Ascendant). If the malefics in Ascendant are aspected by the benefics suffice it to say half of the reduction need only be done. 
20. NISARGA YURDAYA. In the Nisargayu scheme, the planets from the Sun to Saturn contribute 20, 1, 2, 9, 18, 20 and 50, respectively. 
21. FULL SPAN OF LIFE. The full span of life (120 years and 5 days) will be enjoyed by the native, who has Pisces Ascendant with its 9th Navāńśa and Mercury in 25 degrees of Taurus, while others are in their deep exaltation points. 
22. UNLIMITED LONGEVITY. Jupiter along with the Moon in Cancer identical with the Ascendant, Mercury with Venus in an Angle (or separately in Angles), while the rest are in the 3rd, 6th and 11th: One with this combination will enjoy a limitless life span. 
23-24. SPAN OF FULL LIFE FOR VARIOUS ANIMALS. The full span of life of elephants and men are 120 years and 5 days. For horses it is 32 years, for goats etc. 16 years, for camels and donkeys 25 years, for cows and buffaloes 24 years and for dogs 12 years. Just as for the mankind, the longevity for the various animals can be computed. The computations should be done, as explained supra, multiplied by the figure representing full life span and divided by 120. 
25. Only those, who consume wholesome diet, those, who are virtuous, those, who have good conduct and those, who conquer their senses will enjoy the longevity, as laid down by the sages. 
Thus ends the 40th Ch. entitled “LONGEVITY CALCULATION” in Kalyana Varma's Saravali. Ch. 41. Moola Dasa 
1. The Dasa duration of a planet is equal to the number of years it contributes (as per Moola Dasa scheme). All planets yield in their Dasas pleasant, or unpleasant results according to their (natal) dispositions. 
2. ORDER OF THE SCHEME. According to Manitha, those, who are born during day time will have the Dasas commencing with that of the Sun, while the night-born will have it from that of Venus. But this view is not acceptable to other preceptors. 
3. SATYA'S VIEW. The first Dasa will be of the strongest of the Ascendant, the Sun and the Moon followed by the ones in Angle, Panaphara and Apoklima. This is the view held by Satyacharya. 
4-5. The first Dasa will be of the strongest of the Ascendant, the Sun and the Moon. Then the planets in Angles will be Dasa Lords. Thereafter the planets in Panapharas (2nd, 5th, 8th and 11th Houses) will lord over the major periods, while the last Dasas will be headed by the planets posited in Apoklimas (3rd, 6th, 9th and 12th Houses). If Angles etc. are occupied by more than one planet, the strongest will have its Dasa first. Even, if the strengths of these be identical, then the order will be according to maximum years donated by these planets Granting, that these durations are also similar, then the risings of planets will prevail, Even, if one of the triad, viz. the Ascendant, the Sun and the Moon, is strong, then Satya's scheme, as above should be resorted to. If none is strong enough, then the Dasa scheme of other preceptors may be considered. 
6. AUSPICIOUS PERIODS. Planets in exaltation, own Rāśi, own Navāńśa, friendly Sign, possessing full rays and those with full strength prove auspicious in their Dasas. At the commencement of a Dasa a planet, that is strong, or is in a friendly division, or is in aspect to a benefic will also yield similar good results. 
7. INAUSPICIOUS PERIODS. The planet, that is in its Sign of fall, Sign ruled by an enemy, Navāńśa of an enemy, combust in the Sun, devoid of splendour, or is in aspect to malefics will yield inauspicious effects in its Dasa. 
8. If a planet has departed from its exaltation, its Dasa is known, as Avarohini (stepping down) Dasa. If, however, it is in own, or friendly divisions, the effects will be medium, i.e. neither good nor bad. The Dasa of a planet approaching its exaltation, departing from debilitation, is known, as Arohini (climbing) Dasa. If the said planet is in inimical, or debilitation divisions, it will inflict difficulties. 
9. The Sun is the ripener (or baker) of the effects of a Dasa, while the Moon is the sustaining agent. That is why the Moon's transit position at the time of the commencement of a Dasa should be duly considered. 
10-14. EFFECTS OF THE MOON. If the Moon at the commencement of a Moola Dasa is in Virgo, the native throughout the period will be related to courtesans and be associated with them. This view is held by Yavanas. If she is in Cancer at the beginning of Dasa, the native will gain wealth through virtuous ladies. If in Aries, or in Scorpio he will injure the honour of virgins and also bring evils to his own female. If the Sign in question be of Mercury knowledge of Shastras and acquisition of friends will come to pass. In a Sign of Venus, it brings plenty of food and drinks, happiness and destruction of enemies. In a House of Jupiter, it brings happiness, wealth, honour and commandability. Saturn's Sign endows with association with old ladies. Leo denotes movements in forts and forests, agriculture and misunderstanding with wife and children. These are the effects accruing out of the Moon's placement at the commencement of a Dasa. 
15. ASPECTS TO MOON AT THE COMMENCEMENT OF A DASA. If the Moon at the commencement of a Dasa receives the aspect of Mars, or Saturn there will be loss of relatives and of wealth followed by diseases. Mercury's aspect confers learning, while the aspects of other planets will give effects according to their nature. 
16. MAJOR LORD'S PLACEMENT AT THE COMMENCEMENT OF A DASA. If the Lord of the Dasa is in the Ascendant prevailing at the moment the Dasa begins, or in the 3rd, 6th, 10th, or 11th from the said Ascendant, the Dasa then proves excellent. 
17-18. AGAIN MOON'S PLACEMENT. If the Moon at the commencement of a major period occupy a friendly Sign, exaltation Sign, or an Upachaya House (3rd, 6th, 10th, or 11th House), 5th, 9th, or 7th counted from the major Lord, good effects will come to pass in the Dasa in question. If the Moon is otherwise placed, even a planet in exaltation at birth will give inauspicious results in its Dasa. 
19. SPECIAL EFFECTS BASED ON NAVĀŃŚA. Even though a planet may be in friendly Sign, if it occupies simultaneously a Navāńśa belonging to its enemy, or be in fall in Navāńśa, the effects in the Dasa concerned will be mixed. A weak planet's Dasa will be futile. 
20. LAGNA DASA. The Ascendant's major period will prove auspicious, if it is in the first decanate of a Movable Sign; medium in the second decanate and poor in the 3rd decanate. The reverse is true with a Common Sign ascending, i e. third, second and first decanate will, respectively, be auspicious, medium and poor. As for a Fixed Sign ascending first, second and third decanates will, respectively, give poor, auspicious and medium effects. 
21. NAISARGIKA DASA. The Naisargika Dasa follows in the order of the Moon, Mars, Mercury, Venus, Jupiter, the Sun, Saturn and the Ascendant. 
22-24. If the planet is exalted, or is endowed with temporal strength, or full strength, in its Dasa incomparably auspicious results will come to pass. The planet, that is in its own Sign, Moolatrikona Sign, own Navāńśa, or hemmed between benefics will yield moderately auspicious effects. The planet, that is going towards its exaltation (departing from Sign of its fall), or is placed in friendly Signs etc., feebly auspicious effects will be felt. Similar deductions should be made in regard to planets otherwise placed. 
25-26. EFFECTS OF FAVOURABLE SUN'S DASA. If the Sun is favourable, in his Dasa, there will be gains from forests, medicines, travels, poison, evil friendship, forests, ivory, skin, fire and royal association. Courage, diligence, intelligence, fame and valour will be on the increase. Excellence and kingship will be achieved by the native. 
27-28. EFFECTS OF ADVERSE SUN'S DASA. If the Sun is adverse, in his Dasa there will be grief on account of servants, wealth, theft, eyes, weapons, fire, water and king and the native will be tormented by children, wife and relatives He will be interested in sinful acts and be troubled by hunger, thirst (or morbid fever), heart ailments, bilious diseases and bodily damages. 
29-30½. EFFECTS OF FAVOURABLE MOON'S DASA. If the Moon is favourable, in her Dasa there will be gains through female association, soft disposition, journey, water, ice, milk, juice, jaggery, sugar, sports, initiation into Mantras through Brahmins, flowers, robes, sweet food etc. He will achieve success in his undertakings out of his intelligence, will receive honours from elders and the king and will be endowed with increased courage and wisdom. 31-32. EFFECTS OF ADVERSE MOON'S DASA. If the Moon is evil, in her Dasa there will be fear in family, misunderstanding with one's family members, difficulties, loss of wealth, enmity with royal assembly, sleep, indolence, evils through women and grief. 
33-34. EFFECTS OF FAVOURABLE MARS DASA. During the Dasa of favourable Mars, one will gain through kings, fire, thieves, enemies, snakes, poison, weapons, confinements, fictitious articles, lands, goats, buffaloes, copper, gold, prostitutes, gambling, intoxicants, pungent articles/juices, wealth and grains. 
35-36 EFFECTS OF ADVERSE MARS DASA. During the Dasa of evil Mars, there will be enmity with friends, wife, children and brothers, sufferances from thirst, swooning, bloody defects, loss of limbs and wounds. There will be attachment to others' wives and irreligious acts, followed by aversion to elders and to truth. Bilious excesses will trouble the subject. 
37-39. EFFECTS OF FAVOURABLE MERCURY DASA. In the Dasa of favourable Mercury, there will be gains via friends, children, wealth, king, businessmen, priests, gambling etc. The native will acquire horses, lands, gold, fame, ambassadorship, limitless happiness, fortunes, high intelligence, fame, success in religious activities, fond of amusement, destruction of foes and enthusiasm in mathematics and drawings. 
40. EFFECTS OF ADVERSE MERCURY S DASA. If Mercury is evil, in the concerned Dasa the native will be tormented by imbalances of the three temperaments (viz. bile, phlegm and wind), hard disposition, imprisonment, mental grief and excitement. 
41-43. EFFECTS OF FAVOURABLE JUPITER'S DASA. If Jupiter is favourable, the native in that Dasa will gain through ministers (or advisers), kings, dances and states manship. He will gain honours, virtues, courage, wide friend ship, life partner, gold, quadrupeds, conveyances, auspicious acts, destruction of enemies, royal acquiantance and will obtain wealth through public, king, businessmen and elders. 
44. EFFECTS OF ADVERSE JUPITER'S DASA. If Jupiter be inauspicious one will in such Dasa have physical defects, excessive grief, lameness, diseases of the stomach and ears, loss of semen and marrow and fear from kings. 
45-46. EFFECTS OF FAVOURABLE VENUS DASA. If Venus is auspicious one will in the Dasa be successful and will gain lands, residences, bed comforts, wife, garlands, robes, good food, fame, happiness and treasure. He will have liking for music, will develop acqaintance with females, will gain through kings and lands, will derive wisdom, desired happiness and friends and gains through articles used for sexual enjoyments. 
47. EFFECTS OF UNFAVORABLE VENUS DASA. If Venus is inauspicious the native will in the Dasa have litigations with virtuous people, will have troubles from conveyances, furniture, females and kings and will develop intimacy with unsocial elements. 
48-49. EFFECTS OF FAVOURABLE SATURN'S DASA. If Saturn is favourable in his Dasa the native will gain camels, asses etc., association with unchaste, or old ladies, gain through pulses, sesamum and grains eaten by poor people, leadership over villages and iron etc. His people will acquire a permanent position. 
50-51. EFFECTS OF ADVERSE SATURN'S DASA. If Saturn is adverse, there will be loss of conveyances, excitement, enmity, separation from wife and other family members, loss in battles, liking for intoxicants and gambling, windy diseases, loss of meritorious acts, confinement, lassitude, affliction to limbs and enmity with children and servants. 
52. The good and bad effects for the Dasas have been explained above in a general manner. Narrated below are the effects arising out of special considerations. 
53. SUN'S DASA. There are five kinds of placements, which enable us to derive five different types of Sun's Dasa. These positions are: exaltation, fall, Moolatrikona, Angle and enemy's Sign. 
54-59. The Sun in Ascendant gives kingdom during his Dasa; while posited in other Kendras ruled by inimical planets there will be disorders of hip, throat and eyes. Debilitated Sun in his Dasa causes destruction of eyes, fever and head disorders, confinement, leprosy and other disorders. If the Sun is exalted, there will be gain of kingdom with royal insignia in such Dasa. Apart, there will be acquisition of elephants, steeds etc. The Dasa of the Sun placed in his Moolatrikona will indicate destruction of all kinds of miseries and leadership of large provinces. In the Dasa of the Sun placed in inimical Sign, one will incur affliction of eyes, hump-back, disorders caused by fire, facial diseases and humiliation due to misconduct. The 8th House placement of the Sun will cause in his Dasa affliction to the entire body and wanderings in various countries. 
60-65. MOON'S DASA. The Moon's Dasa is generally differentiated in six categories, viz. exalted, debilitated, friendly Sign, inimical Sign and diminishing and increasing Moon's Dasas. The different dignities of the Moon give following results in the Dasa concerned: exaltedkingdom, debilitated death, inimical Sign confinement, friendly Sign association with own men, decreasing Moon fever and disorders of abdomen, head and eyes. If the Moon is full and is endowed with strength, in such Dasa the native will be surrounded by thousands of superior females. If she be relegated to the 8th House, the native in such Dasa will be humiliated by his own men, will live through machinery, grass, firewood, cowdung, bamboo, medicinal plants, fruits and water. He will acquire only deteriorated food and rags and even a king will have to resort to servitude. 
66-68. OTHER PLACEMENT OF PLANETS. Those exalted in the Ascendant confer rulership of a province in their Dasas, while those in exaltation in other Angles will bestow, wealth, conveyances and rulership of a country. If a planet is in the 6th, the native will be subjected to evils, misfortunes etc. In the Dasa of a planet placed in the 8th, death will be inflicted. There will only be confinement in the Dasa of a combust planet. The Dasa of a retrograde planet will cause wanderings, like that of a wheel, evils and enmity. This applies only to malefics in retrogression, but not to benefics. 
69. Though one may be a king, he will become a servant of his own servants in the Dasas of a planet devoid of strength, a planet totally devoid of strength, a planet in fall, a planet in deep fall, a planet in inimical Sign and a planet in dead enemy's. 
70. In the Dasa of a planet placed in enemy's Sign, there will be circumstances to leave one's own country (in distress), diseases, loss of position, frequent quarrels and confinement. 
71. Even a king with vast number of elephants, that can wet the earth with their ichor, will surely wander in difficulty in the Dasa of a planet occupying an inimical Sign. 
72-73. In the Dasas of the planets placed in the 6th, 5th, 9th, or 7th Houses identical with inimical Signs, there will be troubles to limbs and secondary limbs (like the nose), while the Dasa of the planet in the 8th House identical with its inimical House will cause beheading (or afflictions to head), fear from enemies, wanderings in foreign places, troubles of confinement, diseases etc. If the Dasa of a planet, that is in fall be in operation humiliation from royal sources will follow. 
74. The Native will derive (good) effects of a weak planet's Dasa in dreams and thoughts. The effects due to Pancha Maha Purusha Yogas will come to pass in the Dasas of the concerned planets. 
75. The planets in Seershodaya Signs will give their effects in the beginning of the Dasas; those in Ubhayodaya will give in the middle of the Dasas effects due to them and those in Prishtodaya Signs as well, as those in fall will reveal their effects in the concluding parts of their Dasas. 
Thus ends the 41st Ch. entitled “MOOLA DASA” in Kalyana Varma's Saravali. Ch. 42. Effects Of Sub Periods 
1. DISTRIBUTION OF SUB PERIODS TO PLANETS IN MOOLA DASA. A planet, that is conjunct the Dasa Lord will subrule half of the period. The subrulership further goes to planets, as under: one third to that in the 5th/9th from the Dasa Lord; one seventh to that in the 7th from the Dasa Lord and one fourth to that in the 4th/8th with reference to Dasa Lord. 
2-3. The sub-Lords will ripen the sub-period effects according to their own nature. Should there be more than one planet in the Houses specified above, the strongest of them will rule over the sub period (and not others). The sub periods of benefics will yield benefic results, while those of malefics will give inauspicious effects. According to some authorities, planets in Angles will first lord over the sub-periods followed by those in Panaphara (2nd, 5th, 8th and 11th) and Apoklima (3rd, 6th, 9th and 12th) 
4. According to Satyacharya, the sub periods will rule according to the orders of strength in case there is more than one planet in one House. 
5. Take the fractions (as mentioned in Sloka 1) and reduce them to equivalent fractions with a common denominator. Add up the aliquot parts of the Dasa representative of the various numerators leaving out the denominators. The sub periods will be arrived at, when the various aliquots are converted into years within the main Dasa and divided by a common factor. 
6-7. Planets, that are conjunct the major Lord will cause confinement and loss of wealth in their sub periods. If, however, the major Lord is in an Angle, or in a Trine from the Ascendant, there will be great happiness. If a planet conjunct 2, or more planets be in an inimical House, in such sub period, only diseases, evils, quarrels and royal displeasures will come to pass. 
8. In the sub period of a planet in the 7th from the Mooladasa Lord, death of wife, or the wife's becoming a servant of an enemy, or getting attached to another man is denoted. 
9-10. Death, destruction of wealth, or imprisonment will result in the sub period of the planet in the 8th from the Moola Dasa Lord. If 2, or 3, or 4 malefics join in one House other than an Angle, or a Trine, imprisonment, destruction and poverty will be the order of the sub period. 
11. In the sub period of a planet in the 4th from the Mooladasa Lord there will be gain through friends, happiness and increased honours. 
12. SUN DASAMOON BHUKTI. In the major period of the Sun, the Moon's sub period will subdue the valour of the enemies of the native. He will gain health, wealth and happiness. 
13. SUN DASAMARS BHUKTI. In the sub period of Mars and in the major period of the Sun, the native gain corals, gold, success in battle, splendour and happiness. 
14. SUN DASAMERCURY BHUKTI. In the sub period of Mercury under the Sun's major period, the native will suffer from itch, leprosy etc. and will face increase of enemies. 
15. SUN DASAJUPITER BHUKTI. If the Sub period of Jupiter be in operation in the major period of the Sun, there will be destruction of diseases, enemies, sins and poverty and gain of virtues and happiness. 
16. SUN DASAVENUS BHUKTI. In the sub period of Venus under the Sun's major period, one will suffer from head throat diseases, fever and gout, followed by defeat from enemies and leaving the native country. 
17. SUN DASASATURN BHUKTI. In the sub period of Saturn and in the major period of the Sun, there will be royal wrath, poverty and defeat from enemies. 
18. MOON DASASUN BHUKTI. During the Sun's sub period, in the major period of the Moon, the native will suffer from tuberculosis, but will be valorous, will earn wealth through kings and will enjoy all kinds of monetary gains. 
19. MOON DASAMARS BHUKTI. In the major period of the Moon and in the sub period of Mars, there will be bilious complaints, diseases of the blood, fear from fire, evils, ill health and fear from thieves. 
20. MOON DASAMERCURY BHUKTI. In the sub period of Mercury and in the major period of the Moon, one will gain positions with formal seal (or insignia), elephants, horses and wealth and will enjoy incomparable happiness. 
21. MOON DASAJUPITER SUB PERIOD. In the major period of the Moon and in the sub period of Jupiter, there will be gain of wealth, sudden acquisition of robes, jewels and conveyances. 
22. MOON DASAVENUS BHUKTI. In the major period of the Moon and in the sub period of Venus, there will be acquisition of conveyances run in waters, robes, ornaments and many wives. 
23. MOON DASASATURN BHUKTI. In the sub period of Saturn in the major period of the Moon, there will be separation from one's own men, fear from diseases and great grief. 
24 MARS DASASUN BHUKTI. If the Sun's sub period, in the major period of Mars be in operation, the native will be fierce, valorous, be honoured by the king, be successful in battle and will acquire wealth in various ways. 
25. MARS DASAMOON BHUKTI. In the sub period of the Moon in the major period of Mars, the native will procure wealth in various ways, be happy, will have many friends and plenty of corals etc. 
26. MARS DASAMERCURY BHUKTI. In the sub period of Mercury under the major period of Mars, one will have fear from thieves and enemies, loss of horses and elephants and burning sensation. 
27. MARS DASAJUPITER BHUKTI. In Mars Dasa and in Jupiter's sub period there will be good conduct, virtues, meritorious acts etc. 
28. MARS DASAVENUS BHUKTI. In the sub period of Venus in the major period of Mars, the native will have fear of war, diseases, evils and loss of wealth. 
29. MARS DASASATURN BHUKTI. In the sub period of Saturn, in the major period of Mars, there will be evils after evils and loss of wealth and of near and dear. 
30. MERCURY DASASUN BHUKTI. There will be sudden income of wealth, gold, horses, cora1, elephants etc. in tl1e sub period of the Sun and in the major period of Mercury. 
31. MERCURY DASAMOON BHUKTI. In the sub period of the Moon in the major period of Mercury, one will be afflicted by itch, leprosy, tuberculosis, loss of limbs, fear from elephants and destruction of conveyances. 
32. MERCURY DASAMARS BHUKTI. During the sub rulership of Mars in the major period of Mercury, there will be diseases of the head, gout, many kinds of miseries etc. 
33. MERCURY DASAJUPITER BHUKTI. One will be free from enemies, diseases and sins, be virtuous and become a royal adviser in the sub period of Jupiter under the major leadership of Mercury. 
34. MERCURY DASAVENUS BHUKTl. If the sub period of Venus be in operation in the major period of Mercury, one will honour elders, Gods and guests and will acquire robes and ornaments. 
35. MERCURY DASASATURN BHUKTI. In the sub period of Saturn in the major period of Mercury the native will seek sexual gratification, like a eunuch (or, like a bull) and be deprived of virtues, wealth, pleasures and issues. 
36. JUPITER DASASUN BHUKTI. The native will be free from enemies and diseases and will be honoured by the king in the sub period of the Sun in the major period of Jupiter. He will either be endowed with valour and happiness. 
37. JUPITER DASAMOON BHUKTI. In the sub period of the Moon in the Dasa of Jupiter one will marry a thousand women, will conquer diseases and enemies and will prosper in all fronts akin to a king. 
38. JUPITER DASAMARS BHUKTI. In the sub period of Mars in the major period of Jupiter, one will be rude, will win over enemies, be valorous, be famous in war and will enjoy all kinds of happiness. 
39. JUPITER DASAMERCURY BHUKTI. There will be destruction of diseases, acquisition of friends and respect for parents in the sub period of Mercury in the major period of Jupiter. 
40. JUPITER DASAVENUS BHUKTI. In the sub period of Venus in the major period of Jupiter, the native will have fear from enemies, will face destruction and grief and will live through Brahmins. 
41. JUPITER DASASATURN BHUKTI. In the sub period of Saturn and in the major period of Jupiter, the native will be attached to prostitutes and intoxicants and will be insulted in gambling. He will be endowed with buffaloes and acses and be devoid of virtues. 
42. VENUS DASASUN BHUKTI. In the sub period of the Sun in the major period of Venus, there will be disease, of the throat, stomach and eyes and punishments from the king. 
43. VENUS DASAMOON BHUKTI. In the sub period of the Moon in the major period of Venus one will suffer from diseases of nails, teeth and head apart from jaundice. 
44. VENUS DASAMARS BHUKTI. In the sub period of Mars and in the major period of Venus, one will suffer from diseases related to blood and bile, will gain lands, royal patronage and enthusiasm. 
45. VENUS DASAMERCURY SUB PERIOD. In the sub period of Mercury and in the major period of Venus one will gain through women and will enjoy happiness and fulfillment of desires. 
46. VENUS DASAJUPITER BHUKTI. In the sub period of Jupiter in the major period of Venus, there will be growth of virtues, good qualities and wealth and acquisition of kingdom. 
47. VENUS DASASATURN BHUKTI. In the sub period of Saturn and in the major period of Venus, one will sport with old women (i. e. be associated with them), will head over cities, men etc. and will destroy enemies. 
48. SATURN DASASUN BHUKTI. In the sub period of the Sun in the major period of Saturn, there will be destruction of wealth, wife and children and abundant fear from enemies. 
49. SA TURN DASA--MOON BHUKTI. In the sub period of the Moon and in the major period of Saturn, one will lose his wife, or she will be kidnapped. The native will incur separation from relatives, or enmity with them. 
50. SATURN DASAMARS BHUKTI. During the sub period of Mars in the major period of Saturn, one will leave the country (in adverse circumstances) and will incur diseases and grief in many matters. 
51. SATURN DASAMERCURY BHUKTI. In the sub period of Mercury in the major period of Saturn, the native will enjoy fortunes, happiness, success and honour and will financially gain. 
52. SATURN DASAJUPITER BHUKTI. In the sub period of Jupiter and in the major period of Saturn, one will gain a high position and will acquire villages and happiness from his wife. 
53. SATURN DASAVENUS BHUKTI. In the sub period of Venus and in the major period of Saturn, one will have increased number of friends, freedom from grief, increase of fame, happiness from wife, wealth and success. 
54-57. SPECIAL CONSIDERATIONS. The effects of sub periods, as above will stand modified according to the exaltation, fall etc. of the planet. One will have abundant income, happiness etc. in the major period of a benefic planet and in the sub period of another benefic planet. If a planet is combust, during such planet's period, one will have a dirty body and will incur destruction of wealth, happiness, valour, beauty and enthusiasm. In the Dasa of planets inimical to Ascendant Lord, or to the Moon Sign Lord, one will be very foolish, will be deprived of kingdom, will be insulted by enemies and will depend on others. 
58. The planet, that is close to the 10th cusp will confer kingdom. If there is none in the 10th, the strongest of the planets will give the said effect. 
59. One will be opulent, if Mercury, Jupiter and Venus occupy the Ascendant, Saturn the 7th and the Sun the 10th. If Angles are occupied by benefics, while malefic planets are not there, the native will be wealthy becoming leader of forest tribes. 
Thus ends the 42nd Ch. entitled “EFFECTS OF SUB-PERIODS” in Kalyana Varma's Saravali. Ch. 43. Evil Effects Of Dasa 
1-4. In the sub period of a malefic planet and in the major period of another malefic, the native will be troubled by doubts and enemies. It is certain, that death will be inflicted upon the native though he may have long life indications, in the Dasa of Mars and in the sub period of Saturn. If a malefic is in the 6th, or the 8th in aspect to another malefic placed in a malefic's Sign, death will come to pass. In the Dasa of a planet, that is inimical to Ascendant Lord and in the sub period of the Ascendant Lord himself, there may be death, according to Satya. 
Thus ends the 43rd Ch. entitled “EVIL EFFECTS OF DASAS” in Kalyana Varma's Saravali. Ch. 44. Antidotes For Evils Of Dasas 
1-3. If at the time of commencement of a Dasa, even, if one planet occupies the divisions of a benefic, or of an intimate friend and is aspected by a benefic, the evils due to come out of the said Dasa will disappear. If the Lord of the Dasa is not strong enough to cause evil, while the planet functioning, as an antidote (as stated in the previous Sloka) is stronger, the evils are then surely destroyed. Even, if a single planet occupies its exaltation Sign, Moolatrikona Sign, or own Sign and is aspected by a benefic, or is conjunct a benefic, at the start of a Dasa the evils of the Dasa are nullified. 
Thus ends the 44th Ch. entitled “ANTIDOTES FOR EVILS OF DASAS” in Kalyana Varma's Saravali. Ch. 45. Effects of Planetary Dignities 
1-4. EFFECTS OF EXALTED PLANETS. If the Sun is exalted at birth, the native will be fierce, be very wealthy and be pre-eminent. 
With exalted Moon, one will enjoy sweet food, possess superior clothes and will acquire good ornaments. If Mars is exalted the native will be splendourous, valorous, blame worthy and will live in other places. 
When Mercury is exalted the native will be intelligent, be supreme among his family members and be a skillful speaker. One will be famous, wealthy, learned, honourable and skillful with the exaltation of Jupiter. 
If Venus is exalted one will be fond of sports, amusements, music, dance etc. 
Saturn's exaltation denotes association with royal assignment, leadership over villages and towns, gain of forest-born grains and mean females. 
5-7½ EFFECTS OF PLANETS IN MOOLA TRIKONAS. Should the Sun be in his Moolatrikona Sign, the native will be wealthy, intelligent and skillful. 
The Moon in Moolatrikona indicates one with enjoyments and virtues. 
Mars in Moolatrikona will make one a leader of thieves, adventurous and unkind. 
The placement of Mercury in his Moolatrikona Sign denotes a jocular and successful person. 
One will be helpful to others, be preeminent and will have knowledge of justice with Jupiter in Moolatrikona. 
Venus in such a Sign will make one a prominent person in his village/town, wealthy and fortunate. 
If Saturn is so posited the native belongs to a good family, be wealthy and valorous. 
8-11. EFFECTS OF PLANETS IN OWN SIGNS. If the Sun is placed in his own Sign, the native will be very fierce and will do very great acts. 
The Moon in her own Sign denotes one virtuously disposed, who is very intelligent and beautiful. 
If Mars occupies such a Sign, the native will be opulent, impetuous and firm in disposition. 
Should Mercury occupy his own Sign the native will be a sweet speaker and be learned. 
If Jupiter be in his own Sign one will be versed in Vedas, literature etc., be rich and will perform great deeds. 
If Venus be in his own Sign one will be farmer and a rich person. 
Should Saturn be in his own House, the native will be honourable and happy. 
12-14. EFFECTS OF PLANETS IN FRIENDLY SIGNS. If the Sun is in a friendly Sign, one will be firm in friendship and be charitable. 
The Moon in a friendly Sign denotes the native will be happy and very honourable. 
Mars placed in friendly Sign will make one protect the wealth of friends. 
On will be skillful, jocular and rich, with Mercury in a friendly Sign. 
Jupiter in a friendly Sign will make one respectable and a performer of famous deeds. 
If Venus be in a friendly Sign the native will be fond of friends, rich and adventurous. 
Saturn in a Sign of his friend will force the native to depend on other for food and inclined to do unethical deeds. 
15-18. EFFECTS OF PLANETS IN DEBILITATION. The various planets in fall denote the under mentioned effects: The Sun in debilitation causes servitude and humiliation in the hands of one's own men. The Moon in debilitation causes one to be not very meritorious in his acts, sickly and unfortunate. Mars in debilitation causes evils, distressed mind and meanness. Mercury in debilitation indicates one to be mean and causes enmity with his cousins and other relatives. Jupiter in debilitation brings dirtyness, dishonour and utter poverty. Venus in debilitation causes subordination, loss of wife and crooked disposition. Saturn in debilitation causes fall into adversity, blameworthy conduct and pennilessness. 
19-21 l/2 EFFECTS OF PLANETS IN INIMICAL SIGNS. If the Sun is placed in an inimical Sign, the native will be poor and be sensually tormented. 
Should the Moon be so placed, one will be devoid of beauty (or brightness) and will suffer from heart diseases. 
Mars in an inimical Sign denotes, that native will face confinement and defeat at the hands of enemies, poverty, distress and misfortunes. 
If Mercury be placed in a Sign, that is ruled by his enemy, the subject will be devoid of intelligence, will experience many miseries and will be very poor. 
Should Venus be in his enemy's Sign, this person concerned will be a servant, will resort to wrong ways of doing things and be very miserable. 
If Jupiter is placed in a Sign owned by his enemy, one will be a eunuch and be devoid of justice and wealth. 
When Saturn occupies an inimical camp, the native will be dirty and be distressed due to diseases and the like. 
22. EFFECTS IN NAVĀŃŚA. If a planet is in its exaltation Navāńśa, the (good) effects due to the planet will be full. If it is in its own Navāńśa, it will give such results, as applicable to its own Rāśi placement. If it is in Navāńśas of its enemy, or of fall, the (good) effects will be quite little, while moderate results will come to pass, if it is in a friendly Navāńśa. 23-26. EFFECTS OF MORE PLANETS IN EXALTATION. If two planets are simultaneously exalted at birth, the native will be rich and famous. 
Three planets in simultaneous exaltation will make one head a town, wealthy and an Army chief. 
If four are so placed, that they are in exaltation, one will be rich, be honoured by the king and will be of regal disposition. 
Should five heavenly bodies occupy their exaltation Signs the native will be famous, be a king's patron and be very rich. 
When six planets are posited in their exaltation Signs, the person will be a king, be charitable, honourable and endowed with many conveyances. 
When all are in their respective exaltation Signs, the native will be an emperor ruling over the land surrounded by seas. 
27-31. EFFECTS OF MORE PLANETS IN MOOLATRIKONA SIGNS. If two planets be so placed, as to be in Moolatrikona Signs, the native will be a householder contributing to the growth of his race, be pre-eminent and famous. 
When three planets are similarly posited one will be quite wealthy and will head a group of men, or villages. 
If four planets occupy their Moolatrikona Rāśis, the native will be very wealthy, will receive royal honours and be dear to all. 
Should five be so placed, as they are in Moolatrikonas one will be a protector, be principal among men, will head an Army, town and royal treasury, be a householder and be very happy. With six planets disposed in their Moolatrikona Rāśis, though one may belong to a cowherd's race, he will be endowed with learning, charitability and various kinds of wealth, will acquire a kingdom and be famous. 
If seven are in their Moolatrikona Rāśis, one will become a king, be endowed with wealth, wife, strength, learning and be skillful in archery. 
32-34. EFFECTS OF MORE PLANETS IN OWN HOUSES. If two planets are in their own Houses at birth, one will be important in his race, be honoured by his relatives and be fortunate. 
Three planets occupying own Houses indicate growth of the dynasty (i.e. birth of children), acquisition of wealth, position and fame. 
If four planets occupy their own Houses, one will be famous, will perform significant acts and will lead over men and cities. 
If five planets be placed in their own Houses, the native will be equal to a king, be endowed with abundant quadrupeds, lands and females. 
If six planets are in their own Houses, one will acquire famous titles, abundant wealth, relatives and honours and one born in a royal family will become, a ruler. 
If seven planets be so placed one will be a king of kings and will conquer his enemies. 
35-37½. EFFECTS OF MORE PLANETS IN FRIENDLY HOUSES. If two planets occupy their friendly Sign, the native will be endowed with the company of friends and will have good conduct. If three are so, one will patronize his relatives, be endowed with good qualities and be pre-eminent. 
If four are so, one will honour Brahmins and Gods, be skillful and be famous. 
If five are so, one will serve the king, be wealthy and be chief of men. 
When six are so, one will have wide enjoyments, abundant conveyances and wealth and be equal to a king. 
With seven planets in such placement one will have many servants, many conveyances, paraphernalia and be a king. 
38-41. EFFECTS OF MORE PLANETS IN FALL. If two planets occupy their Signs of fall, one will be mean in thoughts and be very irascible. 
Three being so, he will be foolish, not virtuous, be poor and be a servant. 
Four being so, he will be indolent, be devoid of (useful) deeds and be a servant. 
Five being so, he will be bereft of a house and a female and be a servant. 
Six being so, he will be tormented by fear and labor and be emaciated. 
All being so, he will eke out his food by begging, be devoid of everything and will wear torn robes, or will wander without clothes. 
42-45. EFFECTS OF MORE PLANETS IN INIMICAL CAMPS. If there are two planets, that are placed in inimical sings one will be miserable and ever fond of quarrels and be subjected to humiliation. 
With three such planets he will be tormented by many expenses and miseries and will lose wealth in spite of hard labor. 
With four being so placed, he will be at a loss in regard to his near and dear and wealth. 
Five heavenly bodies in such a state indicate, that the native will be troubled by many evils. 
With six planets in inimical camps, he will be very miserable. 
If seven planets are in their inimical Signs, the native belongs to a loathsome family and will be devoid of food, robes, beds etc. 
Thus ends the 45th Ch. entitled “EFFECTS OF PLANETARY DIGNITIES” in Kalyana Varma's Saravali. Next > page 10
