
Saravali 
Page 7
Ch. 32. Ninth House And Effects Thereof 
1. Leaving aside all the other Houses, one should first analyze the House of fortune (or Bhagyasthana) for a native can not obtain benefic results without fortune. So narrated below is an account in this direction. 
2. Bhagyasthana (House of fortune) is that, which is the 9th counted from the Ascendant, or from the Moon. Effects of the 9th counted from the stronger of the Ascendant and the Moon will come to pass. 
3. The House occupied by the Lord of the 9th and the planet occupying the 9th will have a say on one's fortune. Their strength, or weakness will indicate the fortunes. 
4. If the 9th House is aspected, or occupied by its own Lord, the native will make his fortunes in his own country. If others aspect, or join the House in question, the dawn of fortune will be elsewhere. 
5. The native will be extremely lucky, if a planet lends full aspect to the 9th from the 3rd, 5th, or Ascendant. The planet in question should be strong in the process. 
6-7. JUPITER IN THE 9th AND ASPECTS THERETO. If Jupiter is placed in the 9th, the native will become a minister. 
If Jupiter is in the 9th and is aspected by the Sun, one will be equal to a king. 
If Jupiter is in the 9th and is aspected by the Moon one will be splendourous and will enjoy pleasures. 
If Jupiter is in the 9th and is aspected by Mars, he will be endowed with gold. 
If Jupiter is in the 9th and is aspected by Mercury one will be affluent. 
If Jupiter is in the 9th and is aspected by Venus one will have quadrupeds, conveyances and wealth. 
If Jupiter is in the 9th and is aspected by Saturn one will possess immovable properties, asses and buffaloes. 
8-12. JUPITER IN THE 9th IN ASPECT TO TWO PLANETS. If the 9th House is occupied by Jupiter and aspected by both the Sun and Mars, the native will be endowed with sovereignty, precious stones, gold, courage, excellence, strength, conveyances and servants. 
If the 9th House is occupied by Jupiter and aspected by both the Sun and the Moon, he will be blessed with plentifulness (of all things), be devoted to his parents, be famous, be equal to a king and will have plurality of wives. 
If the Sun and Mercury jointly aspect the Jupiter in the 9th, he will be graceful, splendourous, fortunate, be endowed with an excellent wife, ornaments and wealth and will be expert in poetry and arts. 
If the 9th House is occupied by Jupiter and aspected by both the Sun and Venus, one will be festive in disposition, will have (wide) social activities and will be endowed with cows, buffaloes, elephants etc. 
If the Sun and Saturn aspect Jupiter in the 9th, one will be head of a country, town, or group, be famous, learned, virtuous, affluent and will have a tendency of accumulating. 
13-16. JUPITER IN THE 9TH IN ASPECTS TO TWO PLANETS (continued). If Jupiter occupies the 9th in aspect to both Mars and the Moon, one will be an Army chief, or a minister and be endowed with various kinds of happiness. 
If Jupiter occupies the 9th in aspect to both Mercury and the Moon, he will enjoy excellent houses, sleeping comforts and pleasures, be splendourous, patient and very intelligent. 
If Jupiter occupies the 9th in aspect to both the Moon and Venus, he will be very rich, dutiful, valorous, attached to others' wives and be devoid of sons. 
If Jupiter occupies the 9th in aspect to both the Moon and Saturn, he will be very lascivious, endowed with permanent livelihood, will live in foreign places, be argumentative, be a liar and be not virtuous. 
17-22. JUPITER IN THE 9th IN ASPECT TO TWO PLANETS (continued). If Jupiter is in the 9th and is in aspect to both Mars and Mercury, one will be highly learned, very virtuous, will keep up his word and will have a pleasing appearance. 
If Mars and Venus jointly aspect Jupiter in the 9th, one will be wealthy, learned, will live in foreign countries, be sincere, very skillful and cruel. 
If Mars and Saturn jointly aspect Jupiter in the 9th, the native will be base, tale bearing, spiteful, living in foreign places and will be in the company of unsteady people. 
If Mercury and Venus jointly aspect Jupiter in the 9th, one will be an artisan, be very virtuous, learned, fortunate, will keep up his promise and will possess a pleasing appearance. 
If Mercury and Saturn jointly aspect Jupiter in the 9th, the native will be fortunate, learned, eloquent in speech, pleasing, courageous, happy and modest. 
23. Jupiter in the 9th in aspect to 9th Lord will make one a king. The effects stated in connection with Jupiter's position in the 9th and aspects thereof are valid, only when no other planets (than the mentioned) aspect. 
24. If all the planets aspect Jupiter posited in the 9th, the native will possess excellent guise, virtues, splendour, sovereignty and abundant riches. 
25. If the 9th is occupied by a strong benefic, it confers kingdom, according to the wise, in addition to movable properties, wealth, grains, righteousness and increased longevity. 
26. AFFLICTION TO THE 9th. If the 9th House gives place to a debilitated planet, or a combust planet, or a malefic planet and be without a benefic's aspect, the native will be devoid of (moral) strength, wealth and fame and be dirty. 
27. If the malefic in the 9th is the owner of that House, then it proves auspicious. And with a benefic's aspect it is more auspicious. 
28. If Full Moon is in the 9th, while Mars, Saturn and Mercury are strong the native is born to a king. 
29. If a planet is exalted in the 9th, an excellent person is born with plentifulness of wealth and gold. And, if a benefic aspects the exalted planet in question, the native will be a supreme ruler, destroyer of the band of his enemies, will possess divine splendour and great fame. 
30-35. EFFECTS OF OTHER PLANETS IN CONJUNCTION WITH THE SUN IN THE 9th HOUSE. If the Sun and the Moon are together in the 9th, the native will have a short life, will be afflicted by eye diseases, be rich fortunate and fond of quarrels. 
If Mars and the Sun be together in the 9th, the native will experience many kinds of miseries, be fond of quarrels, be fierce, courageous, dear to king and be skillful. 
If Mercury and the Sun are together in the 9th, one will be skillful, miserable, will have many enemies and suffer from many diseases. 
If Jupiter and the Sun be in conjunction in the 9th, the native will be endowed with wealth, will obtain abundant paternal wealth, be long-lived, very courageous and be a worthy person. 
Should Venus and the Sun be together, in the 9th, he will incur diseases and will be endowed with scents, garlands, ornaments, robes and decorative articles. 
If Saturn and the Sun be so placed one will be rich, will suffer from eye diseases, be fond of quarrels and be short-lived. 
36-40. EFFECTS OF OTHERS JOINING THE MOON IN THE 9th. If Mars joins the Moon in the 9th, one will be devoid of mother (i.e. will lose his mother early), will have a deformed body and with ulcers and be wealthy. 
If Mercury joins the Moon in the 9th, he will have knowledge of Shastras, be scholarly, will have some physical deformity, will be excellent among men, will talk much and be famous. 
If Jupiter joins the Moon, he will be distinguished, will be fortunate, will be endowed with abundant riches, will be always happy and be courageous. 
If Venus be the accompanying planet, he will suffer from diseases, will marry an unchaste lady, be plentiful, will have a step-mother and will be in a minister's custody (i.e. will serve a significant person). 
Should Saturn join the Moon in the 9th, he will be devoid of moral merits, be sinful and will have a fallen mother. 
41-44. EFFECTS OF MARS JOINING OTHERS IN THE 9th. If Mars be in the company of Mercury in the 9th, one will be chief of men, will be always emotional, be fortunate, will enjoy pleasures and be skillful in Shastras. 
If it is Jupiter with whom Mars is conjunct in the 9th, one will be endowed with wealth and grains, be honourable, be troubled by sickness and will be pained with bodily wounds. 
If Venus is joining Mars in the 9th, one will live in foreign places, be argumentative, cruel, will hate women, be ungrateful and will indulge in falsehood. 
If Saturn is with Mars in the 9th, one will be sinful, will be of dirty conduct, be interested in other housewives, be deprived of wealth and happiness and will not be with his own men. 
45-47. MERCURY IN CONJUNCTION WITH OTHERS IN THE 9th. If Mercury is with Jupiter in the 9th, one will be learned in Shastras, be a scholar, be wealthy, will speak sweetly, be an artisan and an efficacious and excellent person. 
Venus and Mercury in the 9th denotes, that one will be famous, very learned, valorous, fortunate, skillful in speech and be fond of songs. 
If Saturn and Mercury are in the 9th in conjunction, he will suffer from diseases, be very rich, be endowed with dear and near, be skillful, envious and be garrulous. 
48-49. JUPITER JOINING OTHERS IN THE 9th. If Venus and Jupiter be together in the 9th, one will be a leader of men, be long-lived, eloquent and will be endowed with many kinds of happiness and wealth. 
If Jupiter and Saturn are in the 9th, the native will enjoy wealth and gems, be honourable, will have diseases to trouble him and be devoid of his own men. 
50. VENUS-SATURN CONJUNCTION IN THE 9th. This conjunction denotes, that the native will be sickly, will have many sons, be dear to king, famous and virtuous. 
51. In analyzing the said effects, the Signs and aspects involved should be skillfully understood according to Shastras and results declared accordingly, so say the learned. 
52. EFFECTS OF 3 PLANETS IN CONJUNCTION IN 9th. If the Sun, Moon and Mars are together in the 9th, one will lose his parents in his very boyhood, be base, odious and hurtful. 
53. If the Sun, Moon and Mercury join in the 9th, the native will be a eunuch in appearance, be miserable, will hate all people and be valorous and truthful. 
54. If the Sun, the Moon and Jupiter join in the 9th, one will be excellent and will possess conveyances, wealth and happiness. 
55. If Venus, the Moon and the Sun be together in the 9th, one will lose all his happiness and wealth due to quarrels with females, be dear to king, will have knowledge of politics and will be an eloquent speaker. 
56. If the Sun, the Moon and Saturn join in the 9th, one will be very strong, will have cruel conduct, will serve others and will hate others. 
57. If the Sun, Mars and Mercury be in the 9th, one will be an eloquent speaker, be akin to a snake, when in anger, be fond of quarrels, be hard-hearted and will be interested in living in foreign countries. 
58. If the Sun, Jupiter and Mars are together in the 9th, one will be always diligent, be intent on worshipping his father and God, will have an affluent wife and be virtuous. 
59. If the Sun, Mars and Venus be together in the 9th, one will be fond of quarrels, is of a high descent, will spoil virgins, be fickle-minded and be odious. 
60. If Mars, Saturn and the Sun join in the 9th, one will be valorous, very mean, will hate people, be fond of speaking lies, be cruel and be fatherless from boyhood. 
61. Should the Sun, Mercury and Jupiter join in the 9th, one will be endowed with fortunes, wealth and happiness, be dear to king, be appealing in appearance and be courageous. 
62. Should Venus join the Sun and Mercury in the 9th, one will be splendourous, famous, will destroy his enemies, be equal to a king and be rich. 
63. Should the Sun, Mercury and Saturn join in the 9th, one will be fond of others' women, be a sinner, be interested in living in foreign places, be skillful, be a profligate, be a liar and be unfortunate. 
64. Should the Sun, Venus and Jupiter join in the 9th, one will be very learned, splendourous, will know many things and be intelligent. 
65. The conjunction of the Sun, Jupiter and Saturn in the 9th is indicative, that the native will be highly valorous, be a king, be wealthy, virtuous and plentiful. 
66. If the Sun, Venus and Saturn be together in the 9th, one will be devoid of splendour, be dirty, punished by the king, be devoid of riches and be foolish. 
67. The company formed by the Moon, Mercury and Mars in the 9th denotes, that the subject will enjoy wealth, gold and gems and will be miserable throughout his boyhood. 
68. If the Moon, Mars and Jupiter join in the 9th, one will conquer his five senses, be learned, will honour elders and Gods and will be endowed with learning and wealth and be fortunate. 
69. If Venus, Moon and Mars are together in the 9th, one will have a wounded body, be ugly, will eat a lot, be fond of women, be at their disposal and will lose his strength (or wealth) through them. 
70. Should Saturn, Mars and the Moon be in the 9th, one will not possess a good maternal history, be base, be given up by his mother in boyhood and will be mean among men. 
71. If the Moon, Mercury and Jupiter are together in the 9th one will bring credit to his descent, will be a preceptor, will possess many friends and will be a king endowed with many things. 
72. If the Moon, Mercury and Venus be together in the 9th, one will have a stepmother, be endowed with delight and honour, will have many friends and will be gentle, or pacific. 
73. If the Moon, Mercury and Saturn are together in the 9th, one will be bad in conduct, be courageous, dirty, be averse to war and be poor. 
74. If the Moon, Jupiter and Venus be in the 9th, one will be equal to a king and be a king. 
75. If Jupiter, Saturn and the Moon be in the 9th one will speak sweetly, be truthful, virtuous, famous and skillful in all Shastras. 
76. If Venus, the Moon and Saturn join in the 9th, one will be in agricultural profession, be interested in women, will not indulge in sinful acts, will accomplish his objects (Kritakritya) and be world-famous. 
77. If Mars, Mercury and Jupiter join in the 9th, one will be splendourous, devoid of grief, be learned, firm in his word, famous and be head of a zone. 
78. If Mars, Mercury and Venus are conjunct in the 9th, one will head many provinces, or affairs, be famous, honoured by the king, the fierce and be always zealous. 
79. If Mars, Mercury and Saturn join in the 9th, one will be skillful in cheating others, will be highly gloomy, will not be in a position to understand Shastras (i.e. be not so learned) and cannot understand others' notions. 
80. If Mercury, Jupiter and Venus be together in the 9th one will be equal to God, be spotless, famous, kingly, learned and virtuous. 
81. Should Mercury, Venus and Saturn join in the 9th, one will be intelligent, splendourous, eloquent and happy. 
82. One with Saturn, Venus and Jupiter in the 9th, will have plenty of food, drinks and riches, be fortunate, happy and beautiful. 
FOUR PLANETS IN CONJUNCTION IN 9th. 83. If the Sun, the Moon, Mars and Mercury join in the 9th, one will be rich, learned, fortunate and dear to king. 
84. If Venus, Moon, Sun and Mars are together in the 9th, one will be cunning, will be happy with his wife and will indulge in many mean acts. 
85. One, who has the Moon, Jupiter, Mercury and the Sun in the 9th, will be principle, steady, honoured by the king and be delighted. 
86. One with the Moon, Venus, Mercury and Sun in the 9th, will be a Lord of wealth, morally meritorious, plentiful, eloquent in speech and be calm. 
87. If the Sun, Mercury, Moon and Saturn be together in the 9th, one will be rich, splendourous, kingly, will have many quadrupeds and will possess rich qualities. 
88. One with the Sun, Jupiter, Mercury and Venus will honour God and father, will have a rich wife and be virtuous. 
89. If Venus, Mars, Mercury and the Sun join together in the 9th, one will be hard-hearted, beautiful, interested in valorous acts, be not wealthy and will lose his wealth through his enemies. 
90. If the Sun, Mars, Mercury and Saturn be together in the 9th, one will be interested in others' wives, will incur loss of wealth and be always pitiable. 
91. One with the Sun, Venus, Mars and Jupiter in the 9th, will hate people, be troubled by thirst, will spoil virgins and be fickle-minded. 
92. If the Sun, Mars, Jupiter and Saturn are in the 9th at birth, one will be devoid of happiness, be diligent, fierce and courageous. 
93. If the Sun, Jupiter, Venus and Mercury are in the 9th, one will be an excellent person endowed with wealth, gold and sovereignty. 
94. If the Sun, Mercury, Jupiter and Saturn are together in the 9th, one will be devoid of wealth, be sinful, be interested in other housewives, spiteful and will indulge in mean acts. 
95. Should the Sun, Mercury, Venus and Saturn be in 9th, one will be fortunate, wealthy, truthful and world-famous. 
96. With the Sun, Jupiter, Venus and Saturn in the 9th, one will be truthful, eloquent and will honour elders, Brahmins and guests. 
97. If the Moon, Mars, Mercury and Jupiter are in the 9th, one will have plenty of robes, will lose his mother in boyhood and be wealthy. 
98. With Mars, Venus, Mercury and the Moon in the 9th, one will practice penance, be famous, be a good speaker, be very charitable, ultra-mundane in disposition and be very learned. 
99. If Saturn, Mercury, Moon and Mars are together in the 9th, one will be dejected, poor, base, cunning and interested in others' wives. 
100. If Mars, Moon, Venus and Saturn, are together in the 9th, one is born in a royal family. He will be a principle person, be valorous, will be endowed with plenty of learning and money, be famous and dear to people. 
101. One with Moon, Mars, Saturn and Jupiter in the 9th, will be troubled by thirst, be fond of promoting quarrels and be plentiful in the matter of luck and robes. 
102. If the Moon, Mars, Saturn and Venus are together in the 9th, one will be hard-hearted, sinful, cunning and be bereft of cleanliness and behavior. 
103. If Venus, Jupiter, Mercury and Moon are together in the 9th, one will be wealthy, be endowed with moral merits and be famous in arts. 
104. One with Saturn, Mercury, Jupiter and Moon in the 9th, will be knowledgeable in politics and ethics and be pleasing in appearance. 
105. With Saturn, Venus, Mercury and the Moon in the 9th, the native will be intelligent, fierce, will be an expert in democratic matters and be fortunate. 
106. One with Moon, Saturn, Venus and Jupiter in the 9th, will be cunning, fierce, unconquerable and bold. 
107. If Mars, Mercury, Jupiter and Saturn be together in the 9th, one will destroy his enemies, be fierce in battle and bold. 
108. If Mars, Mercury, Venus and Saturn join together in the 9th, one will be virtuous, wealthy and pious. 
109. If Mars, Jupiter, Venus and Saturn are in the 9th, one will be devoid of wealth, be base, unkind and weak. 
110. SPECIAL EFFECTS. If including Mercury there are 3 to 7 planets in the 9th, the native will be trustworthy, wealthy and be a king. 
111. If the 9th is occupied by other planets, without the company of Mercury, or Jupiter, the native will be sickly, ugly, void of relatives, be troubled by imprisonments and will suffer penury. 
112. Preceptors, like Badalayana, have explained still detailed results arising out of conjunction, or aspects relating to the 9th House. One should understand these also and declare effects after using his wisdom. 
Thus ends the 32nd Ch. entitled “NINTH HOUSE AND EFFECTS THEREOF” in Kalyana Varma's Saravali. Ch. 33. Tenth House And Effects Thereof 
1. Sages have explained effects relating to the Signs coinciding with the 10th House, planets posited therein and planets aspecting the 10th House. I shall now explain those results. 
2. The 10th House counted from the stronger among the Ascendant and the Moon, is called Karmasthana and, if the Lord of that (10th) House is with strength, the effects in regard to Karma will prosper. Otherwise, the same will decline. 
3-6. The effects relating to the 10th House will depend on the nature of the Sign, viz. watery, biped, Aranya (like Leo), or Jangala (Centiped), the form of such Sign and the places indicated by such Sign. The 10th House should be carefully examined on these lines. The occupant of the 10th House counted from the Moon, or from the Ascendant will influence the livelihood of the native according to his (i.e. planet's) nature and disposition. 
7. In a previous Ch., results of placements of planets in the 10th House from the Ascendant have been explained, while dealing with angular positions of various planets. Now specially explained are with reference to the Moon. 
8-13. EFFECTS OF PLANETS IN THE 10TH FROM THE MOON. If the Sun occupies the 10th from the Moon, the native will be successful in his undertakings, be very wealthy, very strong, be a king, will patronize others and be healthy in physique. 
Mars so placed denotes, that the native will be interested in valorous deeds, will live in foreign places will long for sensual enjoyments, be cruel and will be akin to an outcast in conduct. 
If Mercury occupies the 10th from the Moon, one will be learned, rich, will have abundant knowledge of sacred affairs, like Veda etc.), be dear to king, famous, aquainted with many an art and be intelligent. 
If it is Jupiter, that occupies the 10th counted from the Moon, the native will be successful in achieving his desires, righteous, affluent, will have excellent history among men, be a king's minister and be famous. 
If Venus occupies the 10th from the Moon, one will be fortunate, beautiful, famous, will be successful in his undertakings, be rich and be honoured by king. 
Should Saturn occupy the 10th with reference to the Moon, the native will have physical diseases, be poor, grieved, bereft of children and be always emotional. 
14-18. EFFECTS OF THE SUN JOINING ANOTHER PLANET WHEN IN THE TENTH FROM THE MOON. Should the Sun be with Mars, while being in the 10th counted from the Moon, the native will be a labourer (karmakaran), will suffer severely from cough and pulmonary consumption, or consumption in general, be an astrologer and will be an expert in the science of marks and Signs and also in logic. 
Should the Sun be with Mercury in the 10th from the Moon, one will enjoy robes and ornaments, be a trader and will live through the means of water. 
If the Sun is conjunct Jupiter being in the 10th from the Moon, he will be successful in his undertakings, be honoured by the king, brave and famous. 
If the Sun is conjunct Venus in the 10th from the Moon, the subject will patronize his people, be fortunate, dear to the king and will increase his possessions through the help of his wife (or women). 
The Sun and Saturn being together in the 10th from the Moon will make one liable to imprisonment, a servant, poor, wretched (or miserly), lose to thieves and prattle. 
19-22. EFFECTS OF MARS JOINING ANOTHER PLANET IN THE 10th FROM THE MOON. When Mars gets the company of Mercury being in the 10th from the Moon, one will have many an enemy, be skillful in archery and be very valorous. 
If Jupiter be with Mars in the 10th of the Moon, one will be a mighty leader, will gain wealth via friends, will live thereby and be fortunate. 
Venus and Mars being in the 10th from the Moon indicates, that the native will be interested in living in foreign places, will trade in gold, precious stones etc. and will progress through women. 
Saturn and Mars conjunct in the 10th from the Moon, indicates, that the native will be adventurous, base and will suffer from diseases. 
23-25. EFFECTS OF MERCURY JOINING ANOTHER PLANET IN THE 10TH FROM THE MOON. If Jupiter and Mercury be together in the 10th from the Moon, the subject will be rich, honoured by the king, righteous, be leader of men and be famous. 
If Venus and Mercury are conjunct in the 10th counted from the Moon, one will be endowed with friends, learning, wife, wealth and happiness, be a king's minister and a provincial head. 
If Mercury is conjunct Saturn being posited in the 10th from the Moon, the person concerned will be a potter, be famous, imparter of learning and be an author of books. 
26-27. EFFECTS OF JUPITER JOINING ANOTHER PLANET IN THE 10th FROM THE MOON. If Jupiter joins Venus in being in 10th from the Moon, one will serve a superior king, will head Brahmins, be devoid of grief, be an imparter of learning and be skillful. 
Saturn and Jupiter in the 10th from the Moon denote, that one will be base, will cause grief to others, will act, like an aged person, will have a firm residence and will successfully begin his undertakings. 
28. EFFECTS OF VENUS-SATURN CONJUNCTION IN THE 10th FROM THE MOON. One with Venus and Saturn in the 10th from the Moon will be an artist, will trade in scents, be a doctor and will deal in black-salt and camphor. 
Notes: “Neelam” apart meaning black-salt also indicates poison, antimony, sapphire etc., while Churna means apart from camphorflour, chalk, lime etc. 29-48. EFFECTS OF THREE PLANETS IN CONJUNCTION IN THE 10th FROM THE MOON. If the Sun, Mars and Mercury are in the 10th from the Moon, one will be fortunate, excellent among men, equal to king and be honoured by all. 
The Sun, Mars and Jupiter in the 10th of the Moon denote, that he will be fortunate, will destroy his enemies and will be plentiful. 
The Sun, Mars and Venus in the 10th of the Moon will make one cruel, adventurous, steal others' wealth and highly skillful. 
Mars, Saturn and the Sun posited in the 10th of the Moon denote, that he will be intent on doing cruel acts, be foolish, sinful and bad in conduct. 
The Sun, Mercury and Jupiter in the 10th of the Moon indicate, that he will be learned, beautiful, righteous and be dear to his relatives. 
Famous, righteous, devoid of anger, unconquerable, fortunes and plenty of robesthese are the effects produced by the conjunction of Mercury, the Sun and Venus, in the 10th of the Moon. 
When one has the Sun, Mercury and Saturn in the 10th of the Moon, one will be cruel, fickle minded, be not virtuous and will be afflicted by weapons and fire. 
If the Sun, Venus and Jupiter be together in the 10th of the Moon, one will be fortunate, will earn by learning, be righteous and will always enjoy pleasures. 
Saturn, the Sun and Jupiter in conjunction in the 10th counted from the Moon will make one devoid of (worthy) history, still honourable and valorous. 
Venus, Sun and Saturn in conjunction in the 10th counted from the Moon will make one miserly, fickle minded and prohibited by all. 
If Mars, Mercury and Jupiter are in the 10th counted from the Moon, one will be righteous, will have a large family and many children and will be learned and wealthy. 
Mercury, Mars and Venus in the 10th of the Moon will make one interested in fine arts, a dealer of garlands, goldsmith and dear to all. 
Saturn, Mars and Mercury in the 10th of the Moon will make one righteous, addicted to sleep, wicked and dirty. 
If at the time of birth one has Mars, Venus and Jupiter in the 10th from his Janma Rāśi, he will be wealthy, valorous and be interested in honouring Gods and Brahmins. If Saturn, Jupiter and Mars are in the 10th counted from the Moon, one will be bereft of learning, wealth and near and dear, be mean, bereft of happiness and be deformed (or distressed). 
Mars, Venus and Saturn in the 10th counted from the Moon denote, that one will be a minister, or an excellent personage, interested in others' religions, wealthy and have many professions. 
Mercury, Venus and Jupiter in the 10th (with reference to the Moon) identical with Taurus/Libra denote, that all his desires will be fulfilled (i.e. he will be happy in all respects). 
Mercury, Venus and Jupiter in the 10th (with reference to the Moon) in Signs other, then Taurus/Libra denote, that one will suffer from diseases. 
Mercury, Jupiter and Saturn in the 10th of the Moon denote, that one will be interested in authorship and literature, be wealthy, be a very modest servant, be fond of wandering and be beautiful. 
If Saturn, Mercury and Venus be together in conjunction in the 10th counted from the Moon one will be endowed with wisdom, be a boxer, be interested in living' in foreign countries, diligent and tamed (like an elephant). 
If Jupiter, Saturn and Venus join in the 10th from the Moon, one will be learned, righteous, kind and truthful. 
49. Those are the results of planets up to 3 in number joining in the 10th from the Moon. Different results will be experienced, if more than 3 planets join in the 10th of the Moon, as explained below. 
50-61. EFFECTS OF 4 PLANETS JOINING IN THE 10th FROM THE MOON. If the Sun, Mars, Mercury and Jupiter be in the 10th from the Moon, one will be valorous, physically hurt, charitable and interested in all deeds. 
With Mars, Sun, Venus and Mercury in the 10th from the Moon one will be a garland dealer, writer, or an artist. 
With Mars, Sun, Saturn and Mercury in the 10th from the Moon one will be endowed with wealth, conveyances and elephants. 
The Sun, Mercury, Jupiter and Venus in the 10th from the Moon denote, that even though one will have a mean profession, he will be excellent, will have sons and will have agricultural living. 
The Sun, Mercury, Jupiter and Saturn in the 10th from the Moon denote, that one will be skillfully cunning, cruel and will cheat others. 
The Sun, Mercury, Venus and Saturn being in the 10th of the Moon, will make one hardhearted, fortunate, eloquent and interested in agriculture. 
The Sun, Jupiter, Venus and Saturn being in the 10th of the Moon, will make one interested in foreign places and have many an acts to do. 
If Mars, Venus, Mercury and Jupiter are in the 10th from the Moon, he will be skillful courageous and unconquerable in battle. 
If Mars, Saturn, Mercury and Jupiter are in the 10th from the Moon, one will be dirty, ever longing for war and will destroy enemies. 
Should Mars, Mercury, Venus and Saturn join in the 10th of the Moon, one will have abundant learning, be valorous and will be broad-bodied. 
Should Mars, Jupiter, Venus and Saturn join in the 10th of the Moon, one will be courageous and endowed with family and wealth. 
If Mercury, Jupiter, Venus and Saturn are placed in the 10th from Janma Rāśi, one will be calmly disposed, intelligent and dear to people. 
62. MALEFICS IN THE 10TH FROM THE MOON. If Malefics occupy the 10th House counted from the Moon and aspected by benefics, one will be a doctor, Purohit (a religious guide), an astrologer, or will be interested in cheating others. 
63. Whatever effects have been ascribed so far in this Ch. will specially reveal beneficially, if benefics aspect the 10th House from the Moon. If malefics aspect, the benefic results may not be there. 
64. MALEFICS AND EFFECTS. Malefics in the 3rd, or in the 6th with reference to either the Ascendant, or the Moon will prove favourable, while in the 8th, 12th, or the Ascendant they are inauspiciousmore so in the Ascendant. 
65. LIVELIHOOD. One's livelihood should be predicted based on the 10th from the Moon, or from the Ascendant; whichever is stronger will prevail. The earnings (livelihood) will also be indicated by the stronger of the Lords of the 10th counted from the Moon, or from the Ascendant. 
66-80. SIGNS AND PROFESSIONS. If Aries, or many of its divisions be in the 10th, one will live through gardens, intelligence, service, agriculture, trading in juices (Rasa has other meanings, like liquor, poison, mercury, mineral/metallic salt etc.), or be an envoy. With Taurus, or a majority of its divisions in the 10th, one will live through carts, quadrupeds, birds, wild animals and by gathering grains. Similarly Gemini denotes trading through water, precious stones, vessels, conch, writing, accountancy etc. Cancer in this context means weapons, golden ornaments, arrows and hunting. Leo on the 10th, or many of Leo divisions related to the 10th denote livelihood through precious stones, gold, stones (like construction material) agriculture, cows and the like and grains. Wealth comes through vehicles, gems, gold, scents, music, arts and writing, if Virgo features, as above. Libra in similar condition indicates livelihood through teaching, dealing in gold, many ways and means, friends, cows, buffaloes, many salable articles, things emanating from water, grains, fruits, agriculture and arts. Similarly Scorpio denotes livelihood through female association, agriculture, thieving, serving the king, sinful acts, rendering physical treatments (i.e. medical profession), blacksmithy and grains. Ministership under a king, protection of forts, cattle, horses, firewood, indicating omens, machinery, mathematics, medical treatment etc., are denoted by Sagittarius in a similar manner. Capricorn in similar condition denotes livelihood through cots, gardening, chemicals etc. and abundant income through waterborne items. Aquarius indicates weapons, burning, separation (or creating inimical relationship between two), thieving, carrying headloads and through physical stamina. Pisces in similar manner denotes living through weapons, waterborne items, sale of horses etc. 
81. PLANETS IN THE 10th AND THEIR EFFECTS. The Sun in the 10th indicates income through father, the Moon mother, Mars enemies, Mercury friends, Jupiter brothers, Venus females and Saturn servants. 
82. There will be gains in many ways, if the Ascendant, the 2nd and the 11th are, respectively, occupied by strong (favourable) planets, so say the preceptors. 
Thus ends the 33rd Ch. entitled “10th HOUSE AND EFFECTS THEREOF” in Kalyana Varma's Saravali. Ch. 34. Different Houses and Worldly Affairs 
1-7. EFFECTS OF SEVERAL PLANETS ASPECTING THE ASCENDANT. If the Sun aspects the Ascendant, the native will be valorous, will be irascible with females, be cruel, will gain wealth from paternal side and will serve the king. 
If the Moon aspects the Ascendant, he will be under the control of women, fortunate, be very courteous, be very wealthy, softly disposed and will gain by dealing in water-born articles. 
If Mars lends his aspect to the Ascendant, one will be fond of valorous acts and battles, irascible, will have severed relationship, be very righteous and will have a long penis. 
Should Mercury aspect the Ascendant, the native will have rich knowledge of arts and will thereby gain and be quite intelligent, famous and honourable. 
If Jupiter be the aspecting planet with reference to the Ascendant one will be interested in religious observations, be honoured by the king, be famous and will be endowed with (the company of) virtuous people, elders and guests. 
Venus aspecting the Ascendant denotes, that he will be addicted to many prostitutes, be youthful, will have happiness of wealth and pleasure and will be beautiful in appearance. 
If Saturn aspects the Ascendant one will be troubled by heavy loads, travels and diseases, be irascible, will be attached to aged women (i.e. will be fond of seeking union with aged females), be devoid of happiness, be dirty and foolish. 
8. GENERAL ASPECTS TO ASCENDANT. If a planet (whether natural benefic, or natural malefic) aspects the Ascendant identical with its own Sign, that confers happiness and wealth, apart from close relationship with the king. If the Ascendant is not owned by the aspecting planet, a benefic then confers auspicious effects and a malefic evil results. 
9. UNASPECTED ASCENDANT. Should the ascending Sign be not in aspect to even one planet, the native will be devoid of (other) qualities and will acquire exclusive qualities of the Sign concerned. 
10-11. SPECIAL EFFECTS. If two, or more planets aspect the Ascendant, the native acquires happiness and wealth. Even one benefic aspecting the Ascendant is auspicious, while a malefic so aspecting is inauspicious. If the Ascendant is aspected by all the planets one rules over the earth. Should all the planets be endowed with strength, he will enjoy all kinds of happiness, be free from fear and be long-lived. 
12. PLANETS CONJUNCT IN THE ASCENDANT. If three planets are together in the Ascendant, the native will be devoid of miseries and will lord over the earth. But, if these are (exclusively) malefics, he will be distressed due to fear, grief etc., will eat much and will be disregarded by one and all. 
13. ADHI YOGA FROM ASCENDANT. If benefics exclusively occupy the 6th, 7th and 8th, without the company of malefics, Lagnadhi Yoga is caused. This Yoga confers ministership, leadership over Army (justiceship) and kingship, lordship over many women, long life, freedom from diseases and miseries, possession of virtues and happiness. So say Yavana kings. 
14. A planet in own Sign, or in exaltation/friendly Sign, according to sages, confers its effects fully. If it is in fall, or is inimically placed, it is incapable of giving the results (due to the above mentioned Yoga). 
15-20. PRINCIPLES RELATED TO THE 2ND HOUSE. If Mars, Saturn and the Sun occupy the 2nd House, the native's wealth is destroyed. 
If weak Moon aspects the 2nd House, such effects are more pronounced. 
Mars and the Sun in the 2nd cause afflictions to skin apart from causing poverty. 
If Saturn, posited alone in this House, is aspected by Mercury, he will be greatly rich. 
Even, if the Sun is posited in the 2nd House in aspect to Saturn, without aspect of others, pennilessness will come to pass. 
Benefics in the 2nd House cause advent of money in many ways. 
But, if Jupiter posited in the 2nd House remains under Mercury's aspect, or Mercury so posited in the 2nd House in aspect to the Moon, the entire wealth earned by the native will be deprived. 
Weak Moon in the 2nd House in Mercury's aspect denotes, that even the ancestral property will be destroyed; not only this, other sources of income will also be hindered. 
Should the 2nd House [from the] Moon be aspected by Venus, plenty of wealth will be earned. Same is the result by aspect of another benefic (i.e. Jupiter). 
21-24. PRINCIPLES RELATED TO THE 3rd HOUSE. When the 3rd House is owned by a malefic and is occupied by a malefic, the co-born are destroyed. Conversely, a benefic's Sign being the 3rd and occupation of benefics therein will cause happiness thereof. Now explained below is the method to ascertain the number of co-born. The number of Navāńśas past in the 3rd House denotes the number of brothers following the native. If other planets aspect the 3rd House, the said number (caused by Navāńśas) stands increased. Saturn placed in the 3rd in aspect to Mars causes destruction of co-born. But Venus in the 3rd and in aspect to Jupiter increases happiness thereof. Mercury placed in the 3rd House, in aspect to Mars (or in aspect to the Sun, as some texts read ‘Bhaskara Drishtah' instead of ‘Angaraka Drishtah'), the native's friends are destroyed. Rest (relating to the 4th House) may be understood from Bhavadhyaya (Ch. 30). 25-26. ABOUT THE 5th HOUSE. If the 5th House contains a benefic, or is aspected by a benefic, or be a benefic's Rāśi, the native will surely beget children. If it is different, he will not obtain progeny. If the 5th House counted from the Moon, or the Ascendant, the stronger prevailing, has at least one Jupiter's division in the various Varga calculations, or has a benefic's Rāśi in it and is aspected by a benefic, the native will have legitimate issue. 
27. NUMBER OF CHILDREN. If the Navāńśa of the 5th falls in a benefic's Rāśi the number of children equals the number of Navāńśas past in the 5th House. The aspect of a benefic on the 5th Bhava doubles the number, while malefic Rāśi, as 5th House Navāńśa and the said House receiving a malefic's aspect confers progeny with difficulty. 
28. AUTHORIZING OTHER KINSMAN TO RAISE PROGENY FOR THE NATIVE. If the 5th House falls in the divisions (like Rāśi, Navāńśa, drekkana etc.) of Saturn and be with Mercury's aspect, but without that of Jupiter/Mars/Sun, the native obtains progeny by authorizing his kinsman to raise the same for him from his (the native's) wife. Similar result prevails, if Mercury's Rāśi be in the 5th House containing Mercury in it and is in aspect to Saturn, but without the aspect of the others, as cited above. 
29. ADOPTED OR BOUGHT PROGENY. If the 5th House belongs to Saturn and be occupied by Saturn himself with the aspect of the Moon, one procures a child by adoption, or by an act of purchase. Identical effect follows the position of Mercury in the 5th House owned by him receiving the Moon's aspect. 
30. ADOPTION SANS CONSENT. Should the 5th House contain Saturn unaspected by others and fall in a Sapthamsa owned by Mars, the native will adopt a grown up child without the consent of its natural parents. 
31-32. BASE CHILDREN. If the 5th House contains the Sun and falls in the divisions of Saturn receiving the aspect of Mars, the children so obtained will be abject. Should the Moon be in the 5th House and receive exclusively Saturn's aspect, while the 5th House falls in a Navāńśa of Mars, even then the progeny will be foolish and base. 
33. If the 5th House is occupied by Mars falling in many of Saturn's divisions and be in aspect to the Sun, one will obtain a son, that is adopted by a stranger after its being cast off by its original parents, so says sage Karuna. 
34. ISSUE BY A REMARRIED WIDOW. Should the 5th House fall in Saturn's Vargas and contain both the Moon and Saturn therein, in aspect to both the Sun and Venus, progeny will be begotten by a widow given to the native in remarriage. 
35. PROGENY BY A VIRGIN. Should the Moon be in the 7th along with the Sun, or the Moon being in the 5th in aspect to, or in the company of the Sun, one will obtain issue through an unmarried girl. 
36. PROGENY BY A WOMAN PREGNANT AT MARRIAGE. If the 5th House falls in the divisions of the Luminaries and contains the Moon and the Sun in aspect to Venus only, one will have progeny by a woman, who will already be pregnant at the time of marriage. 
37. ISSUELESSNESS. If the 5th House falls in a malefic's Sign and be occupied by strong malefics without benefic's aspect, the native will be childless. 
38. PROGENY BY A FEMALE SLAVE. If the 5th House be in a Navāńśa of Venus and be aspected by Venus, one will beget progeny by a female servant. Some scholars opine, that even, if the Moon's Navāńśa and the Moon so come in the picture, the said effects will come to pass. 
39. SONS AND DAUGHTERS. When the 5th House has exclusively the divisions of the Moon and Venus and be with aspects of Venus and the Moon alone, or be occupied by these two alone, or, when the said House has the divisions of only even Signs, the native will beget only female children. In a contrary situation, (i.e. 5th House falling in divisions of odd Signs only and be excluded from the occupation, or aspect of Venus and the Moon but others), there will be birth of only male children. 
40. CHILDLESSNESS. When the Moon occupies the 10th House, Venus is in the 7th and malefics are in the 4th, the native's dynasty does not descend any further. 
41. LOSS OF CHILDREN. Should Mars be in the 5th, the children of the native will pass away, as they are born. However, if Jupiter, or Venus lend aspect to the said position, the loss relates only to the first child. If all planets aspect (the said Mars), then there is no loss at all of children. 
42. SPECIAL EFFECTS. Should the 5th House be occupied exclusively by malefics, the native will be devoid of wealth, own men and happiness. If Mars is in the 5th House, he will be distressed (or deformed). Saturn so posited denotes sickness. The occupations of Mercury, Jupiter, or Venus will confer abundant happiness and wealth. 
43-44. ENEMIES. If the 6th House is aspected by Saturn and occupied by Mars, the native will have fear from enemies. Occupation, or aspect of benefics will keep one free from such fear. The number of enemies (causing trouble) will correspond to the number of planets posited in the 6th House. Rest of the related matters may be understood from the previous pages, (Ch. 30). 
45 ABOUT THE 7th HOUSE. If Jupiter, Moon, Venus and Mercury be in the 7th, in any manner (i.e. one of them, two, three, or all of them in the 7th), or other divisions falling in the 7th House, or, if the 7th House be in aspect to these, one will procure a wife corresponding to the planet/s and Rāśi/s in question. 
46. Should the 7th House contain malefics, or fall in malefic planets' divisions, the wife of the native will be destroyed (i.e. adversely affected). These results can be deduced from the Ascendant and the Moon, the stronger of them having more significance. If the Moon be in the 7th (from the Ascendant) along with Saturn, the native will marry a widow. 
47. The number of wives will correspond to the number of heavenly bodies aspecting the 7th, or the Navāńśas past in the 7th House. There will be a single wife, if Leo, Aries, or Scorpio rise in Navāńśa, or, if Mercury and Jupiter join together in the 7th House. 
48. If the 7th House has many divisions of Venus and the Moon, or is occupied by these two, there will be plurality of wives. Specially Venus in the 7th will cause such an effect. 
49. Jupiter and Venus related to the 7th House will confer a bride of the same caste, while the Sun, Mars, Saturn and the Moon denote a female belonging to a mean order. As per Ketumalacharya, Venus and Moon related to the 7th House will cause relationship with whores. 
50-51. Mars in the 7th House will make one go devoid of wife. If he is, while so posited in aspect to only Saturn, the wife will certainly pass away. 
Should Mars and Venus be together in the 7th, or 5th, or 9th, the native will beget a languid, or deformed wife. 
52. It is the unanimous opinion of all the sages, that, if the Moon and the Sun are, respectively, in the 12th and the 6th, both the native and his wife will be one-eyed. 
53. If Saturn occupies the Ascendant, while Venus is in the 7th identical with Ganda Rāśi and the 5th is bereft to beneficial aspect, the person acquires a barren wife. 
54-55. One will be devoid of a wife and an issue, if malefics occupy the Ascendant, 12th and 7th, while decreasing Moon is in the 5th. Both the native and his wife will be immoral, if the 7th House falls in the various divisions of Saturn and Mars, while Venus is posited in the 7th in aspect to Mars and Saturn. 
56. When the 7th House is occupied by Mercury and Venus, the native will be bereft of both wife and progeny. If however this combination receives the aspect of a benefic, there will be obtainment of a wife at an advanced age. 
57. Should the Moon, along with even one of Mercury, Jupiter and Venus, be in the 7th, the native will be opulent. 
58. ABOUT THE 11TH HOUSE. The native will gain through kings, wars, thieves, forests, quadrupeds etc., if the Sun is placed in the 11th House, or, if the 11th House is aspected, or owned by the Sun. 
59. Should the Moon be in the 11th House, or her division so related to the 11th House the native will gain through females and through sales of elephants. If the Moon is declining, these are not much, but an increasing Moon increases these gains greatly. 
60. Mars, or his divisions related to the 11th House, as above denotes gains through gold, coral, ornaments, ruby, money, valour, coming and going (i.e. travels), fire and weapons. 
61. Should Mercury, or his divisions be related to the 11th, as above, the native will gain by writing, arts, literature and arguments. 
62. Jupiter, or his divisions so related to the 11th House indicates gains through headship of a city, royal mercy, Sacrifices (religious), meritorious acts, gold and horses. 
63. When the planet Venus, or his divisions are so connected with the 11th House, one will gain through connections with prostitutes, travels, pearls and silver. 
64. Saturn, or his divisions so connected with the 11th House indicates gains through towns and villages, acts of lasting nature, iron, donkeys and buffaloes. 
65. The effects attributed above stand increased, if benefics aspect the 11th House, will decrease by malefic influence and will remain mixed with the interference of both benefics and malefics. 
66. If the 11th House is aspected by (or associated with) all the planets, advent of wealth will be in several ways. The strongest of those will have the highest influence. 
67. A planet in it's own Sign, or in a friendly Sign will give half of the effects attributed. These effects are full, if it is in its exaltation Sign, very meager, if it is combust and just one fourth, if inimically placed. 
68. The effects relating to the 11th House, as mentioned above will be experienced right from birth, according to Yavanas. But according Lokaksha (a preceptor by that name), kings and heads of zones stand to enjoy abundant gains (as against a common man). 
69-70. ABOUT THE 12th HOUSE. If the Sun, or weak Moon is placed in the 12th, the native's wealth will be lost to the king. Mars posited in the 12th in aspect to Mercury, will cause losses in several ways Jupiter, the Moon (with increasing rays) and Venus in the 12th will cause growth of wealth, provided there is no aspect from Mars on them. Rest may be understood from the previous portion (Ch. 30). 
71. MISCELLANEOUS MATTERS. Even a person born in regal scion will become an artisan, if the Ascendant in Mercury's decanate receives the aspect of the Moon from an Angle. 
72. Should Venus be in the 12th House in Virgo identical with Saturn's Navāńśa, while the Luminaries are in the 7th in aspect to Saturn, the native's mother though belonging to a noble race will become a slave. 
73. Should Saturn occupy the 2nd House counted from the Sun, while the Moon and Mars, respectively, are in the 10th cusp and 7th House with reference to the Ascendant, the native will always be distressed. 
74. The native will suffer from pulmonary and spleenary disorders apart from tuberculosis, if the Moon is hemmed between malefics, as Saturn occupies the 7th House. 
75. Should there be an exchange between the Sun and the Moon in the Navāńśa, the native will suffer from phlegmatic disorders. Should the Sun and the Moon be in one Rāśi having identical longitudes, the native will be emaciated at all times. 
76. Should the 8th, 2nd, 6th and the 12th be, respectively, occupied by the Sun, Moon, Mars and Saturn, the native will lose his eyes due to the affliction caused by the strongest of the tour. 
77. If malefics occupy the 6th, 11th, 3rd and 5th, the native will suffer from ear defects, provided there are no aspects from benefic planets. Malefics in the 7th unaspected by benefics will produce dental afflictions. 
78. There will be diseases of the mind, if Saturn occupies the Ascendant, while Mars is in the 5th, or the 9th. Alternatively, Saturn, while being in the Ascendant should be conjunct decreasing Moon to cause the said effects. 
Thus ends the 34th Ch. entitled “DIFFERENT HOUSES AND WORLDLY AFFAIRS” in Kalyana Varma's Saravali. 
