
Saravali 
Page 5
Ch. 25. Effects of Mars in Various Rāśis 1-2. MARS IN ARIES. If Mars at birth occupies Aries, the native will be splendourous, truthful, valorous, be a king, be fond of war, interested in adventurous acts, be an Army chief, or head of a village, or a band; be delighted, charitable be endowed with a number of cows, goats etc. and grains, be fierce and will join many women. 
3-4. If Mars is in Taurus in a nativity, the person will break the vows of chaste women, will eat voraciously, will have little wealth and few sons, be jealous, will maintain many people, will not trust others, will play violently, will speak very harshly, be fond of music, be sinful, be inimical to relatives and will bring infamy to his family. 
5-6. MARS IN GEMINI. Should Mars be in Gemini, the native will be splendourous, be capable of enduring miseries, be very learned, be well versed with poetical rules, skillful in various kinds of fine arts, fond of going to foreign countries, virtuously disposed, highly intelligent, favourably disposed to his sons and friends and will devote to various kinds of assignments. 
7-8. MARS IN CANCER. If Mars is in Cancer at birth, the subject will like living in others' houses, be deformed, sick, will attain riches through agriculture, will enjoy royal food and robes during childhood, will eat food in others' houses, will become wealthy through the source of water, be repeatedly anguished and be always distressed. 
9-10. MARS IN LEO. If Mars is in Leo in a nativity, the native will be impatient, be valorous, intent upon grabbing others' money and children, will like to live in forests, be fond of eating cow's flesh (or beef etc.), will lose his first wife, will kill snakes and animals, will be bereft of children, be devoid of charitable acts and be always active in his jobs. 
11-12. MARS IN VIRGO. Should Mars occupy Virgo at birth, the subject will be worthy of honour, be never rich, be very fond of sexual union and music, be soft and sweet spoken, will have various kinds of expenses, be not much valorous, be learned, will have ribs in their advanced position, will fear enemies very much, be skillful in Shastras and fine arts, be fond of bathing, make-up etc. and be splendourous. 
13-14. If Mars occupies Libra in a nativity, the person will be liable to wandering, will indulge in bad business, be an able speaker, be fortunate, deformed in respect of some limb, will have few relatives, be fond of wars, will lose his first wife, will deal in liquors and will earn through prostitutes to only lose. 
15-16. MARS IN SCORPIO. If Mars occupies Scorpio at birth, the native will be attached to trade, will be interested in Vedic knowledge, be leader of thieves, skillful in his duties, be interested in wars, be highly sinful, will do big crimes, will be perfidious towards his enemies, will betray, be disposed towards killing, be unhelpful, be a talebearer, will be endowed with lands, sons and wife and be troubled by poison, fire, weapons and wounds. 
17-18. MARS IN SAGITTARIUS. Should Mars be in Sagittarius, the native will have many wounds, be emaciated, be harsh in speech, crafty, alienated, be a warrior endowed with chariots, elephants and Army men, will pass arrows on other's Army from his chariot, be happy with hard work, will lose his happiness and money due to anger and will not honour elders. 
19-20. If Mars is posited in Capricorn at birth, one will be wealthy (fortunate), be endowed with happiness and pleasures, be wealthy, will have an excellent disposition, be famous, be an Army chief, or a king, will possess a good wife, be successful in war, will live in his own country, be independent, be a protector, be virtuous and will be interested in various procedures. 
21-22. If Mars is posited in Aquarius at the time of one's birth, he will be devoid of both affection and purity, will look like an old person, will die a bad death, will have spite, jealousy, untruthful disposition, afflicted speech and lost wealth, will be ugly, will have (abundant) hair on the body, will lose money in gambling, will be unsightly, will have miserable profession, be fond of liquor and be unfortunate. 
23-24. MARS IN PISCES. Should Mars be in Pisces at the time of one's birth, the person will be troubled by diseases, will have indifferent children, will live in foreign countries, be insulted by his own relatives, will lose all his wealth by his cunning and cheating disposition, will be depressed in spirits, be very miserable, will disrespect elders and Brahmins, be unkind, will conceive (other's) desires, be fond of praises and be famous. 
25-30. MARS IN OWN RASHI AND IN ASPECT TO OTHERS. Should Mars at birth be in Aries/Scorpio and be aspected by the Sun, the person will possess wealth, wife and children, be a kings minister, be a justice, be famous and be a charitable king. 
Should Mars at birth be in Aries/Scorpio and be aspected by the Moon, the native will be bereft of mother, will have a wounded body, will hate his own people, will not have friends, be jealous and will have female children. 
Should Mars at birth be in Aries/Scorpio and be aspected by Mercury, the subject will be an expert in stealing others' money, be a liar, be devoted to Manmatha (i.e. highly libidinous), be hostile and will frequently visit prostitutes. 
Should Mars at birth be in Aries/Scorpio and be aspected by Jupiter, the native will be learned, sweet-spoken, fortunate, dear to parents, be very affluent and will be a king par excellence. 
Should Mars at birth be in Aries/Scorpio and be aspected by Venus, the native will be imprisoned due to females and will be deprived of his money on account of females, more than once. 
Should Mars at birth be in Aries/Scorpio and be aspected by Saturn, the native will be capable of hindering thieves in spite of his being not valorous, will be devoid of his men and will maintain another woman. 
31-36. MARS IN A HOUSE OF VENUS AND ASPECTED BY OTHERS. If Mars is in Taurus/Libra, with the aspect of the Sun, the person will seek to move in forests and hills, will hate women, will have many enemies, will have fierce appearance and be courageous. 
If Mars is in Taurus/Libra with the aspect of the Moon, the native will not honour his mother, be wicked, will lord many women and be dear to them and will fear war. 
If Mars is in Taurus/Libra with the aspect of Mercury, the native will promote quarrels, will speak much, will have a soft body, will possess (indifferent or) few sons and little wealth and will be learned in Shastras. 
If Mars is in Taurus/Libra with the aspect of Jupiter, the subject will be skillful in music and in play of musical instruments, be fortunate, be dear to his relatives and will be pure. 
If Mars is in Taurus/Libra with the aspect of Venus, the person will be a kings minister, be liked by the king, be an Army chief, will have famous name (i.e. titles etc.) and will be happy. 
If Mars is in Taurus/Libra with the aspect of Saturn, the native will be happy, famous, wealthy, be endowed with friends and own men, be learned and will be head of a group of villages/towns, or group of men. 
37-42. MARS IN MERCURY'S RASHI AND IN ASPECT TO OTHERS. If at birth Mars be in Gemini/Virgo and in aspect to the Sun, the native will be blessed with learning, wealth and courage, be fond of hills, forests and fortresses and be highly strong. 
If Mars is in Gemini/Virgo and is aspected by the Moon, the person will be happy, wealthy, splendourous, will guard women's apartments, will be endowed with women and will manage the kings residence. 
If Mars is in Gemini/Virgo and is aspected by Mercury, one will be skillful in the art of writing, in mathematics and in poetry, be garrulous, be liar, be a sweet speaker, be a messenger (or an ambassador) and will endure lot of misery. 
If Mars is in Gemini/Virgo and is aspected by Jupiter, the native will be a kings representative, be bright, will go to foreign countries, as an ambassador, be skillful in all doings and be a leader. 
If Mars is in Gemini/Virgo and is aspected by Venus, the person will do the jobs of females, be very fortunate and will enjoy food and robes. 
If Mars is in Gemini/Virgo and is aspected by Saturn, the person will be interested in wandering in mines (i.e. places beneath surface), hills and forests, will have husbandry, as his livelihood, be highly miserable, be very valorous, dirty and be devoid of wealth. 
43-48. MARS IN CANCER IN ASPECT TO OTHERS. If Mars be in Cancer at birth and is aspected by the Sun, the native will be subjected to bilious diseases, be splendourous, be a justice in position and be valorous. 
If the Moon aspects Mars in Cancer, the person will be troubled by various diseases, will have mean conduct, will possess an unsightly body and be miserable. 
If Mercury aspects Mars in Cancer, the person will be dirty, sinful, will possess a mean family, will be rejected by his own men and be shameless. 
If Mars in Cancer is aspected by Jupiter, the native will be famous, be king's minister, be learned, charitable, wealthy and be bereft of carnal pleasures. 
If Venus aspects Mars in Cancer, the subject will be grieved on account of women's company, be insulted by women and will lose wealth on account of women. 
Should Saturn aspect Mars in Cancer, the native will acquire money through journey in water, be equal to a king, be sportive in his acts and be always bright. 
49-54. MARS IN LEO IN ASPECT TO OTHERS. If Mars is in Leo and is aspected by the Sun, the native will be humble, helpful to friends, be endowed with own men and be fond of wandering in cow-houses, forests and hills. 
If the Moon aspects Mars in Leo, the native will be ominous for his mother, be intelligent, will possess a hard body, be widely famous and will obtain money through women. 
If Mercury aspects Mars in Leo, the native will be clever in many arts, be a miser, be skillful in poetry and fine arts and be wicked. 
If Jupiter aspects Mars in Leo, the person will be close to the king, be highly learned, be of pure mentality and be an Army chief. 
Should Venus aspect Mars in Leo, the person will have union with many women, be fortunate in respect of his wife and will be ever juvenile. 
Saturn aspecting Mars in Leo denotes, that the person will look, like an old man, be poor, will wander in others' houses/be miserable. 
55-60. MARS IN JUPITER'S HOUSE IN ASPECT TO OTHERS. If Mars occupies Sagittarius, or Pisces at birth and is aspected by the Sun, the subject will be world honoured, be fortunate, will live in forests, hills and fortresses and be cruel. 
If Mars is in Sagittarius, or Pisces and is aspected by the Moon, the person will be deformed, belligerent, learned and be always inimical to the king. 
If Mars is in Sagittarius, or Pisces and is aspected by Mercury, the person will be a scholar, be skillful, learned in fine arts and be highly learned in general. 
If Mars is in Sagittarius, or Pisces and is aspected by Jupiter, the person will be devoid of wife and happiness, will be beyond the reach of enemies, be wealthy and be fond of exercises. 
If Mars is in Sagittarius, or Pisces and is aspected by Venus, the person will be very much dear to women, be interested in cosmetics, makeup etc., be charitable, be libidinous and be fortunate. 
If Mars is in Sagittarius, or Pisces and is aspected by Saturn, the person will have defective body, be sinful, wandering-nature, devoid of happiness and interested in others' religion. 
61-66. MARS IN SATURN'S HOUSE AND ASPECTED BY OTHERS. Should Mars be in Capricorn, or Aquarius and be aspected by the Sun, the subject will have very dark body, be courageous, will have many wives, sons and abundant wealth and be very sharp. 
Should Mars be in Capricorn, or Aquarius and be aspected by the Moon, one will be fickle minded, be not well disposed towards his mother, be fond of beautification, be charitable, be not firm in friendship and be rich. 
Should Mars be in Capricorn, or Aquarius and be aspected by Mercury, the subject will walk very slowly, be not rich, will not have any profession, be not strong, be not outspoken and be not virtuous. 
Should Mars be in Capricorn, or Aquarius and be aspected by Jupiter, the native will be very beautiful, will possess kingly qualities, will fulfill his undertakings, be long-lived and be endowed with relatives. 
Should Mars be in Capricorn, or Aquarius and be aspected by Venus, one will be endowed with various kinds of (carnal) pleasures, be interested in fostering women and be belligerent. 
Should Mars be in Capricorn, or Aquarius and be aspected by Saturn, the person will be a king, be very affluent, will hate women, will possess many children, be learned, be devoid, of happiness and be timid in war. 
Thus ends the 25th Ch. entitled “Effects of Mars in Various Rāśis” in Saravali of Kalyana Varma. Ch. 26. Effects of Mercury in Various Rāśis 
1-2. MERCURY IN ARIES. If Mercury is in Aries at the time of one's birth, the native will be fond of battles (be uncompromising), be very learned, wicked, emaciated, interested in music and dance, be untruthful, be attached to sexual pleasures, be a writer, will produce fictitious things, will eat much, will lose hard-earned money, will incur debts and imprisonment frequently and will be sometimes fickle minded and yet sometimes firm in disposition. 
3-4. Should Mercury be in Taurus, the native will be skillful, eminently liberal, be famous, will have knowledge of Vedas and Śāstras, be fond of exercises, robes, ornaments and garlands, be firm in disposition, will have sincerely earned wealth, will possess a chaste wife, will be a soft and sweet speaker and be after sexual satisfaction. 
5-6. If Mercury occupies Gemini at birth, the subject will have an auspicious appearance, will speak sweetly, be very affluent, be an able speaker, be honourable, will give up his happiness, will cohabit less, will have two wives, be fond of arguments, will be learned in Vedas, Śāstras etc., be a poet, be independent, dear, very munificent, proficient in work and will have many sons and friends. 
7-8. One born with Mercury in Cancer will be learned, will be fond of living in other countries, be interested in cohabiting with women and also in music, be fickle-minded, prattling, inimical to his own relatives, will be fond of arguments, will lose wealth on account of enmity with women, be of bad disposition, be interested in many jobs, be a good poet and will be popular on account of the fame of his ancestors. 
9-10. Should the planet Mercury occupy Leo at one's birth, the native will not possess even bit of wisdom (Kala – bit, hence Gnanakala interpreted thus), be famous in the world, be not truthful, will possess a weak memory, be wealthy, be not strong, will indulge in fratricide, be unfortunate in respect of wife, be independent, mean in conduct, be a servant, be devoid of children, be against his own race, but be favourable to others. 11-12. If Mercury occupies his exaltation Sign at the time of one's birth, the native will be quite virtuous, eloquent, skillful, will have knowledge of writing (be an exponent) and poetry, be learned in fine/mechanical arts, be sweet in disposition, be liked by women, be not much virile, be the eldest son of family, be honoured by virtuous, be disposed to serve others, modest, argumentative, famous, charitable and strong. 
13-14. If Mercury falls in Libra at the time of one's birth, the native will possess knowledge of arts, be intent upon arguments, be an able speaker, will spend money lavishly, will have business in various directions, will honour wise men, guests, Gods and preceptors (elders), be skillful in pretending to serve others, be amiable, devoted to Gods, fraudulent, fickle-minded and sometimes short-tempered and yet sometimes (notably) peaceful. 
15-16. MERCURY IN SCORPIO. If Mercury is posited in Scorpio, one will experience troubles, grief and evils, will hate the virtuous, will be devoid of truth, religion and shame, be a dunce, be not virtuous, be a miser, will cohabit with wicked women, be fond of giving cruel punishments, be not out spoken, be interested in blameworthy jobs, will incur debts, will join base men and will steel other's properties. 
17-18. Should Mercury be in Sagittarius, the native will be famous, liberal, will have knowledge of Vedas and Śāstras, be valorous, will practice abstract meditation, be a minister, or family priest, be chief among his race-men, will be very rich, be interested in performing Yajñas and teaching (Vedas etc.), be a skillful speaker, be charitable and be an expert in writing and fine arts. 19-20. MERCURY IN CAPRICORN. If Mercury is in Capricorn at birth, the native will be mean, dull, impotent, will do others' work, be devoid of virtues, be subjected to various kinds of miseries, will dream, wander etc., be a tale bearer, be untruthful, devoid of relatives, dirty and timid. 
21-22. MERCURY IN AQUARIUS. Should Mercury be in Aquarius at birth, the subject will be bereft of good disposition and good deeds, be attached to many religious acts, will give up doing worthy things, be insulted by others, be impure, be not virtuous, be very wicked, be inimical to wife, be devoid of carnal pleasures, be very unfortunate, very timid, impotent, dirty and modest. 
23-24. Should Mercury be in Pisces, one will be fond of good conduct and purity, will live in foreign countries, be issueless, poor, will have a chaste wife, be virtuous, fortunate, be devoid of religion, be skillful in stitching etc. and be devoid of profane knowledge, acquaintance with Śāstras and fine arts, will be proficient in bagging other's wealth and will be devoid of wealth. 25-30. MERCURY IN ARIES/SCORPIO AND ASPECTED BY OTHERS. Should Mercury occupy a Sign of Mars at birth and be aspected by the Sun, the person will be truthful, be very happy, be honoured by the king and be patiently disposed. 
If Mercury is in a Sign of Mars and is aspected by the Moon, the native will steal the hearts of the fair sex, will serve others, be dirty and be bereft of virtues. 
If Mercury is in a Sign of Mars and is aspected by Mars, one will be a liar, a sweet speaker, will promote quarrels, be learned, affluent, dear to king and valorous. 
If Mercury is in a Sign of Mars and is aspected by Jupiter, one will be happy, will possess a glossy and hairy physique, will have attractive hair, will be very rich, will command others and be sinful. 
If Mercury is in a Sign of Mars and is aspected by Venus, the subject will be in royal service, be fortunate, principal among men, or in his town, will speak skillfully, be trustworthy and will be endowed with a wife. 
If Mercury is in a Sign of Mars and is aspected by Saturn, the person will experience miseries, be fierce, be intent upon doing cruel activities and be devoid of his own men. 
31-36. MERCURY IN TAURUS/LIBRA IN ASPECT TO OTHERS. Should Mercury be in a House of Venus and be aspected by the Sun, the subject will suffer from penury and acute grief, will have a sick physique, be interested in serving others and will be censured. 
Should Mercury be in a House of Venus and be aspected by the Moon, the native will be trustworthy, affluent, firmly pious, devoid of sickness, will have lasting family ties, be famous and be a kings minister. 
Should Mercury be in a House of Venus and be aspected by Mars, the native will be troubled by diseases and enemies, be distressed, will incur royal insult and will be deprived of all worldly objects. 
Should Mercury be in a House of Venus and be aspected by Jupiter, the native will be highly learned, will fulfill his promise, will be leader of a country/city/group of men and be famous. 
Should Mercury be in a House of Venus and be aspected by Venus, the person will be fortunate, soft in disposition, be happy, will enjoy good robes make up etc. and will steal the hearts of the fair sex. 
If Saturn throws his aspect on Mercury in a House of Venus, the subject will be devoid of happiness, be dirty, will experience many diseases and evils, will be subjected to grief on account of his relatives and be distressed. 
37-42. MERCURY IN OWN HOUSE AND IN ASPECT TO OTHERS. Should Mercury be in Gemini/Virgo and be aspected by the Sun, the native will speak truth, be fortunate, dear to king, be a Lord himself, be polite in his activities and be liked by all. 
Should Mercury be in his own House and receive the aspect of the Moon, the person will be sweet in disposition, garrulous, will promote quarrels, be interested in acquiring sastric knowledge, firm and will succeed in all his undertakings. 
Should Mercury be in his own House and receive the aspect of Mars, the person will have an injured body, be dirty, be a genius, will serve the king and be dear to him. 
Should Mercury be in his own House and receive the aspect of Jupiter, one will be a king's minister, be excellent, be beautiful, charitable, rich, be endowed with his own men and be courageous. 
Should Mercury be in his own House and receive the aspect of Venus, the native will be highly learned be a royal employee, be a messenger, will honour friendship and will be interested in base women. 
Should Mercury be in his own House and receive the aspect of Saturn, one will be progressive-minded, be modest, will achieve success in undertakings started by him and will be wealthy with money and clothes. 
43-48. MERCURY IN CANCER IN ASPECT TO OTHERS. Should Mercury be in Cancer, in aspect to the Sun, one will be a dhoby, or a gardener, or a house-builder, or gem smith. 
If the Moon aspects Mercury in Cancer, one will be deprived of wealth (or energy of the physique) on account of women and will be miserable for the same reason. 
If Mars lends his aspect to Mercury in Cancer, he will not have much learning, be garrulous, be a great liar, will produce fictitious things, be a thief and will be affectionate in speech. 
If Jupiter aspects Mercury in Cancer, one will be a great scholar, very dear (to all), be fortunate, dear to the king and will cross the boundaries of learning. 
Should Venus aspect Mercury in Cancer, one will be equal to Cupid in appearance, will possess attractive physique, be well-versed in the art of singing and in playing musical instruments, be fortunate and softly disposed. 
If Saturn aspects Mercury in Cancer, one will be fond of vanity, be sinful, will face imprisonment, be devoid of virtues and will hate co-born and elders. 
49-54. MERCURY IN LEO IN ASPECT TO OTHERS. If Mercury occupies Leo at birth and is aspected by the Sun, the native will be jealous, rich, virtuous, cruel, mean, fickle-minded and shameless. 
If the Moon aspects Mercury in Leo, one will be very beautiful, very skillful, be interested in poetry, fine arts, music and dance, be wealthy and virtuous. 
If Mars lends his aspect to Mercury in Leo, one will be base, miserable, physically injured, unskillful and impotent. 
If Jupiter aspects Mercury in Leo, one will be beautiful, very learned, be a gifted speaker, be very famous and be endowed with attendants and conveyances. 
If Venus aspects Mercury in Leo, one will possess unparalleled beauty, be softly disposed, will have an attractive face, will have many conveyances, be very courageous and be a minister. 
If Saturn aspects Mercury in Leo, one will be tall in stature, be splendourless, be ugly, will emanate bad smell from body out of sweat and be miserable. 
55-60. MERCURY IN JUPITER'S HOUSE IN ASPECT TO OTHERS. Should Mercury be in Sagittarius/Pisces and aspected by the Sun, one will suffer from urinary diseases and epilepsy and be peaceful in disposition. 
If the Moon aspects Mercury in Sagittarius/Pisces, the native will be a writer, be beautiful par excellence, be very affluent, trustworthy, amiable and happy. 
If Mars aspects Mercury in Sagittarius/Pisces, the native will be a leader of townsmen, or thieves, will reside in forests and will be a famous writer. 
Should Jupiter aspect Mercury in Sagittarius/Pisces, the native will be rich by memory, intelligence and descendency, be beautiful, noble and knowledgeable, be a kings minister, or his treasurer and be a writer. 
If Venus aspect Mercury in Sagittarius/Pisces, the native will educate boys and girls, be wealthy, soft in disposition and brave. 
If Saturn aspect Mercury in Sagittarius/Pisces, the native will be intent upon living in forests, will eat much, be wicked, dirty and will be unsuccessful in all his undertakings. 
61-66. MERCURY IN SATURN'S HOUSE IN ASPECT TO OTHERS. If Mercury be in a House of Saturn and is aspected by the Sun, one will be a boxer, be very strong, one will eat abundantly, be censured, will speak sweetly and be famous. 
If Mercury be in a House of Saturn and is aspected by the Moon, one will derive his livelihood through water, be plentiful will sell flowers, liquor and bulbs (vegetables), will have fierce appearance and be firm (i.e. not moving much). 
If Mercury be in a House of Saturn and is aspected by Mars, one will be infirm in speech, be calm in disposition, bashful and happy. 
If Mercury be in a House of Saturn and is aspected by Jupiter, one will be endowed with abundant money and grains, be honoured in his village/town and by his men, be happy and be famous. 
If Mercury be in a House of Saturn and is aspected by Venus, one will be the husband of a base woman, be ugly, be unintelligible, be troubled by sexual passion and will have many sons. 
If Mercury be in a House of Saturn and is aspected by Saturn, one will be sinful, very poor, miserable and mean. 
Thus ends the 26th Ch., entitled ‘Effects of Mercury' in Kalyana Varma's Saravali. Ch. 27. Effects of Jupiter in Various Signs 
1-2. JUPITER IN ARIES. If Jupiter is posited in Aries at birth, one will be argumentative in disposition, will acquire precious stones and ornaments out of his efforts, will be endowed with strength, sons and wealth, will have eminent and famous profession, be splendourous, will have many enemies, much expenses and an injured body and will confer fierce and cruel punishments. 
3-4. Should Jupiter be in Taurus, one will be endowed with a broad body, be corpulent, will honour Brahmins and Gods, be splendourous, fortunate, attached to his wife, be endowed with good appearance, profession, cows and abundant wealth; will possess good articles and ornaments, be distinguished in speech, intelligence and skill; will have political / judicial wisdom, be modest, be endowed with medical accomplishments and be skillful in experiments. 
5-6. Should Jupiter be in Gemini, the native will be affluent, scholarly, proficient, will possess attractive eyes, be eloquent, courteous, skillful, virtuous, will honour elders and relatives, will be able to utter “bejeweled” words (be literally rich in words), which are benevolent in nature, be devoted to his duties and be a good poet. 7-8. If Jupiter be in Cancer at birth, the native will be a scholar, be beautiful, be highly learned, charitable, good-natured, be very strong, be famous, will possess abundant grains and riches, be endowed with truth and penance, will have long-living sons, be honoured by all, will be a king, will have a distinguished profession and will be attached to his friends. 
9-10. Should Jupiter be in Leo at the time of birth, the native will be lastingly inimical, be strong, courageous, will show abundant friendship, be learned, rich, will have eminent relatives, be a king, will have heroism akin to that of a king, will be recognizable in an assembly, will destroy the entire band of his enemies, will possess a strong physique and will live in hills, fortresses, forests and temples. 
11-12. If Jupiter occupies Virgo at birth, one will be a scholar, be virtuous, be skillful in his work, be fond of scents, robes and flowers, will firmly gain in undertakings, will have rich experience in Śāstras and fine arts, be affluent, charitable, pure-hearted, skillful and wonderfully learned. 
13-14. If Jupiter occupies Libra at birth, one will be a scholar, will have many sons, be endowed with foreign assignments, will be very affluent, interested in ornaments, modest, will earn money through dance and drama, be pleasing in appearance, be splendourous, learned in Śāstras, be superior among his colleague-businessmen, will honour Gods and guests and be very learned. 
15-16. Should Jupiter at the time of one's birth be in Scorpio, he will be expert in Śāstras, be a king, will be a commentator of many Bhāşyas (a commentary, which explains Sūtras word by word with comments of its own, for example, on Vedas), be skillful, will construct temples and towns, will have many wives, but few sons, be troubled by diseases, will undergo many difficulties, be very fierce, be ostentatious in his performance, be virtuous and will indulge in contemptuous acts. 
17-18. If Jupiter occupies Sagittarius at birth, one will be a preceptor, will conduct religious vows, initiations, sacrifices etc., will have lasting wealth, be charitable, be friendly to his own men, be fond of helping others, interested in Shastras, be the head of a zone, or a minister, will live in many countries, will prefer loneliness and be interested in visiting shrines. 
19-20. JUPITER IN CAPRICORN. Jupiter in Capricorn denotes, that the native will be less virile, will experience much grief and difficulties, will be mean in conduct, be a dunce, will meet a bad end, will suffer from penury, will serve others, will be bereft of auspiciousness, mercy, purity, affection to his relatives and of religion, will have an emaciated body, be timid, interested in living in other countries and be depressed of spirits. 
21-22. JUPITER IN AQUARIUS. If Jupiter falls in Aquarius at the time of birth, one will be a tale-bearer, be ill disposed, interested in evil jobs, be chief among his racemen, be always attached to base men, be malicious, miserly, will suffer from diseases, will lose wealth on account his own utterances, be devoid of intelligence and virtues and will violate elder's beds. 
23-24. JUPITER IN PISCES. If Jupiter is in Pisces at birth, one will be expert in knowing the meanings of Vedas and other Shastras, will be honoured by friends and virtuous people, will be a headsman in the king's employ, be praiseworthy, unconquerable, rich, devoid of fear, be proud, firm in undertakings, be a king, be skillful in policies, training, behavior and war tactics, be famous and will be calm in his doings. 
25-30. JUPITER IN ARlES/SCORPIO IN ASPECT TO OTHERS. If Jupiter occupies Aries/Scorpio at birth and is aspected by the Sun, the native will be charitable, will be truthful, will have famous sons, be very fortunate and will have abundant hair on the body. 
If Jupiter occupies Aries/Scorpio and is aspected by the Moon, the native will be a historical and poetical writer, will be endowed with many precious stones, be dear to women, be a king and be highly learned. 
If Jupiter occupies Aries/Scorpio and is aspected by Mars, one is of royal scion, will be valorous, fierce, endowed with knowledge of politics, be modest, affluent and will have a disobedient wife and disobedient servants. 
If Jupiter occupies Aries/Scorpio and is aspected by Mercury, the native will be a liar, be crafty, sinful, will be skillful in detecting other's defects, will serve others, be grateful, be modest and be not outspoken. 
If Jupiter occupies Aries/Scorpio and is aspected by Venus, one will be very happy in respect of residences, sleeping comforts, robes, scents, garlands, ornaments and wife and be very timid. 
If Jupiter occupies Aries/Scorpio and is aspected by Saturn, the subject will be dirty, miserly, sharp, adventurous, amiable, famous and will not have lasting children and friendship. 
31-36. JUPITER IN TAURUS/LIBRA IN ASPECT TO OTHERS. If Jupiter occupies a House of Venus at birth and is aspected by the Sun, one will be endowed with attendants and quadrupeds. will wander verily, will have a long body, be learned and be a king's minister. 
If Jupiter occupies a House of Venus and is aspected by the Moon, the native will be abundantly rich, be very calm, Sweet, be dear to mother and wife and will enjoy much pleasures. 
If Jupiter occupies a House of Venus and is aspected by Mars, the native will be dear to the fair sex, be learned, courageous, affluent, happy and be of royal Scion. 
If Jupiter occupies a House of Venus and is aspected by Mercury, the native will be learned, Skillful, sweet, fortunate, endowed with riches, be highly virtuous and be splendourous. 
If Jupiter occupies a House of Venus and is aspected by Venus, the native will be very attractive, affluent, will wear excellent ornaments, be merciful and will enjoy excellent sleeping comforts and excellent robes. 
If Jupiter occupies a House of Venus and is aspected by Saturn, the native will be a scholar, will be endowed with abundant wealth and corns, be excellent among the people of his village/town, be dirty, ugly and be devoid of wife. 
37-42. JUPITER IN MERCURYS HOUSE AND IN ASPECT TO OTHERS. If Jupiter occupies Gemini/Virgo and is aspected by the Sun at birth, one will be great, important in his village be a householder and will be endowed with wife, sons and money. 
If Jupiter occupies Gemini/Virgo and is aspected by the Moon, the native will be affluent, dear to mother, fortunate, happy, will have wife and sons and be incomparable. 
If Jupiter occupies Gemini/Virgo and is aspected by Mars, one will be easily successful at all times, be ugly, rich and be amiable to all. 
If Jupiter occupies Gemini/Virgo and is aspected by Mercury, one will be a skillful astrologer, will have many children and wives and will be exponent of many aphorisms and precepts and speak with great excellence. 
If Jupiter occupies Gemini/Virgo and is aspected by Venus, the native will undertake acts of temple construction, will visit prostitutes and will win women's hearts. 
If Jupiter occupies Gemini/Virgo and is aspected by Saturn, the native will be the head of a group, state, or village and be beautiful. 
43-48. JUPITER IN CANCER IN ASPECT TO OTHERS. If Jupiter occupies Cancer at birth and is aspected by the Sun, native will be famous, be ahead of others and will (in the beginning) be devoid of happiness, wealth and wife, all of which will be acquired by him later. 
If Jupiter occupies Gemini/Virgo and is aspected by the Moon, the native will be very rich, splendourous, be a king, will enjoy abundant wealth and conveyances and will have excellent wife and sons. 
If Jupiter occupies Gemini/Virgo and is aspected by Mars, one will marry in the boyhood itself, will be endowed with gold and ornaments, be learned, valorous and will have a wounded physique. 
If Jupiter occupies Gemini/Virgo and is aspected by Mercury, one will be endowed with relatives and friends, be rich, will promote quarrels, be bereft of sins, be a minister and be trustworthy. 
If Jupiter occupies Gemini/Virgo and is aspected by Venus, one will have many wives, extraordinary riches, various ornaments, be happy and fortunate. 
If Jupiter occupies Gemini/Virgo and is aspected by Saturn, one will be important in his village, or in the Army, or in his town, be talkative, be very affluent, garrulous and will enjoy pleasures in old age. 
49-54. JUPITER IN LEO ASPECTED BY OTHERS. If at birth Jupiter is in Leo and is aspected by the Sun, one will be dear to good men, be famous, be a king, be extremely affluent and virtuous. 
If Jupiter is in Leo and is aspected by the Moon, the native will be very beautiful, dirty, will be very rich through the fortunes of his wife and will conquer his five senses. 
If Jupiter is in Leo and is aspected by Mars, the native will honour elders at all times, will perform distinguished acts, be very skillful, pure, adventurous and cruel. 
If Jupiter is in Leo and is aspected by Mercury, the native will have knowledge of civil works of building construction, will be endowed with profane knowledge, be virtuous, be a sweet speaker, be a minister and be highly learned. 
If Jupiter is in Leo and is aspected by Venus, the native will be dear to females, be fortunate, will receive royal honours and be very strong. 
If Jupiter is in Leo and is aspected by Saturn, one will be garrulous, be an eloquent speaker, be devoid of happiness, be sharp and will have mean children and mean wife. 
55-60. JUPITER IN OWN HOUSE AND IN ASPECT TO OTHERS. If Jupiter is posited in Sagittarius/Pisces at birth and is aspected by the Sun, the native will be inimical to the king and will be miserable being bereft of wealth and relatives. 
If Jupiter is posited in Sagittarius/Pisces and is aspected by the Moon, the native will enjoy many kinds of happiness, be very fortunate in respect of wife and will have the pride of honour, wealth and possessions. 
If Jupiter is posited in Sagittarius/Pisces and is aspected by Mars, one will be injured in war, be cruel, will cause torture, will harm others and will lose children. 
If Jupiter is posited in Sagittarius/Pisces and is aspected by Mercury, the native will be a minister, or a king, will be happy with wealth, fortunes and progeny and will enjoy all kinds of delights. 
If Jupiter is posited in Sagittarius/Pisces and is aspected by Venus, the native will be happy, learned, be devoid of blemishes, be long-lived, fortunate and will be blessed by Goddess Lakshmi. 
If Jupiter is posited in Sagittarius/Pisces and is aspected by Saturn, the native will be dirty, will be fear-stricken, be neglected by the people of his village/town and be devoid of happiness, pleasures and virtues. 
61-66. JUPITER IN A HOUSE OF SATURN IN ASPECT TO OTHERS. If Jupiter is in a House of Saturn at birth and is aspected by the Sun, one will be learned, be a king, be rich by birth, will enjoy various kinds of pleasures and be very courageous. 
If Jupiter is in a House of Saturn and is aspected by the Moon, the native will be devoted to his parents, be superior by birth, be learned rich, virtuous and very charitable. 
If Jupiter is in a House of Saturn and is aspected by Mars, one will be valorous, be an Army chief with the king, splendourous, well-dressed, famous and honoured. 
If Jupiter is in a House of Saturn and is aspected by Mercury, one will be highly libidinous, important among his folk, rich by conveyances and wealth, famous and will have many friends. 
If Jupiter is in a House of Saturn and is aspected by Venus, the native will be endowed with food, drinks, excellent residence, sleeping comforts, wealth, conveyances, excellent wife, ornaments and robes. 
If Jupiter is in a House of Saturn and is aspected by Saturn, the native will be endowed with incomparable learning, be supreme, be a king of his country, be rich with attendants and quadrupeds and will enjoy pleasures. 
Thus ends the 27th Ch. entitled Effects of Jupiter in Various Signs in Kalyana Varma's Saravalī 
Ch. 28. Effects of Venus in Various Signs 
1-2. Should Venus be in Aries at birth, one will be night-blind, will have many blemishes, be inimical, will join other housewives, will visit whores, will move in forests and hills, will be imprisoned on account of women, be base, hard in disposition, be an Army chief, or chief of men, be not reliable and be eminent. 
3-4. VENUS IN TAURUS. Should Venus at birth be in Taurus, one will be endowed with many wives and gems, be an agriculturist, will possess scents, garlands and robes, will live on account of cows, be charitable, will maintain his relatives, will have good appearance, will be learned in many branches, will give away many things, will help the living beings and be a principal person. 
5-6. Should Venus occupy Gemini at birth, one will be famous in sciences and Śāstras, be beautiful, libidinous, be skillful in writing and in poetry, be dear to good people, will derive wealth through music and dances, will have many friends, will honour Gods and Brahmins and be firm in friendship. 
7-8. If Venus occupies Cancer at the time of one's birth, he will be wise, virtuous, learned, strong, soft, chief among men, will have desired happiness and wealth, be good-looking, just, very much troubled on account of women and wine and will be miserable with family troubles. 
9-10. If Venus occupies Leo at birth, the native will respect women, will enjoy wealth and happiness, will have less virility, be dear to relatives, be miserable in spite of his happiness, will help others, will respect Brahmins, elders and preceptors and will be devoid of much discrimination. 
11-12. Should Venus be in Virgo, the native will not be quite discriminative, be soft in disposition, be skillful, will be helpful to others, will speak sweetly, will earn money through several sources, will cohabit with bad women, be mean, be devoid of happiness and pleasures, will beget more daughters and less sons, will visit shrines and be a scholar in an assembly. 
13-14. VENUS IN LIBRA. If Venus occupies Libra, the native will acquire hard-earned money, be valorous, endowed with superior robes etc., interested in living in foreign countries, will protect his own people, be skillful in his duties, rich, meritorious, famous by honouring Gods and Brahmins, be a scholar and be fortunate. 
15-16. If Venus occupies Scorpio, the subject will be jealous, be very malicious, be not religious, be argumentative, be crafty, be not attached to brothers, be not fortunate, will be troubled by enemies, be distressed, will be inimical to unchaste women, be skillful in killing, will incur heavy debts, will suffer penury, be proud and will contract venereal diseases. 
17-18. One, who has Venus in Sagittarius will be endowed with good results accruing out of virtues, dutifulness and wealth, be dear to all people, be splendourous, be an excellent personage, will shine like the Sun before his family members, be a scholar, will be endowed with cows, be fond of decoration, will enjoy wealth, wife and fortunes, be a king's minister, be skillful, will have a stout and long physique and be respected by all. 
19-20. VENUS IN CAPRICORN. If Venus occupies Capricorn at birth, one will be miserable due to heavy expenses, will have an emaciated body, will be fond of aged women, will suffer from heart diseases, be miserly in the matter of money, be a liar, be skillful in cheating, be a eunuch, be devoid of (good) acts, interested in others' work, very distressed, be a dunce and will, however, endure misery. 
21-22. Should Venus be in Aquarius, one will suffer from fear and excitement, be not successful in undertakings, will go to other women, be not virtuous, be inimical to elders and to his children, be bereft of ablutions, like bathing and will not be endowed with (good) robes, ornaments etc. and be dirty. 
23-24. VENUS IN PISCES. If Venus is posited in Pisces at birth, one will be courteous, liberal, virtuous, very wealthy, will destroy enemies, be famous in the world, excellent, distinguished, dear to king, be endowed with good speech and wisdom, be liberal, will derive wealth and respect from the virtuous, will keep up his promise, will maintain his family members and be endowed with knowledge. 
25-30. VENUS IN ARIES OR SCORPIO IN ASPECT TO OTHERS. Should Venus occupy Aries/Scorpio at birth and is in aspect to the Sun, one will be miserable on account of women and will lose wealth and happiness on account of them, will be a king and be learned. 
If Venus is in Aries, or Scorpio and is aspected by the Moon, one will be imprisoned, very fickle-minded, be libidinous, will marry a base lady and will be bereft of children. 
If Venus is in Aries, or Scorpio and is aspected by Mars, one will be devoid of wealth, honour and happiness, will do others' jobs and will perform dirty jobs. 
If Venus is in Aries, or Scorpio and is aspected by Mercury, one will be foolish, profligate, unworthy, be not in good terms with his own relatives, be immodest, thievish, mean and cruel. 
If Venus is in Aries, or Scorpio and is aspected by Jupiter, one will be endowed with beautiful eyes, will have a charitable wife, will possess a beautiful and long body and will have many sons. 
If Venus is in Aries, or Scorpio and is aspected by Saturn, one will be very dirty, lazy and wandering-natured, will serve others and be a thief. 
31-36. VENUS IN OWN HOUSE IN ASPECT TO OTHERS. Should Venus at birth occupy Taurus/Libra and is aspected by the Sun, the person will acquire an excellent wife and abundant wealth, will become a great man and will be subdued by women. 
If Venus is in Taurus, or Libra and is aspected by the Moon, it indicates, that one is born of an excellent mother, will be endowed with happiness, wealth, respect and sons, will have excellence and be splendourous. 
If Venus is in Taurus, or Libra and is aspected by Mars, one will marry a bad female, will lose home and wealth on account of females and be sensuous. 
If Venus is in Taurus, or Libra and is aspected by Mercury, one will be splendourous, sweet, fortunate, happy, bold, wise and virtuous and will possess distinguished strength. 
If Venus is in Taurus, or Libra and is aspected by Jupiter, one will be endowed with wife, sons, abodes, conveyances, riches etc. and will achieve desired objects. 
If Venus is in Taurus, or Libra and is aspected by Saturn, one will have little happiness, little wealth, will be reprobate, will marry a mean lady and will suffer from diseases. 
37-42. VENUS IN GEMINI/VIRGO IN ASPECT TO OTHERS. If Venus is in Gemini/Virgo and aspected by the Sun, one will be well disposed towards the king, his own mother and wife, be learned and rich. 
If Venus is in Gemini, or Virgo and is aspected by the Moon, one will have dark eyes, beautiful hair, be endowed with sleeping comforts, conveyances etc., be splendourous, beautiful in appearance and be fortunate. 
If Venus is in Gemini, or Virgo and is aspected by Mars, one will be highly sensuous, be fortunate and will destroy his wealth through women. 
If Venus is in Gemini, or Virgo and is aspected by Mercury, one will be learned, sweet in disposition, wealthy and endowed with conveyances and children, be fortunate and be leader of men, or be a king. 
If Venus is in Gemini, or Virgo and is aspected by Jupiter, one will be highly happy, be radiant, courageous, learned and be a preceptor. 
If Venus is in Gemini, or Virgo and is aspected by Saturn, one will be very miserable, insulted, fickle-minded, green-eyed and be a dunce. 
43-48. VENUS IN CANCER IN ASPECT TO OTHERS. If Venus is in Cancer and aspected by the Sun, the native's wife will be attached to her duties, will possess a spotless body, will be a king's daughter, (i.e. she will be of a rich heritage), one short-tempered and will be endowed with wealth. 
If Venus is in Cancer and is aspected by the Moon, one will keep his step-mother happy, will have a daughter first and later on many sons, be happy, fortunate and beautiful. 
If Venus is in Cancer and is aspected by Mars, one will be skillful in arts, be very rich, will suffer on account of women, be fortunate and will promote the cause of his relatives. 
If Venus is in Cancer and is aspected by Mercury, one will marry a learned woman, will suffer miseries on account of his relatives, will wander, be wealthy and learned. 
If Venus is in Cancer and is aspected by Jupiter, one will be endowed with many servants, sons, happiness, relatives and friends and be dear to king. 
If Venus is in Cancer and is aspected by Saturn, one will be subdued by women, be poor, base, ugly, fickle-minded and unhappy. 
49-54. VENUS IN LEO IN ASPECT TO OTHERS. If Venus occupies Leo at the time of birth and is aspected by the Sun, one will be jealous, be dear to the fair sex, libidinous will acquire money through women and will possess elephants. 
If Venus is in Leo and is aspected by the Moon, one will present obsequial water to his step mother, will be miserable on account of women, be rich and will have various kinds of mental disposition (i.e. be infirm in disposition). 
If Venus is in Leo and is aspected by Mars, one will be a royal person, be famous, dear to women, be affluent, fortunate and be attached to other's wives. 
If Venus is in Leo and is aspected by Mercury, one will be ever engaged in earning, be miserly in disposition, be addicted to women, will join other's wives, be courageous, crafty, false and wealthy. 
If Venus is in Leo and is aspected by Jupiter, one will be endowed with conveyances, wealth and servants, will marry many women and be a king's minister. 
If Venus is in Leo and is aspected by Saturn, one will be a king, or equal to a king, be famous, will have abundant wealth and conveyances, will marry a prostitute (or a widow), be beautiful in appearance and be miserable. 
55-60. VENUS IN SAGITTARIUS/PISCES IN ASPECT TO OTHERS. If Venus occupies Sagittarius/Pisces at birth and aspected by the Sun, one will be very short tempered, learned, wealthy, be liked by all and will go to foreign countries. 
If Venus is in Sagittarius, or Pisces and is aspected by the Moon, one will be famous, be kingly, will eat rich food, be distinguished and will possess incomparable strength. 
If Venus is in Sagittarius, or Pisces and is aspected by Mars, one will be very much ill-disposed towards women, will be both happy and miserable, be rich and will possess cows. 
If Venus is in Sagittarius, or Pisces and is aspected by Mercury, one will be endowed with all kinds of robes, ornaments, foods and drinks and will possess plenty of money and horses and cows, will possess many wives and many sons, be happy and be very wealthy. 
If Venus is in Sagittarius, or Pisces and is aspected by Saturn, one will be always amassing financial gains, be happy, will enjoy pleasures and abundant wealth and be fortunate. 
61-66. VENUS IN SATURN'S HOUSE IN ASPECTS TO OTHERS. Should Venus be in Capricorn/Aquarius and be in aspect to the Sun, the native will be firm, very dear to females, very wealthy, very happy and truthful and be courageous. 
If Venus is in Capricorn, or Aquarius and is aspected by the Moon, one will be very splenderous, very valorous, very affluent and fortunate. 
If Venus is in Capricorn, or Aquarius and is aspected by Mars, one will lose his spouse, will suffer many evils and diseases, will undergo difficulties and later on be happy. 
If Venus is in Capricorn, or Aquarius and is aspected by Mercury, one will be learned, rich, skillful in sacred precepts, highly scholastic, truthful and happy. 
If Venus is in Capricorn, or Aquarius and is aspected by Jupiter, one will enjoy robes and garlands, be beautiful, will be skillful in music and musical instruments and will posses a good wife. 
If Venus is in Capricorn, or Aquarius and is aspected by Saturn, one will be endowed with servants, conveyances and wealth, be dirty and will possess a black, beautiful and broad physique. 
Thus ends the 28th Ch. entitled Effects of Venus in Various Signs in Kalyana Varma's Saravali 
Ch. 29. Effects of Saturn in Various Rāśis 
1-2. SATURN IN ARIES. If Saturn occupies Aries at the time of one's birth one will be miserable due to his vices and hard labor, be deceitful will hate his relatives, be blameworthy, garrulous, reprobated, poor, bad in appearance, ill-tempered, inimical to his people, will do base acts, be jealous and sinful. 
3-4. If Saturn occupies Taurus at the time of one's birth, he will be bereft of wealth, be a servant, will speak undesirable words, be untruthful, will win the hearts of old women, will have bad friends, will be addicted to women, will serve other women, be not outspoken, will have strong sight, be related to numerous assignments and be a fool. 
5-6. If Saturn occupies Gemini, one will contract debts and imprisonments, will toil, will have vanity in disposition will consecrate by hymns and prayers, be bereft of virtues, be always in hide-out, be libidinous, cunning, wicked and fond of wandering and of sports. 
7-8. SATURN IN CANCER. If Saturn is in Cancer, one will possess a beloved wife, be devoid of wealth in boyhood, will suffer many diseases, be learned, motherless, soft-spoken, distinguished in acts, will always contract diseases, will trouble others, be inimical to relatives, crooked, be kingly in his mid-life and will enjoy growing pleasures. 
9-10. SATURN IN LEO. If Saturn occupies Leo, one will be interested in writing and reading, be skillful, be disdained, devoid of virtues and wife, will live by servitude, be devoid of his own men and happiness, be interested in doing base acts, ill-tempered, be mad with (undue) desires, will carry loads, will toil hard and will have a wrinkled body. 
11-12. SATURN IN VIRGO. If Saturn occupies Virgo at birth the subject will resemble a eunuch, be very crafty, will depend on others for food, be addicted to prostitutes, will have a few friends, be unacquainted with arts, be desirous of indulging in ugly acts, will possess sons and wealth, be indolent, helpful to others, will intent upon spoiling virgins and be cautious in his actions. 
13-14. Saturn posited in Libra at birth indicates, that the subject will be rich, soft-spoken, will earn money and honours from foreign countries, be a king, or a scholar, will have his wealth protected by his relatives, be senior in the circle, will attain a high status owing to his gracious speech in an assemblage, be good and will join corrupt female dancers and prostitutes. 
15-16. SATURN IN SCORPIO. If Saturn occupies Scorpio at birth, the native will be hostile, be crooked, affected by poison and weapons, very ill-tempered, miserly, egoistic, rich, capable of stealing others' money, averse to instruments played on festive occasions, malicious, very miserable and will face destruction, misery and diseases. 
17-18. SATURN IN SAGITTARIUS. If Saturn occupies Sagittarius, one will be skillful in behavior, teaching, Vedic meanings, learning and denotation, (i.e. he will be best placed in these respects), be famous due to virtuous children, family profession and his own virtues, will enjoy excellent affluence in his old age, will speak less, will have many names and be soft in disposition. 
19-20. If Saturn is posited at birth in Capricorn, the native will lord over the lands of others' females, will be endowed with Vedic knowledge, virtues and knowledge of many branches of fine arts, be excellent among his caste-men, be honourable, will respect others, be famous, be interested in bathing and decoration, will be skillful in performance, will live in foreign places, be courageous and be polite in behavior. 
21-22. If Saturn is in Aquarius, the native will be a great liar, be eminent, be addicted to women and wine, be wicked, crafty, will fall prey to evil friendship, be very ill-tempered, be averse to knowledge, conversation and traditional law, be addicted to other women, be harsh in speech and will attempt at many undertakings. 
23-24. SATURN IN PISCES. If Saturn occupies Pisces at birth, one will be fond of Sacrifices and arts, be chief among his relatives and friends, be calm, will have increasing wealth, be skillful in policy-making, be capable of diamond testing, be virtuous, modest and will later on acquire an authoritative position. 
25-30. SATURN IN ARIES/SCORPIO IN ASPECT TO OTHERS. If Saturn occupies a Rāśi of Mars and is aspected by the Sun, one will be interested in agriculture, be very affluent, be endowed with cows, buffaloes and horses, be fortunate and industrious. 
If Saturn is in Aries, or Scorpio and is aspected by the Moon, one will be fickle minded, base, will join mean and ugly women and be devoid of happiness and wealth. 
If Saturn is in Aries, or Scorpio and is aspected by Mars, one will kill animals, be base, be a leader of robbers, be famous and be fond of (joining other) women, meat and wine. 
If Saturn is in Aries, or Scorpio and is aspected by Mercury, one will be untruthful, not virtuous, will eat much, be a famous thief and be devoid of happiness and riches. 
If Saturn is in Aries, or Scorpio and is aspected by Jupiter, one will be endowed with happiness, wealth and fortune, be a king's minister and be chief. 
If Saturn is in Aries, or Scorpio and is aspected by Venus, one will be quite unsteady in disposition, very ugly, will join other women and courtesans and be bereft of pleasures. 
31-36. SATURN IN TAURUS/LIBRA IN ASPECT TO OTHERS. Should Saturn be in a Sign of Venus and is aspected by the Sun, the native will be clear in speech, will lose wealth, be a scholar, will eat in other's houses and be weak in constitution. 
If Saturn is in Taurus, or Libra and is aspected by the Moon, one will gain wealth through women, will be honoured by ministers of kings, be dear to women and be endowed with family. 
If Saturn is in Taurus, or Libra and is aspected by Mars, one will be skillful in war preparations, but will be away from war, will speak much and be endowed with wealth and family. 
If Saturn is in Taurus, or Libra and is aspected by Mercury one will always be jocularly disposed, be equal to a neuter, will serve females and be base. 
If Saturn is in Taurus, or Libra and is aspected by Jupiter, one will share happiness and misery of others, will do others' jobs, be dear to people, charitable and industrious. 
If Saturn is in Taurus, or Libra and is aspected by Venus, one will be happy on account of women and wine (i.e. will enjoy these), be endowed with gems, be very strong and be dear to the king. 
37-42. SATURN IN GEMINI/VIRGO AND IN ASPECT TO OTHERS. If Saturn occupies a Rāśi of Mercury at birth and is aspected by the Sun, the native will be devoid of happiness and wealth, be virtuous, bereft of anger, will endure difficulties and be valorous. 
If Saturn is in Gemini, or Virgo and is aspected by the Moon, one will be equal to a king, will possess a bright physique, will earn wealth and honour through women and will do women's jobs. 
If Saturn is in Gemini, or Virgo and is aspected by Mars, one will be a famous boxer, be stupefied, will carry heavy loads and will possess an ugly body. 
If Saturn is in Gemini, or Virgo and is aspected by Mercury, one will be rich, skillful in war, be a dance master, a skillful singer and an expert in arts. 
If Saturn is in Gemini, or Virgo and is aspected by Jupiter, one will be trustworthy in the king's circle, will possess all kinds of (good) qualities, be liked by good men and will earn wealth through his virtues. 
If Saturn is in Gemini, or Virgo and is aspected by Venus, one will be skillful in beautifying women, be a teacher of Yogas, or a saint and be dear to the fair sex. 
43-48. SATURN IN CANCER IN ASPECT TO OTHERS. If Saturn occupies Cancer at birth and is aspected by the Sun, the native will lose his father in his very boyhood be bereft of wealth, wife and happiness, will eat bad food and be sinful. 
If Saturn is in Cancer and is aspected by the Moon, one will be a source of evil to his mother, be wealthy and will be troubled by his co-born. 
If Saturn is in Cancer and is aspected by Mars, one will enjoy king's wealth, be defective bodied, will possess gold and gems, be endowed with a family and will have a bad group of relatives and wife. 
If Saturn is in Cancer and is aspected by Mercury, one will be hard-hearted, garrulous, will conquer his enemies, will show vanity and will do noble acts. 
If Saturn is in Cancer and is aspected by Jupiter, one will be endowed with lands, houses, friends, sons, wealth, gems and wife. 
If Saturn is in Cancer and is aspected by Venus, one is of a noble descent, but will be bereft of beauty, grace and happiness. 
49-54. SATURN IN LEO IN ASPECT TO OTHERS. If Saturn occupies the Sun-owned Rāśi and is aspected by the Sun himself, the native will be devoid of wealth, happiness and nobility, will be a liar and a drunkard, will possess a bad physique, be a servant and be very miserable. 
If Saturn is in Leo and is aspected by the Moon, one will enjoy abundant wealth, precious stones and women, be widely famous and be dear to the king. 
If Saturn is in Leo and is aspected by Mars, one will everyday move from place to place, be unfortunate, will live in fortresses and hills, be base and be bereft of wife and sons. 
If Saturn is in Leo and is aspected by Mercury, one will not be outspoken, be lazy, poor, will do females' jobs, be dirty and miserable. 
If Saturn is in Leo and is aspected by Jupiter, one will be chief and rich in his town, or among his men, will be endowed with progeny and be trustworthy. 
If Saturn is in Leo and is aspected by Venus, one will be averse to women, be splendourous, slow (or tardy), happy, rich and will attain a good end. 
55-60. SATURN IN JUPITER'S RASHI AND IN ASPECT TO OTHERS. If Saturn occupies Sagittarius, or Pisces at birth, in aspect to the Sun the native will be the father of others' children and through these children he will attain wealth, name, fame and honour. 
If Saturn is in Sagittarius, or Pisces and is aspected by the Moon, one will be bereft of mother, will have two names and be endowed with wife, children and wealth. 
If Saturn is in Sagittarius, or Pisces and is aspected by Mars, one will be troubled by windy diseases, will dislike people, be sinful, mean, blameworthy etc. 
If Saturn is in Sagittarius, or Pisces and is aspected by Mercury, one will be equal to a king, be happy, be a preceptor, be honourable, rich and fortunate. 
If Saturn is in Sagittarius, or Pisces and is aspected by Jupiter, one will be a king, or equal to a king, or a minister, or an Army chief and be free from all kinds of danger. 
If Saturn is in Sagittarius, or Pisces and is aspected by Venus, one will have two mothers and two fathers, will live in forests and hills, will be unsteady and be endowed with many kinds of assignments. 
61-66. SATURN IN OWN HOUSE IN ASPECT TO OTHERS. If Saturn is in Capricorn/Aquarius and is aspected by the Sun, he will be sick, will have an ugly wife, will eat other's food, be miserable, wandering in nature and will carry loads. 
If Saturn is in Capricorn, or Aquarius and is aspected by the Moon, one will be fickle-minded, untruthful, sinful, will not have good terms with his mother, be rich and be sorrowful due to wandering. 
If Saturn is in Capricorn, or Aquarius and is aspected by Mars, one will be very valorous, famous, be superior among great men and sharp. 
If Saturn is in Capricorn, or Aquarius and is aspected by Mercury, he will carry loads, be clouded in mentality (or Tamasik in disposition), be good-looking, wandering-natured, learned, be not quite wealthy and be fortunate. 
If Saturn is in Capricorn, or Aquarius and is aspected by Jupiter, one will be famous for his good qualities, be a king, or be of royal scion, long-lived and be free from diseases. 
If Saturn is in Capricorn, or Aquarius and is aspected by Venus, one will be rich, addicted to other women, fortunate, happy and will enjoy food and drinks. 
Thus ends the 29th Ch. entitled Effects of Saturn in Various Rāśis in Kalyana Varma's Saravali.
