
Saravali 
Page 3
Ch. 13. Lunar Yogas 
1. SUNAPHA, ANAPHA AND DURUDHURA YOGAS. Excepting the Sun, any other planet in the 2nd from the Moon causes Sunapha Yoga, in the 12th Anapha Yoga and in both the 2nd and the 12th Durudhura Yoga. 
2. KEMADRUMA YOGA. Kemadruma Yoga is formed, if at least one of the said three Yogas (viz. Sunapha, Anapha and Durudhura Yogas) is not present, or, if the Moon's Angles are devoid of planets, or, if she is unaspected by all the planets. Such Yoga causes extreme difficulties. 
3. DIFFERENT PERMUTATIONS. By all possible permutations and transmutations, one can see 30 kinds of Sunapha Yoga, 30 kinds of Anapha Yoga and 180 kinds of Durudhura Yoga. 
4. EFFECTS OF SUNAPHA YOGA. One born with Sunapha Yoga will be wealthy, will have self-made prowess (or will reach an exalted position of his own efforts), be very virtuous, be learned in Shastras and their meanings, be very famous, virtuous (like Lord Rama), be peacefully disposed, happy, be a king, or a minister and be highly intelligent. 
5. EFFECTS OF ANAPHA YOGA. One born in Anapha Yoga will be eloquent in speech, magnanimous, virtuous, will enjoy food, drink, flowers, robes and females, will be famous, calm in disposition, happy, pleased and will possess a beautiful body. 
6. EFFECTS OF DURUDHURA YOGA. One born in Durudhura Yoga will be famous on the earth for his speech, wisdom, valour and virtues. He will enjoy freedom, comforts, wealth and conveyances. He will be liberal, but will come to grief by maintaining his family members. He will have good behavior. 
7. EFFECTS OF KEMADRUMA YOGA. The native with Kemadruma Yoga will be deprived of life, drinks, food, residence, robes and friends, though he may belong to regal scion. He will suffer from poverty, grief, sickness and be dirty. He will live by hard labor, be wicked and be inimically disposed to one and all. 
8-9. OTHER KIND OF SUNAPHA ETC. The kind of Sunapha Yoga etc. arising from the Moon's Angles are (also) important. These Yogas give effects according to the state of the Moon (i.e. depending on her rays, being Full, New etc.). The strength of the planets, viz. Mars etc., causing these Yogas, native's country and the race he belongs to must be properly understood before evaluating Sunapha etc. 
10-11. RESULTS OF SUCH YOGAS CAUSED BY MARS ETC. If Sunapha Yoga is caused by Mars (by being in the 2nd of the Moon), the native will be valorous, wealthy, cruel in speech, be an Army chief, will be fierce, torturous, proud and inimical. If Mercury be the cause of Sunapha Yoga, the native will be expert in Vedas, Shastras and music. He will be virtuous and a poet. He will be high-minded, intent on thinking of good for all and will possess a brilliant physique. 
12-14. Should Jupiter cause Sunapha Yoga, a person so born will have high learning, will be famous and himself be a king, or dear to a king. He will have a good family and have plenty of wealth. Venus will give wife, lands, wealth, prowess, quadrupeds and valour. The native will further be honoured by king and will also be courageous. Should Saturn be in the 2nd of the Moon causing Sunapha Yoga, the native will be skillful, be worshipped by the people in his village and city and will have wealth galore. He will be devoted to his work and be brave. 
15-19. ANAPHA YOGA'S EFFECTS GIVEN BY MARS ETC. If Anapha Yoga is caused by Mars-being in the 12th from the Moonthe native will head a band of thieves, will be arrogant in disposition, be honoured, fond of war, given to anger, good, praiseworthy, good-bodied and proud. If by Mercury, the native will be an expert in singing, dancing and writing, will be a poet and an able orator. He will be conferred honours by tile ruler. will have a brilliant body and will perform famous deeds. Should the Yoga be caused by Jupiter, the native will be majestic, strong, intelligent, fond of assembly, famous through a king and will be a poet. Venus causing this Yoga gives an exceedingly great liking for women. The native will be dear to the king and will enjoy pleasures. He will be splendourous, famous and will have abundant gold. If Saturn causes this Yoga, the subject will be broad-shouldered, be a leader, be indired to keep up his commitments, be rich with quadrupeds, devoted to an infamous lady and be virtuous. 
20. EFFECTS OF DURUDHURA YOGA CAUSED BY MARS ETC. If Durudhura Yoga is caused by the pair of Mars and Mercury, the native will be a liar, be very wealthy, expert, very wicked, greatly miserly, addicted to an old lady and be chief in his race. 
21. If durudhura Yoga is caused by Mars and Jupiter, one will be famous by his deeds, be mighty (or wealthy), inimically disposed to many and disposed to anger, will protect his men and will gather money. 
22. If the Moon has Venus and Mars on either side, the native will have a virtuous wife, will be fortunate, argumentative, pure, skillful, will like doing exercises and be bold in war. 
23. If Saturn and Mars plank the Moon, the native will be the husband of a bad lady. He will save a lot of money. He will have vices. He will be given to anger and be a tale bearer. He will win over his enemies. 
24. Should Jupiter and Mercury be on either side of the Moon, the native will be virtuous, learned in Shastras, garrulous, be a good poet, be wealthy, capable of making sacrifices and be famous. 
25. If Durudhura Yoga is caused by Mercury and Venus, the person will be a sweet speaker, be fortunate, splendourous, beautiful, be fond of dance, singing etc., be served, valiant and be a minister. 
26. If Mercury and Saturn plank the Moon, the native will move from one country to the other to earn money. He will not be much educated, will be worshipped by others, but be inimical to his own men. 
27. Should Jupiter and Venus cause this Yoga, by being on either side of the Moon, the native will be courageous, intelligent, will have political wisdom, will possess gold and gems, will be famous and be in the employ of a king. 
28.1f Jupiter and Saturn be such planets, as to cause Durudhura Yoga the native will be happy, will have knowledge of politics, will be sweet in speech, learned, peaceful, wealthy and good looking. 
29. One, who has Durudhura Yoga caused by Venus and Saturn will conduct himself, like an old man (i.e. so mature), be chief in his race, skillful, dear to women and will have plenty of money. He will be honoured by the king and gather abundant wealth. 
30. LUNAR YOGAS FROM THE SUN. If the Moon is in an Angle from the Sun, little effects will be felt in regard to money, wisdom, skill, learning and modesty. These are medium, if the Moon be in Panaphara (i.e. 2nd 5th, 8th and 11th) and exceedingly good in Apoklima (i.e. 3rd, 6th. 9th and 12th). 
31. MOON IN VISIBLE AND INVISIBLE HALVES. In the case of a night birth, if the Moon is with Parivesha (halo) and be declining in the invisible half of the Zodiac (i.e. being posited between Lagna Bhava Madhya and the center of the descendant7th House), or declining Moon in day time be in the visible half (i.e. between the centres of the descendant and the Ascendant), even results will be felt in respect of fear, grief etc., (that is these positions confer bad results). The Full Moon gives kingdom, if she be contrarily posited. 
32. DHANA YOGAS. If all benefics are posited in Upachayas i.e. 3, 6, 10 and 11, the native will acquire much wealth. Two benefics confer moderate wealth, while one confers little wealth in the said Upachaya. These can be deduced from the Moon also. 
33. There are other Raja Yogas, like Adhi Yoga arising from the Moon. I have not dealt with them here which I have done infra. 
Thus ends the 13th Ch. entitled “Yogas from the Moon” in Kalyana Varma's Saravali. Ch. 14. Yogas from the Sun 
1. VASI, VESI, UBHAYACHARI YOGAS FROM THE SUN. Excluding the Moon (and nodes) a planet in the 12th from the Sun causes Vasi Yoga, in the 2nd Vesi Yoga and in both the 12th and the 2nd Ubhayachari Yoga. 
2. RESULTS OF VESI YOGA. One born in Vesi Yoga will be weak-sighted, firm in his word, be hard working and will have a bent body. So say Yavanas. 
3-5. EFFECTS OF VESI YOGA CAUSED BY DIFFERENT PLANETS. Should Jupiter cause Vesi Yoga, the native will accumulate money, be learned and be good-hearted. If Venus produces this Yoga, the person will be timid, will face obstacles in his missions, will have pleasant (or swift) movements and will be defeated. Mercury causing this Yoga indicates, that the native will be a servant, will suffer penury, be soft-spoken and be modest. He will be bashful. Mars denotes, that the native will resort to base means, but be helpful to others. If it is Saturn, that causes Vesi Yoga, one will join others' wives, be wicked, will resemble an old person in appearance,-be fraudulent in disposition and be contemptuous. He will, however, have wealth. 
6. EFFECTS OF VASI YOGA. One born in Vasi Yoga will possess excellent speech (voice), good memory, be employed, will have looks towards, sideways, will possess a strong physique about the waist, will be equal to a king and be a genuine person. 
7-9. EFFECTS OF VASI YOGA BY DIFFERENT PLANETS. If Jupiter should cause Vasi Yoga, the native will possess courage, strength and wisdom. He will keep up his word. In the case of Venus, the person will be valorous, famous, virtuous and reputed. Mercury emanating this Yoga will make one speak sweetly, be beautiful and obey others' orders. The Vasi Yoga caused by Mars indicates, that the subject will be victorious in war, famous and will live with his own fortunes. If by Saturn, the native will be a businessman, wicked, will steal others' money, will hate elders and will be the husband of a pious lady. 
10. The strength of the planet Sun and that of the planets causing these Yogas and their association with various Rāśis and Amsas should be understood and all results be declared accordingly. 11. EFFECTS OF UBHAYACHARI YOGA. One born under Ubhayachari Yoga will have forebearance, will be very fortunate, even bodied, firm, profoundly strong, not very tall, full of everything, learned, happy, will have many servants, will protect his relatives, be equal to a king, ever enthusiastic and will enjoy all pleasures. 
Thus ends the 14th Ch. entitled “Yogas from the Sun” in Kalyana Varma's Saravali. Ch. 15. Conjunctions of Two Planets 
1. INTRODUCTION TO TWO-PLANETARY YOGAS. Vriddha Yavanas have stated the effects of combinations of two planets (in one House). I state those below without ego. 
2. SUN-MOON YOGA. One, who has the Sun and Moon together will be at the disposal of his wife (or females), immodest, be a metallurgist (can be interpreted also, as “able to deceive”), will be quite wealthy and be an expert in sale of intoxicants. 3. SUN-MARS YOGA. Should the Sun and Mars be in one House the native will be splendourous, valorous, dull witted, strong, be a liar, be sinful, disposed to kill (or torture) and be fierce. 
4. SUN-MERCURY YOGA. If the Sun and Mercury are in one House, the native will be in service, will have unsteady wealth, be sweet in speech, will have fame and money, be noble, dear to king and good people and will possess strength, beauty and learning. 
5. SUN-JUPITER YOGA. If the Sun and Jupiter be together, one will be virtuous, be a minister of king, will gain through friends, be with good mind' and be a preceptor. 
6. SUN-VENUS YOGA. If the Sun and Venus be together, one will be skillful in use of weapons, be mighty, weak-sighted in old age, will be able to amuse the public and will have abundant money earned through women. 
7. SUN-SATURN YOGA. If the Sun and Saturn are together, the native will be a metallurgist, be virtuous, mindful of his own duties, will lose his wife and son, will have the qualities suitable to his race, will be pure, but not so upright. 
8. MOON-MARS YOGA. One, who has the Moon and Mars together, will be valorous, brave in war, be a boxer, will suffer bloody imbalances, or diseases, will manufacture articles of mud, skin and minerals and will be an artisan and a metallurgist. 
9. MOON-MERCURY YOGA. One, who has the Moon Mercury combination will be expert in poems and fables, be wealthy, amiable to his wife, beautiful, smiling-faced and will be endowed with distinct virtues. 
10. JUPITER-MOON YOGA. One with Jupiter and the Moon together will be firm in friendship, modest, respectful towards his relatives, wealthy, virtuous and regardful of Gods and the wise. 
11. MOON-VENUS YOGA. Should the Moon and Venus be together, the native will be endowed with flowers, incense and clothes, will know to perform duties (kriya also means rites), be dear to his race, very lazy and expert in buying and selling. 
12. MOON-SATURN YOGA. Should the Moon and Saturn be together, the native will possess a decayed wife, be dear to public, will breed elephants and horses, be devoid of virtues, be under the control of others, unwealthy and defeated. 
13. MARS-MERCURY YOGA. If Mars and Mercury are together at birth, the native will have unlucky wife, little wealth, will work with gold and iron, be an architect, will keep a wicked widow and be expert in making medicines. 
14. MARS-JUPITER YOGA. If Mars and Jupiter be together at birth, the native will be an artisan, Vedic expert, intelligent, expert in speech, wise and fond of using weapons. 
15. MARS-VENUS YOGA. One, who had Mars and Venus together at birth will be worshipped, be chief among his men, be a mathematician (or an astrologer) and be fond of gambling, untruth etc. 
16. MARS-SATURN YOGA. If Mars and Saturn be together, one will be a metallurgist. be expert in jugglery, be deceitful, skillful in thieving, troubled by weapons and poison and be fond of quarrels. 
17. MERCURY-JUPITER YOGA. One, who has Mercury and Jupiter together will be a noted dancer, scholar, singer and instrumentalist. He will be wise and happy. 
18. MERCURY-VENUS YOGA. Should Mercury and Venus be together at birth, the native will be abundantly rich, a politician, an artisan, will study Vedas, be good in speech, will know to sing, make fun and like scents and flowers. 
19. MERCURY-SATURN YOGA. One, who has Mercury and Saturn together at birth, will contract debts, be proud, deceiving, an able poet, intent on moving, expert and will possess auspicious speech. 
20. JUPITER-VENUS YOGA. One, who has Jupiter and Venus together at birth will live by education and arguments, will follow a highly virtuous path, will have accurate conception, or notion (of things) and will have a supreme wife. 
21. JUPITER-SATURN YOGA. A native, who has Jupiter and Saturn together at birth will be heroic, will have plenty of wealth, will be chief of the city (mayor etc.), famous and will be the head of an assembly, a village, or an association. 
22. VENUS-SATURN YOGA. If Venus and Saturn are together at birth, one will be expert in breaking wood, be a barber, painter, or sculptor, boxer, be intent on wandering and be owner of quadrupeds. 
23. Whatever results have been stated, as above are likely to become increased, or decreased according to mutual good, or bad Vargas occupied by the planets in question. 
Thus ends the 15th Ch. entitled “Conjunction of two planets” in Kalyana Varma's Saravali. Ch. 16. Conjunctions of 3 Planets 
1. SUN-MOON-MARS YOGA. Should the Sun, the Moon and Mars be together at birth, the native will be bereft of shame, be sinful, will have knowledge of machinery, will destroy enemies, be brave and will be expert in any kind of work. 
2. SUN-MOON-MERCURY YOGA. If the Sun, Moon and Mercury are together, the native will be splendourous, very intelligent, will be fond of arts, assembly and drinks, be in royal service and bold. 
3. SUN-MOON-JUPITER YOGA. Should the Sun, Moon and Jupiter be in one House; the native will be given to anger, be cunning, expert in service, intent on going to foreign places, be intelligent and fickle minded. 
4. SUN-MOON-VENUS YOGA. Should the Sun, Moon and Venus be in one House at birth, the native will steal others' money, will be a debaucher and be expert in Shastras. 
5. SUN-MOON-SATURN YOGA. If the Sun, Moon and Saturn be together in one House, the native will be lustful, be expert in arguments, be a dunce, be at the disposal of others and be poor. 
6. SUN-MARS-MERCURY YOGA. If the Sun, Mars and Mercury are in one House at birth, the native will be famous, hard-hearted, shameless and be devoid of wealth, sons and wife. 
7. SUN-JUPITER-MARS YOGA. Should Mars, Jupiter and the Sun be together at birth, the native will be an expert speaker, very wealthy, either a kings minister, or even a king himself, be truthful and fierce. 
8. VENUS-MARS-SUN YOGA. One, who has Venus, Mars and the Sun in one House, will be subjected to eye diseases, belongs to a good race, will be fortunate, harsh and wealthy. 
9. MARS-SUN-SATURN YOGA. Should Mars, Saturn and the Sun be together, the native will have deformed limbs, be without wealth, always sick, without his people and be a big fool. 
10. JUPITER-MERCURY-SUN YOGA. If Jupiter, Mercury and the Sun be together at birth, the native will be subjected to eye-diseases, be very wealthy, be interested in Shastras, fables, poetry, meetings and stonework and will become a good writer. 
11. MERCURY-SUN-VENUS YOGA. If Mercury, Sun and Venus be together, the native will be insatiable, talkative, intent on wandering and subjected to grief on account of women. 
12. SATURN-SUN-MERCURY YOGA. One, who has Saturn, the Sun and Mercury in one House will be a neuter, will hate others and will be given up by his relatives. 
13. VENUS-JUPITER-SUN YOGA. Should Venus, Jupiter and the Sun be together at birth, the native will be weak-sighted, bold, intelligent, indigent, be a minister and be devoted to others' jobs. 
14. JUPITER-SATURN-SUN YOGA. If Jupiter, Saturn and the Sun be together at birth. the native will not have a prominent physique, will be worshipped, will hate his own men, will have good wife, children and friends, be dear to the king and be fearless. 
15. VENUS-SATURN-SUN YOGA. One, who has Venus, Saturn and the Sun together at birth will be emotionally upset due to fear from enemies, will be devoid of honour and knowledge of arts and poetry, will have a mean history and will suffer from Leprosy. 
16. MOON-MERCURY-MARS YOGA. Should the Moon Mercury and Mars be together at birth, the native will be sinful, mean in habits and conduct and devoid of friends and relatives throughout life. 
17. MARS-MOON-JUPITER YOGA. A native, who has Mars, the Moon and Jupiter together at birth will have an even body, be addicted to women, be a thief, be splendourous, dear to women and given to anger. 
18. MARS-VENUS-MOON YOGA. One, who has Mars, Venus and the Moon together at birth is the son of a bad woman and also will wed such a lady. He will be of wandering disposition and will have fear from cold. 
19. MARS-MOON-SATURN. If Mars, Moon and Saturn join at birth, the person concerned will lose his mother in boyhood, be mean, wicked and inimical to people. 
20. MERCURY-MOON-JUPITER YOGA. Should Mercury, Moon and Jupiter be together, the native will be wealthy, skillful, eloquent in speech, bright, famous and will have many sons and brothers. 
21. MERCURY-VENUS-MOON YOGA. One, who has Mercury, Venus and Moon together at birth, will be mean in conduct in spite of his being learned and cultured. be Jealous and miserly. 
22. SATURN-MOON-MERCURY YOGA. If Saturn, Moon and Mercury be together, the person concerned will be dependent, deformed, learned, be an able speaker and respected by the king. 
23. VENUS-JUPITER-MOON YOGA. Should Venus, Jupiter and the Moon be in one House at birth, the native will be a chaste woman's son, be a scholar, will have knowledge of arts and many Shastras, be virtuous and beautiful. 
24. MOON-JUPITER-SATURN YOGA. One, who has Moon, Jupiter and Saturn combination at birth will know the inner meaning of Shastras, will seek union with aged women, be devoid of shame and be the head of a village and people. 
25. MOON-VENUS-SATURN YOGA. If the Moon, Venus and Saturn are in combination at birth, one will be a writer, reader of books, Purohita (family guru), will have to his credit merits of past birth and be an astrologer. 
26. MERCURY-JUPITER-MARS YOGA. One, who has Mercury, Jupiter and Mars together will be a good poet, Lord of a group, will marry a virtuous lady, be intent on helping others and an expert singer. 
27. MARS-MERCURY-VENUS YOGA. Should Mars, Mercury and Venus be together at birth, the native will give up his caste, be deformed, fickle-minded, wicked and garrulous. 
28. MERCURY-SATURN-MARS YOGA. Should Mercury, Saturn and Mars be together at birth, one will be a servant, will have dark eyes, be intent on living in foreign places, will have facial diseases and will be witty. 
29. VENUS-JUPITER-MARS YOGA. One, who has Venus, Jupiter and Mars together at birth will be dear to king, will have good sons and enjoy pleasures through women. He will please all persons. 
30. JUPITER-MARS-SATURN YOGA. If Jupiter, Mars and Saturn be together at birth, the native will be honoured by the king, will have wounds on the body, be mean and blamed by friends. He will also be unkind. 
31. SATURN-MARS-VENUS YOGA. If Saturn, Mars and Venus are in one House at birth, the native is born to an immoral lady, will marry such a lady, will be devoid of happiness and will be intent on wandering in distant places. 
32. MERCURY-JUPITER-VENUS. Should Mercury, Jupiter and Venus be together, the native will have good physique, be successful over his enemies, be a king, fortunate, widely famous and truthfully disposed. 
33. MERCURY-SATURN-JUPITER. When Mercury, Saturn and Jupiter are together at birth, it denotes, that the native will enjoy honour, wealth and sovereignty, be learned, will have abundant pleasures, be attached to his wife, be courageous and fortunate. 
34. MERCURY-VENUS-SATURN. One, who has Mercury, Venus and Saturn together at birth will be scurrilous in speech, fraudulent, be a liar, addicted to other women, vehement, (“vishama” has several other meanings, viz., irregular, uneven, mysterious, inaccessible, rough, painful, troublesome etc.), will have knowledge of arts and be attached to his own country. 35. JUPITER-VENUS-SATURN. Should Jupiter, Venus and Saturn be in one House at birth one will become a king even though he might be of mean natal order, will be very famous and be a repository of virtues. 
36. PARENTS. If the Moon is in the company of malefics, it is detrimental to the mother of the native. Predict similar results regarding the father of the native, if the Sun joins malefics at birth. Benefics in the place of malefics in the said Yogas will prove auspicious to the respective parent. If the planets joining be of mixed nature (i.e. one benefic and another malefic), the effects are medium. 
37-38. BENEFICS IN CONJUNCTION AND MALEFICS IN CONJUNCTION. If benefics are in conjunction at birth, the native will enjoy wealth, sovereignty and fame. Such a combination produces an emperor capable of ruling the earth. Should three malefics join at birth, the native will be unlucky, indigent, grief-stricken, ugly and immodest. 
Thus ends the 16th Ch. entitled “3 planets in combination” in Kalyana Varma's Saravali. Ch. 17. Four Planets in Conjunction 
1. SUN-MOON-MARS-MERCURY YOGA. Should these four planets be together at birth. the native will be a writer, a thief and be scurrilous in speech. He will be sickly, cunning and be capable of deceiving others. 
2. MOON-MARS-JUPITER-SUN YOGA. one, who has these four planets in one House at birth, will be wealthy, dear to women, splendourous, will maintain decorum, be free from grief and expert in work. 
3. MOON-MARS-VENUS-SUN YOGA. If these four planets join at birth, one will speak and conduct himself, as a great person, be happy, expert, intent on gathering money and will have learning, sons and wife. 
4. SUN-MOON-MARS-SATURN YOGA. One, who has these four planets together at birth, will have uneven physique, be short in stature, be unwealthy and will collect food by begging and be a proven dunce. 
5. MOON-MERCURY-JUPITER-SUN YOGA. If these four planets are in one House, the native will be a goldsmith (or a gold dealer etc.), be long eyed, be a sculptor, be very wealthy, bold and beautiful bodied. 
6. SUN-MOON-MERCURY-VENUS YOGA. The native, who has these four planets together at birth, will be deformed, lucky, short-statured and dear to king. 
7. SUN-MOON-MERCURY-SATURN YOGA. If these four planets are together at birth, the native will lose his parents in childhood, be devoid of money and happiness, be wandering, will earn food by begging and will be a liar. 
8. VENUS-JUPITER-MOON YOGA. Should these planets be in one House at birth, the subject concerned will be head of water, animals and forests (i.e. his livelihood may be through such sources), will be happy, honoured by the king and be an expert. 
9. SUN-JUPITER-MOON-SATURN YOGA. If the said planets join at birth, the native will be dark-eyed, fierce, will have many sons, be wealthy and fortunate through women. 
10. SUN-MOON-VENUS-SATURN YOGA. Should one have a combination of these planets in one House at birth, the native will have habits, like a female, be very weak, desirous of coming up and timid at all times. 
11. SUN-JUPITER-MARS-MERCURY YOGA. These four planets together at birth indicate, that the subject will be brave, be a composer of Shastras, or a ruler of province, will lose his wife and money, be undesirable and will wander. 
12. SUN-VENUS-MARS-MERCURY YOGA. If these four planets be together at birth, the native will be addicted to other women, be a thief, will have uneven limbs, will be a bad person and will be bereft of energy. 
13. MERCURY-SUN-MARS-SATURN YOGA. If these four planets are together at birth, the subject will be a warrior, scholar, be fierce, will be meanly disposed, be chief among poets and be a minister, or a king. 
14. SUN-MARS-JUPITER-VENUS YOGA. with the conjunction of these four planets, one will be fortunate, worth worship by the people, be wealthy, dear to king and famous. 
15. SUN-MARS-JUPITER-SATURN YOGA. Should these join at birth, one will be rash, prime among his group, will have cherished desires, will be endowed with relatives and friends and dear to king. 
16. SUN-MARS-VENUS-SATURN YOGA. One, who has these four planets together at birth, will be deformed, mean in conduct, oblique-sighted, will hate his relatives and will always be insulted. 
17. SUN-MERCURY-VENUS YOGA. With these planets in one House, one will be wealthy, happy, chief, will have cherished desires, will have relatives and be noble. 
18. SATURN-SUN-MERCURY-JUPITER YOGA. One, who has these four planets together at birth, will have a neuter's habits, be prestigious, fond of quarrels, will have brothers, or sisters and be not enthusiastic. 
19. SUN-MERCURY-VENUS-SATURN YOGA. Should these four planets be in conjunction at birth, one will be scurrilous in speech, fortunate, learned, soft spoken, happy, energetic, pure, wealthy, bold and helpful to friends. 
20. SUN-SATURN-VENUS-JUPITER YOGA. These four planets in conjunction at birth will make the person a miser, a poet, chief, leader of sculptors and mean. 
21. MOON-MARS-MERCURY-JUPITER YOGA. One, who has the conjunction of these four planets at birth, will be an expert in Shastras, be a king, or a great minister and be extremely intelligent. 
22. MOON-MARS-MERCURY-VENUS YOGA. If these four planets are together at birth, one will be fond of quarrels, will sleep much, be mean, will marry an unchaste lady, be fortunate, will hate his relatives and be not happy. 
23. MOON-MERCURY-MARS-SATURN YOGA. One, who has these four planets together will be bold, be without parents, is from an ignoble race, will have many wives, friends and sons and will have good conduct. 
24. MOON-MARS-JUPITER-SATURN YOGA. If these four planets are together at birth, one will be deformed, will have a good wife, be highly tolerant, be self-respected, learned will have many friends and be happy. 
25. MARS-MOON-SATURN-JUPITER YOGA. One, who has these four planets conjunct at birth will be deaf, wealthy, bold, rash in speech, firm in nature, wise and liberal. 
26. MARS-MOON-SATURN-VENUS YOGA. If these four planets are together, one will marry an unchaste lady, will be proud, will have eyes resembling that of a snake and will be always emotional. This is certain. 
27. MERCURY-JUPITER-MOON-VENUS YOGA. One, who has these four planets together will be learned, be devoid of parents, good looking, wealthy, very lucky and be without enemies. 
28. MOON-MERCURY-JUPITER-SATURN YOGA. Should these be conjunct one will be virtuous, famous, noble and splendourous, fond of relatives, wise, be a kings minister and be a chief poet. 
29. MOON-MERCURY-SATURN-VENUS YOGA. If these planets are together at birth, the native will be intent on seeking sexual pleasures with others' wives, will have an unchaste wife, be devoid of relatives, learned and will hate people. 
30. MOON-JUPITER-VENUS-SATURN YOGA. The native with these four planets conjunct will be devoid of mother, be lucky, will suffer from skin diseases, will be subjected to grief, be intent on roaming, will know many languages and will be truthful. 
31. MERCURY-MARS-JUPITER-VENUS YOGA. If these four planets are in one House, the subject will be fond of picking up quarrels with his wife, will be wealthy, worshipped by the people, will possess good qualities and be free from sickness. 
32. MARS-MERCURY-JUPITER-SATURN YOGA. One, who has these four planets in one House at birth, will be brave, learned, be a good speaker, be without wealth, truthful and will have good habits. He will be able to argue and endure. He will be intelligent. 
33. MERCURY-MARS-SATURN-VENUS YOGA. If these four planets are together at birth, the native will be an expert boxer, will depend on others, will have coarse body, will possess pride of war, be famous and will breed dogs. 
34. MARS-JUPITER-VENUS-SATURN YOGA. If these four planets are together at birth, the native will be splendourous, wealthy, addicted to other women, fond of bravery, fickle-minded and ill-disposed. 
35. MERCURY-JUPITER-VENUS-SATURN YOGA. Should these be together at birth, the native will be intelligent, interested in Shastras, be a debaucher and an obedient servant. 
Thus ends the 17th Ch. entitled “Effects of four planets in conjunction “ in Kalyana Varma's Saravali. Ch. 18. Effects of Conjunction of Five Planets 
1. SUN-MOON-MARS-JUPITER-MERCURY YOGA. If these five planets are together at birth, the native will be subjected to grief, will be cunning, be bereaved of wife and will experience physical distresses. 
2. SUN-MOON-MARS-VENUS-MERCURY YOGA. If these five planets join at birth, the native will be intent on doing others' jobs, will lose his strength, or courage through his relatives and friends and will befriend a neuter. 
3. SATURN-SUN-MERCURY-MOON-MARS YOGA. Should these be conjunct at birth, the native will be short lived, imprisoned and be devoid of every kind of happiness, wife, sons and money. 
4. MARS-MOON-JUPITER-VENUS-SUN YOGA. Should these five planets join at birth, the native will be blind by birth, subjected to much grief, be devoid of parents, always dejected in mood and fond of singing. 
5. SATURN-MOON-MARS-JUPITER-SUN YOGA. If there be a combination of these planets in one House, the native will be all expert warrior, will steal others' money, give trouble to others, be a tale-bearer and fickle-minded. 
6. SUN-MOON-VENUS-SATURN-MARS YOGA. Should the said five planets join in one House, the native will be devoid of respect, money and prosperity, will have dirty conduct and be addicted to women. 
7. MERCURY-MOON-JUPITER-SUN-SATURN YOGA. One with the conjunction of these planets will be a machinist, will enjoy great prosperity, be a king's minister, be a judge and be famous. 
8. MERCURY-MOON-JUPITER-SUN-SATURN YOGA. With these five planets in one House, the native will be timid, be deprived of people dear to him, expert in cheating, given to anger and will depend on others for food. 
9. SUN-MOON-MERCURY-SATURN-VENUS YOGA. One, who has the said five planets together at birth will be tall in stature, will have a hairy body and be not endowed with happiness, money and sons. 
10. SUN-MOON-JUPITER-VENUS-SATURN YOGA. One with these five planets together at birth, will indulge in jugglery, be fickle-minded, be liked by women, be learned, will have many enemies and be fearless. 
11. MERCURY-MARS-SUN-JUPITER-VENUS YOGA. If these planets join at birth, the native will be sensuous, will have a fleet of horses, will do good acts, be an Army chief, be dear to king, very fortunate and free from grief. 
12. SUN-MARS-MERCURY-JUPITER-SATURN YOGA. Should a native have these planets conjunct, he will be emotional, sick, will earn food by begging going from House to House and will live in dilapidated Houses. 
13. MARS-MOON-MERCURY-VENUS-SATURN YOGA. One with these five planets together at birth will be troubled by wounds, imprisonment and diseases, be learned, honoured by the people, be poor and deformed. 
14. MARS-SATURN-SUN-VENUS-MERCURY YOGA. One with the said five planets together will be troubled by diseases and enemies, be deprived of position, subjected to much grief and will roam out of agony. 
15. MOON-MARS-JUPITER-VENUS-SATURN YOGA. If these five planets are together, one will be a messenger, a dunce, a neuter, will possess dirty habits, be very unfortunate, deformed and bereft of money. 
16. SUN-MARS-JUPITER-VENUS-SATURN YOGA. Should there be a conjunction of these five planets, at birth, one will be expert in dealing with equipment and machinery related to water, minerals, mercury and such other chemicals and will achieve some fame in these lines. 
17. SUN-VENUS-SATURN-MERCURY-JUPITER YOGA. One with these planets in conjunction will be learned in many Shastras, will help friends, be dear to elders, virtuous and merciful. 
18. MERCURY-MOON-JUPITER-MARS-VENUS YOGA. Should these planets be in conjunction at birth, one will be humble, free from sickness, endowed with learning, wealth, truth and happiness, be helpful to relatives and will have many friends. 
19. MARS-SATURN-MERCURY-JUPITER-MOON YOGA. One with the conjunction of these five planets will be night blind, penniless, dependent on others for food, miserable and will bring discredit to his relatives. 
20. MERCURY-MOON-MARS-VENUS-SATURN YOGA. with these planets in conjunction, one will have a number of enemies and friends as well, be helpful to others, wicked and highly regarded. 
21. MOON-MERCURY-VENUS-JUPITER-SATURN YOGA. If these planets are together at birth in a nativity, the subject will be a kings minister, be equal to a king, chief of the people and be worshipped by all people. 
22. MARS-JUPITER-MERCURY-VENUS-SATURN YOGA. If these five planets be conjunct, the native will be good-hearted, rash (considered to be one of the 33 subordinate feelings), dear to king, free from grief, addicted to excessive sleep and be indigent. 
Thus ends the 18th Ch., entitled “Effects of five planets in conjunction”, In Kalyana Varma's Saravali. Ch. 19. Effects of 6 Planets in Conjunction 
1. MERCURY-MOON-SUN-MARS-JUPITER-VENUS YOGA. If these six planets join together, the native will be learned, virtuous, will have an emaciated body, be acquainted with many languages and will have distinguished knowledge. 
2. SUN-MOON-MARS-MERCURY-JUPITER-SATURN YOGA. Should these planets be together, the native will be liberal, helpful to others, fickle minded, of Sattvik disposition and will gratify his sexual desires in lonely places. 
3. MERCURY-MOON-SUN-MARS-SATURN-VENUS YOGA. Should these six planets join in one House, the native will be a thief, be addicted to others' women, subjected to leprosy, discarded by his own men, be a dunce, deprived of position and be issueless. 
4. VENUS-MOON-SUN-MARS-JUPITER-SATURN YOGA. If these six planets are together, the native will be mean, will do others' jobs, suffer from tuberculosis, breathing and sneezing troubles (i.e. sneezing etc.) and will be blamed by his relatives. 
5. SUN-MOON-MERCURY-JUPITER-VENUS-SATURN YOGA. One with this six-planetary conjunction will be a king's minister, fortunate, patient and will suffer from grief. He will have no wife and wealth. 
6. MERCURY-MARS-SATURN-JUPITER-VENUS-SUN YOGA. If the said six planets are together the subject will always wander in shrines, be deprived of issues and wealth and will live in forests and hills. 
7. MARS-SATURN-VENUS-MOON-MERCURY-JUPITER YOGA. One with these six planets will be pure at all times, valorous, will seek sexual union with many women, be dear to king, be a minister and be endowed with wealth, issues and happiness. 
8. PLANETARY CONJUNCTIONS. If 5, or 6 planets join at birth, normally such natives will be penniless, subjected to grief and be dull-witted. Even aspects among such planets will yield similar results according to Kandalas. 
Thus ends the 19th Ch., entitled “Effects of six planet combinations” in Kalyana Varma's Saravali. Ch. 20. Combinations For Renunciation 
1. Various sages have explained widely the combinations of four, or more planets producing an ascetic. I now explain below such of the Yogas. 
2. One born with the conjunction of the Sun, the Moon, Venus, Jupiter and Mars; or the Luminaries, Mercury and Mars; or the Sun, Mars, Saturn, Mercury and Venus becomes an ascetic. 
3. The native having the combination of Mars, the Luminaries (i.e. the Sun and the Moon), Mercury and Jupiter; or the Luminaries, Saturn and Mercury; or the Luminaries, Mars and Saturn takes to renunciation and become a mendicant. 
4. The Sun, Jupiter, Saturn and Mercury-being together, or Mars, the Sun, Mercury and Jupiter joining denotes a mendicant. 
5. Should Venus, the Sun, Mars and Saturn; or Jupiter, Mars, the Sun and Saturn; or Mars, the Moon, Jupiter and Saturn with strength be in conjunction at birth, native takes to asceticism. 
6. One will be initiated into a religious vow, if anyone of the following group of planets be found together at birth: d) Mars. Saturn, Mercury and Jupiter; 2) Mars, Saturn Mercury, the Sun and Venus; 3) the Luminaries, Mars Saturn and Venus. 
7. One becomes a mendicant to live in forests and hilly areas, if the planets group themselves in conjunction at birth, as under: 1) Venus, Mars, Saturn, Jupiter and the Sun; 2) Mars, the Moon, Jupiter, Mercury and Saturn; 3) Venus, Mercury, Saturn, the Moon and Mars. 
8. The native will become a sage, giving up (even) his food and be honoured by the people, if the heavenly bodies form conjunction, as under: 1) The Moon, Mercury, Mars, Jupiter and the Sun; 2) The Luminaries, Mercury, Venus and Mars. 
9. The native will be initiated into a religious vow, if 1) the Luminaries, Mars, Mercury, Jupiter and Saturn, or 2) The Moon, Mars, Saturn, Mercury, Jupiter and the Sun, or 3) Mars, the Luminaries, Saturn, Venus and Mercury, join together at birth. 
10. A famous sage is indicated by the combination of 1) the Luminaries, Jupiter, Saturn and Venus, or 2) Venus, the Luminaries, Jupiter, Saturn and Mercury. 
11. Note the conjunction of the following planets: 1) Mars, Mercury, Jupiter, Venus, Saturn and the Sun. 2) Venus, the Luminaries, Saturn, Jupiter and Mercury. It indicates an ascetic. 
12. If conjunction is found among the planetary group, viz. 1) the Luminaries, Jupiter and Saturn; 2) Saturn, the Luminaries and Venus; 3) Sun, Mercury, Mars and Jupiter, the native will become an ascetic living on roots and fruits. 
13. The native will become an ascetic with bark garments, if Mars, the Sun, Mercury and Venus are found together at birth. The same effect follows the conjunction of Mars, the Moon, Jupiter and Mercury. 
14. A patient ascetic (awaiting the blessing of the Supreme) is indicated by either the combination of the Moon, Mercury, Mars and Saturn, or of Mercury, Mars, Jupiter and Saturn. 
15. A sage living only by eating fruits is denoted by the combination of the Luminaries, Venus and Mercury; or Mars, Mercury, Venus and Saturn; or Saturn, the Moon, Jupiter and Venus. 
16. An ascetic, who will be highly honourable, living in forests, is denoted by each of the under mentioned planetary conjunctions: 1) The Sun, Mars, the Moon and Venus, 2) the Luminaries, Mars and Mercury, 3) Jupiter, Venus, Saturn and the Sun, 4) Venus, Jupiter, the Moon and Mars. 
17. Find the planets together in individual groups, as under 1) Venus, Moon, Mars, Jupiter and Saturn, 2) the Moon, Mercury, Mars, Jupiter and Venus, 3) The Luminaries, Mars, Mercury and Jupiter. The result is, that the ascetic will be sorrowful (Unsuccessful mendicant). 
18. Mars, Saturn, Jupiter, Venus and Mercury with strength, or Saturn, the Sun, Mercury, the Moon and Mars with strength in conjunction produce one with clotted hair and bark-garments. 
19. The Luminaries, Mercury, Mars and Venus, or the Luminaries, Mars, Jupiter, Venus, if be together, the native certainly will become an ascetic. 
20. If the Sun denotes asceticism (i.e. being the strongest in the Yoga), there will only be faith in the religious order, while competence (to fulfill the order) will lack. If the planet, contributing to such order is overpowered by another planet (i.e. in eclipse, planetary war etc.) the native will give up the order after being initiated into it. Should many planets denote such an order, there may be many kinds of religious orders, but these will depend on the order of the planet. 
21. If the planet indicating asceticism is combust in the Sun, or is aspected by another heavenly body, the native will only have an earnest desire to be initiated into the religious order, but will not attain fruition of his aim. So say Yavanas. 
22. The native will attain religious order, if the Moon, posited in a decanate of Saturn, is aspected by Mars and Saturn. The same effect is produced, if the Moon occupies the Navāńśa of Aries/Scorpio in aspect to Saturn. 
23. If the Lord of the Moon Sign receives the sole aspect of Saturn (i.e. unaspected by others than Saturn), one will enter religious order. Even in this context, the earlier Yogas, if present will only prevail. 
24. If the Lord of the Moon Sign, bright with rays, lends his aspect to Saturn, while Saturn is in an Angle, the native will lose his fortunes only to enter into a religious order. 
25. If one among the Sun, the Moon and Jupiter be devoid of strength and occupy the Ascendant, or the 10th, or the 12th in aspect to strong Saturn, the native will become distressed ascetic. 
26. Should the Moon with strength be in the 10th, falling in a benefic's Navāńśa, while others occupy their exaltation marks and all being in aspect to strong Saturn, the native will become the Lord of the earth to only become an ascetic. 
27. If waxing Moon, with superior strength, aspects the Ascendant Lord, the latter being bereft of strength and being alone (in that Rāśi), the native will be devoid of wealth and own men, be miserable, sorrowful, will take to asceticism and will obtain his food with great inconvenience. 
28. One will become a religious mendicant, if Saturn occupying a benefic's Navāńśa aspects others including the Moon. The Moon in this case should only be in Aquarius Navāńśa. 
29. If the Lord of the Moon Sign aspects all the other planets, while these are all together in one Rāśi, the native will become an ascetic. 
30. The Sun rules the ascetics of the following orders: Those, who worship the Fire God in forests, or on river banks, those, who worship (the omnipotent) Sun-God, Elephant-faced Ganesa and His benevolent mother Parvati, those, who recite the hymns of Gayatri (which are very sacred), those, who are vowed to bathe in the sacred Ganges everyday and those, who maintain (absolute) celibacy. 
31. The religious order belonging to the Moon attracts the following various persons: Those disciples, who smear their bodies with sacred ashes, those, who worship the Feet of Lord Shiva, those, who are abandoned by the society, those, who are devoted to Bhagavati, those, who give up company of others, those, who take to Soma Siddhanta and those, who carry bowls in their hands (for begging alms). 
32. The Buddhist monks, the tonsured, those, who wear white apparels, those, who beg wearing good robes, those, who wear blood-red clothes and those, that have conquered their five senses-all these mendicants are ruled by Mars. 
33. Mercury denotes an alm-seeker, a conjurer, a snake poison curer and one, who eats the flesh of a peacock. 
34. The ascetics ruled by Jupiter are: those, who hold a single scepter (or mace), those, who hold three scepters, those, who wear red coloured apparels, those, who are in the third stage of their religious life, those, who pull on their lives with fruits and water (alone), those, who still are attached to family ties, those, who maintain celibacy and those, who take to visiting shrines etc. 
35. Venus rules the mendicants of Saivite and Vaish-navite sects. 
36. Religious hypocrites, bare mendicants and the ascetics, who sit under shadowy trees in forests are ruled by Saturn. 
37. Should Raja Yogas be simultaneously present along with the above ascetic Yogas, all the evil results are nullified and the native will become very virtuous, will be adorned by all the kings. himself becoming a king and will take to religious order. 
Thus ends the 20th Ch., entitled ‘Combinations for Renunciation' in Kalyana Varma's Saravali. Ch. 21. Nabhasa Yogas 
1. NABHASA YOGAS. Yavanas have explained 1800 kinds of Nabhasa Yogas, out of which I detail below 32. 
2-4. KINDS OF NABHASA YOGA. The following are the 32 Nabhasa Yogas Nau, Chatra, Koota, Chaapa, Sringataka, Vajra, Damini, Pasa, Veena, Kamala, Musala, Vapi, Hala, Sara, Samudra, Chakra, Maala. Sarpa, Ardha Chandra, Yava, Kedara, Gada, Pakshi, Yupa, Yuga, Sakata, Soola, Danda, Rajju, Sakthi, Nala and Gola. The Asraya Yogas, viz. Musala, Rajju and Nala are dealt with by Acharya Manitha. 
5-6. Gola, Yuga, Soola, Pasa, Veena (Vallaki), Kedara and Damini arc the seven Sankhya Yogas. The two Dala Yogas viz. Sarpa (Bhujanga) and Mala are explained by Parasara Maharishi. Savitracharya dealt with remaining 20 Yogas. 
7. One born with an Asraya will obtain the good effects, viz., happiness, advantages and qualities, provided there is no other kind of (Nabhasa) Yoga present in the horoscope. If other (Nabhasa) Yoga is present in addition to an Asraya Yoga, then the effects of Asraya Yoga do not come to pass, but the other (Nabhasa) Yoga prevails. 
8-10. EFFECT OF AKRITI, SANKHYA AND DALA YOGAS. One born in Akriti Yoga will be satisfied with his own fortunes, will earn through a king, be dear to king and be famous. Should there be a Sankhya Yoga, the native will be happy only with others' wealth, will live only through others help and be always not peaceful. A native with Dala Yoga will sometimes enjoy his own fortune, yet sometimes that of others, will pick up the fruits thrown on the ground by others, be sometimes happy and sometimes sorrowful. 
11. NAUKA, KOOTA, CHATRA AND CHAPA YOGAS. If the seven planets occupy continuous Houses starting from the Ascendant and the other three Angles, Yogas called Nauka, Koota, Chatra and Chapa are, respectively, formed. 
12. YUPA, SARA, SAKTHI AND DANDA YOGAS. If the seven planets occupy for continuous Houses counted from the Ascendant and its Angles, the resultant Yogas are known, as Yupa, Sara (or Ishu-arrow), Sakthi and Danda, respectively. 
13. ARDHA CHANDRA AND GADA YOGAS. If the seven planets occupy continuously seven Houses commencing from a House, which is not angular to the Ascendant, the Yoga produced is known, as Ardha Chandra (Ardha Sasi) Yoga. Gada Yoga forms, when all the seven planets occupy two successive Angles from the Ascendant. 
14. VAJRA, YAVA, PADMA AND VAPI YOGAS. If benefics occupy the Lagna and 7th, while malefics are in the 4th and 10th Vajra Yoga is formed. Conversely, if malefics are in the Lagna and 7th, while 4th and 10th are occupied by benefics, Yava Yoga is produced. If all the planets are disposed in four kendras, Padma (Kamala) Yoga is formed. Should the seven planets be relegated either to Apoklima Houses (3, 6, 9 and 12th), or to Panapharas (2, 5, 8 and 11 Houses), Vapi Yoga is formed. 
15. SAKATA, VIHAGA, HALA AND SRINGATAKA YOGAS. If all planets occupy only the Ascendant and the 7th House, Sakata Yoga is formed. Similar participation of all the planets in the 4th and 10th Houses constitutes Vihaga (Pakshi) Yoga. Should all the planets be in mutual Trines, avoiding the Ascendant, Hala Yoga is formed. All planets relegated only to the Ascendant and its Trines give rise to Sringataka Yoga. 
16. CHAKRA AND SAMUDRA YOGAS. Should all the planets occupy alternative Rāśis commencing from the Lagna, Chakra Yoga is formed. If these occupy alternative Rāśis from the 2nd onwards, Samudra Yoga is formed. 
17. Thus, I have explained the twenty different Akriti Yogas. Now, I explain the Asraya Yogas, as per the schools of thought of senior Garga etc. 
18. ASRAYA AND DALA YOGAS. Should all the planets be in Dual Rāśis, Nala Yoga is formed. Similarly, if these are in Fixed Rāśis, Musala Yoga takes place and in Movable Rāśis Rajju Yoga is formed. All Angles occupied exclusively by benefics cause Maala Yoga, while malefics in all Angles produce Sarpa Yoga. These two are Dala Yogas. 
19. SANKHYA YOGAS. If all the seven planets occupy one Rāśi, Gola Yoga is formed. Similarly in 2 Rāśis-Yuga Yoga, In 3 Rāśis-Sula Yoga, in 4 Rāśis-Kedara Yoga, in 5 Rāśis-Pasa Yoga, in 6 Rāśis-Damini and in 7 Rāśis-Veena (Vallaki) Yoga. 
20-21. EFFECTS OF NABHASA YOGAS. NAU YOGA. The native's livelihood will be through water; he will have many gains, will be very famous, be pleased, mean, strong and stingy. This and other Yogas are effective at all times independant of Dasas. 
22. KOOTA YOGA. The native with Koota Yoga will be a liar, be crafty, be a jailer, be poor, wicked, cruel and will always live in hills and fortresses. 
23. CHHATRA YOGA. The native with Chhatra Yoga will help his own men, be kind, liberal, dear to king, very intelligent and will enjoy happiness in boyhood and at the end. 
24. CHAPA YOGA. (KARMUKA YOGA). The native with Chapa Yoga will be a liar, jailer, thief and will live in forests. He will not have wealth in the middle of his life. 
25. ARDHA CHANDRA YOGA. One born with Ardha Chandra Yoga will be fortunate, be an Army chief, be brilliant bodied, dear to king and strong. He will possess gems, gold and ornaments. 
26. VAJRA YOGA. One born with Vajra Yoga will be happy at the beginning and end of his life, bold, beautiful, free from sickness, unfortunate and be inimical to his own people. 
27. YAVA YOGA One born with Yava Yoga will observe fasts and other religious rules, be intent on doing auspicious acts, be happy in the middle of life, be liberal and will have lasting wealth. 
28. KAMALA YOGA. One born with Kamala Yoga will be highly famous, very virtuous, assuredly long living, very rich, very bright in appearance and will be the Lord of the earth. 
29. VAPI YOGA. One born with Vapi Yoga will be skillful in amassing wealth, will enjoy lasting riches and happiness, be beautiful and will be endowed with happiness from sons. 
30. SAKATA YOGA. One born with Sakata Yoga will be troubled by diseases, will have a bad wife, will be a dunce, will live by pulling carts, will be poor and be without relatives and friends. 
31. VIHAGA YOGA. (PAKSHI YOGA). The native with this Yoga will be intent on wandering, will have mean habits, will be a messenger, will live through sexual dealings, shameless and fond of quarrels. 
32. GADA YOGA. One born with this Yoga, will always care for honour and money, will perform yagnas etc., will be expert in Sastras and music and will be endowed with money, gold, jewels and wealth. 
33. SRINGATAKA YOGA. One born with this Yoga will be fond of quarrels, be a warrior, be happy, dear to king, will have a fortunate wife, be rich and will hate the fair sex. 
34. HALA YOGA. The native of this Yoga will eat in plenty, will be indigent, will have agricultural profession, will be subjected to grief, be emotional, be forsaken by relatives and friends and will be a servant. 
35. CHAKRA YOGA. One born in this Yoga will be a king at whose feet will be the heads of the other prostrating kings adoring diamond-studded crowns. (That is, the subordinate kings, wearing diamond-studded crowns will honour a Chakra Yoga native, who will be the chief of such kings) 
36. SAMUDRA YOGA. Should a person be born under this Yoga, he will have abundant wealth and precious stones, will be a king, be endowed with pleasures, be dear to people, will have steady mind and be truthful in disposition (“Sattvavanta”). 37. YUPA YOGA. The native with this Yoga will have self-protection, be charitable, be endowed with riches and happiness and will observe religious fastings and vows. He will be a distinguished person. 
38. SARA YOGA. The native with sara Yoga will manufacture arrows (arms etc. in modern context), will catch hold of thieves (for example, be a police officer), will live in forests to hunt animals, will be equal to a mad person, will torture and be fond of mean handiworks. 
39. SAKTI YOGA. One born with this Yoga will be devoid of wealth, deformed, subjected to grief, mean, lazy short-lived, expert in war and be beautiful. 
40. DANDA YOGA. The native with this Yoga will lose his wife and sons, will be poor, discarded by all people, be out of the men of his circle, be grieved, mean and will be servant. 
41. MAALA YOGA. One born with maala Yoga will always be happy, be endowed with conveyances, robes, wealth and pleasures, splendourous and will have plurality of wives. 
42. SARPA YOGA. The native born under this Yoga will be crooked in disposition, pitiless, always be a subject of grief, poor and will live in other's House and eat their food. 
43. RAJJU YOGA. The subject with this Yoga will be fond of wandering, attractive in appearance, will earn money in foreign countries, be cruel and mischievously disposed. 
44. MUSALA YOGA. One born under this Yoga will be endowed with honour, wealth and wisdom, be attached to his duty, be liked by king, be famous. steady-minded and bold. 
45. NALA YOGA. One born with nala Yoga will have uneven physique (i.e. some limbs long and some short), will gather money, be skillful, be helpful to his relatives and be attractive in appearance. 
46. GOLA YOGA. One born in this Yoga will be indigent, indolent, devoid of learning and honour, dirty and always grieved. 
47. YUGA YOGA. One born with this Yoga will be a religious hypocrite, be bereft of wealth, forsaken by people and devoid of sons, honour and virtues. 
48. SULA YOGA. The native with sula Yoga will be harsh, indolent, poor, torturous, become a prohibited person, bold, successful in war and fearful. 
49. KEDARA YOGA. One born under this Yoga will be useful to many, will have agricultural profession, be truthfully disposed, fickle minded and wealthy. 
50. PASA YOGA. One born with pasa Yoga will be bonded, be attached to work, worldly in disposition, will talk too much, will not have good qualities and will have many servants. 
51. DAMINI YOGA. One born with this Yoga will be helpful, will have cattle, be Lord of money, be foolish, will have many sons and jewels, be bold and learned. 
52. VEENA YOGA. One born with this combination will have friends, be eloquent, interested in Sastras, musical instruments and singing. He will be happy, will have many servants and be famous. 
Thus ends the 21st Ch., entitled “Nabhasa Yogas” in Kalyana Varma's Saravali.  
